<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JMIR Hum Factors</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JMIR Hum Factors</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">JMIR Human Factors</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>JMIR Human Factors</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2292-9495</issn><publisher><publisher-name>JMIR Publications</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Toronto, Canada</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC10732231</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">v10i1e49687</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/49687</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Paper</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Original Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Factors Associated With Levels of Public Engagement in Protective Behaviors During the Early COVID-19 Pandemic: Causal-Comparative Study Based on the Health Belief Model</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Kushniruk</surname><given-names>Andre</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="reviewer"><name><surname>Mondal</surname><given-names>Himel</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="reviewer"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Chenhao</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="reviewer"><name><surname>Allam</surname><given-names>Ayman</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib id="contrib1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Chia-Chun</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8239-6632</contrib-id></contrib><contrib id="contrib2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Hsi</given-names></name><degrees>MSc</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6019-7760</contrib-id></contrib><contrib id="contrib3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>Shao-Yu</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2874-5202</contrib-id></contrib><contrib id="contrib4" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Wei-Wen</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6439-5369</contrib-id><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">1</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">2</xref><address><institution>School of Nursing, National Taiwan University College of Medicine</institution><addr-line>No. 1, Sec. 1, Jen-Ai Road</addr-line><addr-line>Taipei, 100233</addr-line><country>Taiwan</country><phone>886 2223123456 ext 288422</phone><email>weiwen@ntu.edu.tw</email></address></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<institution>School of Nursing, National Taiwan University College of Medicine</institution>
<addr-line>Taipei</addr-line>
<country>Taiwan</country>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<institution>National Taiwan University Hospital</institution>
<addr-line>Taipei</addr-line>
<country>Taiwan</country>
</aff><author-notes><corresp>Corresponding Author: Wei-Wen Wu <email>weiwen@ntu.edu.tw</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>e49687</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>6</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="rev-request"><day>29</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>12</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9;Chia-Chun Tang, Hsi Chen, Shao-Yu Tsai, Wei-Wen Wu. Originally published in JMIR Human Factors (https://humanfactors.jmir.org), 19.12.2023.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" ext-link-type="uri">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work, first published in JMIR Human Factors, is properly cited. The complete bibliographic information, a link to the original publication on <ext-link xlink:href="https://humanfactors.jmir.org" ext-link-type="uri">https://humanfactors.jmir.org</ext-link>, as well as this copyright and license information must be included.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://humanfactors.jmir.org/2023/1/e49687"/><abstract><sec sec-type="background"><title>Background</title><p>While the challenges of COVID-19 are still unfolding, the enhancement of protective behavior remains a top priority in global health care. However, current behavior-promoting strategies may be inefficient without first identifying the individuals with lower engagement in protective behavior and the associating factors.</p></sec><sec sec-type="objective"><title>Objective</title><p>This study aimed to identify individuals with and potential contributing factors to low engagement in protective behavior during the COVID-19 pandemic.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>This is a causal-comparative study. A theory-based web-based survey was used to investigate individuals&#x02019; protective behavior and potential associating factors. During June 2020, the distribution of the survey was targeted to 3 areas: Taiwan, Japan, and North America. Based on the theory of the health belief model (HBM), the survey collected participants&#x02019; various perceptions toward COVID-19 and a collection of protective behaviors. In addition to the descriptive analysis, cluster analysis, ANOVA, and Fisher exact and chi-square tests were used.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>A total of 384 responses were analyzed. More than half of the respondents lived in Taiwan, followed by Japan, then North America. The respondents were grouped into 3 clusters according to their engagement level in all protective behaviors. These 3 clusters were significantly different from each other in terms of the participants&#x02019; sex, residency, perceived barriers, self-efficacy, and cues of action.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>This study used an HBM-based questionnaire to assess protective behaviors against COVID-19 and the associated factors across multiple countries. The findings indicate significant differences in various HBM concepts among individuals with varying levels of behavioral engagement.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>infectious disease</kwd><kwd>protective behavior</kwd><kwd>COVID</kwd><kwd>health belief model</kwd><kwd>causal comparative</kwd><kwd>causal</kwd><kwd>protective</kwd><kwd>prevention</kwd><kwd>opinion</kwd><kwd>opinions</kwd><kwd>attitude</kwd><kwd>attitudes</kwd><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>pandemic</kwd><kwd>infection control</kwd><kwd>public safety</kwd><kwd>public health</kwd><kwd>survey</kwd><kwd>surveys</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p>Since the emergence of COVID-19, with the first case reported in December 2019, the disease has spread globally and was declared a pandemic by the World Health Organization (WHO) in March 2020. Thereafter, the pandemic has become a series of COVID-19 waves that demonstrated different trends among regions. For example, while daily new cases reached more than 100 cases per million people in the United States in June 2020, Japan and Taiwan had about 0.49 and 0.02 daily new cases per million people, respectively. The situation reversed in September 2022, when approximate daily new cases for Taiwan, Japan, and the United States were 1723, 619, and 171 cases per million people, respectively. No matter how the pandemic surges and declines, it is clear a few years later that the world is still struggling to fight the disease [<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. As of June 2023, the number of confirmed cases of COVID-19 exceeded 676 million globally, with a death toll of over 6 million [<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Therefore, preventing and slowing the transmission of the disease remains important in health care worldwide.</p><p>Despite the efforts made by the authorities to educate the public regarding the disease and promote protective behaviors, promoting these strategies may be inefficient. The webpages of the WHO and Centers for Disease Control and Prevention of many countries all have messages containing information about the current COVID-19 situation and, most importantly, encourage the practice of protective behaviors [<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>-<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. However, promotion strategies regarding protective measures, based on how they were shown on the government or authority websites and in publications, were mostly knowledge-based and did not deliver specific messages to at-risk groups. Such general approaches may have very limited effects, as the evidence suggests that, in addition to knowledge, several other factors may affect engagement in protective measures. For example, sex, geographic regions, perceived severity and threat, worries, and trust in the information source may all influence the adoption of protective behaviors [<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>-<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Thus, it is important to identify not only the individuals who have lower compliance with protective behaviors, but also the possible contributing factors. Subsequently, tailored messages that contain crucial elements for a specific population can be designed. Furthermore, the WHO stressed on its website that it is essential for everyone to realize the importance of &#x0201c;doing it [protective behaviors] all [<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].&#x0201d; Therefore, rather than focusing on a single behavior, it is necessary to look at all behaviors collectively.</p><p>To untangle the association between protective behaviors and the possible factors, it may be beneficial to use a theoretical model, such as the health belief model (HBM), to organize and conceptualize this correlation. The HBM was originally developed in the 1950s by social psychologists to enhance the effectiveness of health education programs. This model proposes that individuals&#x02019; decisions to implement disease-preventive behaviors are related to perceived susceptibility, severity, benefits, barriers, and self-efficacy. The HBM has been used widely and researchers have modified it to include cues to action, as evidence suggests that these can also affect protective behaviors [<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Several studies have used the HBM to examine the relationship between health beliefs and protective behaviors during COVID-19. A study that examined protective behavior in Morocco and India found that perceived severity and susceptibility were vital factors that affected avoidant protective behavior, such as social distancing [<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Another study pointed out that the self-efficacy of adolescents in Iran predicted their protective behavior, which included social distancing, wearing masks, and hand hygiene [<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. While the abovementioned evidence pointed out that specific HBM factors demonstrated powerful impacts on some protective behaviors, an Ethiopian study found that a set of HBM factors, which included self-efficacy, perceived benefits, perceived barriers, and perceived susceptibility to COVID-19, were all significant predictors of adherence to protective behaviors [<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Alternatively, findings from an international investigation suggested that perceived severity was of little importance in predicting compliance with protective behaviors [<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In summary, even though HBM factors have been shown to influence protective behaviors during COVID-19, the results were mixed regarding which factors made significant contributions and were different across areas. Moreover, although emerging studies have addressed protective measures against COVID-19, very few studies have investigated all the desired protective measures as a group to identify individuals who were less willing to perform these protective behaviors.</p><p>This study aimed to identify individuals with low protective behavioral engagement during COVID-19 and the potential factors that contributed to the low levels of engagement. Specifically, we aimed to (1) use an HBM-based web-based survey to describe individuals&#x02019; engagement level in protective behaviors across countries and distinguish between the low and high engagement groups and (2) identify the ascription of the factors to different groups.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Study Design</title><p>This cross-sectional study used a causal-comparative design. This design was selected because the groups were predetermined prior to the relationships among the variables of interest being analyzed [<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Recruitment</title><p>Data was collected as part of a large-scale transnational survey where the web-based survey was advertised on social media (Facebook, Instagram, and Google Ads) and the responses were recorded from June 8 to June 29, 2020. Due to budget limitations, we targeted the advertisement only to Taiwan, the United States, Canada, and Japan. Participants were included if they were aged 20 years or older and able to read and understand the selected language (English, Mandarin, or Japanese). Based on the recommendation for the estimation of a sample size for comparative studies, about 59 participants were needed for the high and low engagement groups (the proportion of the 2 groups was estimated to be 10% and 30%) [<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Measures</title><p>A web-based survey, designed by the investigator, was used and developed based on a literature review and the HBM (<xref rid="figure1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). Details regarding the survey content and development process have been published elsewhere [<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p><fig position="float" id="figure1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The Theoretical Model Guiding the Survey Design: Health Belief Model.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="humanfactors_v10i1e49687_fig1" position="float"/></fig><p>The survey contained 7 subscales (ie, perceived susceptibility, severity, benefits, barriers, self-efficacy, cues to action, and actions) with a total of 35 items that inquired about an individual&#x02019;s perception of the pandemic and actions of protective measures. All items were rated on a 5-point Likert scale that showed the level of agreement or frequency (eg, always, sometimes, or never). Higher scores represented higher levels of agreement or more frequent adoption of behaviors. The 7 subscales were defined as follows:</p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Perceived susceptibility refers to one&#x02019;s belief in the likelihood of being infected by COVID-19 [<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].</p></list-item><list-item><p>Perceived severity refers to one&#x02019;s feeling about the seriousness of getting the disease or of keeping it untreated [<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Items on the perceived severity of the medical consequences on the physical and social aspects (eg, financial burden, regulation, and punishment) were formulated.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Perceived benefits refer to an individual&#x02019;s opinion on the advantages of acting on the recommended health measures [<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Protecting oneself and others, as well as providing a sense of safety, were the most commonly indicated benefits [<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].</p></list-item><list-item><p>Perceived barriers have the following two different definitions: (1) the potential negative consequences of a particular health action that act as impediments to undertaking recommended behaviors [<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] or (2) barriers that must be reduced in order to engage in the recommended behaviors [<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. We incorporated both interpretations in designing the survey.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Self-efficacy refers to a person&#x02019;s belief in their capability to execute behaviors to achieve the expected outcomes [<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Health behavior is a series of mental and behavioral processes, which includes behavioral intention, pre-action, action, maintenance [<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], resistance, harm reduction, coping, and recovery [<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Factor analysis finalized 2 constructs, namely, prevention self-efficacy and maintenance self-efficacy.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Cues to action refer to factors that might trigger an execution of the actions. We confirmed 3 constructs through factor analysis: recommendations from formal information sources (eg, government), recommendations from informal information sources (eg, friends) [<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], and environmental cues (eg, condition of targeted places, surrounding people&#x02019;s behaviors) [<xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].</p></list-item><list-item><p>Action refers to preventive behaviors that can protect oneself from a COVID-19 infection. We identified and organized the proper actions suggested by the Taiwan Centers for Disease Control, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention of the United States, the WHO, and the European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control [<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>-<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. There were 6 personal protective measures recommended by more than one institution that were adopted as behavioral measures, which included wearing a facemask, avoiding nonessential travel, social distancing, hand hygiene, cough etiquette, and cleaning and ventilation.</p></list-item></list><p>Apart from the abovementioned variables, demographic data were also included in the web-based survey. Cronbach &#x003b1; was .71.</p></sec><sec><title>Ethical Considerations</title><p>The study was approved by the Research Ethics Committee of the National Taiwan University Hospital (202005043RINC). All participants were required to provide digital written consent before the anonymous survey began.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>In addition to the descriptive analysis, cluster analysis was applied to group participants based on their level of engagement in all protective behaviors. The scores of the 6 behaviors were first standardized based on the <italic>z</italic> scores, given that the scales for these behaviors were different. Additionally, k-means clustering was used, and 3 clusters were determined using the <italic>NbClust</italic> package [<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] in the statistical computing software R (R Foundation for Statistical Computing). ANOVA, Fisher exact tests, and chi-square tests were used to further examine the differences among the groups. Posthoc tests, Fisher least significant difference, and Bonferroni correction were applied to further clarify the directions of the aforementioned analyses. Finally, multinomial logistic regression was applied to adjust the relationships among potentially related health belief variables. A 2-sided <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Basic Information of the Participants</title><p>Among the 629 responses received, 245 (38.95%) were excluded due to duplication (n=1) or incompletion (n=244). Of the remaining 384 participants (age: mean 39.92, SD 14.65 years), 145 (37.8%) were male, 238 (62%) were female, 1 participant did not specify their sex, 106 (27.6%) were health care professionals or students, and 65 (16.9%) had chronic diseases. Nearly all participants (n=352, 91.6%) had completed a college education or higher. For the past 6 months, 258 (67.2%) participants had lived in Taiwan, 86 (22.4%) in Japan, 28 (8%) in North America, 5 (1.3%) in Europe (Switzerland, Germany, and the United Kingdom), 2 (0.52%) in Hong Kong, 1 (0.26%) in China, and 1 (0.26%) in Macau. The protective behaviors that were mostly adopted by the public were avoiding traveling abroad (n=224, 58.3%), practicing good cough etiquette (n=218, 56.8%), wearing facemasks (n=186, 48.4%), handwashing (n=179, 46.6%), cleaning and ventilating (n=128, 33.3%), and maintaining social distance (n=101, 26.3%). <xref rid="table1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> displays the demographic data and the frequencies of the adopted protective behaviors.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic data and adopted protective behaviors (n=384).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="1000" cellpadding="5" cellspacing="0" border="1"><col width="30" span="1"/><col width="30" span="1"/><col width="640" span="1"/><col width="0" span="1"/><col width="300" span="1"/><thead><tr valign="top"><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Variables</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Value</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="top"><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Age (years), mean (SD)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">39.32 (14.65)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">
<bold>Sex, n (%)</bold>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">145 (37.8)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">238 (62)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Prefer not to answer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.3)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">
<bold>Education, n (%)</bold>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Primary school or lower</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 (0.3)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Junior and senior high school</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (8.1)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">College or university</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">209 (54.4)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Graduate school</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">143 (37.2)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Has chronic disease, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">65 (16.9)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">Health care professional or student, n (%)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">106 (27.6)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">
<bold>Residential locations over the last 6 months, n (%)</bold>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Taiwan</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">258 (67.2)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Japan</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86 (22.4)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">North America</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 (8.1)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Other<sup>a</sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 (2.3)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="5" rowspan="1">
<bold>Frequencies of adopted protective behavior, n (%)</bold>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Wearing facemask</bold>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Never or rarely</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">6 (1.5)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sometimes</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">190 (49.5)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Always</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">186 (48.4)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Avoid traveling</bold>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Never or rarely</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">9 (2.3)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sometimes</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">148 (38.5)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Always</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">224 (58.3)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Social distancing</bold>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Never or rarely</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">25 (6.5)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sometimes</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">257 (66.9)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Always</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">101 (26.3)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Hand hygiene</bold>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Never or rarely</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">8 (2)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sometimes</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">196 (51)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Always</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">179 (46.6)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Cough etiquette</bold>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Never or rarely</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">5 (1.3)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sometimes</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">159 (41.4)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Always</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">218 (56.8)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Cleaning and ventilating</bold>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Never or rarely</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">11 (2.9)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sometimes</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">245 (63.8)</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Always</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">128 (33.3)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table1fn1"><p><sup>a</sup>Other locations included Switzerland, Germany, the United Kingdom, Hong Kong, China, and Macau.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Cluster Analysis</title><p>Cluster analysis divided participants into 3 groups: those who adopted protective measures more frequently (cluster 1, high engagement; n=181, 47.1%), less frequently (cluster 2, low engagement; n=34, 8.9%), and those in-between (cluster 3, medium engagement; n=169, 44%) (<xref rid="table2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Note that since the values were standardized scores, negative values do not imply that participants did not engage in such behaviors. For instance, cluster 1 had higher standardized scores (<italic>z</italic> scores: 0.47334-0.67822) for all 6 behaviors than cluster 2 (<italic>z</italic> scores: &#x02013;0.81341 to &#x02013;1.65617) and cluster 3 (<italic>z</italic> scores: &#x02013;0.29885 to &#x02013;0.41468). Higher <italic>z</italic> scores represented more frequent adoption of protective behaviors.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Final cluster centers for all participants (n=384).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="1000" cellpadding="5" cellspacing="0" border="1"><col width="160" span="1"/><col width="190" span="1"/><col width="200" span="1"/><col width="170" span="1"/><col width="190" span="1"/><col width="90" span="1"/><thead><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Behavior</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cluster 1: high engagement (n=181), <italic>z</italic> score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cluster 2: low engagement (n=34), <italic>z</italic> score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cluster 3: medium engagement (n=169), <italic>z</italic> score</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>F</italic> test (<italic>df</italic>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> value</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wearing facemask</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58259</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;1.61597</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.29885</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">144.666 (2, 381)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Avoid traveling</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">.047334</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.81341</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.34331</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.679 (2, 381)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Social distancing</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.65691</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;1.43586</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.41468</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">164.140 (2, 381)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hand hygiene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67822</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;1.65617</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.39318</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">214.035 (2, 381)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cough etiquette</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64384</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;1.51134</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.38550</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">165.072 (2, 381)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cleaning and ventilating</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58074</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;1.21134</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.37828</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">103.839 (2, 381)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Analysis of Variance</title><p>ANOVA was used to examine whether the variables of the HBM were different among the 3 groups. The 1-way ANOVA showed significant differences in perceived barriers (<italic>F</italic><sub>2,381</sub>=3.046, <italic>P</italic>=.049), self-efficacy (<italic>F</italic><sub>2,381</sub>=23.935, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;.001), cues of action regarding recommendations from informal information sources (<italic>F</italic><sub>2,381</sub>=21.152, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;.001), and environmental cues (<italic>F</italic><sub>2,381</sub>=8.396, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;.001) (<xref rid="table3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>ANOVA results between groups in terms of health belief model variables (n=384).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="1000" cellpadding="5" cellspacing="0" border="1"><col width="30" span="1"/><col width="280" span="1"/><col width="280" span="1"/><col width="0" span="1"/><col width="170" span="1"/><col width="0" span="1"/><col width="170" span="1"/><col width="0" span="1"/><col width="70" span="1"/><thead><tr valign="top"><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Dependent variables</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Sum of squares (<italic>df</italic>)<break/>
<break/>
</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Mean square</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1"><italic>F</italic> test (<italic>df</italic>)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> value</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="top"><td colspan="9" rowspan="1">
<bold>Perceived severity</bold>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Between groups</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.732 (2)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">4.366</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.685 (2, 381)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">.51</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Within groups</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2429.619 (381)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">6.377</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<break/>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="9" rowspan="1">
<bold>Perceived benefit</bold>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Between groups</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.492 (2)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">10.246</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">1.829 (2, 381)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">.16</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Within groups</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2133.914 (381)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">5.601</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<break/>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="9" rowspan="1">
<bold>Perceived barrier</bold>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Between groups</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.615 (2)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">30.308</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">3.046 (2, 381)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">.049</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Within groups</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3790.625 (381)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">9.949</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<break/>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="9" rowspan="1">
<bold>Self-efficacy</bold>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Between groups</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">514.435 (2)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">257.218</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">23.935 (2, 381)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Within groups</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4094.374 (381)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">10.746</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<break/>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="9" rowspan="1">
<bold>Cues: formal information</bold>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Between groups</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.462 (2)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">5.731</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">2.351 (2, 381)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">.1</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Within groups</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">928.660 (381)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">2.437</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<break/>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="9" rowspan="1">
<bold>Cues: informal information</bold>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Between groups</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.089 (2)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">28.044</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">21.152 (2, 381)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Within groups</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">505.159 (381)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">1.326</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<break/>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="9" rowspan="1">
<bold>Cues: environmental</bold>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Between groups</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">165.485 (2)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">82.743</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">8.396 (2, 381)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Within groups</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3754.887 (381)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">9.855</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<break/>
</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The least significant difference posthoc test was performed to clarify the direction of the ANOVA results (<xref rid="table4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). Individuals in cluster 1 perceived significantly fewer barriers than those in cluster 2 (<italic>P</italic>=.02). No significant differences was identified between cluster 1 and 3 or between cluster 2 and 3. For self-efficacy, cluster 1 had significantly higher scores than cluster 2 (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;.001) and cluster 3 (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;.001), while cluster 3 had significantly higher scores than cluster 2 (<italic>P&#x0003c;</italic>.001). Regarding recommendations from information sources, cluster 1 followed behavioral instructions recommended by informal sources more often than cluster 2 (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;.001) and cluster 3 (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;.001), while cluster 3 cluster followed the suggested behaviors more often than cluster 2 (<italic>P</italic>=.001). When making decisions about adopting protective measures, clusters 2 and 3 considered environmental cues more often than cluster 1 (<italic>P</italic>=.001 and <italic>P=</italic>.003, respectively). There was no significant difference between clusters 2 and 3 regarding the consideration of environmental cues. In order to clarify if there was an interaction between the 2 health belief variables that are significantly different among the 3 groups, perceived barriers and self-efficacy were included in the multinominal logistic regression analysis. The results showed that after controlling for perceived barriers, self-efficacy was still significantly associated with group differences (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;.001).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Results of 1-way ANOVA and Fisher least significant difference tests examining the impact of health belief model variables on the 3 engagement levels of protective behavior during COVID-19.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" width="1000" cellpadding="5" cellspacing="0" border="1"><col width="30" span="1"/><col width="280" span="1"/><col width="0" span="1"/><col width="320" span="1"/><col width="0" span="1"/><col width="200" span="1"/><col width="0" span="1"/><col width="170" span="1"/><thead><tr valign="top"><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Pairwise comparisons</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">Mean difference (SE)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">95% CI</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> value</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="top"><td colspan="8" rowspan="1">
<bold>Perceived barrier</bold>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cluster 1<sup>a</sup> vs cluster 2<sup>b</sup></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x02013;1.401 (0.590)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x02013;2.56 to &#x02013;0.24</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">.02</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cluster 1 vs cluster 3<sup>c</sup></td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x02013;0.438 (0.337)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x02013;1.10 to 0.23</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">.20</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cluster 2 vs cluster 3</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.963 (0.593)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x02013;0.20 to 2.13</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">.11</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="8" rowspan="1">
<bold>Self-efficacy</bold>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cluster 1 vs cluster 2</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">3.944 (0.613)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">2.74 to 5.15</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cluster 1 vs cluster 3</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">1.479 (0.351)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.79 to 2.17</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cluster 2 vs cluster 3</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x02013;2.465 (0.616)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x02013;3.68 to &#x02013;1.25</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="8" rowspan="1">
<bold>Cues: informal information</bold>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cluster 1 vs cluster 2</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">1.248 (0.215)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.82 to 1.67</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cluster 1 vs cluster 3</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.546 (0.123)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">0.30 to 0.79</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cluster 2 vs cluster 3</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x02013;0.702 (0.216)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x02013;1.13 to &#x02013;0.28</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">.001</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td colspan="8" rowspan="1">
<bold>Cues: environmental cue</bold>
</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cluster 1 vs cluster 2</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x02013;2.045 (0.587)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x02013;3.20 to &#x02013;0.89</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">.001</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cluster 1 vs cluster 3</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x02013;1.019 (0.336)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x02013;1.68 to &#x02013;0.36</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">.003</td></tr><tr valign="top"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<break/>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cluster 2 vs cluster 3</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">1.026 (0.590)</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">&#x02013;0.13 to 2.19</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">.08</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table4fn1"><p><sup>a</sup>Cluster 1: high engagement with protective behaviors.</p></fn><fn id="table4fn2"><p><sup>b</sup>Cluster 2: low engagement with protective behaviors.</p></fn><fn id="table4fn3"><p><sup>c</sup>Cluster 3: medium engagement with protective behaviors.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Categorical Data Analysis</title><p>Fisher exact and chi-square tests were used to evaluate whether categorical variables were significantly different among the clusters. The 3 clusters were significantly different based on sex (n=383, <italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sup>2</sup><sub>2</sub>=8.276, <italic>P</italic>=.02). Bonferroni correction showed that there were significantly more men (13.8%) than women (5.9%) in cluster 2. A Fisher exact test also revealed that the clusters were significantly different based on the place of residence (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;.001). Bonferroni correction showed that there were fewer participants from Taiwan (37.2%) than Japan (68.6%) and North American (71%) in cluster 1, and more from Taiwan (51.6%) than Japan (27.9%) and North American (22.6%) in cluster 3.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>Principal Findings</title><p>This study identified individuals with different levels of engagement in protective behaviors and the significantly different characteristics among them. We categorized individuals into 3 distinct groups: high, low, and medium levels of engagement in protective behaviors. That is, a group of individuals who stuck to all protective behaviors, while another group engaged in them significantly less. While most studies focused only on the adherence to a single behavior, our study was one of the few that addressed a group of protective measures. Observing and categorizing the adherence to behaviors collectively is particularly valuable when identifying possible populations or factors contributing to gaps in outbreak prevention. These results led to the second aim of our study, which addressed the more important question of the factors associated with the different levels of behavioral engagement.</p><p>Individuals from each group were significantly different from each other in terms of both intrinsic and extrinsic factors. Intrinsic factors included sex, perceived barriers, and self-efficacy, while extrinsic factors covered cues to action and residency. For the intrinsic factors, some of our results supported the current evidence, and some demonstrated variations compared to previous studies. Similar to other studies, the results of our study confirmed that sex played an important role in behavioral engagement during a pandemic. Specifically, women were more willing to perform protective measures than men [<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>-<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. This suggests that men may need more health education or incentives to enhance their self-protective behaviors. Prior studies have indicated that a high level of self-efficacy was strongly associated with self-protective behaviors [<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], which aligned with our finding that self-efficacy was a strong factor associated with engagement in protective behaviors, even after controlling for perceived barriers, another health belief variable that was significantly associated with group differences. Individuals with higher self-efficacy in performing protective behaviors and preventing infection are more willing to adopt protective behaviors.</p><p>Some studies conducted at the beginning of the COVID-19 pandemic showed that perceived risk, perceived susceptibility [<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], perceived severity [<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>], and perceived benefits [<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>] predicted behavioral engagement. In contrast, our study did not find significant differences in the aforementioned variables among the groups. Our results suggested that perceived barriers were a significant contributing factor [<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>,<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Several reasons may cause this variation, including the data collection time and location. Compared to other studies, we collected data during a relatively later period, approximately 6 months after the first reported COVID-19 case [<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. It is suspected that fear of a disease decreases when the public knows more about it. Thus, the role of fear-related concepts, such as perceived risk, perceived susceptibility, and perceived severity, in the adoption of preventive measures may not be as important as it was when COVID-19 was an unknown disease. Therefore, future studies should explore whether some intrinsic factors (eg, self-efficacy) remain fairly constant in their impact on protective behavior, while other factors may change over time or by disease status. Inconsistent results may also be related to location, as our study was the first to include a large population from Taiwan, which reported lower COVID-19 cases and deaths compared to other countries [<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. However, our results showed that Taiwanese people were a minority within the high engagement cluster. The relatively stable situation in Taiwan may not have triggered the constant urge to implement protective measures for infection prevention.</p><p>It is interesting to note that the 2 extrinsic factors, informal recommendations and environmental cues, had contrasting relationships with the adoption of protective measures. While it seems that all participants followed the recommendations from formal sources to a certain extent, our results suggested that individuals who practiced protective measures more often actually followed recommendations from informal sources more frequently. Alternatively, individuals who adopted protective measures at a medium or lower frequency were more likely to make relevant decisions based on environmental cues, such as the behaviors of surrounding people. There is a tendency for individuals with the highest adherence to protective behaviors to grasp all kinds of information and strictly follow the recommendations. However, individuals with lower adherence made their decisions more flexibly based on the changing situation. Future research should investigate whether these differences are affected by decision-making styles. For example, Scott and Bruce identified 5 distinct decision-making styles. Among these styles, the rational decision-making style is characterized as making decisions based on &#x0201c;a search for and logical evaluation of alternatives,&#x0201d; and the dependent style is &#x0201c;according to advice from others [<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>].&#x0201d;</p><p>This study had several limitations. First, we did not follow the behavioral changes and associated factors longitudinally. Future longitudinal studies are needed to understand the more dynamic phenomenon of the adoption of protective behaviors. Second, the web-based data collection method inevitably reached a younger population with a higher educational level. Thus, our results may not be generalizable to younger or older populations or populations with a lower educational level. The number of participants would be more representative of public opinion if the countries of origin and types of occupation were more equal in number. Specifically, while about a quarter of the study participants were health workers or students, their knowledge and training may have affected their health-related beliefs and behaviors. Future studies may explore if a health-related background can affect health beliefs and behaviors. Third, due to the lack of compensation and the length of the questionnaire, respondents&#x02019; motivation was weakened, and about 38% of the responses were incomplete. A similar phenomenon was also observed in other studies, which have shown an effective response rate of web-based surveys ranging from 10.2% to 58.6% [<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>This study is one of the few that used an HBM-based questionnaire to survey a collection of protective behaviors against COVID-19 and the associated factors across different countries. The results identified 3 groups of people with different levels of behavioral engagement. These individuals were significantly different from each other in terms of a number of the HBM concepts, including demographics, perceived barriers, perceived self-efficacy, and cues to action. Our results are worth considering in future policy-making and research. Specifically, enhancing self-efficacy may be a powerful way to facilitate engagement in protective measures, especially since self-efficacy continuously affects individuals&#x02019; adoption of behavior regardless of the stage of the pandemic. Tailored messages targeted at men during stable but ongoing pandemic conditions are important for minimizing the possible ignorance of these protective measures. Future studies are needed to clarify whether the degree of impact of the associating factors on protective behaviors changes over time, and whether decision-making styles contribute to the engagement with protective behaviors.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We acknowledge Mr. Hsu-Chiang Pan for survey validation and Dr. Winne Tung, Mr. William Lin, Mrs. Juri Matsuda, and Mr. Feng Chen for survey translation. We thank the National Taiwan University Hospital Statistical Consulting Unit and Dr. Chieh-Yu Liu for statistics consultation. We thank Miss Dona Chen for English Language editing and review.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>Conflicts of Interest: None declared.</p></fn></fn-group><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term id="abb1">HBM</term><def><p>health belief model</p></def></def-item><def-item><term id="abb2">WHO</term><def><p>World Health Organization</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><ref-list><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>COVID-19 surge makes Taiwan vulnerable</article-title><source>Emerald Expert Briefings</source><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2023-12-12</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.emerald.com/insight/content/doi/10.1108/OXAN-ES261623/full/html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.emerald.com/insight/content/doi/10.1108/OXAN-ES261623/full/html</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mallapaty</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>India's massive COVID surge puzzles scientists</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2021</year><month>04</month><volume>592</volume><issue>7856</issue><fpage>667</fpage><lpage>668</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/d41586-021-01059-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">33883710</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">10.1038/d41586-021-01059-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33883710</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Coronavirus disease (COVID-19) pandemic</article-title><source>World Health Organization</source><year>2021</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2023-12-12</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Guidelines for prevention of SARS-CoV-2 infection</article-title><source>Taiwan Centers for Disease Control</source><year>2020</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2023-12-12</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov.tw/File/Get/7qnbqMBoJRLr74SOuNdGvg" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cdc.gov.tw/File/Get/7qnbqMBoJRLr74SOuNdGvg</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) protect yourself</article-title><source>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</source><year>2020</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2021-03-31</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/prevent-getting-sick/prevention.html" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/prevent-getting-sick/prevention.html</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Guidelines for the use of non-pharmaceutical measures to delay and mitigate the impact of 2019-nCoV</article-title><source>European Centre for Disease Prevention and Control</source><year>2020</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2021-03-31</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ecdc.europa.eu/en/publications-data/guidelines-use-non-pharmaceutical-measures-delay-and-mitigate-impact-2019-ncov" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ecdc.europa.eu/en/publications-data/guidelines-use-non-pharmaceutical-measures-delay-and-mitigate-impact-2019-ncov</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dohle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Wingen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acceptance and adoption of protective measures during the COVID-19 pandemic: the role of trust in politics and trust in science</article-title><source>Soc Psychol Bull</source><year>2020</year><month>12</month><day>23</day><volume>15</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.32872/spb.4315</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Satchell</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Fido</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Latzman</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional fear predicts public health compliance in the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>PsyArXiv Preprints. Preprint posted online on December 12, 2023</source><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://osf.io/preprints/psyarxiv/jkfu3" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.31234/osf.io/jkfu3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>J&#x000f8;rgensen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bor</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Compliance without fear: individual-level protective behaviour during the first wave of the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>Br J Health Psychol</source><year>2021</year><month>05</month><volume>26</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>679</fpage><lpage>696</lpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://europepmc.org/abstract/MED/33763971" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bjhp.12519</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">33763971</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8250211</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33763971</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pagnini</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonanomi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tagliabue</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Balconi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertolotti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Confalonieri</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Dio</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Gilli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Graffigna</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Regalia</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Saita</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Villani</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Knowledge, concerns, and behaviors of individuals during the first week of the coronavirus disease 2019 pandemic in Italy</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><year>2020</year><month>07</month><day>01</day><volume>3</volume><issue>7</issue><fpage>e2015821</fpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://europepmc.org/abstract/MED/32706385" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2020.15821</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">32706385</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">2768619</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7382000</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32706385</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jadil</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouzir</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exploring the predictors of health-protective behavior during the COVID-19 pandemic: a multi-country comparison</article-title><source>Environ Res</source><year>2021</year><month>08</month><volume>199</volume><fpage>111376</fpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://europepmc.org/abstract/MED/34043969" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.envres.2021.111376</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">34043969</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">S0013-9351(21)00670-8</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9750228</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34043969</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ditsungnoen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenbaum</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Praphasiri</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Dawood</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoocharoen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindblade</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Muangchana</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Knowledge, attitudes and beliefs related to seasonal influenza vaccine among pregnant women in Thailand</article-title><source>Vaccine</source><year>2016</year><month>04</month><day>19</day><volume>34</volume><issue>18</issue><fpage>2141</fpage><lpage>2146</lpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S0264-410X(16)00119-5" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2016.01.056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">26854910</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">S0264-410X(16)00119-5</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4811693</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26854910</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fathian-Dastgerdi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Khoshgoftar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tavakoli</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaleh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors associated with preventive behaviors of COVID-19 among adolescents: applying the health belief model</article-title><source>Res Social Adm Pharm</source><year>2021</year><month>10</month><volume>17</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>1786</fpage><lpage>1790</lpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://europepmc.org/abstract/MED/33558153" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sapharm.2021.01.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">33558153</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">S1551-7411(21)00037-1</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7857029</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33558153</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shewasinad Yehualashet</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Asefa</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Mekonnen</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gemeda</surname><given-names>BN</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiferaw</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Aynalem</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bilchut</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Derseh</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>Mekuria</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Mekonnen</surname><given-names>WN</given-names></name><name><surname>Meseret</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tegegnework</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Abosetegn</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predictors of adherence to COVID-19 prevention measure among communities in North Shoa Zone, Ethiopia based on health belief model: a cross-sectional study</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2021</year><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e0246006</fpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://dx.plos.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0246006" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0246006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">33481962</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">PONE-D-20-27771</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7822535</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33481962</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaarsma</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Strachan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Davidson</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jerke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Beattie</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Duncan</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ski</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effective communication and ethical consent in decisions related to ICDs</article-title><source>Nat Rev Cardiol</source><year>2011</year><month>07</month><day>26</day><volume>8</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>694</fpage><lpage>705</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrcardio.2011.101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">21788961</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">nrcardio.2011.101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21788961</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Salkind</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Causal-comparative design</article-title><source>Encyclopedia of Research Design</source><year>2010</year><publisher-loc>Thousand Oaks</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Sage Publications</publisher-name><fpage>124</fpage><lpage>131</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mudgal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Thakur</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaur</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How to calculate sample size for observational and experiential nursing research studies?</article-title><source>Natl J Physiol Pharm Pharmacol</source><year>2019</year><fpage>1</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5455/njppp.2020.10.0930717102019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Factors influencing the protective behavior of individuals during COVID-19: a transnational survey</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2021</year><month>11</month><day>04</day><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>21654</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-01239-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-021-01239-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">34737327</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">10.1038/s41598-021-01239-w</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC8568907</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34737327</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glanz</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rimer</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Viswanath</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><source>Health Behavior and Health Education 4th Edition</source><year>2008</year><publisher-loc>San Francisco</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Jossey-Bass</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Golden</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Manika</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Self-efficacy, threat, knowledge and information receptivity: exploring pandemic prevention behaviors to enhance societal welfare</article-title><source>Acad Health Care Manag J</source><year>2011</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>44</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>DKC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagger</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Health beliefs of wearing facemasks for influenza A/H1N1 prevention: a qualitative investigation of Hong Kong older adults</article-title><source>Asia Pac J Public Health</source><year>2019</year><month>04</month><volume>31</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>246</fpage><lpage>256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1010539519844082</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">31007032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31007032</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosenstock</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Strecher</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Social learning theory and the Health Belief Model</article-title><source>Health Educ Q</source><year>1988</year><volume>15</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/109019818801500203</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">3378902</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3378902</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bandura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Self-efficacy: toward a unifying theory of behavioral change</article-title><source>Psychol Rev</source><year>1977</year><volume>84</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>191</fpage><lpage>215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0033-295x.84.2.191</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">847061</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luszczynska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarzer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Planning and self-efficacy in the adoption and maintenance of breast self-examination: a longitudinal study on self-regulatory cognitions</article-title><source>Psychol Health</source><year>2003</year><month>01</month><volume>18</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/0887044021000019358</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luszczynska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarzer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Conner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Normand</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Social Cognitive Theory</article-title><source>Predicting Health Behaviour: Research and Practice with Social Cognition Models. Second Edition</source><year>2005</year><publisher-loc>England, UK</publisher-loc><publisher-name>McGraw-Hill Education</publisher-name><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>169</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marlatt</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bear</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Quigley</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Bandura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Self-efficacy and addictive behavior</article-title><source>Self-Efficacy in Changing Societies</source><year>1995</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>315</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bish</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Michie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Demographic and attitudinal determinants of protective behaviours during a pandemic: a review</article-title><source>British J Health Psychol</source><year>2010</year><month>12</month><day>24</day><volume>15</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>797</fpage><lpage>824</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1348/135910710x485826</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowling</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Fielding</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Anxiety, worry and cognitive risk estimate in relation to protective behaviors during the 2009 influenza A/H1N1 pandemic in Hong Kong: ten cross-sectional surveys</article-title><source>BMC Infect Dis</source><year>2014</year><month>03</month><day>27</day><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>169</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2334-14-169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24674239</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Charrad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghazzali</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Boiteau</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Niknafs</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>NbClust: an R package for determining the relevant number of clusters in a data set</article-title><source>J Stat Soft</source><year>2014</year><volume>61</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18637/jss.v061.i06</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Papageorge</surname><given-names>NW</given-names></name><name><surname>Zahn</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Belot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>van den Broek-Altenburg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jamison</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tripodi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Socio-demographic factors associated with self-protecting behavior during the Covid-19 pandemic</article-title><source>J Popul Econ</source><year>2021</year><volume>34</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>691</fpage><lpage>738</lpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://europepmc.org/abstract/MED/33462529" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00148-020-00818-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">33462529</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">818</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7807230</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33462529</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chuang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tseng</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Social capital and health-protective behavior intentions in an influenza pandemic</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2015</year><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>e0122970</fpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://dx.plos.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0122970" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0122970</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">25874625</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">PONE-D-14-49564</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC4398366</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25874625</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khubchandani</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Saiki</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kandiah</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Masks, gloves, and the COVID-19 pandemic: rapid assessment of public behaviors in the United States</article-title><source>Epidemiologia</source><year>2020</year><month>11</month><day>05</day><volume>1</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.mdpi.com/resolver?pii=epidemiologia1010004" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/epidemiologia1010004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">36417208</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">epidemiologia1010004</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC9620870</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36417208</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of governmental and individual predictors on&#x000a0;COVID-19 protective behaviors in China: a path analysis model</article-title><source>Public Adm Rev</source><year>2020</year><volume>80</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>797</fpage><lpage>804</lpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://europepmc.org/abstract/MED/32836438" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/puar.13236</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">32836438</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">PUAR13236</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7276878</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32836438</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Davila</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Regis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kraus</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predictors of COVID-19 voluntary compliance behaviors: an international investigation</article-title><source>Glob Transit</source><year>2020</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>76</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S2589-7918(20)30009-8" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.glt.2020.06.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">32835202</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">S2589-7918(20)30009-8</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7318969</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32835202</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jose</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Narendran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bindu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Beevi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Benny</surname><given-names>P V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Public perception and preparedness for the pandemic COVID 19: a health belief model approach</article-title><source>Clin Epidemiol Glob Health</source><year>2021</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S2213-3984(20)30166-4" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cegh.2020.06.009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">33521389</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">S2213-3984(20)30166-4</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7837111</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33521389</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wise</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zbozinek</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Michelini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mobbs</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Changes in risk perception and self-reported protective behaviour during the first week of the COVID-19 pandemic in the United States</article-title><source>R Soc Open Sci</source><year>2020</year><month>09</month><volume>7</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>200742</fpage><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/abs/10.1098/rsos.200742?url_ver=Z39.88-2003&#x00026;rfr_id=ori:rid:crossref.org&#x00026;rfr_dat=cr_pub0pubmed" ext-link-type="uri"/>
</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsos.200742</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">33047037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">rsos200742</pub-id><!--<pub-id pub-id-type="pmcid">PMC7540790</pub-id>--><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33047037</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><article-title>Situation report - 94</article-title><source>World Health Organization</source><year>2020</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2023-12-12</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.who.int/publications/m/item/situation-report---94" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/publications/m/item/situation-report---94</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Howell</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The countries who've handled coronavirus the best - and worst</article-title><source>MoveHub</source><year>2023</year><date-in-citation content-type="access-date">2023-12-12</date-in-citation><comment>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.movehub.com/blog/best-and-worst-covid-responses/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.movehub.com/blog/best-and-worst-covid-responses/</ext-link>
</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruce</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decision-making style: the development and assessment of a new measure</article-title><source>Educ Psychol Meas</source><year>2016</year><month>07</month><day>02</day><volume>55</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>818</fpage><lpage>831</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0013164495055005017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name><name><surname>Benjamens</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>El Moumni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lange</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Pol</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global overview of response rates in patient and health care professional surveys in surgery: a systematic review</article-title><source>Ann Surg</source><year>2022</year><volume>275</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>e75</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/sla.0000000000004078</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32649458</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hardigan</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Popovici</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Carvajal</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Response rate, response time, and economic costs of survey research: a randomized trial of practicing pharmacists</article-title><source>Res Social Adm Pharm</source><year>2016</year><volume>12</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.sapharm.2015.07.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="medline">26329534</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pii">S1551-7411(15)00127-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26329534</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
