<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="issn">2168-8184</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cureus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2168-8184</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cureus</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Palo Alto (CA)</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38125217</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC10732474</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.49123</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Ophthalmology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Dry Eye Symptoms in Jazan University Lecturers During the COVID-19 Pandemic Using Ocular Surface Disease Index (OSDI)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Muacevic</surname><given-names>Alexander</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>John R</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Abuallut</surname><given-names>Ismail</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Hurissi</surname><given-names>Eman</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Khawaji</surname><given-names>Ethar A</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Khormi</surname><given-names>Ghada</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Othathi</surname><given-names>Rahaf</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Azyabi</surname><given-names>Fahad Y</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Awlaqi</surname><given-names>Abdulaziz</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bakreen</surname><given-names>Mohammed Ghazi M</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ghulaysi</surname><given-names>Saleh</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-4" ref-type="aff">4</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label>
Ophthalmology, Jazan University, Jazan, SAU </aff><aff id="aff-2">
<label>2</label>
Medicine and Surgery, Jazan University, Jazan, SAU </aff><aff id="aff-3">
<label>3</label>
Emergency Medicine, Jazan University, Jazan, SAU </aff><aff id="aff-4">
<label>4</label>
College of Medicine, Jazan University, Jazan, SAU </aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
Eman Hurissi <email>eman.harisi1998@gmail.com</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>20</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><month>11</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e49123</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2023, Abuallut et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Abuallut et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License CC-BY 4.0., which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://www.cureus.com/articles/194320-dry-eye-symptoms-in-jazan-university-lecturers-during-the-covid-19-pandemic-using-ocular-surface-disease-index-osdi">This article is available from https://www.cureus.com/articles/194320-dry-eye-symptoms-in-jazan-university-lecturers-during-the-covid-19-pandemic-using-ocular-surface-disease-index-osdi</self-uri><abstract><p>Background</p><p>Dry eye disease (DED) is a disease of the ocular surface charac&#x000ad;terized by instability of the tear film, which causes ocular surface inflamma&#x000ad;tion and damage that leads to ocular symptoms, discomfort, and visual disturbance. Dry eye is a common ocular condition and a major reason for ophthalmologist visits. Compulsory e-learning has arisen in colleges and schools with the coronavirus disease 19 (COVID-19) pandemic as a tool for new teaching and learning. DED is an emerging threat to public health and is directly proportional to digital screen viewing length. DED diagnosis flowchart begins with history-taking of associated risk factors and a screening test by Ocular Surface Disease Index (OSDI). Therefore, we aim to assess the prevalence and the severity of DED among Jazan University lecturers and to identify the associated risk factors.</p><p>Methods&#x000a0;</p><p>A total of 150 participants were recruited for this descriptive, observational study. Participants completed an online questionnaire that contained questions about sociodemographics, electronic devices they used, the average number of hours of use in a day as well as the distance and posture while reading, and factors that may influence visual symptoms&#x000a0;such as the use of glasses, frequent changes in glasses prescription and DED symptoms.</p><p>Results</p><p>The results showed that the prevalence of DED was high, with 23% of participants having mild DED, 12% having moderate DED, and 29% having severe DED. DED was associated with a number of sociodemographic and clinical factors, including younger age, female gender, occupation as a lecturer, and use of digital devices.</p><p>Conclusion</p><p>This study highlights the need to develop strategies to prevent and control DED among high-risk groups, such as university lecturers. Future research should focus on identifying more effective ways to prevent DED and to improve the management of DED symptoms.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>jazan</kwd><kwd>pandemic</kwd><kwd>covid-19</kwd><kwd>ded</kwd><kwd>osdi</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Multiple factors play roles in the development of dry eye disease (DED). It's a disease of the ocular surface characterized by instability of the tear film, which causes ocular surface inflammation and damage that leads to ocular symptoms, discomfort, and visual disturbance. New data suggests that neurosensory abnormalities are included in the definition of DED&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>].</p><p>The main symptom of DED is dryness and a gritty feeling; in addition, the complaint includes searing or itching in the eyes, foreign body sensation, extra tearing, discomfort, redness of the eyes, and photophobia. [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].&#x000a0;In 2017, Stapleton et al. conducted a review of the available evidence on dry eye. The prevalence of DED ranges from 5 to 50 percent globally, according to epidemiological studies. The prevalence was higher in women and the elderly population. Moreover, DED is more prevalent in Asian countries compared to Western countries. It's associated with lower quality of life and reduced work productivity, particularly through vision loss and pain [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. DED is dramatically increasing in Saudi Arabia, and it's a common ocular condition and a major reason for ophthalmologist visits. The age-adjusted DED prevalence in the Saudi Arabian population ranged from 7% to 32.1%&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. DED has been associated with comorbidities, including musculoskeletal, neurological, ophthalmic, allergic,&#x000a0;physical, dermatological, and atopic disorders [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>].&#x000a0;</p><p>In 2014, Paulsen et al. conducted a cohort study to investigate the risk factors for DED. The results of the study showed that significant associations were found with female sex, current contact lens use, allergies, arthritis, thyroid disease, antihistamine use, and steroid use&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Recent studies published to investigate the prevalence of DED during the COVID-19 pandemic and the effect of e-learning on the development of DED In 2022, Wejdan Alnahdi&#x000a0;et al. conducted a study to measure the prevalence of DED and its association with screen time in the pediatric population during the COVID-19 pandemic using the Ocular Surface Disease Index (OSDI) questionnaire. The results of the study showed an increase in the symptoms of DED during the COVID-19 pandemic due to prolonged screen time [<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Another study conducted by Santa-Cruz-Pavlovich et al. in 2023 aimed to assess the difference in the incidence of DED since the onset of online courses started using OSDI. The results of this study showed that since the online courses started, university students have complained of severe DED symptoms [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. Moreover, in 2023, Lulla&#x000a0;et al. conducted a study to investigate the changes in the prevalence of DED among medical students during COVID-19 and compare it to pre-pandemic periods using a modified OSDI questionnaire. The prevalence of DED was 41.5 during the pre-pandemic period and 55.19 during the pandemic period [<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Therefore, we aim to assess the prevalence and severity of DED among Jazan University lecturers and identify the associated risk factors.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><p>A cross-sectional descriptive study was conducted at Jazan University, Jizan City, Kingdom of Saudi Arabia, in 2021. The study applied to all lecturers at Jazan University who used e-learning during the COVID-19 pandemic, including males, females, Saudis, and non-Saudis. The research team translated previously OSDI-used English into Arabic.&#x000a0;The questionnaire is divided into three parts. The first part included questions on sociodemographic characteristics. In the second part, participants were asked questions about the electronic devices they used, the average number of hours of use in a day, as well as the distance and posture while reading. Additional information on factors that might have influenced visual symptoms was collected, such as the use of glasses, frequent changes in glasses prescription, and the use of smartphones at bedtime with lights switched off. The third part assessed DED symptoms using a series of questions about visual symptoms such as headaches, blurred vision, fatigue, etc. Each question had five answer choices from zero to four (0 = never, 1 = mild, 2 = moderate, 3 = severe, 4 = very severe). Data&#x000a0;were&#x000a0;collected in an Excel sheet (Microsoft, Redmond, Washington), double-checked, coded, and transferred to statistical software for analysis (SPSS version 25; IBM Inc., Armonk, New York). For descriptive statistics, the results were presented as frequencies and percentages (demographic and eye-related variables),&#x000a0;mean&#x000a0;and standard deviations&#x000a0;(OSDI scores), and figures (OSDI severity). The data were&#x000a0;then subjected to a normality test, which revealed a non-normal distribution (Shapiro-Wilk test, p&#x0003c;0.05). Accordingly, the non-parametric Mann-Whitney U test was used to determine the differences in OSDI scores between the different categories.&#x000a0;A p-value of&#x000a0;0.05 was considered significant. Approval for this study was obtained from the Ethical Committee of Jazan University (approval No. REC-43/02/006). Before data collection, patients' permission was obtained. The participant's data are stored with strict confidentiality in a computerized&#x000a0;registry.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>A total of 150 faculty members completed the survey. About two-thirds (70.0%, n=145) were non-medical, while more than half (56.0%, n=84) were&#x000a0;&#x02264;40 years old. The majority of the participants were female (76.7%, n=115), lecturers (86.0%, n=129), non-smokers (95.3%, n=143), and had no systemic disease (80.7%, n=121). More details are presented in Table <xref rid="TAB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Characteristics of the study population</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage (%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Specialty</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medical</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-medical</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.0</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Age</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;40 yrs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.0</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;40 yrs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.0</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Sex</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.3</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">115</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.7</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Faculty position</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lecturer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">129</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.0</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Teaching assistant</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Smoking</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">143</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.3</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Have systemic disease</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.3</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">121</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">80.7</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The degree of OSDI severity among the participants is shown in Figure <xref rid="FIG1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. Over one-third (36.7%) of the participants were normal, (22.7%) had mild OSDI, 12% had moderate OSDI, and 28.6% had severe OSDI.</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Distribution of OSDI severity degrees among the study population</title><p>OSDI -&#x000a0;Ocular Surface Disease Index</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0015-00000049123-i01" position="float"/></fig><p>As shown in Table <xref rid="TAB2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, about one-third (32.7%) of the participants used eye medications, 28.0% had previous ocular surgery, and 70.0% claimed that they felt eye fatigue (dryness).&#x000a0;Fifty-eight (38.7%) participants used mobile phones for over six hours before COVID-19. However, this number increased substantially to 95 (63.3%) participants after COVID-19. Forty-one (27.3%) participants maintained a distance of 25 cm between the eye and mobile, while 109 (72.7%) maintained a higher distance. Most participants (76.7%) reported using their mobile before bedtime. Half of the participants (50%) wore eyeglasses, and 44.7% changed the size of their glasses after COVID-19.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Responses of the participants to the eye-related variables </title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Frequency</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentage (%)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Using eye medication</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">101</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67.3</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Had ocular surgery</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.0</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">108</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.0</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Feeling eye fatigue (dryness)</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">105</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.0</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.0</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Time spent using mobile before COVID-19</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;6 hrs/day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.3</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;6 hrs/day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">38.7</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Time spent using mobile after COVID-19</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;6 hrs/day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;6 hrs/day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.3</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Distance between eye and mobile</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 cm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.3</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;25 cm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">109</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.7</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Using mobile before bedtime</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">115</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">76.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.3</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Wearing eyeglasses</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.0</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.0</td></tr><tr><td colspan="3" rowspan="1">Changed the size of the glasses</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.7</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.3</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Subjects in the medical field showed higher OSDI scores (26.8&#x000b1;23.4) than those in the non-medical field (24.5&#x000b1;19.0) with (p=0.984). Younger subjects (&#x02264;40 years) reported higher OSDI scores than older subjects&#x000a0;(26.5&#x000b1;21.4 compared to 23.4&#x000b1;19.0; p=0.374). In addition, teaching assistants, non-smokers, and subjects with systemic disease recorded higher OSDI scores than their counterparts but with&#x000a0;(p&#x0003e;0.05). Which, as shown, indicated&#x000a0;no significant difference. However, Female subjects reported significantly higher OSDI scores than males (27.4&#x000b1;21.2 compared to 17.7&#x000b1;15.4; p=0.016). More details are presented in Table <xref rid="TAB3" ref-type="table">3</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Differences in OSDI scores among participants according to the demographic variables</title><p>OSDI -&#x000a0;Ocular Surface Disease Index</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Item</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Response</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">OSDI score</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean&#x000b1;SD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Specialty</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medical</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.8&#x000b1;23.4</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.984</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-medical</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.5&#x000b1;19.0</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Age</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;40 yrs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.5&#x000b1;21.4</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.374</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;40 yrs</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.4&#x000b1;19.0</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Sex</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Male</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.7&#x000b1;15.4</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.016</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.4&#x000b1;21.2</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Faculty position</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lecturer</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.9&#x000b1;20.2</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.814</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Teaching \ssistant</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.8&#x000b1;22.0</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Smoking</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.8&#x000b1;19.0</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.964</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.2&#x000b1;20.5</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Have systemic disease</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.0&#x000b1;21.7</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.161</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.0&#x000b1;19.9</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Subjects who used eye medications scored higher OSDI than their counterparts but with (28.9&#x000b1;21.2 compared to 23.3&#x000b1;19.8; p=0.089). Similarly, subjects with previous ocular surgery, who spent &#x0003e;6 hours/day using mobile before and after COVID-19, and who maintained a 25 cm distance between the eye and mobile, scored higher OSDI than their counterparts but with&#x000a0;(p&#x0003e;0.0%) which lastly indicated no significant difference. However, subjects who felt eye fatigue, wore eyeglasses, and changed the size of their glasses recorded significantly higher OSDI scores than their counterparts (P&#x0003c; 0.05). On the other hand, subjects who used mobile before bedtime recorded lower OSDI scores than their counterparts (24.6&#x000b1;20.5 compared to 27.2&#x000b1;20.1) but with no significant difference (p=0.365).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Differences in OSDI scores among participants according to the eye-related variables</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Item&#x000a0;</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Response</td><td colspan="2" rowspan="1">OSDI score</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean&#x000b1;SD</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-value</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Using eye medication</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.9&#x000b1;21.2</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.089</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.3&#x000b1;19.8</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Had ocular surgery</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.0&#x000b1;18.8</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.220</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.4&#x000b1;21.0</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Time spent using mobile before COVID</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;6 hrs/day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.1&#x000b1;19.3</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.773</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;6 hrs/day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.3&#x000b1;22.1</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Time spent using mobile after COVID</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02264;6 hrs/day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.6&#x000b1;18.5</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.690</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;6 hrs/day</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.1&#x000b1;21.4</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Distance between eye and mobile</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 cm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.4&#x000b1;23.5</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.577</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;25 cm</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.3&#x000b1;19.1</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Feeling eye fatigue (dryness)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.6&#x000b1;20.1</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.1&#x000b1;18.9</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Wearing eyeglasses</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.1&#x000b1;21.2</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.3&#x000b1;17.8</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Changed the size of your glasses</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.3&#x000b1;22.8</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.000</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.4&#x000b1;16.1</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">Using mobile before bedtime</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.6&#x000b1;20.5</td><td rowspan="2" colspan="1">0.365</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.2&#x000b1;20.1</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>During the COVID-19 pandemic, several countries, including Saudi Arabia, imposed measures to control the spread of the virus. One of these measures is lockdown. The educational system in schools and universities has been changed to&#x000a0;online.&#x000a0;Increased screen and electronic device exposure time can create a longer blinking interval, which can increase tear evaporation and lead to the development of DED [<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. In 2017, the prevalence of DED, according to Dry Eye Workshop (DEWS) II, ranged from 20% to 50% [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. In our study, we aimed to assess the prevalence and severity of DED among Jazan University lecturers during the COVID-19 pandemic and identify the associated risk factors based on the OSDI questionnaire. The OSDI is a tool used to measure DED-related symptoms' severity and their related visual function impairment. OSDI has high sensitivity and specificity, reaching 60% and 79%, respectively&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p><p>In our study, 150 faculty members participated in filling out the OSDI form. According to the OSDI diagnostic criteria, over one-third (37% of the participants) had no DED symptoms. Nearly two-thirds (63%) of the participants experienced DED with various degrees of severity during the pandemic. Furthermore, we found that the degree of OSDI severity among the participants was 23% mild OSDI, 12% moderate OSDI, and 29% severe OSDI. High cases of DED during the pandemic have been reported in many studies. In 2022, a study conducted by Alnahdi&#x000a0;et al. aimed to measure the prevalence of DED and its association with screen time in the pediatric population during the COVID-19 pandemic using the OSDI questionnaire. The results of the study showed that 76.1% of participants had symptomatic DED, while 23.9% had no DED. The authors found an increase in the symptoms of DED during the COVID-19 pandemic due to prolonged screen time exposure [<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Another study conducted in 2022 by Garca-Ayuso&#x000a0;et al. aimed to assess the prevalence of DED using the OSDI questionnaire among university students. The results of the study showed that the prevalence of symptomatic DED was 51.8%&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Moreover, in 2023,&#x000a0;Lulla&#x000a0;et al. conducted a study to investigate the changes in the prevalence of DED among medical students during the COVID-19 pandemic and compare it to pre-pandemic periods using a modified OSDI questionnaire. The prevalence of DED was 41.5 during the pre-pandemic period and 55.19 during the pandemic period [<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Another study conducted by Pavlovich et al. in 2023 aimed to assess the difference in the incidence of DED since the onset of online courses using the OSDI questionnaire. The results of this study showed that since the online courses started, university students have complained of severe DED symptoms [<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p><p>Globally, the prevalence of DED was higher in women and the elderly population [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. However, our study showed a higher OSDI score in females and younger subjects, and our results are consistent with the results of the Tripathi et al. study that was conducted in 2022. The study aimed to determine the magnitude and severity of DED. The study results reported an increase in the prevalence of symptomatic DED from 25% to 41% in&#x000a0;young participants&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p><p>A large number of cross-sectional studies have explained the association between digital screen time exposure and DED. A study conducted among 3549 office workers who use visual display terminals (VDTs) by Uchino&#x000a0;et al. aimed to assess the prevalence of DED and its associated risk factors. The results of the study showed that the participants who used digital screens for more than four hours per day experienced severe symptoms of dry eye [<xref rid="REF14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Moreover, Lulla et al.'s study revealed an increase in DED symptoms by 1.7 times during the pandemic period in students who spent more than five hours on a digital screen [<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Also, Iqbal et al. Found an association between an increased risk of DED development and an increase in screen time for more than three hours [<xref rid="REF15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. These findings are consistent with our results that showed higher OSDI scores in subjects who spent more than six&#x000a0;hours per day using the mobile before the pandemic (25.3 OSDI score) and after the pandemic (26.1 OSDI score). The OSDI score for the subjects who spent more than six hours/day using mobile was 25.1 before the pandemic and 23.6 after the pandemic. However, no significant difference has been shown in our study.</p><p>In our study, we found higher OSDI scores in the participants who had undergone previous ocular surgery. Ishrat et al. found similar results in a study aimed at investigating the incidence of DED after cataract surgeries. Fifty percent of the patients developed DED at one&#x0202f; month, and 9% developed DED at three&#x0202f;months after surgery&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].</p><p>In addition, in 2012, Fraunfelder&#x000a0;et al. conducted a review that explained the relationship between DED and the use of multiple systemic and topical ocular medications. The authors found that ocular medications, either systemic or topical, can cause DED through various mechanisms [<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. This result is consistent with our results, which found a higher OSDI score in participants who use ocular medications.</p><p>Moreover, we found a higher OSDI score in subjects who had a history of systemic diseases. In 2021, Yu&#x000a0;et al. conducted a large multi-center randomized clinical trial on DED patients. The authors found that patients who have systemic diseases experienced more severe DED signs in comparison with patients without systemic diseases [<xref rid="REF18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p><p>Furthermore, in our study, we found that higher OSDI scores were reported in subjects in the medical field, teaching assistants, and non-smokers. Regarding the association between DED and smoking, Tariq et al. conducted a meta-analysis, and the results indicate that smoking doesn't increase the risk for DED [<xref rid="REF19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].</p><p>This study has limitations; there is possible self-selection bias as the survey was distributed online. However, to the best of our knowledge, this is the first study that analyzed the prevalence of DED using a standard tool such as OSDI among Jazan University lecturers during the COVID-19 pandemic. Further, this study highlighted the high prevalence of DED associated with e-learning and called attention to the importance of early diagnosis and management of DED, especially in the highest-risk group, to prevent some of the severe complications.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>In this study, we found a high prevalence of DED with various degrees of severity according to OSDI. Younger age, female gender, occupation as a lecturer, and use of digital devices were associated with DED. This study highlights the need to develop strategies to prevent and control DED among high-risk groups, such as university lecturers. Future research should focus on identifying more effective ways to prevent DED and to improve the management of DED symptoms.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Concept and design:</bold>&#x000a0; Eman Hurissi, Ismail Abuallut, Ethar A. Khawaji, Ghada Khormi, Rahaf Othathi, Fahad Y. Azyabi, Abdulaziz Awlaqi, Mohammed Ghazi M. Bakreen, Saleh Ghulaysi</p><p><bold>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</bold>&#x000a0; Eman Hurissi, Ismail Abuallut, Ethar A. Khawaji, Ghada Khormi, Rahaf Othathi, Fahad Y. Azyabi, Abdulaziz Awlaqi, Mohammed Ghazi M. Bakreen, Saleh Ghulaysi</p><p><bold>Drafting of the manuscript:</bold>&#x000a0; Eman Hurissi, Ismail Abuallut, Ethar A. Khawaji, Ghada Khormi, Rahaf Othathi, Fahad Y. Azyabi, Abdulaziz Awlaqi, Mohammed Ghazi M. Bakreen, Saleh Ghulaysi</p><p><bold>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</bold>&#x000a0; Eman Hurissi, Ismail Abuallut, Ethar A. Khawaji, Ghada Khormi, Rahaf Othathi, Fahad Y. Azyabi, Abdulaziz Awlaqi, Mohammed Ghazi M. Bakreen, Saleh Ghulaysi</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Human Ethics</title><fn fn-type="other"><p>Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study. Ethical Committee of Jazan University issued approval REC -43/02/006</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Animal Ethics</title><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Animal subjects:</bold> All authors have confirmed that this study did not involve animal subjects or tissue.</p></fn></fn-group><notes><fn-group content-type="competing-interests"><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn></fn-group></notes><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="REF1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>TFOS DEWS II definition and classification report</article-title><source>The ocular surface</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Akpek</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>276</fpage><lpage>283</lpage><volume>15</volume><year>2017</year><uri xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jtos.2017.05.008">http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.jtos.2017.05.008 </uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28736335</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Dry eye and quality of life</article-title><source>Archivos de la Sociedad Espanola de Oftalmologia</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Garcia-Catalan</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jerez-Olivera</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Benitez-Del-Castillo-Sanchez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>451</fpage><lpage>458</lpage><volume>84</volume><year>2009</year><uri xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.4321/s0365-66912009000900004">https://doi.org/10.4321/s0365-66912009000900004 </uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19809924</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>TFOS DEWS II epidemiology report</article-title><source>Ocul Surf</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Stapleton</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bunya</surname><given-names>VY</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>334</fpage><lpage>365</lpage><volume>15</volume><year>2017</year><uri xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtos.2017.05.003">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtos.2017.05.003</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28736337</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Prevalence and risk factors of dry eye symptoms in a Saudi Arabian population</article-title><source>Middle East Afr J Ophthalmol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Alshamrani</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Almousa</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Almulhim</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><volume>24</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28936049</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Prevalence of dry eye symptoms and its risk factors among patients of King Abdulaziz Specialist Hospital (Taif), Saudi Arabia</article-title><source>Saud J Health Sci</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Alhamyani</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kalakattawi</surname><given-names>RMN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kalakattawi</surname><given-names>AMN</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>140</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><volume>6</volume><year>2017</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Prevalence and risk factors of dry eye in 79,866 participants of the population-based Lifelines cohort study in the Netherlands</article-title><source>Ocul Surf</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Vehof</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Snieder</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jansonius</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>83</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><volume>19</volume><year>2021</year><uri xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtos.2020.04.005">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jtos.2020.04.005</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32376389</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Dry eye in the beaver dam offspring study: prevalence, risk factors, and health-related quality of life</article-title><source>Am J Ophthalmol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Paulsen</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cruickshanks</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dalton</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>799</fpage><lpage>806</lpage><volume>157</volume><year>2014</year><uri xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajo.2013.12.023">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajo.2013.12.023</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24388838</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Relationship between screen time and dry eye symptoms during the COVID-19 pandemic in the pediatric population of the Western Region of Saudi Arabia</article-title><source>Cureus</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Alnahdi</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hadrawi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Danish</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alghamdi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Taher</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alfaraidi</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alageel</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><volume>14</volume><year>2022</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Online education and dry eye disease during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>Revista mexicana de</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Santa-Cruz-Pavlovich</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bola&#x000f1;os-Chang</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>240</lpage><volume>96</volume><year>2022</year><uri xlink:href="https://www.scielo.org.mx/pdf/rmof/v96n6/2604-1227-rmof-96-06-231.pdf">https://www.scielo.org.mx/pdf/rmof/v96n6/2604-1227-rmof-96-06-231.pdf </uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Dry eye among medical students before and during COVID-19</article-title><source>Indian J Ophthalmol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Lulla</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Loganathan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Balan</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Swathi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1468</fpage><lpage>1471</lpage><volume>71</volume><year>2023</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37026284</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Assessment of dry eye symptoms among university students during the COVID-19 pandemic</article-title><source>Clin Exp Optom</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-Ayuso</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Di Pierdomenico</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moya-Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Valiente-Soriano</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Galindo-Romero</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sobrado-Calvo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>507</fpage><lpage>513</lpage><volume>105</volume><year>2022</year><uri xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1080/08164622.2021.1945411">https://doi.org/10.1080/08164622.2021.1945411</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34279190</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Reliability and validity of the Ocular Surface Disease Index</article-title><source>Arch Ophthalmol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Schiffman</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Christianson</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jacobsen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hirsch</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reis</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>615</fpage><lpage>621</lpage><volume>118</volume><year>2000</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10815152</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Dry eye disease related to digital screen exposure in medical students</article-title><source>Pan-Am J Ophthalmol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Tripathi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Agarwal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kharya</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>35</fpage><volume>4</volume><year>2022</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Prevalence of dry eye disease among Japanese visual display terminal users</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Uchino</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schaumberg</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dogru</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>1982</fpage><lpage>1988</lpage><volume>115</volume><year>2008</year><uri xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ophtha.2008.06.022">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ophtha.2008.06.022</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18708259</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Computer vision syndrome survey among the medical students in Sohag University Hospital, Egypt</article-title><source>J Ophthalmol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Iqbal</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>El-Massry</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Elagouz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><volume>8</volume><year>2018</year><uri xlink:href="http://OphthalmologyResearch:AnInternationalJournal">http://Ophthalmology Research: An International Journal</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Incidence and pattern of dry eye after cataract surgery</article-title><source>Saudi J Ophthalmol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Ishrat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nema</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chandravanshi</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>34</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><volume>33</volume><year>2019</year><uri xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.sjopt.2018.10.009">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.sjopt.2018.10.009</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30930661</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The role of medications in causing dry eye</article-title><source>J Ophthalmol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Fraunfelder</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sciubba</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mathers</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>285851</fpage><volume>2012</volume><year>2012</year><uri xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1155/2012/285851">https://doi.org/10.1155/2012/285851</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23050121</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Systemic conditions associated with severity of dry eye signs and symptoms in the dry eye assessment and management study</article-title><source>Ophthalmology</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bunya</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maguire</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Asbell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ying</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1384</fpage><lpage>1392</lpage><volume>128</volume><year>2021</year><uri xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ophtha.2021.03.030">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ophtha.2021.03.030</uri><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33785415</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Association of dry eye disease with smoking: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Indian J Ophthalmol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Tariq</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Amin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mohiuddin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>1892</fpage><lpage>1904</lpage><volume>70</volume><year>2022</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35647954</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
