<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="methods-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Psychiatry</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Psychiatry</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-0640</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38125285</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC10732355</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpsyt.2023.1253727</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Psychiatry</subject><subj-group><subject>Study Protocol</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A feasibility study of goal-directed network-based real-time fMRI neurofeedback for anhedonic depression</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Xiaoxia</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/242890/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/funding-acquisition/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Xiaoyan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/resources/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Jing</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/resources/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>Yushun</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/formal-analysis/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/software/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/visualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Zhengzhi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c002" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/974397/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/resources/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Basic Psychology, School of Psychology, Army Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Chongqing</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Chongqing City Mental Health Center, Southwest University</institution>, <addr-line>Chongqing</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Department of Radiology, Southwest Hospital, Army Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Chongqing</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>Department of Medical Equipment and Metrology, College of Biomedical Engineering, Army Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Chongqing</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><sup>5</sup><institution>School of Psychology, Army Medical University</institution>, <addr-line>Chongqing</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Alessandro Colasanti, Brighton and Sussex Medical School, United Kingdom</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Laurel Morris, Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai, United States; David MA Mehler, University Hospital RWTH Aachen, Germany; Apurva Watve, University of Zurich, Switzerland</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Xiaoxia Wang <email>lemonowang@gmail.com</email></corresp><corresp id="c002">Zhengzhi Feng <email>fzz@tmmu.edu.cn</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>05</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>1253727</elocation-id><history>
<date date-type="received"><day>07</day><month>7</month><year>2023</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>06</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date>
</history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2023 Wang, Zhou, Li, Gong and Feng.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Wang, Zhou, Li, Gong and Feng</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Anhedonia is a hallmark symptom of depression that often lacks adequate interventions. The translational gap remains in clinical treatments based on neural substrates of anhedonia. Our pilot study found that depressed individuals depended less on goal-directed (GD) reward learning (RL), with reduced reward prediction error (RPE) BOLD signal. Previous studies have found that anhedonia is related to abnormal activities and/or functional connectivities of the central executive network (CEN) and salience network (SN), both of which belong to the goal-directed system. In addition, it was found that real-time functional magnetic resonance imaging (rt-fMRI) neurofeedback (NF) could improve the balance between CEN and SN in healthy individuals. Therefore, we speculate that rt-fMRI NF of the CEN and SN associated with the GD system may improve depressive and/or anhedonic symptoms. Therefore, this study (1) will examine individuals with anhedonic depression using GD-RL behavioral task, combined with functional magnetic resonance imaging and computational modeling to explore the role of CEN/SN deficits in anhedonic depression; and (2) will utilize network-based rt-fMRI NF to investigate whether it is feasible to regulate the differential signals of brain CEN/SN of GD system through rt-fMRI NF to alleviate depressive and/or anhedonic symptoms. This study highlights the need to elucidate the intervention effects of rt-fMRI NF and the underlying computational network neural mechanisms.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>rt-fMRI neurofeedback</kwd><kwd>CEN/SN</kwd><kwd>prediction error</kwd><kwd>anhedonia</kwd><kwd>goal-directed system</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>This research was financially supported by the Talented Youth Foundation of AMU (PRC) (no. 410301053421) and the Natural Science Foundation of China (NSFC no. 81971278).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="6"/><ref-count count="59"/><page-count count="10"/><word-count count="7437"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Mood Disorders</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Anhedonia is a transdiagnostic psychiatric symptom typical of psychiatric disorders, such as depression, posttraumatic stress disorder (PTSD), and schizophrenia according to the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders, Fifth Edition (DSM-5), and is associated with an elevated risk of suicide and chronicity of the disease (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). The biological endophenotypes of anhedonia include reduced anticipation of upcoming rewards, reduced experienced pleasure during the reward presentation, and impaired reward learning (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Specifically, reward learning (RL) is the ability to adapt to the contingencies between action and the reward feedback, with two systems working together: The habitual system supports routine responses to deal with regular situations, while the goal-directed (GD) system is sensitive to environmental change to flexibly adapt to unfamiliar situations. The deficits in goal-directed systems play an important role across the lifespan and in various mental disorders, such as subclinical depression, trauma-related disorders, addiction, and obsessive-compulsive disorder (OCD) (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Specifically, goal-directed reward learning (GD-RL) could discriminate between depressed patients and healthy controls using a machine learning algorithm (Naive Bayes) and could predict the concurrent depressive symptoms and depression traits 1 year later (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). To sum up, deficits in the goal-directed system may contribute to depression during both the symptomatic and clinical phases. However, a translational gap still remains in the clinical imaging study of the goal-directed system (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>).</p><p>Neurally, the goal-directed system may involve functional interactions between the central execution network (CEN) and the salience network (SN). The CEN, including the medial frontal gyrus (MFG), superior frontal gyrus (SFG), and the anterior cingulate cortex (ACC), especially the perigenual ACC (pgACC), is essential for external, goal-directed cognitive processes (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). The SN, including the anterior insula (aINS), the dorsal anterior cingulate cortex (dACC), the amygdala (AMY), the substantia nigra/ventral tegmental area (SN/VTA), ventral striatum (VS), and thalamus, is responsible for detecting salient stimuli in the environment and allocating cognitive resources to facilitate goal-directed behavior (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). SN may function as a gate to detect the salience of stimuli and co-activate task-relevant networks such as CEN to facilitate goal-directed behavior (<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>), through the shift between default mode network (DMN) and CEN (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Previous studies showed global circuit&#x02013;phenotype associations across clinical anxiety and depression, with distinct CEN (e.g., ACC and dlPFC) and SN (e.g., aINS and AMY) circuits (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Therefore, abnormalities in the goal-directed system, and in particular the CEN/SN decoupling, may represent distinctive neural phenotypes of depression.</p><p>On the one hand, the dysfunctional networks of CEN and SN persist during depressive episodes. We previously found that depressed patients showed impaired goal-directed behavior, accompanied impairments in CEN, such as over-activation in the left lateral PFC (LPFC), as well as SN, such as under-activation in VTA, dorsal striatum (DS), and orbital frontal cortex (OFC) (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>) (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>), the last of which plays a critical role in controlling the transition between goal-directed and habitual behavior (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). The neural abnormalities in VTA during habitual learning do not normalize during remission (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). Further evidence suggested that enhanced resting-state functional connectivity (RSFC) between subregions of ACC (including pgACC and sgACC) and caudate could predict future anhedonia symptoms in adolescent depression (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Specifically, neural activation to uncertain rewards in ACC during reward learning tasks could predict anhedonia symptoms 1 year later when baseline anhedonia is controlled for (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Collectively, these studies suggest that neural impairments in the CEN and SN within the goal-directed system are not only present during the acute phase of depression but also predict the course of the disease.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Hypothesized role of goal-directed function impairments in anhedonia symptoms of depression.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpsyt-14-1253727-g0001" position="float"/></fig><p>On the other hand, the stress-resilience model of depression provides a framework for understanding distinct subnetworks (CEN and SN) underlying anhedonic symptoms of depression. Emerging findings from functional abnormalities of higher functional connectivity between CEN (dlPFC and pgACC) and SN (striatum and VTA) during reward-related tasks were shown in depressed patients, as well as hypo-activation in CEN (pgACC and mOFC) and SN (VS/DS) (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Anhedonia was associated with SN overactivity in the resting state, lack of SN activation in response to positive stimuli in task-related states, and SN overactivity in response to negative stimuli (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Stress mediates the relationship between goal-directed reward learning and anhedonia (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Stress may contribute to impaired goal-directed processes by enhancing the connectivities between CEN and SN circuits (e.g., dlPFC and amygdala/VS) (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). The resilience to stress involves the interactions among heightened CEN (PFC) and lessened SN (mesostriatal reward circuits) neural activities (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Taken together, goal-directed behavior depends on the adaptive redistribution of neural resources between the CEN (&#x02193;) and SN (&#x02193;), and stress may lead to an imbalance between the CEN (&#x02193;) and SN (&#x02193;), as well as aberrant connectivity during reward processing, which may contribute to anhedonia symptoms.</p><p>Neurofeedback based on real-time functional magnetic resonance imaging (rt-fMRI) uses measured changes in brain activation to help participants regulate activity in selected regions or networks. During rt-fMRI neurofeedback, participants are provided with visually presented brain network activation information in real time (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). The rt-fMRI neurofeedback targeting the brain areas within SN involved in emotion processing (e.g., amygdala, insula, and striatum) decreased the anhedonic or depressive scores (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). However, the effects of rt-fMRI neurofeedback (NF) based on CEN-SN on anhedonia to the best of our knowledge have not been investigated previously. Network-based NF can be used to recalibrate the balance between brain networks (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). It has been recommended that researchers use NF methods that consider neural response across regions (i.e., functional connectivity) (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). Recent studies have found that participants can flexibly regulate the balance between the CEN and SN through rt-fMRI neurofeedback which could promote resilience to stress (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). Therefore, the use of rt-fMRI neurofeedback to improve goal-directed reward learning is a potential intervention that involves the interaction between CEN and SN. Additionally, reward learning studies have typically adopted computational modeling during behavioral tasks to estimate expected value and reward prediction errors (RPEs) (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Therefore, the current study was designed to adopt reward learning tasks (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>) and computational modeling in anhedonic individuals to examine goal-directed brain network dynamics. Network-based rt-fMRI neurofeedback will be utilized to improve the balance of CEN/SN within the goal-directed brain network (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). The within-group changes of depressive symptoms after rt-fMRI NF training of goal-directed brain network will be examined to assess the effects of rt-fMRI NF intervention to improve depressive and/or anhedonic symptoms for depressed patients. The goal-directed RL, as well as CEN/SN changes (CEN-SN functional connectivity) at 3- and 6-month follow-ups, will also be examined to evaluate the long-term rt-fMRI neurofeedback training effects. This study may provide evidence to elucidate the effect of rt-fMRI NF based on the goal-directed system in alleviating depressive/anhedonic symptoms. The rt-fMRI NF training may have clinical implications with improved safety and minor side effects (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Methods and analysis</title><sec><title>Aim</title><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>To determine whether rt-fMRI neurofeedback of the goal-directed system could improve the depressive and/or anhedonic symptoms of depressed patients after training and at follow-ups;</p></list-item><list-item><p>To examine the short-term and long-term effects of rt-rMRI neurofeedback on the goal-directed RL behavioral and/or connectivity imaging mediators.</p></list-item></list></sec><sec><title>Participants</title><p>The study was approved by the ethical review committee at the Army Medical University (AMU, PRC) and conformed to the Declaration of Helsinki. The study has been submitted to the Chinese Clinical Trials Registry (ChiCTR, <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.chictr.org.cn/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.chictr.org.cn/</ext-link>). The trial identifier will be made available upon approval of the registration. After signing the informed consent form, the clinical data and general information of all participants will be collected, including age, gender, duration of illness, years of education, and medication history. The clinical diagnosis and symptom assessment will be completed by psychiatrists according to DSM-5 combined with a Mini-international Neuropsychiatric Interview (MINI). We will use the Hamilton Depression Scale-17 (HAMD-17) and the Montgomery&#x02013;&#x000c5;sberg Depression Rating Scale (MADRS) to assess anhedonia symptoms. Participant selection and recruitment processes were not conducted prior to the submission of the study.</p><p>(1) High anhedonic depression group. Inclusion criteria: &#x02460; diagnosed with major depression, with at least one core symptom (loss of pleasure or interest in all or nearly all activities) (MADRS item 8 &#x02265; 4) or non-reactive mood (items 1 or 2 &#x02265;5, &#x02461; at least three following symptoms during the most severe phase of this depressive episode, including (a) significant psychomotor disturbance (HAMD items 8 or 9 ll1); (b) appetite/weight loss (HAMD items 12 or 16 = 2); (c) late insomnia (waking at least 2h earlier than usual) (HAMD item 6 &#x02265; 1); and (d) guilt (HAMD &#x02265; 1) (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>); &#x02462;right-handedness. Exclusion criteria: &#x02460; comorbid with other mental disorders or drug or alcohol dependence; &#x02461; has received any previous antidepressant or antipsychotic medication (including benzodiazepines and other sedatives and hypnotics); &#x02462; with severe physical diseases such as heart, liver, or kidney impairment, endocrine disorders, or infectious diseases; &#x02463; substance dependence or abuse; &#x02464; vision impairments; &#x02465; pregnant or breastfeeding women; &#x02466; MRI contraindications; and &#x02467; currently receiving any emotional ability training.</p><p>(2) Healthy control group. Inclusion criteria: &#x02460; without a history of mental illness and family history of mental illness; &#x02461; age 18&#x02013;55; &#x02462; HAMD-17 &#x0003c; 7; and &#x02463; right-handedness. Exclusion criteria: &#x02460; diagnosed with depression or other axis I diseases; &#x02461; has received any previous antidepressant or antipsychotic treatment (including benzodiazepines and other sedative and hypnotic drugs); &#x02462; with severe physical diseases such as heart, liver, renal impairment, endocrine diseases, and infectious diseases; &#x02463; substance dependence or abuse; &#x02464; vision impairment; &#x02465; women pregnant or breastfeeding; &#x02466; MRI contraindications; and &#x02467; currently receiving any emotional ability training.</p></sec><sec><title>Procedure</title><p>This study is a double-blind randomized yoke-controlled rt-fMRI NF experiment, with follow-up assessments at 3 and 6 months after rt-fMRI NF (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). Participants will be randomly assigned to the experimental group (NF/YC) and given random numbers by a third party, who encodes the intervention with matching random numbers. The experimenter who will rate the outcome and/or analyze the data will be blind to group assignment. The CRED-NF checklist indicating which analyses will be performed and listed as supplementary material (available on the Open Science Framework preregistration, <ext-link xlink:href="https://osf.io/ec396" ext-link-type="uri">https://osf.io/ec396</ext-link>; CRED-NF checklist, <ext-link xlink:href="https://osf.io/8wcqt" ext-link-type="uri">https://osf.io/8wcqt</ext-link>).</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Consolidated Standards of Reporting Trials (CONSORT) flow diagram summarizing the study design.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpsyt-14-1253727-g0002" position="float"/></fig><sec><title>Pre- and post-test</title><p>Before and after the neurofeedback intervention, the primary and secondary outcome measures of the depressive and anhedonic symptoms will be assessed in all subjects. The behavioral tasks will be repeated post-training to evaluate the NF training effect on goal-directed behavior. The follow-up assessments include the primary outcome of depression and secondary outcome of anhedonia, the goal-directed RL (model-based weighting parameter &#x003c9;), and the CEN-SN functional connectivity (Pearson's correlation) based on prediction errors (PEs) (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).</p><sec><title>Primary and secondary outcome measures</title><p>Primary outcome measures: HAMD-17 (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). The severity of depressive symptoms will be assessed using the total score of HAMD-17. The higher the score, the more severe the depressive symptoms.</p><p>Secondary outcome measures: Snaith&#x02013;Hamilton Pleasure Scale (SHAPS) (<xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). The scale includes four aspects of interest/entertainment, social interaction, sensory experience, and food/drink, and has a total score of 14 to 56. It has good validity and reliability to evaluate the hedonic experience of adult outpatients with MDD (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>).</p><p>The changes in depression and anhedonia symptoms will be assessed using HAMD-17 and SHAPS before and after the NF intervention, respectively. Follow-up assessments of depression (HAMD) and anhedonia (SHAPS) symptoms will be conducted at 3 and 6 months after the intervention.</p></sec><sec><title>Behavioral task</title><p>The reward learning task (two-stage Markov decision task) (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>) will be adopted. All participants will practice an 8-min Markov decision task outside of the scanner room before formal NF training, for which instructions will be provided to the participants. After practice, the participants will rest for 5 min before completing the formal NF training. The practice and formal tasks will be presented using MATLAB 2019a (<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.mathworks.com" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.mathworks.com</ext-link>) and Psychtoolbox 3.0 (<ext-link xlink:href="http://psychtoolbox.org" ext-link-type="uri">http://psychtoolbox.org</ext-link>).</p><p>The task will be divided into two stages. In stage 1, participants choose one of two stimuli (red) (stage 1, left panel), which leads to the second stimulus (green) in 70% of the cases and to the third stimulus (blue) (stage 2) in 30% of the cases. The other stimulus (stage 1, right panel) leads to the second stimulus (green) in 30% of the cases and to the third stimulus (blue) in 70% of the cases. The six stimuli at the two stages will be selected from the alphabets that are unfamiliar to the participants to encourage progressive learning. The possibility that the stimulus of stage 1 changes to the second stage through the key press of participants is called the transition probability (common transition 70% vs. rare transition 30%). The selection of experimental stimuli in stage 2 may result in either a reward or no reward. To motivate participants to continue learning, the reward will follow a slowly drifting Gaussian random walk with probability changes ranging from 0.25 to 0.75 (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Schematic diagram of the Markov reward decision task adapted from Daw et al. (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpsyt-14-1253727-g0003" position="float"/></fig><p>Participants will be encouraged to make options to receive as many rewards as possible and will be informed prior to practice and formal experiments that all rewards will be paid off at the end of the experiment. The task flow is as follows (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Flowchart of the Markov reward decision task, adapted from Daw et al. (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpsyt-14-1253727-g0004" position="float"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Real-time fMRI neurofeedback of individual goal-directed system in anhedonic depression</title><p>The anhedonic depressed participants (<italic>n</italic> = 40) will be randomized into the neurofeedback (NF) group (<italic>n</italic> = 20) and the yoke control (YC) group (<italic>n</italic> = 20). We used blocked randomization to form the allocation list (1:1 ratio) for the two comparison groups (NF and YC), by using a computer random number generator to select random permuted blocks (size = 10). The NF group will receive rt-fMRI neurofeedback intervention, with ~60 min per session, once per week for a total of four sessions. Participants in the YC group who are paired with one specific participant from the NF group will receive feedback signals from that participant during the same run. Thus, for the YC group, the sham rt-fMRI signals will not be corresponding to the participant's brain activity. The healthy control (HC) group (<italic>n</italic> = 20) will receive no intervention.</p><sec><title>Sample size</title><p>The sample size is determined based on a heuristic justification (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>) according to median recruits (<italic>n</italic> = 18) of fMRI neurofeedback (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>). Moreover, given that this is a feasibility study with constraints on limited resources, a power calculation is not necessary according to the reporting and experimental design consensus in the NF field (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Real-time magnetic resonance imaging</title><p>MR images will be collected using 3.0T Siemens (Trio, Erlangen, Germany) with a 32-channel head coil. T1-weighted structural images will be collected from the whole brain with the magnetization-prepared rapid gradient echo (MPRAGE) sequence for anatomical localization of functional images. FOV = 256 &#x000d7; 256 mm, 176 sagittal slices, layer thickness = 1.0 mm, resolution = 1.0 mm<sup>2</sup>, TR/TE = 1900/2.52 ms, and flip angle = 9&#x000b0;. Echo-planar imaging (EPI) T2<sup>*</sup>-weighted functional images will be collected across the whole brain using a gradient echo planar imaging (EPI) sequence, FOV = 192 &#x000d7; 192 mm, matrix size = 64 &#x000d7; 64, and spatial resolution = 3 &#x000d7; 3 &#x000d7; 3 mm<sup>3</sup>, flip angle = 90&#x000b0;, and TR/TE = 2000/30 ms. To reduce the head motion, a strip of medical tape will be attached horizontally over the forehead of the participant and be spread to both sides of the head coil so that the participant could feel the head motion subjectively to prevent it from exceeding the range of head motion (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>).</p><p>Real-time functional imaging will be achieved by using a customized function during MR image reconstruction, with TurboExport (Brain Innovation, Maastricht, The Netherlands) to convert input pixel data for each volume into images. Each image generated will be preprocessed in real time using the Turbo-BrainVoyager (Brain Innovation, Maastricht, The Netherlands). Preprocessing includes motion correction (by realigning each image to the first image of the session) and spatial smoothing (Gaussian kernel of half-height and 5 mm in full width). The computer presenting the task will communicate with Turbo-BrainVoyager via Transmission Control Protocol (TCP) to acquire preprocessed real-time data to be coregistered to the localizer anatomical image (first session) and generate feedback displays to the participants.</p></sec><sec><title>Network-based rt-fMRI NF intervention</title><p>The network-based rt-fMRI NF intervention of each session will be divided into 6 runs (5 NF runs and 1 transfer run), at 10 min/run. Subjects will be asked to raise or lower the height of a progress bar on the screen through cognitive effort. The height of the bar will depend on the signal intensity of regions of interest (ROIs) in the CEN and SN measured on each trial. Participants will be asked to regulate their brain signals through internal thought without specific instructions, with the feedback signaling the balance between the average signal intensities of the CEN and SN. They will know neither the source nor the calculation of the feedback signal. Before each session, participants will be explicitly instructed to try to avoid movement, including facial expressions, limb movements, and irregular breathing patterns.</p><p>During the scan, anatomical images will be recorded first (~5 min) and preprocessed immediately after image reconstruction based on a separate computer using BrainVoyager. After that, the results will be transmitted to Turbo-BrainVoyager to obtain real-time functional data aligned to the target ROIs of neurofeedback. Each run will start with a rest phase, during which the baseline and change in the feedback signal will be calculated. The feedback will be based on the differential signal between the mean values of all the voxels in the individualized ROIs in the CEN and SN. The baseline for this difference signal will be defined as the median difference between the initial resting signal of the SN and the CEN ROIs, and the lower and upper limits will be set to be two standard deviations from this baseline. The upper and lower limits will be updated to the average of the five lowest/highest median differences of this run before each block (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). The regulatory success targets the larger differential signal between CEN and SN. The transfer run will test the generalization of NF training without feedback signals during which the participants will be required to regulate their brain signals in the same way as the NF training run (<xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>).</p><p>After each run, the participants will appraise their control over the progressive bar height (0&#x02013;10 points) and their cognitive difficulties (0&#x02013;10 points) with handles. Between runs, the participants will be allowed to rest for 5 min without significant head movement. After the NF intervention outside the scanner, the participants will write down the strategies they used to regulate their brain signals (e.g., through internal thought) and evaluate the effectiveness of strategies (0&#x02013;10 points). To evaluate the demand characteristics, they will also indicate which group (NF or YC) they believe they belong to.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><sec><title>Behavioral data</title><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>IBM SPSS Statistics 22 (<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.ibm.com/spss" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.ibm.com/spss</ext-link>) will be used. The 2 (groups: high anhedonia group and healthy control group) &#x000d7; 2 (transition conditions: common transition and rare transition) &#x000d7; 2 (reward feedback: reward and non-reward) factor mixed design will be conducted. The general linear mixed model (GLMM) will be used to investigate the main effects and interactions of the group, transition condition, and reward feedback on choice behavior. The interactions of transition conditions and reward feedback will represent the effect of the goal-directed system on the choice behavior (goal-directed RL), and the main effect of reward feedback will represent the effect of the habitual system on the choice behavior (habitual RL). The three-way interaction of the group, transition condition, and reward feedback will be examined to test for group differences in goal-directed RL. The two-way interaction of group and reward feedback will be examined to test for group differences in habitual RL.</p></sec><sec><title>Computational modeling</title><p>MATLAB 2019a (<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.mathworks.com/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.mathworks.com/</ext-link>) and the Reinforcement Learning algorithm will be used to model the behavioral data and estimate the learning rate &#x003b1;, inverse temperature parameter &#x003b2;, repetition parameter p, and model-based learning weight &#x003c9; of individual subjects.</p><p>&#x02460; value estimates. The state-action values for the first and second stages of each trial are determined by the weighted sum of the model-based action value Q<sub>MB</sub> and the model-free action value Q<sub>MF.</sub> The weighted sum is expressed as follows.</p><disp-formula id="E1">
<label>(1)</label>
<mml:math id="M1" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math>
</disp-formula><p>It is assumed that individual behavioral choice in the first stage is the weighted sum of goal-directed and habitual learning, with the weight of &#x003c9; (0~1). If &#x003c9; is close to 0, the choice mainly depends on habitual learning; if &#x003c9; is close to 1, the choice mainly depends on goal-directed learning.</p><p>(a) Model-based state-action value:</p><disp-formula id="E2">
<label>(2)</label>
<mml:math id="M2" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mi>max</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;&#x000a0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mrow><mml:mi>max</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02208;</mml:mo><mml:mo>{</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>}</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</disp-formula><p>(b) Model-free state-action value:</p><disp-formula id="E4">
<label>(3)</label>
<mml:math id="M4" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math>
</disp-formula><p>For the first and second stages, learning rates &#x003b1;<sub>1</sub> and &#x003b1;<sub>2</sub>, respectively, represent the extent to which the reward results are used for learning.</p><p>(c) Prediction error:</p><disp-formula id="E5">
<label>(4)</label>
<mml:math id="M5" overflow="scroll"><mml:mtable class="eqnarray" columnalign="left"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003b4;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>r</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math>
</disp-formula><p>The action probabilities of the first and second stages of each trial are regarded as a softmax function of the inverse temperature parameter &#x003b2;, the repetition parameter <italic>rep</italic>, and the indicator function <italic>p</italic> as follows.</p><disp-formula id="E6">
<label>(5)</label>
<mml:math id="M6" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable columnalign="left"><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>|</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000b7;</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle displaystyle="true"><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000b7;</mml:mo><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo></mml:msup><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:math>
</disp-formula><p>The inverse temperature parameters &#x003b2;<sub>1</sub> and &#x003b2;<sub>2</sub> represent the randomness of the first- and second-stage choices. The repetition parameter p and the indicator function represent the reproducibility of the choice, that is, the tendency to choose the same choice as in the previous trial, regardless of the actual value of the choice. Additionally, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0 represents choices the same as the previous trial, and <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0 represents choices different from the previous trial.</p><p>The parameters of each subject will be estimated using the R software and its Stan toolkit with the Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) estimation which has been previously described (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). The model evidence of the Akaike information criterion (AIC) and the Bayesian information criterion (BIC) will be calculated separately to estimate the model fit of reinforcement learning to the behavior.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Imaging data</title><sec><title>Preprocessing analysis</title><p>DPABI V7.0 software (<ext-link xlink:href="http://rfmri.org/DPABIV7" ext-link-type="uri">http://rfmri.org/DPABIV7</ext-link>) will be used for data pre-processing, in which the DICOM data will be converted into NIFTI format. In order to remove the effects of subject maladaptation during the scan as well as the effects of inhomogeneous magnetic fields on the results, data from the first 10 time points will be removed. Then, time correction, head motion correction, image standardization, image smoothing, detrending, and filtering (0.01~0.08 Hz) will be conducted, as well as the removal of head motion parameters.</p></sec><sec><title>Task-state PE signal analysis</title><p>BOLD signal analysis of ROIs during the task will be performed using SPM12 (<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.fil.ion.ucl.ac.uk/spm/software/spm12/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.fil.ion.ucl.ac.uk/spm/software/spm12/</ext-link>). The PE and relative partial differential calculations in the action selection phase and the reward outcome phase will be included as regressors in the general linear model, with &#x003c9; (see Equation 1) as a covariate (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). The standard hemodynamic function will be constructed for ROIs using MarsBaR (<ext-link xlink:href="https://sourceforge.net/projects/marsbar/" ext-link-type="uri">https://sourceforge.net/projects/marsbar/</ext-link>) with FDR correction for control of false discovery rate in voxelwise tests (<xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). The ROIs will be made with WFU_PickAtlas software (<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.nitrc.org/projects/wfu_pickatlas" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.nitrc.org/projects/wfu_pickatlas</ext-link>) according to the activation map during MDT for PEs.</p><p>The ROIs within CEN/SN will be mapped to CEN and SN which are functionally defined according to 14 intrinsic connectivity networks (ICNs) that are comprised of 90 distinct ROIs (<xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). The DMN, SN, and CEN will be constructed from network templates with the Group ICA of fMRI Toolbox (GIFT, <ext-link xlink:href="http://mialab.mrn.org/software/gift/" ext-link-type="uri">http://mialab.mrn.org/software/gift/</ext-link>) for use in the constrained ICA. The differential functional image (CEN - SN strength) during the first session will be used to create individualized network masks as neurofeedback target regions during the subsequent sessions. The nuisance regressors including six motion parameters and temporal derivatives as well as their quadratic terms and 25 physiological noise components will be taken into consideration. The first two runs of the first session will be discarded without additional analysis. The time courses (extracted using Turbo-BrainVoyager online) of ROIs will be high-pass filtered (0.01 Hz/100 s) and normalized (z-transformed).</p></sec><sec><title>Self-regulation performance</title><p>For each subject in the patient group in each session, self-regulation performance will be assessed with the CEN-SN activation difference (computed through online time courses of ROIs extracted using Turbo-BrainVoyager) during the training. Self-regulation performance will be defined as the mean % signal change of ROIs (CEN and SN) over all the NF runs. The self-regulation performance will then be submitted to an ANOVA with the factors group (NF vs. YC) and session (four sessions) for the group and/or time effects of rt-fMRI NF training.</p><p>Additionally, to investigate the pre- and post-training difference in CEN-SN functional connectivity for each patient group, we will apply the paired <italic>t</italic>-tests or Wilcoxon signed-rank tests (depending on parametric or non-parametric distributions) between the pre- and post-training tests, while undergoing MDT behavioral task during neuroimaging.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Intervention effect analysis</title><sec><title>Primary and secondary outcomes</title><p>We will examine the difference in depressive symptoms between the NF and YC groups at the post-test after the training. Bayesian ANCOVA with the group as a fixed factor and the baseline HAMD scores as covariates will be used, using the default JASP (<ext-link xlink:href="https://jasp-stats.org/" ext-link-type="uri">https://jasp-stats.org/</ext-link>) multivariate Cauchy priors (<xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>), and the statistical approach has been described previously (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). The advantage of ANCOVA over repeated-measures (RM) models has been mentioned elsewhere (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>). The additional covariates include age, gender, and duration of illness. The dependent variable will be post-test HAMD scores. Similar analyses will be performed on the anhedonic symptoms (SHAPS), with the same covariates and dependent variable. Additionally, similar analyses will also be performed on the primary and secondary outcomes at 3- and 6-month follow-ups.</p></sec><sec><title>GD-RL behavioral and connectivity imaging indicators</title><p>The behavioral (model-based weighting parameter &#x003c9;) and connectivity imaging indicators (CEN-SN activation difference) will be used as potential mediating factors to determine whether behavioral and imaging indicators could explain the changes in depressive and/or anhedonic symptoms. Within-group explorative analysis will be conducted using a stepwise regression using a bootstrapping test when multiple mediators are concerned (<xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>) with PROCESS macro (<ext-link xlink:href="http://www.afhayes.com/" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.afhayes.com/</ext-link>) of SPSS 22.</p></sec></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s3"><title>Discussion</title><p>The deficits in RL represent a sub-phenotype of anhedonia, with partially separable neural substrates (<xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). The decision-theoretic view of depression favors the compromise of the GD system, rather than the habitual system in depression (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>), the former of which is present in both behavioral and neural manifestations during RL for clinical and subclinical depression (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). Acute stress affects the allocation of neural resources within large-scale brain networks, especially the balance between the CEN/SN in the GD system due to cognitive demands (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). Additionally, the acute stress (during the last month) is supposed to trigger shifts in goal-directed vs. habitual behavior pattern, which is concomitant with specific network configurations, especially frontostriatal circuits (CEN: LPFCal SN: VTA/putamen/caudate&#x02193;, lateral/medial OFC&#x02193;) (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Stronger PEs may contribute to highly variable momentary mood fluctuations due to stronger reward feedback dynamics, whereas the influence of PEs on RL is compromised in depressed individuals (<xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). In summary, these studies highlight a promising target for RL-based NF interventions for anhedonic depression to produce flexible mood changes. Moreover, the focus on the GD-RL and imaging substrates in the current protocol may provide more insights with regard to the factors driving NF outcomes (<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>).</p><p>The novelty of the current study is that we focus on neither single ROI nor functional connectivity limited to a few ROIs, but rather the balance between two functionally intertwined brain networks (CEN/SN), and this approach has been utilized in self-regulation and sustained attention (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>, <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). However, the impact of network-based NF on reward learning is still unknown. Thus, we propose to simultaneously decrease CEN and increase SN activity (CEN: LPFC&#x02193;; SN: VTA/putamen/caudate&#x02191;, lateral/medial OFC&#x02191;), which could potentially improve mood and its fluctuations. Individualized NF training based on a goal-directed subnetwork is potentially advantageous for improving treatment response to anhedonia symptoms for depressed patients.</p><p>Additionally, the current study takes into account the potential confounding factors of motivation and demand characteristics. The mechanism underlying NF may come from NF-specific or non-specific contextual factors as well as general non-specific effects such as practice, placebo, and natural change (cognitive development or decline)(<xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). Therefore, a double-blind yoke-controlled design is adopted in this study to control for individual differences in motivation and effort. As a limitation, insufficient power may result from the limited sample size. To control for inter-subject variance, yoke-controlled NF will be provided for the participants to modulate the fMRI signals, in which sham feedback has been shown to regulate neural activity in cognitive control compared to passively viewing conditions (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>).</p><p>The caveat of this study is the use of CEN and SN based on intermittent, rather than continuous imaging feedback signals, due to the signal calculation speed of network parameters and the high cognitive load of momentary feedback (<xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). Accumulating evidence indicates that intermittent feedback is more efficient than continuous feedback to reinforce the participants' internal thoughts (<xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>, <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>). However, other studies showed that continuous feedback improved regulation ability (<xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). Additionally, monetary reward elicits a greater extent of self-regulation than non-reward feedback (<xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>). Therefore, further study would be able to determine the influence of intermittent vs. continuous feedback and trial-by-trial virtual monetary reward on GD-RL, though the monetary reward in this study is not contingent on participants' decision as in the Markov decision (MD) task. Feedback design for NF training should be carefully considered in future research.</p><p>Finally, accumulating evidence converges on the feasibility and effectiveness of frontostriatal connectivity as NF targets (<xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>). Within SN, the lateral and medial part of OFC as well as ACC densely project to the dorsal (e.g., caudate) and ventral striatum, which are involved in goal-directed control of instrumental actions (<xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>). Moreover, the clinical efficacy of NF targeting both emotion areas and higher visual areas may indicate the non-specific training effects of NF, e.g., the brain control and reinforcement components (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Therefore, confounds from the non-specific training effects should be taken into consideration during the explanation of the results. Additionally, further empirical studies and systematic reviews may shed light on the most efficient NF targets and provide more evidence on NF targeting specific ROIs of CEN/SN and connectivity-based and network-based NF within the GD-RL systems.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ethics-statement" id="s4"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>The study was reviewed and approved by the ethical review committee at the Army Medical University (AMU, PRC). Written informed consent to participate will be obtained from participants.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s5"><title>Author contributions</title><p>XW: Conceptualization, Data curation, Funding acquisition, Methodology, Writing&#x02014;original draft. XZ: Data curation, Methodology, Resources, Writing&#x02014;review &#x00026; editing. JL: Data curation, Methodology, Resources, Writing&#x02014;review &#x00026; editing. YG: Formal analysis, Software, Visualization, Writing&#x02014;review &#x00026; editing. ZF: Supervision, Writing&#x02014;review &#x00026; editing, Resources.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>We greatly appreciate Drs. Nathaniel D. Daw, Quentin J. M. Huys, and Catherine A. Hartley for their generous guidance on the statistical and computational modeling of behavioral data for two-stage MDT. We also appreciate the technical guidance and support from Dr. Chen Liu for neuroimaging and NF.</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s7"><title>Publisher's note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luca</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Flavia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>David</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Giulia</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adele</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Andrea</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Can anhedonia be considered a suicide risk factor? A review of the literature</article-title>. <source>Medicina.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>55</volume>:<fpage>8</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/medicina55080458</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30621105</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lucido</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bekhbat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goldsmith</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Treadway</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Haroon</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Felger</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Aiding and abetting anhedonia: impact of inflammation on the brain and pharmacological implications</article-title>. <source>Pharmacol Rev.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>73</volume>:<fpage>1084</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>117</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1124/pharmrev.120.000043</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34285088</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Banca</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Voon</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vestergaard</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Philipiak</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pocinho</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Imbalance in habitual versus goal directed neural systems during symptom provocation in obsessive-compulsive disorder</article-title>. <source>Brain.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>138</volume>:<fpage>798</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>811</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awu379</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25567322</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Decker</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Otto</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Daw</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hartley</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>From creatures of habit to goal-directed learners: tracking the developmental emergence of model-based reinforcement learning</article-title>. <source>Psychol Sci.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>848</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>58</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0956797616639301</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27084852</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of subclinical depression on prefrontal&#x02013;striatal model-based and model-free learning</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comput Biol.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>e1009003</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pcbi.1009003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33989284</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sebold</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Deserno</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nebe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schad</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Garbusow</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hagele</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Model-based and model-free decisions in alcohol dependence</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychobiology.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>70</volume>:<fpage>122</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000362840</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25359492</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>The Reward Deficits Model and Computational Neural Mechanism of Anhedonia in Major Depression</source> [Doctor thesis]. <publisher-loc>Chongqing</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Army Medical University</publisher-name>. (<year>2018</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Leri</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rizvi</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Anhedonia as a central factor in depression: neural mechanisms revealed from preclinical to clinical evidence</article-title>. <source>Prog Neuropsychopharmacol Biol Psychiatr.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>110</volume>:<fpage>110289</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pnpbp.2021.110289</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33631251</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>LY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Horst</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cranmore</surname><given-names>SAW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Horiguchi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cardinal</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Controlling one's world: identification of sub-regions of primate PFC underlying goal-directed behavior</article-title>. <source>Neuron.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>109</volume>:<fpage>2485</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>98</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2021.06.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34171290</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seeley</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Menon</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schatzberg</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Glover</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kenna</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Dissociable intrinsic connectivity networks for salience processing and executive control</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci.</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>2349</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>56</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5587-06.2007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17329432</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seeley</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The salience network: a neural system for perceiving and responding to homeostatic demands</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>39</volume>:<fpage>9878</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>82</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1138-17.2019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31676604</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shaw</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McKinnon</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heisz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dynamic task-linked switching between brain networks &#x02013; A tri-network perspective</article-title>. <source>Brain Cogn.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>151</volume>:<fpage>105725</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bandc.2021.105725</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33932747</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goulden</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Khusnulina</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bracewell</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bokde</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McNulty</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The salience network is responsible for switching between the default mode network and the central executive network: replication from DCM</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>99</volume>:<fpage>180</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2014.05.052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24862074</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldstein-Piekarski</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Samara</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Staveland</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Mapping neural circuit biotypes to symptoms and behavioral dimensions of depression and anxiety</article-title>. <source>Biol Psychiatry.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>91</volume>:<fpage>561</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2021.06.024</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34482948</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fettes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schulze</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Downar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cortico-striatal-thalamic loop circuits of the orbitofrontal cortex: promising therapeutic targets in psychiatric illness</article-title>. <source>Front Syst Neurosci.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>25</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnsys.2017.00025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28496402</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Geugies</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mocking</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Figueroa</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Groot</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Marsman</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Servaas</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Impaired reward-related learning signals in remitted unmedicated patients with recurrent depression</article-title>. <source>Brain.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>142</volume>:<fpage>2510</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awz167</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31280309</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rzepa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCabe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Decreased anticipated pleasure correlates with increased salience network resting state functional connectivity in adolescents with depressive symptomatology</article-title>. <source>J Psychiatr Res.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>82</volume>:<fpage>40</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychires.2016.07.013</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27459031</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rzepa</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McCabe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Anhedonia and depression severity dissociated by dmPFC resting-state functional connectivity in adolescents</article-title>. <source>J Psychopharmacol.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>1067</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0269881118799935</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30260258</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ely</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alonso</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gabbay</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Reward function as an outcome predictor in youth with mood and anxiety symptoms</article-title>. <source>J Affect Disord.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>278</volume>:<fpage>433</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>42</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2020.09.074</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33010568</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pizzagalli</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prefrontal cortex and depression</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychopharmacology.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>47</volume>:<fpage>225</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>46</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41386-021-01101-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34341498</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pisoni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smoski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Neural signatures of saliency-mapping in anhedonia: a narrative review</article-title>. <source>Psychiatry Res.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>304</volume>:<fpage>114123</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.psychres.2021.114123</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34333324</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maier</surname><given-names>SU</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Makwana</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hare</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Acute stress impairs self-control in goal-directed choice by altering multiple functional connections within the brain's decision circuits</article-title>. <source>Neuron.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>87</volume>:<fpage>621</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2015.07.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26247866</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tabibnia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>An affective neuroscience model of boosting resilience in adults</article-title>. <source>Neurosci Biobehav Rev.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>115</volume>:<fpage>321</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>50</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2020.05.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32522489</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tursic</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>L&#x000fc;hrs</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Linden</surname><given-names>DEJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goebel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A systematic review of fMRI neurofeedback reporting and effects in clinical populations</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage Clin.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>102496</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nicl.2020.102496</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33395987</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mehler</surname><given-names>DMA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sokunbi</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Habes</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barawi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Subramanian</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Range</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Targeting the affective brain-a randomized controlled trial of real-time fMRI neurofeedback in patients with depression</article-title>. <source>Neuropsychopharmacology.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>2578</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>85</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41386-018-0126-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29967368</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Siegle</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zotev</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Misaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Randomized clinical trial of real-time fMRI amygdala neurofeedback for major depressive disorder: effects on symptoms and autobiographical memory recall</article-title>. <source>Am J Psychiatry.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>174</volume>:<fpage>748</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ajp.2017.16060637</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28407727</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pamplona</surname><given-names>GSP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Heldner</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Langner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koush</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Michels</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ionta</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Network-based fMRI-neurofeedback training of sustained attention</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>221</volume>:<fpage>117194</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2020.117194</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32711065</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fede</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Manuweera</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Momenan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A guide to literature informed decisions in the design of real time fMRI neurofeedback studies: a systematic review</article-title>. <source>Front Hum Neurosci.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>60</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnhum.2020.00060</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32161529</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kogias</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Krentz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>L&#x000fc;hrs</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goebel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hermans</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Self-regulation of stress-related large-scale brain network balance using real-time fMRI neurofeedback</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>243</volume>:<fpage>118527</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2021.118527</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34469815</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Daw</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gershman</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Seymour</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dayan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Model-based influences on humans' choices and striatal prediction errors</article-title>. <source>Neuron.</source> (<year>2011</year>) <volume>69</volume>:<fpage>1204</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuron.2011.02.027</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21435563</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trambaiolli</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kohl</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Linden</surname><given-names>DEJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mehler</surname><given-names>DMA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Neurofeedback training in major depressive disorder: a systematic review of clinical efficacy, study quality and reporting practices</article-title>. <source>Neurosci Biobehav Rev.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>125</volume>:<fpage>33</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>56</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2021.02.015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33587957</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lodhi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Balbuena</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Melancholic features in bipolar depression and response to lamotrigine: a pooled analysis of five randomized placebo-controlled trials</article-title>. <source>J Clin Psychopharmacol.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>315</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/JCP.0000000000001393</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33779579</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A rating scale for depression</article-title>. <source>J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatr.</source> (<year>1960</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>56</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jnnp.23.1.56</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snaith</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morley</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Humayan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hargreaves</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Trigwell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A scale for the assessment of hedonic tone the snaith&#x02013;hamilton pleasure scale</article-title>. <source>Br J Psychiatr.</source> (<year>1995</year>) <volume>167</volume>:<fpage>99</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>103</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/bjp.167.1.99</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7551619</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakonezny</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greer</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Byerly</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carmody</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Grannemann</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Evaluation of anhedonia with the Snaith-Hamilton Pleasure Scale (SHAPS) in adult outpatients with major depressive disorder</article-title>. <source>J Psychiatr Res.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>65</volume>:<fpage>124</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychires.2015.03.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25864641</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lakens</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Sample size justification</article-title>. <source>Collabra Psychol.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>33267</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1525/collabra.33267</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thibault</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>MacPherson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lifshitz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roth</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Raz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Neurofeedback with fMRI: a critical systematic review</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>172</volume>:<fpage>786</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>807</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2017.12.071</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29288868</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ros</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Enriquez-Geppert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zotev</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Whitfield-Gabrieli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Consensus on the reporting and experimental design of clinical and cognitive-behavioural neurofeedback studies (CRED-nf checklist)</article-title>. <source>Brain.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>143</volume>:<fpage>1674</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>85</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/brain/awaa009</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32176800</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Benjamins</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Luhrs</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van Hoof</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goebel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Active head motion reduction in magnetic resonance imaging using tactile feedback</article-title>. <source>Hum Brain Mapp.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>4026</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>37</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.24683</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31179609</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aslan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kirsch</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gerchen</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Feasibility of training the dorsolateral prefrontal-striatal network by real-time fMRI neurofeedback</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>75</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-05675-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34992222</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Genovese</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lazar</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Thresholding of statistical maps in functional neuroimaging using the false discovery rate</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage.</source> (<year>2002</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>870</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/nimg.2001.1037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11906227</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cha</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bourakova</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Frequency specific contribution of intrinsic connectivity networks to the integration in brain networks</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-40699-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30626917</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shirer</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ryali</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rykhlevskaia</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Menon</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Greicius</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Decoding subject-driven cognitive states with whole-brain connectivity patterns</article-title>. <source>Cerebral Cortex.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>158</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>65</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cercor/bhr099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21616982</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quintana</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Bayesian alternatives for common null-hypothesis significance tests in psychiatry: a non-technical guide using JASP</article-title>. <source>BMC Psychiatry.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>1761</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12888-018-1761-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29879931</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Analyzing pre-post randomized studies with one post-randomization score using repeated measures and ANCOVA models</article-title>. <source>Stat Methods Med Res.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>2952</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>74</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0962280218789972</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30084297</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Preacher</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hayes</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Asymptotic and resampling strategies for assessing and comparing indirect effects in multiple mediator models</article-title>. <source>Behav Res Methods.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>879</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3758/BRM.40.3.879</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18697684</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borsini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wallis</surname><given-names>ASJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zunszain</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pariante</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kempton</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Characterizing anhedonia: a systematic review of neuroimaging across the subtypes of reward processing deficits in depression</article-title>. <source>Cognit Aff Behav Neurosci.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>816</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3758/s13415-020-00804-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32472419</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huys</surname><given-names>QJM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Daw</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dayan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Depression: a decision-theoretic analysis</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Neurosci.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>38</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-neuro-071714-033928</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25705929</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reinen</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Whitton</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pizzagalli</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Slifstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abi-Dargham</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>McGrath</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Differential reinforcement learning responses to positive and negative information in unmedicated individuals with depression</article-title>. <source>Eur Neuropsychopharmacol.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>53</volume>:<fpage>89</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>100</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.euroneuro.2021.08.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34517334</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hermans</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Henckens</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Joels</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Dynamic adaptation of large-scale brain networks in response to acute stressors</article-title>. <source>Trends Neurosci.</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>304</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tins.2014.03.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24766931</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kao</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hur</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jarvis</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rutledge</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Computational models of subjective feelings in psychiatry</article-title>. <source>Neurosci Biobehav Rev.</source> (<year>2023</year>) <volume>145</volume>:<fpage>105008</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2022.105008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36549378</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kober</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Witte</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ninaus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neuper</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Learning to modulate one's own brain activity: the effect of spontaneous mental strategies</article-title>. <source>Front Hum Neurosci.</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>695</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnhum.2013.00695</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24151462</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scheinost</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Avery</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hampson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Constable</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chun</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Connectome-based neurofeedback: a pilot study to improve sustained attention</article-title>. <source>Neuroimage.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>212</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroimage.2020.116684</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32114151</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hartwell</surname><given-names>KT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Borckardt</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Govindarajan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Intermittent &#x0201c;real-time&#x0201d; fMRI feedback is superior to continuous presentation for a motor imagery task: a pilot study</article-title>. <source>J Neuroimag.</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>58</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>66</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1552-6569.2010.00529.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20977537</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marxen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jacob</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Posse</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ackley</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hellrung</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Amygdala Regulation Following fMRI-Neurofeedback without Instructed Strategies</article-title>. <source>Front Hum Neurosci.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>183</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fnhum.2016.00183</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27199706</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sorger</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kamp</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Weiskopf</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goebel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>When the brain takes 'bold' steps: real-time fMRI neurofeedback can further enhance the ability to gradually self-regulate regional brain activation</article-title>. <source>Neuroscience.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>378</volume>:<fpage>71</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>88</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroscience.2016.09.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27659118</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sepulveda</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sitaram</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rana</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Montalba</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tejos</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ruiz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>How feedback, motor imagery, and reward influence brain self-regulation using real-time fMRI</article-title>. <source>Hum Brain Mapp.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>37</volume>:<fpage>3153</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hbm.23228</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27272616</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mehta</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Prata</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The &#x0201c;highs and lows&#x0201d; of the human brain on dopaminergics: Evidence from neuropharmacology</article-title>. <source>Neurosci Biobehav Rev.</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>80</volume>:<fpage>351</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neubiorev.2017.06.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28624433</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jahanshahi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Obeso</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rothwell</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Obeso</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A fronto-striato-subthalamic-pallidal network for goal-directed and habitual inhibition</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Neurosci.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>719</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrn4038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26530468</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
