<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">bioRxiv</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BIORXIV</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>bioRxiv</journal-title></journal-title-group><publisher><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38076803</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC10705395</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2023.11.29.569283</article-id><article-version-alternatives><article-version article-version-type="status">preprint</article-version><article-version article-version-type="number">1</article-version></article-version-alternatives><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Heterogeneity in lung macrophage control of <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> is determined by T cells</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>Rocky</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>Travis</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rakib</surname><given-names>Tasfia</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Jinhee</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3374-6699</contrib-id><name><surname>Behar</surname><given-names>Samuel M.</given-names></name><xref rid="CR1" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><aff id="A1">Department of Microbiology and Physiological Systems, University of Massachusetts Medical School, Worcester, Massachusetts, USA.</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn fn-type="con" id="FN1"><p id="P1"><bold>Author contribution</bold>. Conceptualization, R.L. and S.M.B.; Methodology, R.L., and J.L.; Investigation, R.L., T.W., T.R., and J.L.; Formal analysis, R.L., T.W., and S.M.B.; Writing &#x00026; Editing, R.L., T.W., T.R., and J.L., and S.M.B.; Supervision, S.M.B.; Funding Acquisition, S.M.B.</p></fn><corresp id="CR1"><label>*</label>Correspondence: Samuel M. Behar, <email>samuel.behar@umassmed.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>01</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><elocation-id>2023.11.29.569283</elocation-id><permissions><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under a <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License</ext-link>, which allows reusers to copy and distribute the material in any medium or format in unadapted form only, and only so long as attribution is given to the creator. The license allows for commercial use.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf">nihpp-2023.11.29.569283.pdf</self-uri><abstract id="ABS1"><p id="P2">Following <italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> infection, alveolar macrophages are initially infected but ineffectively restrict bacterial replication. The distribution of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> among different cell types in the lung changes with the onset of T cell immunity when the dominant infected cellular niche shifts from alveolar to monocyte-derived macrophages (MDM). We hypothesize that changes in bacterial distribution among different cell types is driven by differences in T cell recognition of infected cells and their subsequent activation of antimicrobial effector mechanisms. We show that CD4 and CD8 T cells efficiently eliminate <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> infection in alveolar macrophages, but they have less impact on suppressing infection in MDM, which may be a bacterial niche. Importantly, CD4 T cell responses enhance MDM recruitment to the lung. Thus, the outcome of infection depends on the interaction between the T cell subset and the infected cell; both contribute to the resolution and persistence of the infection.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec id="S1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="P3"><italic toggle="yes">Mycobacterium tuberculosis</italic> causes the chronic lung infection tuberculosis (TB). Following inhalation of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>, alveolar macrophages are initially infected, setting in motion a series of events that result in the recruitment of numerous cell types to the lung, including both innate (e.g., neutrophils and macrophages) and adaptive (e.g., B and T cells) immune cells<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>. These cells cooperate to form granulomas, the characteristic pathological lesion of TB. The fate of granulomas is varied. Some undergo fibrosis and/or calcification. In others, progressive bacterial replication leads to dissemination, necrosis, and cavitation. While most people develop immunity and avoid symptomatic disease, 10% develop clinical TB at some point during their lives. Impairment of cell mediated immunity greatly increases the risk of developing active TB, and genetic, environmental, and microbial factors play a role. Understanding how <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> is contained is an important question as a major clinical goal is to develop vaccines that prevent susceptible people from developing disease. A better understanding of the mechanisms that lead to containment of infection and why they fail in susceptible individuals is needed.</p><p id="P4">Tremendous heterogeneity exists among cells in the myeloid lineage. Monocytes, macrophages, dendritic cells (DC), and polymorphonuclear cells (PMNs) (hereafter referred collectively to as &#x0201c;myeloid cells&#x0201d;) both reside in and are recruited to the lung parenchyma during <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> infection. Heterogeneity is based on cell ontology but is also shaped by homeostatic signals specific for the tissue niches where the cells reside (e.g., alveolar macrophages), and by episodic inflammatory signals that lead to cell recruitment, activation, and differentiation. After inhalation of aerosols containing <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>, alveolar macrophages (AM) are the first cell type in the lung infected<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup>. Subsequently, AM in the alveoli traffic into the parenchyma and trigger innate inflammatory responses. Monocytes and neutrophils are recruited to the lung. Monocytes differentiate into macrophages and dendritic cells<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup>, which <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> infects<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>. New experimental approaches show that pre-existing heterogeneity among human macrophages affect <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> growth<sup><xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup>. Importantly, macrophages differ in their intrinsic control of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> in vivo, which may be triggered by cell-specific responses<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup>. In particular, AM have a metabolic environment that is conducive to bacillary growth by serving as a source of iron and fatty acids, while glycolytically-biased monocyte-derived macrophages (MDM) are more restrictive<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup>. While AM are the initial cell type infected after aerosol <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> infection<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup>, after infection is established, the number of infected CD11c<sup>+</sup> monocyte-derived cells (hereafter, MDM) outnumbers infected AM<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>. While intrinsic features of infected myeloid cells in the lung may affect their propensity to sustain or restrict <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> growth early after infection, we hypothesize that once adaptive immunity is initiated and recruited to the lungs, T cell immunity will modify the capacity of myeloid cells to restrict <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> replication.</p><p id="P5">In animal models, <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> is controlled within weeks after infection and bacterial exponential growth is replaced by a plateau phase. The timing of this transition is coincident with the development of T cell immunity. The use of MHCII<sup>+/+</sup>/MHCII<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mixed bone-marrow chimeric mice provides direct evidence that cognate interactions between CD4 T cells and infected cells is important for containment of infection in vivo, although Mtb was not eliminated from MHCII<sup>+</sup> lung macrophages<sup><xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref></sup>. Infected CD11c<sup>+</sup> MDM are highly activated, express NOS2, and upregulate CD14, CD38 and ABCA1, to a greater degree than their uninfected counterparts, providing additional evidence that infected cells interact with T cells<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>. Yet, it is paradoxical that MDM should be a dominant reservoir of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> and show evidence of being activated by T cells. These data suggest that T cell control of Mtb-infected macrophages is suboptimal and raises the possibility of a cellular niche that supports continued bacillary persistence.</p><p id="P6">Not all <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>-specific T cells efficiently recognize <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>-infected macrophages, depending on the antigen<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup> and the number of bacilli per macrophage<sup><xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup>. It is unknown whether the interaction of CD4 and CD8 T cells with <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>-infected cells varies depending on the type of infected cell. We hypothesize that some <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> bacilli occupies a protected cellular niche. We reasoned that for cell types in which <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> could be eliminated or its growth restricted by T cells, T cell depletion would lead to an increase in infected cells. In contrast, for cell types in which <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> persists, even in the face of T cell pressure, T cell depletion should have minimal effect. We report that CD4 and CD8 T cells cooperate to restrict <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> infection in several types of infected cells. <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>-infection in AM is efficiently controlled by T cells, particularly by CD4 T cells. In contrast, both CD4 and CD8 T cells are required to restrict <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> replication in MDM. Interestingly, T cell depletion had the least effect on MDM compared to other cell types. This hierarchy is the reverse of the intrinsic capacity of AM and MDM to control bacterial replication early after infection. Thus, depending on the cell type, the influence of T cells on <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> containment varies. We propose that although T cell interact with <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>-infected MDM, they have a limited ability to restrict infection in these cells. Although MDM are better than AM in their intrinsic capacity to restrict intracellular <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>, once T cell immunity is initiated, AM largely inhibit <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> growth while T cells contribute only modestly to the ability of MDM to limit intracellular infection.</p></sec><sec id="S2"><title>Results</title><sec id="S3"><title>CD4 and CD8 T cells synergize to restrict <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> growth in the lung.</title><p id="P7">To determine how T cells exert pressure on different types of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>-infected macrophages, we combined low dose aerosol infection with Rv.YFP<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> and antibody-mediated depletion of T cells. The in vivo infection was allowed to progress for three weeks, during which time T cell immunity to <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> is initiated and recruited to the lung<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup>. Then, groups of mice were treated with a control antibody, antibody to CD4, to CD8, or a combination of anti-CD4 and anti-CD8 for two weeks. The mice were analyzed 5 weeks post infection (wpi) (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1a</xref>). Both CD4 and CD8 T cells were eliminated from the lungs of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> infected mice, although CD8 depletion was slightly less efficient (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1b</xref>). Neither CD4 nor CD8 T cell depletion led to a statistically significant increase in lung CFU (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1c</xref>). In contrast, the combined depletion of CD4 and CD8 T cells led to an increase in lung CFU (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1c</xref>). These data show that early after infection, both CD4 and CD8 T cells make a synergistic contribution to controlling <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> replication in vivo.</p></sec><sec id="S4"><title>Monocyte-derived macrophages are the dominant cellular niche for <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>.</title><p id="P8">Advances in multiparametric flow cytometry have improved our ability to characterize myeloid cells in the lung. We adapted our myeloid flow panel for spectral flow cytometry and measured the distribution of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> among different myeloid cell types in the lung, 3- and 5-weeks post-infection. Some important technical features of the panel and its analysis are described in the <xref rid="S10" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>. Myeloid cells were defined as live CD45<sup>+</sup> cells after lymphoid cells were excluded based on the CD19, Thy1.2, and NK1.1 lineage markers. Neutrophils and eosinophils were identified by their expression of Ly6G and SiglecF, respectively (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2a</xref>). CD64 and Mertk distinguished macrophages from non-macrophages (i.e., monocytes and DC).</p><p id="P9">Alveolar macrophages (AM) were discriminated from other lung macrophages by their high levels of SiglecF and CD11c. CD11b expression divided AM into two subsets. Non-AM macrophages have been called recruited macrophages (RM), interstitial macrophages (IM) and CD11c<sup>Hi</sup> monocyte-derived cells (MDC)<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup>. We previously referred to these cells as CD11c<sup>Hi</sup>; however, in recognition of heterogeneity in their CD11c expression, we have dropped the CD11c moniker. As these monocyte-derived cells are distinct from resident macrophages (e.g., AM), we refer to them as monocyte-derived macrophages (MDM). MDM were divided into three subsets based on their SiglecF and CD11c expression. The SiglecF<sup>int</sup>CD11c<sup>+</sup> (MDM1) were the most variable between experiments and could be immature AM<sup><xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, <xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref></sup>. SiglecF<sup>&#x02212;</sup>CD11c<sup>+</sup> (MDM2) were the most abundant of the three and were most like what we previously referred to as CD11c<sup>Hi</sup> MDC (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2a</xref>)<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>. In additions, SiglecF<sup>&#x02212;</sup>CD11c<sup>&#x02212;</sup> (MDM3) may be nerve associated macrophages that have been recently described in the lung<sup><xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref></sup>. Finally, we subdivided monocytes and DC (M/DC) based on CD11c and Ly6C expression (M/DC1&#x02013;4). The most abundant of these were M/DC1 (Ly6c<sup>&#x02013;</sup>CD11c<sup>VAR</sup>) and M/DC3 (Ly6c<sup>+</sup>CD11c<sup>&#x02212;</sup>). The former was likely a mixed DC population, and the latter were probably classical monocytes.</p><p id="P10">Between three and five weeks after infection, the total number of macrophages and monocyte/DCs in the lung significantly increased (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S1a</xref>). During this interval, the number of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>-infected macrophages increased 5.4-fold, while the number of infected eosinophils, neutrophils, and monocyte/DCs remained the same. This led to macrophages becoming the dominant infected cell type (<xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Figure S1b</xref>, <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1c</xref>). With the greater granularity afforded by spectral flow cytometry, we defined what was driving these changes in 11 predefined cell subsets (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2a</xref>). Between three and five weeks after infection, SiglecF<sup>&#x02212;</sup>CD11c<sup>+</sup> non-AM macrophages (i.e., MDM2) underwent a 14-fold increase in cell number such that they accounted for ~14% of the lung myeloid cells (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2b</xref>). M/DC1 cells (Ly6c<sup>&#x02013;</sup>CD11c<sup>+</sup>), also increased in number (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2b</xref>). Thus, the dominant myeloid cell types in the lung changed from predominantly neutrophils and monocytes (M/DC3) to macrophages (MDM2) and DC (M/DC1). This was accompanied by a dramatic shift in the type of cells infected by <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2c</xref>). The number of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>-infected non-alveolar macrophages (MDM1, &#x02212;2, &#x02212;3) all increased by more than 10-fold. In absolute numbers, MDM2 increased the most and came to account for 45% of infected cells (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2c</xref>). To confirm that these results were not due to differences in YFP expression between the different macrophage populations, we determined the intracellular CFU within AM and MDM from the lungs of infected B6 mice. Consistent with our flow cytometric analysis (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2a</xref>, <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">c</xref>), MDM had 10-fold more <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> CFU than AM (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2d</xref>). The significant increase in <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>-infected macrophage number occurred despite the onset of T cell immunity during this phase of infection<sup><xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>, <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref></sup>. We hypothesized that MDM could represent a cellular niche against which T cell immunity inefficiently controlled <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> replication.</p></sec><sec id="S5"><title>The effectiveness of T cell immunity depends on the type of infected cell.</title><p id="P11">We predicted that a cellular niche that was shielded from T cell immunity would be largely unaffected by T cell depletion, compared to cell types that require T cell signals to restrict intracellular <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> replication. As described above, three weeks after infection, once effector T cells were recruited to the lung, groups of mice were treated with mAb to CD4, CD8 or both CD4 and CD8 for two weeks. Then, the frequency of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>-infected cells was determined for 11 myeloid cell types by flow cytometry (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1a</xref>, <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref>).</p><p id="P12">T cell depletion led to a statistically significant increase in the percentage of infected neutrophils, AM1, MDM1, and MDM2 (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3a</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">b</xref>). Only combined CD4 and CD8 depletion led to an increased frequency of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>-infected neutrophils, suggesting that CD4 and CD8 T cells are redundant in their ability to control infection in these cells (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3b</xref>). In contrast, CD4 depletion alone led to a significantly increased frequency of infected AM1, MDM1, and MDM2 (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3a</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">b</xref>). Although CD8 depletion alone had no effect, CD4 and CD8 double depletion significantly increased the frequency of infected AM1, MDM1, and MDM2 compared to CD4 depletion alone (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3a</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">b</xref>). Importantly, these data indicate CD4 and CD8 T cells act synergistically to control <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> infection in macrophages in vivo. Only depletion of CD4 and CD8 T cells led to an increase in the number of bacilli per cell in AM1, AM2, and MDM1, based on the median fluorescence intensity of Rv.YFP (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3c</xref>). Interestingly, the Rv.YFP signal of MDM2, the most abundant infected cell type, was unaffected by T cell depletion (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3c</xref>).</p><p id="P13">We next analyzed how T cell pressure affected the frequency of infected cells among all myeloid cells, since the abundance of each cell type varies. In control (undepleted) mice, MDM2 made the largest contribution (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3d</xref>). CD4 T cell significantly augmented the fraction of infected neutrophils and AM1 among myeloid cells (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3b</xref>, <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">3d</xref>). In contrast, CD4 T cell depletion did not alter the contribution of infected MDM2. While CD8 depletion alone had no effect, combined anti-CD4 and anti-CD8 mAb treatment significantly increased the frequency of infected neutrophils and M/DC2, compared to anti-CD4 or CD8 mAb treatment alone. Combined CD4 and CD8 depletion also increased the fraction of infected MDM1 and MDM2. However, the contribution of MDM2 to <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>-infected myeloid cells after CD4+CD8 depletion increased 1.4-fold (compared to undepleted mice). This change was small compared to the increased proportion of infected neutrophils or AM1 (9.5- and 5.8-fold, respectively). Thus, even though MDM are highly activated, their high rate of infection and dominant niche for <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> raise the possibility that they are inefficiently recognized by T cells<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref></sup>. Conversely, the emergence of other cell populations as an important niche for <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> after T cell depletion shows that T cell immunity effectively controls <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> infection in other myeloid cell types.</p></sec><sec id="S6"><title>CD4 T cells maintain high levels of NOS2 expression by macrophages.</title><p id="P14">Nitric oxide synthase 2 (NOS2) is induced by IFN&#x003b3; in macrophages and its expression is essential for survival of mice after <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> infection. NOS2 converts L-arginine into nitric oxide (NO), which is toxic to <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>; however, its role in vivo is more complicated as is its relevance to human TB<sup><xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref></sup>. NOS2 is expressed by <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>-infected macrophages in the lung lesions of B6 mice, both by AM and MDM<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref></sup>. We measured NOS2 expression by myeloid cells in the lung following <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> infection and T cell depletion as described above. At baseline (i.e., undepleted), 25&#x02013;42% of MDM1 and MDM2 expressed NOS2 (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4a</xref>). Other cell types such as AM1, MDM3, and M/DC2 also produced significant amounts of NOS2. The NOS2 expression by these different cell types correlated with their degree of infection (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4b</xref>, r=0.98). In general, more cells in each population expressed NOS2 than were infected. This led us to determine how many <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>-infected cells expressed NOS2 (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4c</xref>). There were too few eosinophils and AM2 to generate reliable data. However, for the other subsets, there was a hierarchy of NOS2 producing cells. Nearly 100% of the <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>-infected MDM subsets expressed NOS2. In contrast, ~70% of AM1, 50&#x02013;60% of M/DC except for M/DC3 produced NOS2. We did not detect intracellular NOS2 in neutrophils (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4c</xref>).</p><p id="P15">We next looked at the effect of T cells on the expression of NOS2 in <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>-infected cells by segregating the frequency of NOS2<sup>+</sup> vs. NOS2<sup>&#x02013;</sup> infected cells. After CD4 depletion, slightly more than half of the <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>-infected cells failed to express NOS2. CD4 depletion led to an increase in <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>-infected neutrophils and AM1, and most infected cells failed to express NOS2 (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4d</xref>). Consistent with our previous results, CD8 depletion did not affect the frequency of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>-infected cells nor their expression of NOS2, although it modestly increased the number of infected neutrophils. The ratio of NOS2<sup>+</sup> vs. NOS2<sup>&#x02013;</sup> infected cells was decreased after CD4 and CD4+CD8 depletion in all myeloid populations (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4d</xref>, <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">e</xref>). Remarkably, although ~50% of the <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>-infected MDM2 no longer expressed NOS2 after CD4 or CD4/CD8 depletion, the frequency of infected cells only increased incrementally (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4d</xref>). Interestingly, the ratio of NOS2<sup>+</sup>/NOS2<sup>&#x02013;</sup> infected cells was increased in AMs after CD8 depletion but not in MDM (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4d</xref>, <xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">e</xref>). Although NOS2 continues to be expressed in myeloid cells even in the absence of T cells, these data indicate that CD4 T cells are crucial for maintaining high levels of NOS2 expression in infected macrophages.</p></sec><sec id="S7"><title>Aminoguanidine treatment does not affect control of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> infection.</title><p id="P16">NOS2 is essential for resistance to <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> infection in B6 mice and mice that lack the NOS2 gene succumb to infection 4&#x02013;5 wpi<sup><xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup>. NO has been suggested to be more important in regulating inflammation than in direct killing of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic><sup><xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup>. We tested whether inhibition of NOS2 in vivo, through administration of aminoguanidine (AG), would exacerbate <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> infection as observed with CD4 T cell depletion. To verify that AG treatment was successful, NO was measured in lung homogenate using the Griess reaction. AG appeared to have successfully inhibited the production of NO by NOS2 (data not shown). We observed an increase in the number of viable bacilli in the lungs but not the spleens of mice treated with AG for two weeks (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5a</xref>, <xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">5b</xref>). The total number of neutrophils and M/DC3 but not any of the other myeloid populations were significantly increased after treatment (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5c</xref>). The frequency of infected neutrophils was increased after AG treatment, consistent with the exacerbation of TB disease as previous described<sup><xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup>. However, AG treatment did not alter the proportion of infected cells among the other myeloid subsets (<xref rid="F5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5d</xref>). Thus, it appears that this early stage of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> infection after T cell recruitment to the lung, NO has little or no role in the control of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> within macrophage subsets.</p></sec><sec id="S8"><title>CD4 T cells drive the recruitment of MDM to the site of infection.</title><p id="P17">Our data suggests that AM depend on CD4 T cells to augment their intrinsic capacity to control <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> (<xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3a</xref>). In contrast, MDMs are less sensitive to the loss of T cell pressure. T cells secrete numerous chemokines including CCL2, CCL3, and CCL4, which direct cellular recruitment to the site of infection. As such, we postulated that CD4 T cells recruitment of myeloid cells to the lung could augment containment of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> infection. could recruit MDM to the lung. To determine whether T cells were important in the recruitment of myeloid cells, C57BL/6 and RAG<sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> mice, the latter being devoid of B and T cells, were infected with <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>. At 3 weeks post infection, CD4 T cells from infected C57BL/6 mouse were transferred via the intravenous route to the RAG<sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> mice (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6a</xref>). As expected, transfer CD4 T cells were sufficient to protect help contain <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6b</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> infection of RAG<sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> mice led to an increase in many of the different myeloid cell types in the lung (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6c</xref>). Transfer of immune polyclonal CD4 T cells led to a large significant increase in the number of MDM in the lung (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6c</xref>). Immune polyclonal CD4 T cells reduced the fraction of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> infected cells (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6d</xref>, left) and decreased the intracellular bacillary load, based on YFP MFI (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6d</xref>, right), for most of the myeloid cell types in the lung. Given these effects of CD4 T cells, one would expect that the total number of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> infected cells should decrease. Although one sees dramatic reductions in the number of infected AM and neutrophils, the number of infected MDM and other cells did not significantly change (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6e</xref>, left). In fact, because of these changes, CD4 T cells induce a shift in the dominant infected cell type from neutrophils to MDM (<xref rid="F6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6e</xref>, right).</p></sec></sec><sec id="S9"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P18">The interaction between T cells and infected phagocytes determines the course of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> infection. While T cell immunity is required to contain infection, it is not sufficient to sterilize mice or the approximately 10% of people that develop active tuberculosis. In the murine TB literature, infection of pulmonary DC has been reported, but using better lineage markers, multiparametric flow cytometry, and single cell RNASeq, it now appears that CD11c<sup>+</sup> macrophages are the dominant infected macrophage population in the lung<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup>. Given the inherent diversity of cell types, activation states, and degree of infection of cells in the lung, we asked whether the impact of T cell immunity is equally distributed among different myeloid cell types. We hypothesized that there could exist cellular niches in which <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> is able to persist because T cells are unable to recognize certain infected cells. Here we report that T cell control of intracellular infection depends on the type of infected cell. <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>-infection of AM is efficiently limited by T cells. In contrast, T cells have only a modest impact on controlling <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>-infection among MDM.</p><p id="P19">Using a newly designed flow antibody panel that takes advantage of spectral flow cytometers, we validated our previous results and those of other labs. Three weeks after low dose aerosol <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> infection, most bacilli are found within three cell populations: neutrophils, macrophages, and monocyte/DCs. By five weeks, relatively few bacteria reside in DC or monocytes; instead, most <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> is within macrophages. The macrophages are of two types: AM and MDM. With additional markers, the macrophages can be subdivided into 5 populations. A priori, these different macrophage populations could reflect different ontogeny or activation states. For example, significantly more CD11b<sup>+</sup> AM were infected than CD11b<sup>&#x02212;</sup> AM. As CD11b is upregulated upon AM activation<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup>, we speculate that uninfected CD11b<sup>&#x02212;</sup> AM could occupy uninfected regions of the lung. Similarly, we find that the expression of SiglecF and CD11c among the MDM defined three distinct populations and responded differently to <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> infection.</p><p id="P20">CD8 depletion had little or no effect on early <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> recrudescence in the lung. Similarly, CD4 depletion led to a statistically significant increase in only one of three experiments. In contrast, dual depletion led to a dramatic increase in <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> burden in the lung. The increase in lung and spleen CFU tracked with the distribution of Rv.YFP in infected cells. An exact correlation between CFU and YFP<sup>+</sup> should not be expected as flow cytometric analysis cannot assess extracellular Mtb, differentiate between live and dead bacilli, and only poorly assess the number of bacilli/cell. CD4 depletion increased the frequency of YFP<sup>+</sup> neutrophils and macrophages, and the increase of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>-infected cells was even greater after dual CD4 and CD8 depletion. The greater perturbation in the distribution of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> among myeloid cells following CD4 but not CD8 depletion suggests that CD4 and CD8 T cell effectors are only partially redundant<sup><xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup>. Alternatively, depletion of CD4 T cells might not be efficiently compensated by CD8 T cells because CD4 T cell help is required to maintain CD8 T cell antibacterial effector function<sup><xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref></sup>. The large changes in the frequency of infected cells that occurred when both CD4 and CD8 T cells were depleted indicates that CD4 and CD8 T cells have a synergistic role in mediating control of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> infection in both AM and MDM subsets.</p><p id="P21">In addition to the synergistic role of CD4 and CD8 T cells in mediating control of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> infection, our data also points to differential requirements for these T cell subsets in helping AM and MDM to contain <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>. While CD8 T cells appear to have minimal impact on the ability of AM to control intracellular <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>, CD8 T cells are important in the ability of MDM to restrict <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> growth. We and others have demonstrated that CD8 T cells are more efficient at recognizing cells with high bacterial burden<sup><xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref></sup>, and the difference in intracellular burden between AM and MDM could explain why the two populations react differently to the loss of CD8 T cell pressure.</p><p id="P22">NOS2 is essential for host resistance to <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> infection in B6 mice, and mice that lack the NOS2 gene succumb to infection after 4&#x02013;5 weeks<sup><xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref></sup>. Induction of nitric oxide (NO) requires two canonical signals: IFN&#x003b3; and a microbial signal such as LPS<sup><xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref></sup>. Nitric oxide (NO) production by NOS2-expressing macrophages can kill <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis in vitro</italic> and has led to the paradigm that IFN&#x003b3; production by CD4 T cells induces NO production by macrophages, leading to control of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic><sup><xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref></sup>. The <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> role of NO is less certain. NO regulates inflammation during <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> infection in vivo<sup><xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup>. We find NOS2 expression by macrophages was diminished only after CD4 depletion. NOS2 expression by macrophages was similar after CD4 depletion or dual CD4 and CD8 depletion, indicating that CD8 T cells had no effect on NOS2 expression and suggesting that CD8 T cells may not rely on the induction of NOS2 to control <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>.</p><p id="P23">As CD4 depletion led to reduced NOS2 expression and increased frequency of YFP<sup>+</sup> macrophages, <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> inhibition of NOS2 should mimic CD4 depletion should lead to a loss of bacterial control. Surprisingly, aminoguanidine treatment of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> infected mice had no effect on the intracellular <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> burden within either AM or MDM, despite evidence of NO inhibition. However, we do observe increased recruitment of neutrophils as well as an increase in overall lung CFU, both of which have been previous reported following treatment with aminoguanidine<sup><xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup>. One possibility is that the length of the treatment wasn&#x02019;t long enough to significantly perturb the intracellular burden to the point where we can detect intracellular changes. The lack of change on the intracellular <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> burden following aminoguanidine treatment may also point towards an IFN&#x003b3;-independent effector mechanism for controlling the growth of intracellular <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> within AM and MDM<sup><xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>, <xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref></sup>.</p><p id="P24">The idea that AM ineffectively restricts <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> is based on their &#x0201c;M2-like&#x0201d; nature and improved host control of pulmonary <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> after their depletion<sup><xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref></sup>. David Russell&#x02019;s lab elegantly showed that IM (herein referred to as MDM) have a greater intrinsic ability to control <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> than AM<sup><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup>. Thus, AM appear to be a sanctuary for <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>. Yet, these data focus on early events after infection. Our data provide additional context for what subsequently happens. Early on, neutrophils, macrophages, and monocytes/DCs are infected similarly. However, once immune T cells are recruited to the lung, monocyte-derived macrophages harbor the bulk of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> by five weeks after infection. A caveat of our studies is that they focus on relatively early (i.e., 3&#x02013;5 wpi) interactions between T cells and lung macrophage subsets. Many studies show that early and late T cell responses differ greatly<sup><xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref></sup>. It will be important to characterize lung macrophage subsets and their interactions with T cells during chronic infection, although this remains technicially challenging. Still, it is paradoxical that CD11c<sup>+</sup> MDM are better able to control <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> infection<sup><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> but are also the major niche for <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic><sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup>. Our data shows that the relative permissiveness of macrophage for <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> is modified by T cells. Initially, AM poorly constrain <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>, but T cells dramatically improve the ability of AM to control intracellular infection. In the absence of T cells, AM emerge again as a haven for <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>. In contrast, MDM become a niche where <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> persists in the long term even in the presence of T cells.</p><p id="P25">Why would this be the case? We speculate that MDM are already optimally activated following <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> infection and MDM have an intrinsic capacity to restrict <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>. While T cells promote MDM control of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> infection, the magnitude of this effect is less than for AM. T cells, and T cell factors adds little to the intrinsic ability of MDM to control <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> infection. Over time, their intrinsic activation could potentially impair their APC function if degradation of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> antigens prevented reduced their flow into antigen presentation pathways. Alternatively, we consider the possibility that macrophages with only one or two bacteria could be difficult for T cells to recognize. Interestingly, we observed that T cells reduced the bacillary content of infected cells to a point, and the minimum value was similar for all the different cell types. If the intrinsic antibacterial activity of MDM reduces the intracellular bacterial burden without killing the bacilli, the result could be a macrophage where <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> persists but can&#x02019;t be recognized by T cells. Finally, there is an additional factor. Transfer of CD4 T cells to RAG knockout mice leads to reduced CFU and YFP signal compared to un-transferred mice, showing CD4 T cells are critical to protection. However, CD4 T cells also promote the recruitment of macrophages to the lung, presumably through the elaboration of chemokines such as CCL2, CCL5, or CX3CL1. Although monocyte and macrophage recruitment to an inflammatory site is generally viewed as a beneficial response, in the case of tuberculosis, it provides a new crop of macrophages that can be infected by <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> and are permissive for its survival and replication.</p></sec><sec id="S10"><title>Methods</title><sec id="S11"><title>Ethics Statement.</title><p id="P26">Studies involving animals were conducted following relevant guidelines and regulations, and the studies were approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee at the University of Massachusetts Medical School (Animal Welfare A3306&#x02013;01), using the recommendations from the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals of the National Institutes of Health and the Office of Laboratory Animal Welfare.</p></sec><sec id="S12"><title>In vivo infection.</title><p id="P27">C57BL/6J were purchased from Jackson Laboratories (Bar Harbor, ME). H37Rv expressing yellow fluorescent protein (YFP) has been previously described<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref></sup>. The mice were exposed to an aerosolized inoculum of Rv.YFP using a Glas-Col Inhalation Exposure System (Glas-Col LLC, Terre Haute, IN) as described<sup><xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref></sup>. The number of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> deposited in the lungs was determined for each experiment and varied ranging between 37&#x02013;90 CFU.</p></sec><sec id="S13"><title>CD4 and CD8 T cell depletion.</title><p id="P28">200 &#x003bc;g of either anti-CD4 (clone GK1.5) or anti-CD8 (clone 2.43) mAb were injected intra-peritoneally biweekly starting on day 21 for 14 days to deplete CD4 and/or CD8 T cells.</p></sec><sec id="S14"><title>Lung cell preparation.</title><p id="P29">To isolate total lung leukocytes, lungs were perfused by slowly injecting PBS into right ventricle immediately after mice were killed. The lungs were minced with a gentleMACS dissociator (Miltenyi) and digested (30 min, 37&#x000b0;C) in 250 U/ml collagenase and 60 U/ml DNase (both from Sigma-Aldrich). Lung cell suspensions were passed through a 70-&#x003bc;m and 40-&#x003bc;m strainers sequentially to remove cell clumps. Lung cells were resuspended in autoMACS running buffer (Miltenyi) that contains BSA, EDTA, and 0.09% sodium azide for subsequent staining.</p></sec><sec id="S15"><title>Flow cytometry analysis.</title><p id="P30">Cells were first stained with Zombie Fixable Viability dye (Biolegend) for 10 minutes at room temperature (RT), after which cells were stained with 5 ug/ml of anti-mouse CD16/32 mAb (BioXcell) in autoMACS running buffer (Miltenyi) for 10 minutes at 4&#x000b0;C. Next, the cells were then stained with a surface antibody cocktail for 20 minutes at 4&#x000b0;C. The antibodies included a dump channel was used to exclude T cells, B cells, and NK cells for efficient myeloid cell analysis and included anti-Thy1.2 (clone 30H12), anti-CD19 (clone 6D5), and anti-NK1.1 (clone PK136) with PE-Cy7. Macrophages were subsequently defined based on a combination of CD11c (clone N418), SiglecF (clone E50&#x02013;2440), Mertk (clone 2B10C42), CD64 (clone X54&#x02013;5/7.1), Ly6c (clone HK1.4). To inactivate the bacteria, samples were fixed with 1% paraformaldehyde/PBS for 1 hour at room temperature and then washed with MACS buffer. Samples were run on either a 4 or 5 laser Cytek Aurora. Erdman (non-fluorescent) infected mice used for unstained control, single stains and YFP-FMO. Autofluorescence was treated as a fluorescent parameter during unmixing either automatically through the SpectralFlo software or by manually deriving an autofluorescence fingerprint (assigned to BV510). After unmixing FMOs were used to apply manual compensation to correct for unmixing anomalies. Flow data were analyzed using FlowJo v10.7.1.</p><sec id="S35"><title>Adoptive transfer model:</title><p id="P31">Spleens and lymph nodes from C57BL/6J mice were mechanically disrupted onto 70 &#x003bc;m strainers using the plungers of 3 mL syringes. CD4 T cells were purified from spleens and lymph nodes using MojoSort<sup>&#x02122;</sup> CD4 isolation kit and magnet (Biolegend). Purities of cells were determined for each experiment using flow cytometry. 2&#x02013;5 million CD4 T cells were transferred into TCR&#x003b1; KO mice before infecting with Erdman.</p></sec></sec><sec id="S16"><title>Cell sorting.</title><p id="P32">Cells were sorted using Sony MA900 located in the biosafety level 3 lab in University of Massachusetts Medical School. Cells were stained with Zombie violet to exclude dead cells. Target cells were separated 2-way into polypropylene FACS tubes containing 2 ml of FBS. CD45 (clone 104) was used to identify hematopoietic cells, after which Thy1.2 (clone 30H12), CD19 (clone 6D5) and Ly6G (clone 1A8) were used to remove lymphocytes and neutrophils. Macrophages were identified using a combination of CD11c (clone N418), SiglecF (clone E50&#x02013;2440), Mertk (clone 2B10C42), CD64 (clone X54&#x02013;5/7.1).</p></sec><sec id="S17"><title>Aminoguanidine treatment and NO quantification.</title><p id="P33">Mice were supplied with drinking water containing 2.5% aminoguanidine hemisulfate (A7009&#x02013;100G Sigma) starting from week 3 post infection. Water was replaced once a week. Nitric oxide levels were quantified in lung homogenates using a Greiss assay (G4410&#x02013;10G Sigma) as previously described<sup><xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="S18"><title>Statistical analysis.</title><p id="P34">Statistical analysis was performed using Prism 9 (GraphPad). P-values were calculated using unpaired t test, one-way ANOVA, or two-way ANOVA as indicated in the figure legends.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="SM1"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="SD1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>1</label><media xlink:href="NIHPP2023.11.29.569283V1-supplement-1.pdf" id="d64e1127" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="S19"><title>Acknowledgements.</title><p id="P35">This work was funded by NIH/NIAID grants to S.M.B.: R01AI106725, R01 AI123286, and P01 AI132130.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="FN2"><p id="P36"><bold>Declaration of interests.</bold> The authors declare no competing interests.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name>, <etal/>
<article-title>Alveolar Macrophages Provide an Early Mycobacterium tuberculosis Niche and Initiate Dissemination</article-title>. <source>Cell Host Microbe</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>439</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>446 e434</lpage> (<year>2018</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30146391</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <etal/>
<article-title>Initiation of the adaptive immune response to Mycobacterium tuberculosis depends on antigen production in the local lymph node, not the lungs</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source>
<volume>205</volume>, <fpage>105</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>115</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18158321</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chackerian</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alt</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Perera</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dascher</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Behar</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Dissemination of Mycobacterium tuberculosis Is Influenced by Host Factors and Precedes the Initiation of T-Cell Immunity</article-title>. <source>Infection and Immunity</source>
<volume>70</volume>, <fpage>4501</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4509</lpage> (<year>2002</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12117962</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Skold</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Behar</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Tuberculosis triggers a tissue-dependent program of differentiation and acquisition of effector functions by circulating monocytes</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>
<volume>181</volume>, <fpage>6349</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6360</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18941226</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Norris</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ernst</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mononuclear cell dynamics in M. tuberculosis infection provide opportunities for therapeutic intervention</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>e1007154</fpage> (<year>2018</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30365557</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gonzalez-Juarrero</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shim</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kipnis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Junqueira-Kipnis</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Orme</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Dynamics of macrophage cell populations during murine pulmonary tuberculosis</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>
<volume>171</volume>, <fpage>3128</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3135</lpage> (<year>2003</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12960339</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <etal/>
<article-title>Mycobacterium tuberculosis infects dendritic cells with high frequency and impairs their function in vivo</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>
<volume>179</volume>, <fpage>2509</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2519</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17675513</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Repasy</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal/>
<article-title>Intracellular bacillary burden reflects a burst size for Mycobacterium tuberculosis in vivo</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>e1003190</fpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23436998</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boyce</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sassetti</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Behar</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>. <article-title>CD11cHi monocyte-derived macrophages are a major cellular compartment infected by Mycobacterium tuberculosis</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>e1008621</fpage> (<year>2020</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32544188</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bryson</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name>, <etal/>
<article-title>Heterogeneous GM-CSF signaling in macrophages is associated with control of Mycobacterium tuberculosis</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>2329</fpage> (<year>2019</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31133636</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pisu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grenier</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>. <article-title>Dual RNA-Seq of Mtb-Infected Macrophages In Vivo Reveals Ontologically Distinct Host-Pathogen Interactions</article-title>. <source>Cell Rep</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>335</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>350 e334</lpage> (<year>2020</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31940480</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nazarova</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name>. <article-title>Growth of Mycobacterium tuberculosis in vivo segregates with host macrophage metabolism and ontogeny</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source>, (<year>2018</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rothchild</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <etal/>
<article-title>Alveolar macrophages generate a noncanonical NRF2-driven transcriptional response to Mycobacterium tuberculosis in vivo</article-title>. <source>Sci Immunol</source>
<volume>4</volume>, (<year>2019</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pisu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal/>
<article-title>Single cell analysis of M. tuberculosis phenotype and macrophage lineages in the infected lung</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source>
<volume>218</volume>, (<year>2021</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ernst</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cutting edge: Direct recognition of infected cells by CD4 T cells is required for control of intracellular Mycobacterium tuberculosis in vivo</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>
<volume>191</volume>, <fpage>1016</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1020</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23817429</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <etal/>
<article-title>Mycobacterium tuberculosis-specific CD4+ and CD8+ T cells differ in their capacity to recognize infected macrophages</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>e1007060</fpage> (<year>2018</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29782535</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bold</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Banaei</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ernst</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Suboptimal activation of antigen-specific CD4+ effector cells enables persistence of M. tuberculosis in vivo</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>e1002063</fpage> (<year>2011</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21637811</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Patankar</surname><given-names>YR</given-names></name>, <etal/>
<article-title>Limited recognition of Mycobacterium tuberculosis-infected macrophages by polyclonal CD4 and CD8 T cells from the lungs of infected mice</article-title>. <source>Mucosal Immunol</source>
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>140</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>148</lpage> (<year>2020</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31636345</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sutiwisesak</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal/>
<article-title>A natural polymorphism of Mycobacterium tuberculosis in the esxH gene disrupts immunodomination by the TB10.4-specific CD8 T cell response</article-title>. <source>PLOS Pathogens</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>e1009000</fpage> (<year>2020</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33075106</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lewinsohn</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heinzel</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alderson</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lewinsohn</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mycobacterium tuberculosis-specific CD8+ T cells preferentially recognize heavily infected cells</article-title>. <source>Am J Respir Crit Care Med</source>
<volume>168</volume>, <fpage>1346</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1352</lpage> (<year>2003</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12969871</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mott</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Papavinasasundaram</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sassetti</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Behar</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>. <article-title>High Bacillary Burden and the ESX-1 Type VII Secretion System Promote MHC Class I Presentation by Mycobacterium tuberculosis-Infected Macrophages to CD8 T Cells</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>
<volume>210</volume>, <fpage>1531</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1542</lpage> (<year>2023</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37000471</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McCubbrey</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Allison</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lee-Sherick</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jakubzick</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Promoter Specificity and Efficacy in Conditional and Inducible Transgenic Targeting of Lung Macrophages</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>1618</fpage> (<year>2017</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29225599</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aegerter</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal/>
<article-title>Influenza-induced monocyte-derived alveolar macrophages confer prolonged antibacterial protection</article-title>. <source>Nat Immunol</source>
<volume>21</volume>, <fpage>145</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>157</lpage> (<year>2020</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31932810</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Misharin</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name>, <etal/>
<article-title>Monocyte-derived alveolar macrophages drive lung fibrosis and persist in the lung over the life span</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source>
<volume>214</volume>, <fpage>2387</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2404</lpage> (<year>2017</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28694385</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ural</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name>, <etal/>
<article-title>Identification of a nerve-associated, lung-resident interstitial macrophage subset with distinct localization and immunoregulatory properties</article-title>. <source>Sci Immunol</source>
<volume>5</volume>, (<year>2020</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chackerian</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alt</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Perera</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dascher</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Behar</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Dissemination of Mycobacterium tuberculosis is influenced by host factors and precedes the initiation of T-cell immunity</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>
<volume>70</volume>, <fpage>4501</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4509</lpage> (<year>2002</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12117962</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cooper</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cell-Mediated Immune Responses in Tuberculosis</article-title>. <source>Annual Review of Immunology</source>
<volume>27</volume>, <fpage>393</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>422</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lewinsohn</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lewinsohn</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Missing Link in Correlates of Protective Tuberculosis Immunity: Recognizing the Infected Cell</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source>
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>869057</fpage> (<year>2022</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35493495</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jamaati</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal/>
<article-title>Nitric Oxide in the Pathogenesis and Treatment of Tuberculosis</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>2008</fpage> (<year>2017</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29085351</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mogues</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Goodrich</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>LaCourse</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>North</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>The relative importance of T cell subsets in immunity and immunopathology of airborne Mycobacterium tuberculosis infection in mice</article-title>. <source>The Journal of experimental medicine</source>
<volume>193</volume>, <fpage>271</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>280</lpage> (<year>2001</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11157048</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>MacMicking</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>North</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>LaCourse</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mudgett</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nathan</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name>. <article-title>Identification of nitric oxide synthase as a protective locus against tuberculosis</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>94</volume>, <fpage>5243</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5248</lpage> (<year>1997</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9144222</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name>, <etal/>
<article-title>Nitric oxide controls the immunopathology of tuberculosis by inhibiting NLRP3 inflammasome-dependent processing of IL-1beta</article-title>. <source>Nat Immunol</source>
<volume>14</volume>, <fpage>52</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23160153</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name>, <etal/>
<article-title>Nitric oxide prevents a pathogen-permissive granulocytic inflammation during tuberculosis</article-title>. <source>Nat Microbiol</source>
<volume>2</volume>, <fpage>17072</fpage> (<year>2017</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28504669</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barreira-Silva</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boyce</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cavallo</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Behar</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>. <article-title>CD4 T cell help prevents CD8 T cell exhaustion and promotes control of Mycobacterium tuberculosis infection</article-title>. <source>Cell Rep</source>
<volume>36</volume>, <fpage>109696</fpage> (<year>2021</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34525366</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lowenstein</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <etal/>
<article-title>Macrophage nitric oxide synthase gene: two upstream regions mediate induction by interferon gamma and lipopolysaccharide</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
<volume>90</volume>, <fpage>9730</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9734</lpage> (<year>1993</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7692452</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nunes-Alves</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Booty</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jayaraman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rothchild</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Behar</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>. <article-title>In search of a new paradigm for protective immunity to TB</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>289</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>299</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24590243</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name>, <etal/>
<article-title>IFN-&#x003b3;-independent immune markers of Mycobacterium tuberculosis exposure</article-title>. <source>Nature Medicine</source>
<volume>25</volume>, <fpage>977</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>987</lpage> (<year>2019</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Van Dis</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <etal/>
<article-title>IFN-gamma-independent control of M. tuberculosis requires CD4 T cell-derived GM-CSF and activation of HIF-1alpha</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>e1010721</fpage> (<year>2022</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35877763</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sakai</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <etal/>
<article-title>CD4 T Cell-Derived IFN-gamma Plays a Minimal Role in Control of Pulmonary Mycobacterium tuberculosis Infection and Must Be Actively Repressed by PD-1 to Prevent Lethal Disease</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>e1005667</fpage> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27244558</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jagannath</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <article-title>Macrophage heterogeneity and plasticity in tuberculosis</article-title>. <source>J Leukoc Biol</source>
<volume>106</volume>, <fpage>275</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>282</lpage> (<year>2019</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30938876</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jayaraman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal/>
<article-title>TIM3 Mediates T Cell Exhaustion during Mycobacterium tuberculosis Infection</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>e1005490</fpage> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26967901</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lovewell</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baer</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mishra</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sassetti</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Granulocytes act as a niche for Mycobacterium tuberculosis growth</article-title>. <source>Mucosal Immunol</source>, (<year>2020</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal/>
<article-title>Host genetic background is a barrier to broadly effective vaccine protection: Relevance to BCG and Mycobacterium tuberculosis Infection</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source>
<comment>(in press)</comment>, (<year>2023</year>).</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1:</label><caption><p id="P37">The effect of CD4 and CD8 T cell depletion on lung and spleen CFU.</p><p id="P38">(A) Experimental schematic. Mice were infected with Rv.YFP as indicated and rested for 3 weeks, after which CD4 and CD8 depleting mAbs were given over the course of two weeks at the indicated timepoints. (B) Proportion of CD4 and CD8 T cells in the lungs of infected C57BL/6 mice at 5 weeks post infection following treatment with either anti-CD4 and/or anti-CD8 depleting mAbs. (C) Lung and spleen CFU at 5 weeks post infection following treatment either anti-CD4 and/or anti-CD8 depleting mAbs. Each point represents an individual mouse from two independent experiments (n=5/group) for week 3 data, and three independent experiments for week 5 data. Each condition was compared to the undepleted group using the Brown-Forsythe and Welch&#x02019;s ANOVA test was performed.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2023.11.29.569283v1-f0001" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2:</label><caption><p id="P39">Distribution of <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic>-infected cells early after infection.</p><p id="P40">(A) Gating strategy for identifying various myeloid populations. In brief, a viability dye was used to exclude dead cells. CD3, CD19 and NK1.1 were used to exclude lymphocytes and NK cells from the hematopoietic cells. Mertk and CD64 were used to separate macrophages from monocyte/DC subsets. SiglecF and CD11c were used to separate AM from MDM populations, then used to subset various MDM populations. CD11b was used to subset different AM populations. CD11c and Ly6c were used to subset various monocyte/DC populations. (B) Quantification of various myeloid cells in the lung at week 3 and week 5 post infection, expressed in terms of total cell numbers (top) or as a percentage of total myeloid cells (bottom). (C) Quantification of the YFP signal in various myeloid cells in the lung at week 3 and week 5 post infection, expressed in terms of total cell numbers (top), %YFP of each population (middle) or the fraction of each population of the total YFP+ cells (bottom). (D) Flow sorted AM and MDM2 were plated to determine intracellular CFU within each purified population. (C, D) Each point represents an individual mouse from two independent experiment (n=5/group) for week 3 data, and three independent experiments for week 5 data. A two-way ANOVA was performed using Bonferonni&#x02019;s multiple comparison test. (D) Representative results from two different experiments using cells purified from lung cells pooled from five mice, tested in triplicate, and analyzed using a t-test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2023.11.29.569283v1-f0002" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3:</label><caption><p id="P41">Lung myeloid cells react differently to the loss of CD4 and CD8 T cell pressures. Quantification of YFP signal within various myeloid populations in the lung at 5 weeks post infection following CD4 and/or CD8 depletion. (A) Representative flow plots of YFP signal in AM1 and MDM2, plotted against autofluorescence. Top number represents the frequency of YFP+ events, bottom number are the total number of YFP+ cells. (B-D) Graphical representation of YFP signal in different myeloid subsets, expressed as (B) %YFP+ cells within each subset (C) MFI of YFP within each subset (D) and %YFP+ cells out of total myeloid cells. Each point represents an individual mouse from two independent experiments (n=5/group). A two-way ANOVA was performed using Tukey&#x02019;s multiple comparison test. Some statistical comparisons have been omitted for clarity.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2023.11.29.569283v1-f0003" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4:</label><caption><p id="P42">T cell depletion affects NOS2 expression. (A) The percentage of different myeloid cell types in the lung that express NOS2 5 wpi. (B) Correlation between %NOS2 expression and %YFP signal in various myeloid populations. (C) The percentage of infected (YFP+) cells that express NOS2. (D) The effect of CD4 and/or CD8 T cell depletion on the distribution of YFP+ cells among NOS2+ and NOS2&#x02212; cells, as a percentage of total myeloid cells in the lung 5 wpi. (E) Data from panel D expressed as a ratio of NOS2+ vs. NOS2&#x02212; cells. Each point represents an individual mouse. The data is representative data from one of two independent experiments (n=5/group). A two-way ANOVA was performed using "&#x00160;&#x000ed;d&#x000e1;k's multiple comparisons test.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2023.11.29.569283v1-f0004" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5:</label><caption><p id="P43">Inhibition of NOS2 does not increase intracellular bacterial burden. (A) Experimental schematic for AG treatment. Mice were giving AG in their drinking water starting from week 3 post infection over the course of two weeks. (B) Lung and spleen CFU from mice treated with AG at 5 wpi. (C) Total numbers of various myeloid populations in the lung at 5 wpi. (D) %YFP+ as a fraction of total myeloid cells following AG treatment at 5 wpi. Each point represents an individual mouse from two independent experiments (n=5/group). A two-way ANOVA was performed using Tukey&#x02019;s multiple comparison test (D) or Dunnett&#x02019;s test (E).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2023.11.29.569283v1-f0005" position="float"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p id="P44">Adoptive transfer of CD4 T cells drive recruitment of MDM to the lung. (A) Experimental schematic for CD4 T cell adoptive transfer. RAG<sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> were infected with Rv.YFP as indicated and rested for 3 weeks. In parallel, C57BL/6 mice were also infected with <italic toggle="yes">M. tuberculosis</italic> Erdman strain, and at 3 wpi, polyclonal CD4 T cells were purified and transferred i.v. into the RAG<sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> mice. Cells were isolated from RAG<sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> mice two weeks post transfer, and bacterial burden was also examined. (B) Lung CFU was determined in RAG<sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> mice that either received CD4 T cells or PBS. (C) Total numbers of various myeloid populations were also enumerated at this timepoint. (D) % YFP (left) and the MFI of YFP (right) within each myeloid population was examined. (E) Total number of YFP+ cells within each myeloid subset (left) and the % of infected cells within each population as a fraction of total infected cells (right). The data is representative data from one of three independent experiments (n=5/group). Statistical analysis was performed using a t-test (B), a two-way ANOVA with Tukey&#x02019;s multiple comparison test (C), or &#x00160;&#x000ed;d&#x000e1;k's multiple comparisons (D, E).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nihpp-2023.11.29.569283v1-f0006" position="float"/></fig></floats-group></article>
