<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Virulence</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Virulence</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Virulence</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2150-5594</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2150-5608</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Taylor &#x00026; Francis</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37941391</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC10732690</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/21505594.2023.2275493</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2275493</article-id><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" vocab-term="Version of Record" article-version-type="VoR">Version of Record</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila melanogaster</italic> model shows that fast growing <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> species are the deadliest despite eliciting a strong immune response</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">J. B. WANG ET AL.</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="right-running-head">VIRULENCE</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Jonathan B.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff"/><xref rid="an0002" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><xref rid="b0001" ref-type="bio"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Hsiao-Ling</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff"/><xref rid="an0002" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sheng</surname><given-names>Huiyu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7386-6775</contrib-id><name><surname>St. Leger</surname><given-names>Raymond J</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff"/><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><aff id="aff0001">Department of Entomology, <institution-wrap><institution>University of Maryland</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>College Park</city>, <state>MD</state>, <country>USA</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">CONTACT Raymond J St. Leger <email xlink:href="mailto:stleger@umd.edu">stleger@umd.edu</email></corresp><fn id="an0002"><label>*</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>8</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>8</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id seq="98">2275493</elocation-id><pub-history><event event-type="tagger"><event-desc>Integra</event-desc><date><day>06</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="final"><event-desc>Integra</event-desc><date><day>06</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="received"><date><day>10</day><month>7</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="revised"><date><day>03</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="accepted"><date><day>19</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2023 The Author(s). Published by Informa UK Limited, trading as Taylor &#x00026; Francis Group.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. The terms on which this article has been published allow the posting of the Accepted Manuscript in a repository by the author(s) or with their consent.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="KVIR_14_2275493.pdf"/><abstract><title>ABSTRACT</title><p>We used <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila melanogaster</italic> to investigate how differences between <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> species in growth rate and mechanisms of pathogenesis influence the outcome of infection. We found that the most rapid germinators and growers <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> and on fly cuticle were the fastest killers, suggesting that pre-penetration competence is key to <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> success. Virulent strains also induced the largest immune response, which did not depend on profuse growth within hosts as virulent toxin-producing strains only proliferated post-mortem while slow-killing strains that were specialized to other insects grew profusely pre-mortem. <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> strains have apparently evolved resistance to widely distributed defenses such as the defensin Toll product drosomycin, but they were inhibited by Bomanins only found in <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> spp. Disrupting a gene (<italic toggle="yes">Dif</italic>), that mediates Toll immunity has little impact on the lethality of most <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> strains (an exception being the early diverged <italic toggle="yes">M. frigidum</italic> and another insect pathogen <italic toggle="yes">Beauveria bassiana</italic>). However, disrupting the sensor of fungal proteases (<italic toggle="yes">Persephone</italic>) allowed rapid proliferation of strains within hosts (with the exception of <italic toggle="yes">M. album</italic>), and flies succumbed rapidly. Persephone also mediates gender differences in immune responses that determine whether male or female flies die sooner. We conclude that some strain differences in growth within hosts depend on immune-mediated interactions but intrinsic differences in pathogenic mechanisms are more important. Thus, <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> varies greatly in tolerance to different <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> strains, in part because some of them produce toxins. Our results further develop <italic toggle="yes">D. melanogaster</italic> as a tractable model system for understanding insect-<italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> interactions.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>KEYWORDS</title><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic></kwd><kwd>resistance and tolerance; <italic toggle="yes">metarhizium</italic></kwd><kwd>immune activation; immunity</kwd><kwd>gender differences; Bomanins</kwd><kwd>inhibit <italic toggle="yes">metarhizium</italic>; Persephone</kwd><kwd>fungal loads</kwd></kwd-group><support-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>National Institute of Food and Agriculture</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="open-funder-registry">10.13039/100005825</institution-id></institution-wrap>
</funding-source><award-id>1015969</award-id></award-group><funding-statement>The work was supported by the&#x000a0;National Institute of Food and Agriculture [1015969].</funding-statement></funding-group></support-group><counts><fig-count count="8"/><table-count count="1"/><ref-count count="61"/><page-count count="1"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" disp-level="1" id="s0001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Most models of interactions between hosts and pathogens are based on the concept of tightly coupled, co-evolved interactions between species pairs [<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. This is despite the fact that most pathogens of plants and animals are generalists that infect multiple-host species and evidence that many emerging diseases are caused by generalists, of which fungal diseases make up the majority [<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The outcomes of pathogen infection vary widely because hosts differ in their resistance and tolerance to infection, while pathogens vary in their ability to grow on or within hosts [<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. This variation determines the burden of disease and represents the raw material from which populations can evolve resistance [<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Insects are continually exposed to a vast number of potential pathogens, and they have evolved a series of intricate mechanisms to resist pathogen attacks [<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. These pathogens are dynamic agents of host selection as reflected in the genetic variation in resistance in wild insect populations [<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6&#x02013;8</xref>].</p><p>Fungi cause a large proportion of insect diseases [<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] and include the ascomycete genus <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic>, which is a radiating lineage of insect pathogens [<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. In addition to their crucial role in natural ecosystems, <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> spp. are frequently used as biological insecticides [<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>] and for genomic studies on the nature of adaptive differences by which novel pathogens emerge and form new species [<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. While many <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> strains in nature seem to be limited to a narrow range of hosts, others attack a broad range of species. Thus, <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium album, Metarhizium acridum</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium majus</italic> specialize in hemipterans, orthopterans, and coleopteran insects, respectively [<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium frigidum</italic> has evolved independently as a generalist, whereas <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium pingshaense, Metarhizium anisopliae</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium robertsii,</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium brunneum</italic> (the PARB clade) have more recently evolved and parasitize many insect orders, including dipterans [<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> spp. thus provide a model for studying the basis of generalism and specificity and the potential of pathogens to cross the species barrier and infect new hosts.</p><p>An infection by <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> typically starts with conidial adhesion to the insect integument, followed by germination, which is triggered by topographical and chemical signals from insect cuticles and environmental cues, such as relative humidity [<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Germlings produce adhesive infection structures (appressoria), and hyphal penetration through the host cuticle occurs through a combination of mechanical pressure and cuticle-degrading enzymes including many proteases [<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Penetrating multicellular hyphae respond to factors present in the host hemolymph by switching to growth as single-celled blastospores that facilitate dissemination and have mechanisms to evade the insect immune system [<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Once the host is dead, the fungus breaches the cuticle from the inside outwards, allowing the formation of conidia that, upon dispersal, start new infections [<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Thus, the onward transmission of <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> requires the death of the host, that is, it is an obligate killer.</p><p>Some <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> strains are capable of infecting <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila melanogaster</italic> providing a genetically tractable system for studying host&#x02013;pathogen interactions. Those strains that are not adapted to <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> are presumably unable to infect, grow within the fly, or transmit to new hosts as well-adapted pathogens. Relating host specificity and infection, <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> species differ in the host-related factors required to induce appressoria [<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], and in their infection strategies. For example, both <italic toggle="yes">M. anisopliae</italic> ARSEF strain 549 (Ma549) and <italic toggle="yes">M. robertsii</italic> ARSEF strain 2575 (Mr2575) have broad host ranges, but Ma549 is biotrophic (grows through the living host) and produces little destruxins (toxins) whereas Mr2575 kills with toxins and is subsequently necrotrophic [<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. Like Ma549, the broad host range <italic toggle="yes">M. frigidum</italic> also lacks destruxins, although in general nontoxigenic <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic>, spp. such as <italic toggle="yes">M. album, M. acridum,</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">M. majus</italic> have narrow host ranges [<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p><p>Fungal infection processes encounter a dedicated immune response that includes melanization and antimicrobial peptides (AMPs) [<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], generated by the highly conserved Toll pathway, the chief <italic toggle="yes">D. melanogaster</italic> antifungal pathway described in the literature [<xref rid="cit0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="cit0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. In this species, the circulating protease Persephone (<italic toggle="yes">Psh</italic>), an immune sensor of pathogen proteases, and GNBP3, which detects fungal wall components, act exclusively to detect infection. They link their activation to proteolytic serine protease cascades, which induce Toll-mediated AMP transcription through nuclear translocation of <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> Dif, an NF-&#x003ba;B homolog [<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="cit0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. Insects disrupted in <italic toggle="yes">Dif</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">Psh</italic> succumb quickly to the entomopathogenic fungus <italic toggle="yes">Beauveria bassiana</italic> [<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. We previously found that despite fungal recognition and Toll immune elicitation by flies, infection with Ma549 could not be successfully eliminated [<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. A genome-wide association study (GWAS) deploying the <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> Genetic Reference Panel (DGRP) found considerable genetic variation in the susceptibility of <italic toggle="yes">D</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">melanogaster</italic> to Ma549, but how long DGRP lines took to succumb to Ma549 was not associated with differences in genes implicated in canonical immune processes [<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. These studies have revealed a complex genetic architecture for disease resistance to Ma549, with large numbers of pleiotropic genes and alleles with sex-, environment-, and genetic background-specific effects. The extent to which the resistance architecture of <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> differs against different <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> strains is unclear.</p><p>In this study, we used a strain of <italic toggle="yes">M. robertsii</italic> isolated from <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila suzukii</italic>, a generalist strain of <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> spp. with diverse pathogenic strategies, and specialists not adapted to <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic>, in comparative analyses to examine the relationship between virulence, growth, nutritional plasticity, transmission, and mechanisms to evade host immunity. We tested whether virulence was positively correlated with pathogen growth rate and transmission, as commonly assumed by virulence theory [<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], and examined whether virulence was correlated with life-history variables that influence the progression of pathogenesis (<xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>, Supplementary Table S1). These variables included: (i) the spore dose required to establish infection; (ii) the impact of humidity on infection as humidity is particularly critical for fungal sporulation, germination, and invasion of insect hosts [<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]; (iii) the time of onset, magnitude, and efficacy of the Toll immune response; (iv) the period of time preceding death when the host is immobilized (immobilization time); (v) the interval between death and the onset of sporulation; and (vi) sporulation capacity per cadaver. We found that the most virulent strains elicited the strongest immune responses. Therefore, their success as pathogens may be due to their ability to adapt to and resist the insect innate immune response. To investigate this possibility, we surveyed <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> strains against <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> mutants with defects in the immune system. Overall, our analysis indicated that the outcome of an infection depends on factors specific to each pathogen interacting with diverse aspects of host immunity and that there are no simple extrapolations between the magnitude of an immune response and duration of survival, even between related pathogens and a single host species.
<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Phylogeny of <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> spp. (a) a phylogenomic tree for the <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> species used in this study. Right of tree, the bars indicate times for the onset of a fly&#x02019;s immune response (detected by Drs-GFP fluorescence), immobilization and death. The % germination provided are after 18 or 40 hrs in yeast extract medium (YEM) or in glucose medium, and after 16 hrs on insect cuticle (fly wings). Fungal growth in the hemolymph (colony forming units (CFU&#x02019;s) at the commencement of the immobilization period), sporulation (spore counts per cadaver) and radial growth on PDA are provided as measures of growth. Further details are provided in Supplemental tables S1 and S2. (b) rapid germination and growth of <italic toggle="yes">M. robertsii</italic> 2575 conidia (expressing cherry) compared to <italic toggle="yes">M. majus</italic> 1946 (expressing GFP) on fly wings (the ungerminated conidia of <italic toggle="yes">M. majus</italic> are approximately 10&#x02009;&#x000b5;m long) (c) GFP-expressing <italic toggle="yes">M. robertsii</italic> 2105 photographed on the abdomen and wings of a fly 24- and 60-hours post-infection. Flies or their wings were visualized with epifluorescence, with filters set to detect GFP or cherry fluorescence.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="KVIR_A_2275493_F0001_OC" content-type="color" specific-use="web-only" position="float"/><graphic xlink:href="KVIR_A_2275493_F0001_PB" content-type="black-white" specific-use="print-only" position="float"/></alternatives></fig></p></sec><sec disp-level="1" id="s0002"><title>Results</title><sec disp-level="2" id="s0002-s2001"><title>Infection protocols</title><p><xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1a</xref> shows the phylogeny of the <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> strains deployed in this study and the distribution of experimentally determined phenotypes. Further details, including their USDA ARSEF collection accession numbers, original hosts, and infection parameters, including differences in LT<sub>50</sub>, are shown in Supplementary Table S1. Infection involved immersing flies in a spore suspension, typically 2.5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>4</sup> per ml for studies with mutant flies, which results in&#x02009;~200 spores/fly [<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. At a high spore concentration (1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> per ml), LT<sub>50</sub>&#x02019;s ranged from 2.92 (<italic toggle="yes">M. robertsii</italic> 2575) to 5.72 (<italic toggle="yes">M. acridum</italic> 5736). Infection with <italic toggle="yes">M. album</italic> 1941 did not reduce the fly lifespan.</p><p>Laboratory infection of <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> by the &#x0201c;natural route&#x0201d; through the cuticle rather than injection typically involves rolling flies on a plate of sporulating fungi, so the insects are covered in a layer of spores. Taylor and Kimbrell [<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] reported that after infection with <italic toggle="yes">B. bassiana</italic> spores in this manner, all parts of the body are groomed and cleaned as much as possible, leaving only the areas that are hard to reach, mainly the back of the thorax, with any visible fungal spores. Our alternative procedure of immersing flies in a spore suspension did not produce a visible layer of spores on the insect. However, using GFP-expressing spores of various <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> strains, we found that grooming removed most, but not all, spores from the sclerites (smooth and hard portions of the fly&#x02019;s body); although, irrespective of the strain, spores were frequently trapped in loose aggregations in the intersegmental regions of the abdomen (<xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1c</xref>). Therefore, grooming is unlikely to contribute to the differential virulence of <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> strains.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="s0002-s2002"><title>How does environmental humidity affect the lethality of <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> strains with different virulence?</title><p>We investigated whether favorable humidity for spore germination and pathogenicity was involved in the differential virulence of the strains. We used Toll activity readout (Drs-GFP) flies [containing a reporter construct that expressed GFP (green fluorescent protein) under control of the drosomycin reporter] to check if there was a time difference for immune-response fluorescence at 98% and 80% relative humidity (RH) when infected with representative virulent <italic toggle="yes">M. anisopliae</italic> (Ma2105), intermediate virulence <italic toggle="yes">M. acridum</italic> (Mac324), and low-virulence <italic toggle="yes">M. pingshaense</italic> (Mp443) strains. All three fungal strains killed significantly faster at 98% RH than at 80% RH (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) (<xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). At each RH, Ma2105 was significantly more virulent than Ma324 or Mp443 (At 98% RH, Ma2105 vs. Ma324, <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.54, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0403; Ma2105 vs Mp443, <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7.61 <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0046. At 80% RH, Ma2105 vs. Ma324, <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;9.02, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.005; Ma2105 vs Mp443, <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;36.46 <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0004). Increased spore germination at high RH produced an earlier immune response (<xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>), consistent with more rapid penetration into the insect as Drs-GFP immunofluorescence was negatively correlated with speed of kill (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;0.782, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0128 at 72&#x02009;h post-infection). Although 98% humidity dramatically increased both mortality and Drs-GFP immunofluorescence for the three strains, it did not make Mp443 or Mac324 as virulent to flies as Ma2105.
<fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>The effect of humidity on <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> spp. Fly (Drs-GFP) immune system responses to infection with 5&#x000d7;10<sup>6</sup> spores of <italic toggle="yes">M. anisopliae</italic> 2015, <italic toggle="yes">M. acridum</italic> 324 and <italic toggle="yes">M. pingshaense</italic> 443 at different relative humidity&#x02019;s (98%, and 80%) was studied by measuring drosomycin expression and calculating LT<sub>50</sub> values. a) control and infected flies were maintained in petri dishes covered in nylon mesh (pink) and with access to food placed on the mesh. The petri dishes were placed on water saturated tissues (98% RH) or over a saturated solution of NaCl (80% RH). b) faster kills at higher RH elicits earlier and higher Drs-GFP immunofluorescence in infected insects. Fluorescence data was collected 16, 24, 48, and 72 h post-infection. Points represent the means of 10 individual flies&#x000b1;SE. Control flies were treated with water instead of spore suspensions and incubated at different RH in parallel with infected flies.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="KVIR_A_2275493_F0002_OC" content-type="color" specific-use="web-only" position="float"/><graphic xlink:href="KVIR_A_2275493_F0002_PB" content-type="black-white" specific-use="print-only" position="float"/></alternatives></fig></p><p>Using a high (1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> per ml) spore concentration to provide a sufficient number of spores to count on cuticle surfaces, we also monitored the germination of GFP-fluorescent Mp443 or Ma2105 on different parts of <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> bodies at different RH levels (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). At 80% RH, germination occurred almost exclusively on intersegmental abdominal membranes, whereas after 16&#x02009;h at 98% humidity, more than 50% of spores had germinated on all parts of the fly&#x02019;s body. We conclude that <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> intersegmental membranes possess an adequate microclimate to promote germination at low ambient RH, as has been reported for larger insects [<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. <table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>The germination rates of two <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> strains on <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila melanogaster</italic> at different relative humidity.</p></caption><!--OASIS TABLE HERE--><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup><col width="1*" align="left"/><col width="1*" align="left"/><col width="1*" align="center"/><col width="1*" align="center"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left">&#x000a0;</th><th align="left">&#x000a0;</th><th align="center">98% RH<hr/></th><th align="center">80% RH<hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left">Hours post-infection</th><th align="left">Location</th><th align="center">Germination rates (%)<break/>(mean&#x000b1;SEM)</th><th align="center">Germination rates (%)<break/>(mean&#x000b1;SEM)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><bold>Strain Mp443</bold></td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">16 hr</td><td align="left">Ventral abdomen</td><td align="center">59.9&#x000b1;8.06</td><td align="center">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">Dorsal abdomen intersegmental</td><td align="center">75.1&#x000b1;4.35</td><td align="center">19.6&#x000b1;7.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">Dorsal abdomen segments</td><td align="center">66.8&#x000b1;3.56</td><td align="center">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">24 hr</td><td align="left">Ventral abdomen</td><td align="center">85.2&#x000b1;5.93</td><td align="center">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">Dorsal abdomen<break/>intersegmental</td><td align="center">88.1&#x000b1;2.83</td><td align="center">17.4&#x000b1;1.81</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">Dorsal abdomen segments</td><td align="center">68.6&#x000b1;5.12</td><td align="center">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">48 hr</td><td align="left">Ventral abdomen</td><td align="center">62.1&#x000b1;0.30</td><td align="center">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">Dorsal abdomen<break/>intersegmental</td><td align="center">overgrown</td><td align="center">81.1&#x000b1;3.85</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">Dorsal abdomen<break/>segments</td><td align="center">50.8&#x000b1;10.77</td><td align="center">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Strain Mr2105</bold></td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">16 hr</td><td align="left">Ventral abdomen</td><td align="center">65.3&#x000b1;7.88</td><td align="center">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">Dorsal abdomen intersegmental</td><td align="center">90.9&#x000b1;1.17</td><td align="center">29.2&#x000b1;4.19</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">Dorsal abdomen<break/>segments</td><td align="center">62.4&#x000b1;3.61</td><td align="center">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">24 hr</td><td align="left">Ventral abdomen</td><td align="center">81.3&#x000b1;5.20</td><td align="center">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">Dorsal abdomen intersegmental</td><td align="center">91.7&#x000b1;2.91</td><td align="center">35.7&#x000b1;8.63</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">Dorsal abdomen<break/>segments</td><td align="center">66.9&#x000b1;12.05</td><td align="center">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">48 hr</td><td align="left">Ventral abdomen</td><td align="center">overgrown</td><td align="center">2.5&#x000b1;2.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">Dorsal abdomen<break/>intersegmental</td><td align="center">overgrown</td><td align="center">overgrown</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">Dorsal abdomen<break/>segments</td><td align="center">overgrown</td><td align="center">0</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="s0002-s2003"><title>How do pathogen genotypes with different infection strategies interact with <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila melanogaster</italic>?</title><p>Comparing all <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> strains, there were strong correlations (r&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.75, p&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.0008) between lethal spore doses needed to kill 50% of the flies (LC<sub>50</sub>), and the median lethal time to kill 50% (LT<sub>50</sub>) at three spore doses (1&#x000d7;10<sup>6</sup>, 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup> and 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>4</sup> spores per ml), confirming that the fastest killers are also those effective at the lowest spore doses. Spore production on cadavers is a measure of pathogen transmission potential, and therefore, pathogen fitness [<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. The pathogen genotype affected the timing of onset of sporulation on cadavers, which also correlated with immobilization time (a period of pre-mortem low mobility) (r&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.74, p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.001), and values for LC<sub>50</sub> (r&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.77, p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0005) and LT<sub>50</sub> (1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup>, r&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.69, p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0031). Although spore production per cadaver was negatively associated with the onset of sporulation (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic> =- 0.37), that is, early sporulators were heavy sporulators, this was not statistically significant (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.1644) (Supplementary Table S1).</p><p>Virulence was linked to the host range when we grouped strains into either <italic toggle="yes">M. frigidum</italic> and PARB clade (minus Mp443) generalists or presumed specialists (species associated with a narrow range of hosts in nature). There was a significant difference in LT<sub>50</sub> values (Welch&#x02019;s t-test, <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;4.39, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0007) between generalist (&#x000b5;&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.81&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.257&#x02009;days) and specialist (&#x000b5;&#x02009;=&#x02009;5.25&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.202&#x02009;days) strains. The hemipteran specialist <italic toggle="yes">M. album</italic> 1941 (Mal1941) did not immobilize or kill the flies. Flies infected with <italic toggle="yes">M. majus</italic> (297 and 1946), <italic toggle="yes">M. acridum</italic> (Mac324 and 5736), and <italic toggle="yes">M. pingshaense</italic> (Mp443) had an extended immobilization time (&#x000b5;&#x02009;=&#x02009;15.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.70 h.) compared to generalists (&#x000b5;&#x02009;=&#x02009;8.18&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.71 h.). However, the difference was not significant (<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.97, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.1152). The 7.4-h average difference in immobilization time accounted for&#x02009;~6.2% of the longer LT<sub>50</sub> values delivered by <italic toggle="yes">M. pingshaense</italic> 443 and <italic toggle="yes">M. majus</italic> 297. The hyphae of generalists take significantly less time to emerge from <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> cadavers (emergent period) than specialists (generalists &#x000b5;&#x02009;=&#x02009;36.21&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.32 h; specialists &#x000b5;&#x02009;=&#x02009;59.23&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.21 h) (<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.6, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.045). Generalists sporulated faster (&#x000b5;&#x02009;=&#x02009;63.99&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.12&#x02009;h) than specialists (&#x000b5;&#x02009;=&#x02009;94.42&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.58 h, <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.71, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.012) and produce more spores (&#x000b5;&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.16 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.46 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> spores) than specialists (&#x000b5;&#x02009;=&#x02009;6.21 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.60 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> spores) (<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.65, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0031).</p><p>The saprophytic growth of each <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> line was estimated from the radial growth of colonies on potato dextrose agar (PDA). Fast growing strains on PDA also germinated faster on <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> wings (e.g. host cuticle, <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1a</xref>) (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.67, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0046) and killed faster, as shown by the negative correlation with LT<sub>50</sub> values (spore dose 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>6</sup> spores/ml, <italic toggle="yes">r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;0.75, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0009). Fast growers on PDA sporulated faster on cadavers (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;0.54, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0313), but the association with higher sporulation capacity fell short of significance (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.49, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0531) (Supplementary Table S2). We previously characterized variations in metabolic flexibility between different <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> strains based on their ability to germinate in yeast extract media (YEM) or on glucose and sodium nitrate as sole carbon and nitrogen sources and to produce appressoria <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> against a hard hydrophobic surface [<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. We repeated these experiments with the strains used in this study. As shown in <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> and Supplementary Table S1, five of the strains were metabolically restricted, showing little or no growth in glucose or a low concentration (0.0125%) of YEM. However, of the five metabolically restricted strains, <italic toggle="yes">M. robertsii</italic> 1046 and <italic toggle="yes">M. pingshaense</italic> 2162 killed flies rapidly, whereas <italic toggle="yes">M. pingshaense</italic> 443 and two <italic toggle="yes">M. majus</italic> were weakly virulent (S <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). Two of the <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> lines tested, <italic toggle="yes">M. anisopliae</italic> 2105 and <italic toggle="yes">M. robertsii</italic> 14447, were collected from close <italic toggle="yes">D. melanogaster</italic> relations, <italic toggle="yes">Hydrelli</italic> spp., and <italic toggle="yes">D. suzukii</italic>, respectively. Unlike Mr14447, glucose promoted the germination of Ma2105 conidia and even allowed the formation of appressoria. Mr14447 produced appressoria only in 0.01% YEM. Similar to many other lines isolated from scarabaeid coleopterans [<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], <italic toggle="yes">M. robertsii</italic> 1046 did not germinate readily on YEM or glucose but killed <italic toggle="yes">D. melanogaster</italic> at a rate similar to that of Mr14447 and the metabolically flexible <italic toggle="yes">M. robertsii</italic> 2575 (Table S1, <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1a</xref>). <italic toggle="yes">M. robertsii</italic> 2575 (Mr2575) also grew approximately 30% faster than Mr1046 on PDA, but both strains exhibited more than 90% germination on fly wings. Thus, virulence does not depend on whether a strain has broad or narrow nutrient requirements for germination and growth <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic>. While fast radial growth on PDA is a reliable predictor of rapid germination on the cuticle and virulence, slower growers on PDA may also be fast killers if they can germinate rapidly on fly wings (<xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1a</xref>). All rapid (&#x0003e;90% in 14&#x02009;h) germinators on fly wings killed quickly, suggesting that pre-penetration competence is key to <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> success.</p><p>We previously reported that lines of the <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila melanogaster</italic> Genetic Reference Panel (DGRP) show significant genetic variation in their ability to tolerate Ma549 colonizing their hemolymphs [<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. It is also conceivable that <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> lines are better able to tolerate some <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> strains colonizing the hemolymph than others. We looked for colony forming units (CFUs) in the hemolymph of flies infected with each <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> strain at the start of the immobilization period (which varied between strains) (<xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1a</xref>, Supplementary Table S1). Negative correlations between CFU counts and growth on PDA (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;0.5, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0489) or germination on the host cuticle (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;0.54, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.03) (Supplementary Table S2) indicated that slow-growing strains on PDA and cuticle tended to proliferate abundantly in the hemolymph. Thus, most flies infected with the virulent Mr2575 did not show CFUs until post-mortem, whereas the slow-killing <italic toggle="yes">M. majus</italic> Mm297 produced 1677.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;387.3 CFUs per fly at immobilization time.</p><p>Generalist strains are often toxigenic, producing destruxins (dtxs), whereas nontoxigenic <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> spp. (e.g. <italic toggle="yes">M. acridum, M. majus, M. album</italic>) usually have narrow host ranges and kill by growing within the host [<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Destruxins suppress immune responses to facilitate fungal colonization in insects [<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. Mr2575 produces high levels of dtxs, even when colonizing plants [<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>], suggesting that their production is constitutive. Mr2575 grew well on PDA and fly cuticle, suggesting that toxin production does not necessarily compete with metabolic processes associated with growth. We used an Mr2575 null mutant of dtxs [<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] to test whether dtxs contribute to the short immobilization period. A Kruskal&#x02013;Wallis test showed no significant differences (&#x003c7;2&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.19, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.91) in the immobilization period of Drs-GFP flies infected with 2575&#x00394;Dtx and Mr2575, pointing to the complexity of virulence determination beyond individual toxic metabolites.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="s0002-s2004"><title><italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> immune response to different <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> strains.</title><p>We next hypothesized that immune activity might play a role in variation in pathogen success. Drs-GFP flies were used to measure immune activation. There was an association between a strain&#x02019;s virulence and the induction of drosomycin, as illustrated by the time course of GFP immunofluorescence in Drs-GFP flies (<xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>). Low-virulence strains that germinated poorly on the cuticle-induced fluorescence later than fast killers (<xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>), suggesting delayed penetration and activation of the immune system, as indicated by the positive relationship between LT<sub>50</sub> and the onset of immunofluorescence (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.71, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.002). The intensity of the immune response was not significantly correlated with LT<sub>50</sub>s (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.32, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.22) and the propensity for generalist strains, which usually kill faster, to produce greater maximum immunofluorescence (&#x000b5;&#x02009;=&#x02009;4.64 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.12 &#x000d7; 10<sup>4</sup>) compared to specialists (&#x000b5;&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.63 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup>&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.69 &#x000d7; 10<sup>4</sup>) also falls short of significance (<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.78, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;.011). However, the very slow killing <italic toggle="yes">M. pingshaense</italic> 443 produced late and weak immunofluorescence; thus, by day 4, immunofluorescence was more than two standard deviations below flies infected with other fungi (<xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>).
<fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Drs-GFP immunofluorescence response of <italic toggle="yes">D. melanogaster</italic> to infection with different <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> strains of high, medium and low virulence to <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila.</italic></p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="KVIR_A_2275493_F0003_OC" content-type="color" specific-use="web-only" position="float"/><graphic xlink:href="KVIR_A_2275493_F0003_PB" content-type="black-white" specific-use="print-only" position="float"/></alternatives></fig></p><p>Although virulent strains trigger early detection by the host immune system, there is substantial variation between individual flies in their drosomycin expression for each pathogen. Thus, on day 2, the rapid killers Ma549 and Mr2575 produced approximately 1.4- and 2.7-fold differences, respectively, in extremes of low to high fluorescence (<xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>). In non-destructive experiments using a fluorescence microscope, we found that&#x02009;~80% of Drs-GFP flies infected with Ma549 fluoresced by day 2, and the remaining flies began fluorescing after 2.5&#x02009;days. However, we found no significant differences in longevity between early- and late-fluorescing flies.
<fig position="float" id="f0004" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Boxplots showing the variability in immunofluorescence between individual Drs-GFP flies infected with either Ma549 and 2575.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="KVIR_A_2275493_F0004_OC" content-type="color" specific-use="web-only" position="float"/><graphic xlink:href="KVIR_A_2275493_F0004_PB" content-type="black-white" specific-use="print-only" position="float"/></alternatives></fig></p><p>Collectively, our results show a link between proliferation of CFUs in the hemolymph and slow speed of kill, and a strong positive association between late drosomycin expression and late mortality, that is, slow killing strains proliferate in the hemocoel and yet induce a late immune response. Neither immune response nor virulence is dependent on extensive fungal proliferation in the hemocoel which suggests that penetration through the cuticle induces the immune response. Thus, Mr2575 and the metabolically restricted Mr1046 were similar in both virulence and timing of drosomycin induction, although Mr2575 produced very few CFU (&#x0003c;1 per insect) before host death, and Mr1046 infected flies had CFU counts&#x02009;&#x0003e;100 (<xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). Our results are consistent with virulent strains inducing an earlier immune response of greater magnitude than less virulent strains, showing that virulence does not depend on suppressing a strong immune response.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="s0002-s2005"><title>Psh-dependent processes and Bomanin peptides confer resistance to <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> strains post cuticle penetration</title><p>To obtain a broader understanding of how successful pathogens adapt to and resist the insect innate immune response, we surveyed <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> strains against <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> mutants with defects in the immune system. A model showing the potential interconnections of the components of Toll and Imd responses represented by the mutants is shown in <xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>. Flies, either wild type or immune deficiency mutants, were also challenged with <italic toggle="yes">B. bassiana</italic> 80.2, a strain that has been used in several previous studies to screen defective <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> mutants, thus facilitating direct comparisons between these earlier studies and <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> spp. Flies lacking Persephone (<italic toggle="yes">Psh<sup>&#x02212;</sup></italic>), a serine protease implicated in the recognition of pathogen proteases [<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], succumbed to most <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> strains in approximately half the time as their isogenic background. The acridid specialist strain Mac324 killed <italic toggle="yes">Psh<sup>&#x02212;</sup></italic> flies ~6&#x02009;days earlier than the WT, indicating that even some specialists can overcome a non-natural host insect with a key defect in the immune system. However, the low virulence of Mp443 was not improved by the loss of Persephone, and both the WT (w[1118]<sup>6326</sup>) and <italic toggle="yes">Psh<sup>&#x02212;</sup></italic> were still alive 10&#x02009;days post-infection with Mal1941.
<fig position="float" id="f0005" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>A simplified model of the immune (Toll and Imd) pathways, principally based on Dudzic et al. [<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>].</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="KVIR_A_2275493_F0005_B" content-type="black-white" position="float"/></fig></p><p>Persephone activates a serine protease cascade that induces Toll-mediated AMP transcription through nuclear translocation of <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> DIF, an NF-&#x003ba;B homolog [<xref rid="cit0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. However, flies lacking Dif (<italic toggle="yes">Dif</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;</sup>) succumbed to most <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> strains at approximately the same time as the background controls (<xref rid="f0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>). An exception was <italic toggle="yes">M. frigidum</italic> 7436, in which the survival time of male (female) <italic toggle="yes">Dif</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;</sup> flies was 85% (72%) of that of WT flies (<xref rid="f0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>), <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.36, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.014 (<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7.89, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0007). Similar results were obtained with <italic toggle="yes">B. bassiana</italic> Bb 80.2: the survival time of male (female) <italic toggle="yes">Dif</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;</sup>flies was 72% (68%) of that of WT flies, <italic toggle="yes">t</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6.33, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0003 (<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;11.28, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.43e-6) (<xref rid="f0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>). These results are in close agreement with earlier studies on Bb 80.2, but according to Le Bourg [<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], the appearance of high mortality in infected <italic toggle="yes">Dif</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;</sup> may partly be an artifact of this mutant&#x02019;s low longevity. We found that the mean lifespan of <italic toggle="yes">Dif</italic><sup>&#x02212;</sup> (51.17&#x02009;days) was not significantly different from that of the background CNBW (46.13&#x02009;days) (<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.45, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.15); therefore, longevity should not have constrained our results. The disparity in the survival of their mutants indicates that the high susceptibility of flies lacking Psh is not necessarily linked to <italic toggle="yes">Dif</italic> for most <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> infections despite their being in the same pathway.
<fig position="float" id="f0006" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Quantifying the role that individual components of the insect immune system play in resisting infection. survival (measured as LT<sub>50</sub>&#x02019;s) of fly lines disrupted in known immune genes and their isogenic WT backgrounds against <italic toggle="yes">M. anisopliae</italic> (Ma549), <italic toggle="yes">M. frigidum</italic> (Mf7436) or <italic toggle="yes">B. bassiana</italic> (Bb80.2). Shown is the combination of three independent experiments for each pathogen with&#x02009;~&#x02009;20 flies per genotype per experiment. Significance was evaluated using t-tests and is shown relative to the WT (***<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001; **<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01; *<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="KVIR_A_2275493_F0006_OC" content-type="color" specific-use="web-only" position="float"/><graphic xlink:href="KVIR_A_2275493_F0006_PB" content-type="black-white" specific-use="print-only" position="float"/></alternatives></fig></p><p>Persephone activates the sp&#x000e4;etzle-processing enzyme (SPE), which processes the extracellular Toll ligand sp&#x000e4;etzle (spz) [<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>). We analyzed the role of these genes in resistance to Bb 80.2, and two representative pathogenic <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic>&#x02019;s, <italic toggle="yes">M. frigidum</italic> (Mf7436) and <italic toggle="yes">M. anisopliae</italic> (Ma549). Flies lacking <italic toggle="yes">Grass</italic> (functions upstream of SPE), <italic toggle="yes">SPE</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">spz</italic> were significantly more susceptible to <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> spp. and <italic toggle="yes">B. bassiana</italic> Bb 80.2 than their backgrounds. The survival time of <italic toggle="yes">spz</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">rm7</italic></sup> mutants was reduced by 40% to 60% (depending on the fungal strain), similar to <italic toggle="yes">psh<sup>&#x02212;</sup></italic> flies. The antifungal peptide drosomycin is a product of <italic toggle="yes">Dif</italic> [<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> spores (Mf7436, Ma2105, Ma549 and Mac324) germinated at a higher frequency in aqueous solutions of drosomycin than in water alone (<xref rid="f0007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>), suggesting that <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> spp. can use drosomycin as a nutrient source. Combining the antimicrobial peptides metchnikowin and cecropin with drosomycin had no additional impact on <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> spores compared with drosomycin alone. The saprophytic non-pathogenic fungus <italic toggle="yes">Neurospora crassa</italic> used as a control was strongly inhibited by drosomycin (<xref rid="f0007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7</xref>).
<fig position="float" id="f0007" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 7.</label><caption><p>The effect of drosomycin on <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium.</italic> (a) percent germination of spores of <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> spp in water or yeast extract plus or minus drosomycin. (b) <italic toggle="yes">N. crassa</italic> on agar showing growth inhibition by 0.01&#x02009;&#x000b5;g drosomycin applied to center of plate.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="KVIR_A_2275493_F0007_B" content-type="black-white" position="float"/></fig></p><p>Toll has also been reported to mediate the expression of Bomanins (Boms), a family of a dozen secreted peptides [<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Boms are believed to be directly antifungal, even though synthetic Bom peptides lack <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> antifungal activity [<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Ten of the 12 <italic toggle="yes">Bom</italic> genes are tandemly arrayed in a cluster, and a mutant (Bom&#x02206;55C) lacking this cluster was almost as susceptible to <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> spp. as <italic toggle="yes">Psh <sup>&#x02212;</sup></italic> flies (<xref rid="f0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>). Similar results have been reported for septic wounding with bacteria and a non-entomopathogenic filamentous fungus, suggesting that the loss of the 55C <italic toggle="yes">Bom</italic> cluster is highly detrimental to defense [<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>].</p><p>To discriminate between disease (fungal load) and death, we assayed fungal load over the course of Ma549 infection, using wild-type, <italic toggle="yes">Dif</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;</sup>, <italic toggle="yes">Psh</italic><sup>&#x02212;</sup>, and <italic toggle="yes">Bom</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">&#x00394;55C</italic></sup> flies in parallel (<xref rid="f0008" ref-type="fig">Figure 8</xref>). Because Ma549 infected <italic toggle="yes">Bom</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">&#x00394;55C</italic></sup> and <italic toggle="yes">Psh</italic><sup>&#x02212;</sup> flies had a median survival of about 3.5&#x02009;days, time points were taken at intervals of up to 4 days for these lines. Fungal loads in the three lines of WT flies only climbed rapidly when flies were close to death, indicative of resistance breaking down (<xref rid="f0008" ref-type="fig">Figure 8</xref>). In contrast, CFUs were elevated 48&#x02013;72 h post-infection in <italic toggle="yes">Bom</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">&#x00394;55C</italic></sup> and <italic toggle="yes">Psh</italic><sup>&#x02212;</sup> flies, so that at 72&#x02009;h <italic toggle="yes">Bom</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">&#x00394;55C</italic></sup> flies averaged 75 CFUs compared to 0.25 in the wild-type. The fungal load of <italic toggle="yes">Psh</italic><sup>&#x02212;</sup> flies was similarly elevated relative to that of wild-type flies. This early elevation in fungal load in <italic toggle="yes">Psh</italic><sup>&#x02212;</sup> and <italic toggle="yes">Bom</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">&#x00394;55C</italic></sup> flies suggests that <italic toggle="yes">Psh</italic><sup>&#x02212;</sup> signaling, in general, and Bom peptides specifically, contribute to resistance against Ma549. The appearance of CFUs 1.5&#x02009;days post-infection in <italic toggle="yes">Psh</italic><sup>&#x02212;</sup> flies precedes detectable Drosomycin-fluorescence in Drs-GFP flies by about half a day and perhaps represents a more accurate estimate of the speed of crossing of the integument.
<fig position="float" id="f0008" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 8.</label><caption><p>Time course of Ma549 fungal loads in the hemolymph of select immune mutants and their corresponding isogenic WT backgrounds. Results are presented as box plots.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="KVIR_A_2275493_F0008_OC" content-type="color" specific-use="web-only" position="float"/><graphic xlink:href="KVIR_A_2275493_F0008_PB" content-type="black-white" specific-use="print-only" position="float"/></alternatives></fig></p><p>Toll has been reported to be responsible for sexual dimorphism in longevity in flies infected with bacteria and <italic toggle="yes">B. bassiana</italic> [<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. We previously found that males in most DGRP lines are more resistant to Ma549 than their female counterparts [<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], and this was true for four of the five isogenic background strains deployed in this study. Exceptionally, female w[1118]<sup>DrosDel</sup> flies, the background of <italic toggle="yes">SPE</italic>
<sup><italic toggle="yes">SK6</italic></sup>, <italic toggle="yes">Relish</italic>
<sup><italic toggle="yes">E20</italic></sup> and <italic toggle="yes">spz</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">rm7</italic></sup>, lived longer than males following infection with Mf7436 and <italic toggle="yes">B. bassiana</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;3, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). Female w[1118]<sup>DrosDel</sup> flies infected with Ma549 also lived longer than males, but this was not statistically significant (<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2.25, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.07). Most of these mutations reverse the direction of dimorphism so that w[1118]<sup>DrosDel</sup> becomes like most other fly lines with males more resistant than females. Flies lacking peptidoglycan recognition protein SA (PGRP-SA) implicated in the recognition of Gram-positive bacteria, did not affect the susceptibility of females to fungi, but male <italic toggle="yes">PGRP-SA</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">seml</italic></sup> was significantly more resistant to Ma549 (<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;7.22, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0001) and <italic toggle="yes">B. bassiana</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;8.94, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.29E&#x02013;5). <italic toggle="yes">Psh<sup>&#x00394;</sup></italic> flies infected with <italic toggle="yes">M. frigidum</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;3.46, p<italic toggle="yes">=</italic>0.01) retained significant sexual dimorphism, unlike <italic toggle="yes">psh<sup>&#x00394;</sup></italic> (<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1.58, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.16) flies infected with Ma549.</p><p>The Imd pathway is not involved in the detection of a fungal infection, but downstream crosstalk with the Toll pathway has been suggested previously; in particular, the survival of Imd pathway mutants against <italic toggle="yes">B. bassiana</italic> is lower than that of the wild-type [<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. In our study, flies mutated in <italic toggle="yes">Relish</italic>, the terminal transcription factor in the Imd pathway, but not <italic toggle="yes">Imd</italic> itself, showed variably reduced survival, ranging from 15% (females infected with Ma549) to 37% (females infected with Mf7436). As reported by Shahrestani et al. [<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], we also found that disrupting <italic toggle="yes">Relish</italic> eliminated sexual dimorphism in the survival of <italic toggle="yes">B. bassiana</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.67, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.52). The 37% reduction in female longevity compared to the background w[1118]<sup>DrosDel</sup> was sufficient to reverse sexual dimorphism in response to <italic toggle="yes">M. frigidum</italic> infection so that males lived longer than females (<xref rid="f0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>). These results suggest that the immune sexual dimorphism common in <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> lines is dependent on the specific interactions of each pathogen with immune pathways that contain some components (e.g., PGRP-SA) differentially affecting survival of males and other components (e.g., Relish) differentially affecting survival of females, at least in some lines and to some infections.</p></sec></sec><sec disp-level="1" id="s0003"><title>Discussion</title><p>There could be a fitness advantage to higher virulence for an entomopathogen with an insect host that must be quickly disabled before it dies from other causes that will likely also kill the pathogen [<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The observable variations in pathogenicity shown by <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> species are, therefore, likely maintained by more complicated evolutionary processes. Classic evolution of virulence theory is based on trade-offs between pathogen growth, transmission, and host survival, which predicts that by extracting more resources from the host, the pathogen will grow faster and produce more infectious propagules [<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. However, experimental data for numerous pathogens show the opposite correlation, with slower growing pathogens being more virulent than faster growing ones [<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. Insect pathosystems involving fungi also differ from those commonly treated in traditional models in that sporulation of entomopathogens only occurs after host death, so that host death may increase pathogen fitness by allowing transmission. This is exemplified by a strain-like Mr2575, which kills the host with toxins and then colonizes post-mortem [<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Despite this, our data showed that fast growth on PDA was associated with rapid kill (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>&#x02264;-0.65, p&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.006) and sporulation (r&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.49, p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0531). Thus, although <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> species possess a broad spectrum of mechanisms of pathogenesis (e.g. only some broad-host-range strains produce toxins that could require a high investment of resources), they do not swamp a simple non-host-specific relationship between the growth potential of mycelia and virulence. However, the strains that exhibited lower virulence and mycelial growth on PDA produced greater fungal loads in the hemolymph preceding or during the immobilization period and also induced late expression of drosomycin. In contrast to proliferation in the hemolymph, saprophytic growth on PDA was significantly correlated with rapid germination on fly wings (r&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.67, p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0046), suggesting that 1) radial growth on agar is a measure of potential virulence because it predicts rapid growth on host surfaces and 2) faster growth through the cuticle by virulent strains induces early expression of the Toll pathway. For non-toxin-producing strains (e.g. most specialists), variable numbers of fungal cells produced by different strains within the insect influence the rate of killing. A previous screen of mutant <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> lines found that greater growth of Ma549 (a generalist strain that produces few toxins) within the host was correlated with shorter life spans and earlier onset of sporulation (63.7% of the variation in life span was explained by variation in fungal load) [<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].</p><p>For some bacteria that kill insects by bacteremia, LT<sub>50</sub> values also directly correlate with <italic toggle="yes">in vivo</italic> growth rates [<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Although such a quantitative relationship is not unexpected for an entomopathogen, a few studies on <italic toggle="yes">B. bassiana</italic> have not found correlations between virulence and <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> growth rate [<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Such associations appear to be limited to some plant pathogenic fungi [<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>], including <italic toggle="yes">Alternaria brassicicola</italic> where <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> growth rate was weakly correlated with aggressiveness to its host [<xref rid="cit0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. These authors also found a trade-off between growth and spore production, such that faster growing isolates produced fewer spores, and postulated that such trade-offs might contribute to the maintenance of variation in pathogen populations. We did not detect similar trade-offs with fast-growing <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> strains after host death and sporulation; instead, trade-offs seemed more likely to affect latent periods, which are longer for less virulent pathogens. Complicating interpretations of these data, the forces generating diversity within <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> spp. will likely reflect adaptation to multiple environments, including plant roots, for at least some generalists such as Mr2575 [<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. It has been suggested that the ability to infect a phylogenetically broad range of hosts may have evolved to maximize protection to the plant (the permanent home of the fungus as distinct from the ephemeral insect) and provision of nutrients to the plant from cadavers via the fungus [<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Thus, the virulence of plant-colonizing broad-host-range strains to insects is likely to evolve depending on any ways in which virulence affects changes in transmission to plants.</p><p>Specialization to particular hosts can be qualitative, characterized by the inability of a pathogenic isolate to infect many hosts, or quantitative, where the pathogens have lower performance [<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. The specialization of most <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> strains appears to be quantitative, as they kill fruit flies, albeit slowly. Compared to most generalists, specialists also showed lower rates of <italic toggle="yes">in vitro</italic> mycelial growth and were less nutritionally flexible, that is, little growth on 0.01% YEM and glucose. This is consistent with more limited ecological associations with plants and as saprophytes and poor germination on cuticle. However, the hemipteran specialist <italic toggle="yes">M. album</italic> 1941 was not able to cause disease even in flies with impaired immunity. The other <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> strains killed normal hosts, and, except for Mp443, this was amplified when the immune system was compromised.</p><p>Most <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> species that readily kill multiple orders of insects also produce toxins, whereas the nontoxigenic <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> spp. (e.g. <italic toggle="yes">M. acridum, M. majus, M. album</italic>) have narrow host ranges [<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. There are exceptions to this: the broad host range Ma549 does not produce much destruxins (Dtx) <italic toggle="yes">in insecta</italic> [<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>] [<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The specialists had a notably long &#x0201c;immobilized time&#x0201d; compared to the generalists, which commenced with the appearance of numerous fungal propagules in the hemolymph. However, disrupting Dtx in Mr2575 did not significantly lengthen the immobilization time, or as previously reported longevity [<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], suggesting that Dtx production by itself is not the time limiting factor for either pathogenic parameter.</p><p>Flies disrupted in <italic toggle="yes">Psh</italic> or <italic toggle="yes">Spz</italic> were similarly highly susceptible consistent with the so called danger arm of the Toll pathway being the principal one activated [28]. However, disrupting the downstream <italic toggle="yes">Dif</italic> resulted in only a small and statistically insignificant increase in susceptibility to Ma549 [<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. We found that the impact of <italic toggle="yes">Dif</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;</sup> on <italic toggle="yes">B. bassiana</italic> was significant but much less than that of disrupting <italic toggle="yes">Psh</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">B. bassiana</italic> kills more slowly than Ma549 and most other generalist <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> strains, but it is unlikely that the apparent lack of impact of <italic toggle="yes">Dif</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;</sup> on Ma549 was due to the rapid lethality of <italic toggle="yes">M. anisopliae</italic>, as <italic toggle="yes">Dif</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;</sup> did not significantly increase the susceptibility to low-virulence <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> isolates, unlike <italic toggle="yes">Psh</italic><sup>&#x02212;</sup>. An interesting exception was provided by the increased susceptibility of <italic toggle="yes">Dif</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;</sup> to <italic toggle="yes">M. frigidum</italic> 7437, which, like <italic toggle="yes">B. bassiana</italic> is a broad host range strain but kills comparatively slowly (<xref rid="f0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>). A potential complicating factor is the possibility of partial redundancy between Dif and its paralog, the neighboring dorsal gene, but this is only reported to affect the induction of drosomycin at the larval stage [<xref rid="cit0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>].</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Beauveria</italic> spp. evolved into insect pathogens independent of the <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> lineage, and similar expansion of protease, chitinase families, etc., reflects the convergent evolution of an &#x0201c;entomopathogenicity toolkit&#x0201d; associated with functions necessary for insect pathogenesis [<xref rid="cit0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. As <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Beauveria</italic> inevitably confront the insect immune system, they independently evolved a series of strategies to evade or overcome these immune responses. There are features unique to <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> spp., which include blastospores producing a collagen coat (MCL1) to mask antigenic cell wall &#x003b2;-glucans from phagocytes [<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], as well as destruxins [<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="cit0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. Despite this, several generalist <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> species evoke a rapid and robust innate immune response, showing that they do not escape recognition or block activation. A cost of opportunistically infecting multiple-host species may be that a generalist <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> spp. cannot adapt to the immune system of each potential host. <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> like <italic toggle="yes">Beauveria</italic> [<xref rid="cit0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] has evolved resistance to the defensin-like peptide drosomycin, presumably under strong long-term selective pressure. Defensins are ubiquitous in arthropods, and <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> can be engineered to express large quantities of scorpine (from the scorpion <italic toggle="yes">Pandinus imperator</italic>), a structurally similar but more potent antifungal/protozoan than drosomycin, with no harm to itself [<xref rid="cit0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. In contrast to defensins, Bom peptides are unique to <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> spp [<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. They may have evolved in response to the selective pressure exerted by entomopathogenic fungi after they became resistant to defensins. Similarly, Gottar <italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>, (2006) [<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] speculated that the <italic toggle="yes">Psh</italic>-dependent system evolved after the <italic toggle="yes">GNBP</italic>-3-based fungal cell-wall sensing system. <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> may have evolved ways to escape ancient widely distributed defenses, including the effects of <italic toggle="yes">Dif</italic> activation and drosomycin, but not more recent insect innovations such as <italic toggle="yes">Psh</italic> activation and phylogenetically restricted Bomanins.</p></sec><sec disp-level="1" id="s0004"><title>Materials and methods</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Fungal strains. Beauveria bassiana</italic> 80.2 (Bb80.2) was kindly donated by George Dimopoulos (Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health). This <italic toggle="yes">B. bassiana</italic> strain has been used as a representative fungal pathogen in <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> studies [<xref rid="cit0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. We validated the species identification as <italic toggle="yes">B. bassiana</italic> by BLASTing the sequencing results of the <italic toggle="yes">Tef-</italic>1&#x003b1; region after PCR amplification using primers F:ATGGGTAAGGACGACAAGAC and R:GGAAGTACCAGTGATCATGTT. <italic toggle="yes">M. robertsii</italic> ARSEF 14447 was isolated from a female Spotted Wing <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> (<italic toggle="yes">Drosophila suzukii</italic>) collected by the first author, Dr Jonathan Wang, at a fruit farm in Keedysville, Maryland. Other fungal strains were obtained from the USDA Entomopathogenic Fungus Collection (Ithaca, N.Y., USA). The strains used were <italic toggle="yes">M. anisopliae</italic> (generalists 2105, 7427, and 549), <italic toggle="yes">M. robertsii</italic> (generalists 2575 and 1046), <italic toggle="yes">M. brunneum</italic> (generalist 346), <italic toggle="yes">M. frigidum</italic> (generalists 4124, 7436), <italic toggle="yes">M. pingshaeaense</italic> (generalists 538, 2162, gryllid specialist 443), <italic toggle="yes">M. majus</italic> (scarab specialists 297, 1946), <italic toggle="yes">M. acridum</italic> (acridid specialists 5736, 324), and <italic toggle="yes">M. album</italic> (hemipteran specialist 1941) (see S <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> for the origin of the strains). These fungal cultures were moved from&#x02009;&#x02212;80&#x000b0;C stock tubes 10&#x02013;14&#x02009;days before each bioassay and grown on potato dextrose agar (PDA) at 27&#x000b0;C. Infection structures (appressoria) were induced by germinating conidia in yeast extract medium (YEM, 0.0125%) in polystyrene petri dishes, as described previously [<xref rid="cit0058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Alternatively, to test the isolates&#x02019; nutritional requirements for germination and differentiation, conidia were germinated in 0.1% YEM or in glucose medium (1% glucose, 0.1% NaNO<sub>3</sub>, 0.05% KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 0.05% MgSO<sub>4</sub>) as previously described [<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. To facilitate studies of strain differences, we transformed several <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> strains to express green fluorescent protein (GFP). Plasmid construction and transformation for GFP fluorescence were performed as described previously, and transformants were selected based on WT growth in culture and WT levels of virulence [<xref rid="cit0059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>].</p><p><italic toggle="yes">Fly strains and infection protocols</italic>. <italic toggle="yes">Bom</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">&#x00394;55C</italic></sup> was kindly donated by Steven Wasserman (University of California, San Diego, CA, USA). Drs-GFP, <italic toggle="yes">Dif</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">1</italic></sup>, <italic toggle="yes">psh<sup>&#x00394;</sup></italic> and their isogenic control lines were kindly donated by Dominique Ferrandon (University of Strasbourg) [<xref rid="cit0060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">PGRP-SA</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">seml</italic></sup>, <italic toggle="yes">SPE</italic>
<sup><italic toggle="yes">SK6</italic></sup>, <italic toggle="yes">Grass</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">Herrade</italic></sup>, <italic toggle="yes">Relish</italic>
<sup><italic toggle="yes">E20</italic></sup>, and <italic toggle="yes">spatzle</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">rm7</italic></sup> mutants and their isogenic control lines were kindly donated by Bruno Lemaitre (&#x000c9;cole Polytechnique F&#x000e9;d&#x000e9;rale de Lausanne, Lausanne, France). Most of the mutants had w[1118] backgrounds, but we found that w[1118] from different sources differed slightly but consistently in susceptibility to <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> spp. and <italic toggle="yes">B. bassiana</italic>, and are distinguished here as w[1118]<sup>6326</sup>, w[1118]<sup>VDRC</sup> and w[1118]<sup>DrosDel</sup> (S3 Table). The IMD (17474) mutant line was obtained from the Bloomington <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> Stock Center (flystocks.bio.indiana.edu/). We sequenced both <italic toggle="yes">Dif</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">1</italic></sup> and its isogenic control (cn bw) to confirm that guanine 1104 (found in the cn bw) was point-mutated into adenine, resulting in a radical missense change from glycine to aspartic acid in <italic toggle="yes">Dif</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">1</italic></sup>.</p><p>For infection bioassays, <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> strains were used, as described previously for Ma549 [<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Fungal cultures were thawed 10&#x02013;14&#x02009;days before each bioassay from&#x02009;&#x02212;80&#x000b0;C stock vials and grown on potato dextrose agar media plates at 27&#x000b0;C. Drs-GFP flies 2&#x02013;4-days old were assayed at a final spore concentration of 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>4</sup> to 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>6</sup> (2.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>4</sup> for mutant studies) conidia/ml. Infected flies were maintained at 27&#x000b0;C and&#x02009;~85% relative humidity on standard cornmeal molasses medium without tegosept or propionic acid.</p><p>To prepare the inoculum, conidia were suspended in sterile-distilled water, vortexed for 2&#x02009;min, and filtered through Miracloth (22&#x02013;25&#x02009;&#x000b5;m) (Andwin Scientific) to remove mycelia. Spore concentrations were determined using a hemocytometer and were adjusted with water. Flies were vortexed with 20&#x02009;mL spore suspensions for 30 s, collected by filtering the suspensions through Miracloth, and transferred to vials containing fresh food. Less than 10% of flies vortexed with water alone (mock-infected) or conidial suspensions died within 1 day, with no significant differences between lines, so flies succumbing within 1-day post-infection were deleted from the infection data. Following infection, flies were examined at six-hour intervals to determine the time to immobilization (flies not walking but still responding to touch) and time to death (completely moribund). Survival was monitored after topical inoculation in groups with at least three replicates (20&#x02013;30 flies each) per sex per line. The number of dead flies was recorded twice per day for 10&#x02013;14&#x02009;days and the LT50 values (lethal time in days at which 50% of the flies died) were calculated using R.</p><p>Drosomycin reporter Drs-GFP flies were used to check for temporal differences in immune-response fluorescence. In a previous study, we reported that Dif<sup>&#x02212;</sup> mutant Drs-GFP flies showed greatly reduced expression of <italic toggle="yes">Drs</italic> GFP fluorescence in response to Ma549, which was confirmed by real time-PCR [<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>], suggesting that <italic toggle="yes">Drs-</italic>GFP provides a true readout of activation of the Toll pathway in response to <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic>. The fluorescence of 10 individual flies per time interval per infection with a 1&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup> spore suspension of each <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> strain was quantified using a FilterMax F5 microplate reader. Data were collected for up to 10&#x02009;days post-infection for the less virulent strains (Mp443, Ma324, <italic toggle="yes">M. album</italic> 1941).</p><p>We used previously described protocols for the bioassay of fungal growth in the hemolymph [<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. At each time point, 10 flies of each sex were individually homogenized with 45&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of 0.1% Tween 80. The homogenate was spread onto Rose Bengal Agar plates supplemented with ox bile, oxytetracycline, streptomycin, penicillin, and chloramphenicol. Colony-forming units (CFUs) were counted after 7&#x02013;10&#x02009;days of incubation at 25&#x000b0;C.</p><p>To determine the effect of destruxin (Dtx) on the immobilization period of ~10 female Drs-GFP flies, they were infected with either Ma549, Mr2575, or Mr2575&#x00394;Dtx, collected without anesthesia, placed into food vials, and monitored at 3&#x02009;h. intervals until death. Germination rates of cuticles and fungal growth in the hemolymph by GFP-tagged <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium</italic> strains infecting w[1118]<sup>DrosDel</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> were monitored as previously described [<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. For each fly, we evaluated conidia on the tergum and wings in four abdominal intersegmental regions and six dorsal and ventral areas on the abdominal segments.</p><p>We tested the effects of different (98% and 80%) relative humidity (RH) levels on infection parameters of a virulent <italic toggle="yes">Metarhizium anisopliae</italic> strain (Ma2105) isolated from <italic toggle="yes">Hydrellia sp</italic>. [Ephydridae; close relation to <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic>], and an <italic toggle="yes">M. pingshaense</italic> strain (Mp443) with a strong host preference for crickets (Gryllidae) and low virulence in <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic>. Female w[1118]<sup>DrosDel</sup> flies were infected with GFP-fluorescent Mp443-GFP or Ma2105-GFP, and spore germination rates and hyphal lengths were monitored microscopically post-infection at different RH. RH was measured using a traceable Digital Humidity/Temperature Meter (Fisher Scientific&#x02122;). Ninety-eight % and 80% RH were achieved using ddH<sub>2</sub>0 soaked paper towels and highly concentrated NaCl, respectively. These liquids were placed into a plastic Tupper ware box that contained a support for Petri dishes containing flies. Control or infected flies were briefly immobilized with CO<sub>2</sub> and gently tapped into Petri dishes. They were localized to each dish with an autoclaved nylon mesh stretched over the dish and sealed with the edges of a lid, in which the face had been removed. Approximately 1 g of the cornmeal molasses diet was placed on the mesh, and flies were free to walk over the mesh to feed (<xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).</p><sec disp-level="2" id="s0004-s2001"><title>Post-mortem analysis</title><p>The ability of the different fungal strains to colonize and exploit <italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic> cadavers was measured. For the emergent period, latent period, and sporulation capacity, 10 female flies harvested within 6 h of death were individually transferred into tubes containing a damp cotton ball. At 6-h intervals, we recorded the interval between death and emergent hyphae covering at least half of the fly cadaver (emergent period) and the appearance of spores (latent period). After 20&#x02009;days, 500&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of 0.1% Tween 80 was added to each tube, the tubes were vortexed (1 min), and spores per individual fly were counted using a hemocytometer (sporulation capacity). The results represent the average of 10 flies per fungal strain. Correlations between LT<sub>50</sub> survival values, emergent period, sporulation capacity, and immobilization time were analyzed using GraphPad Prism 7 (GraphPad Software, Inc.) or R.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="s0004-s2002"><title>Analysis of immune peptides</title><p>The expression and purification of drosomycin was performed as previously described [<xref rid="cit0061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. The sequence encoding the mature drosomycin (Drs) was amplified via PCR from <italic toggle="yes">D. melanogaster</italic> genomic DNA and cloned into the NcoI and BamHI sites of a pET-32b expression vector derivative used for transformation of <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> strain Rosetta-gami (Novagen). Recombinant drosomycin, fused to a His<sub>6</sub> tag, was purified on a HisTrap&#x000ae; affinity column (GE Healthcare) and the tag was cleaved with thrombin. Drosomycin was purified using a Resource&#x000ae; 3-ml reverse phase high-pressure liquid chromatography column. The molecular mass of recombinant drosomycin was confirmed by mass spectroscopy. Cecropin A was purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, USA). Metchnikowin was synthesized as a service by Peptide 2.0, Inc. (Chantilly, VA). The effect of peptides on different fungi was determined by adding 50&#x02009;&#x000b5;L of peptide (0.5&#x02009;mg/ml) to 60&#x02009;&#x000b5;L of water or 0.2% yeast extract containing <italic toggle="yes">~</italic>1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup> fungal spores/mL, and calculating the percentage of germinated spores at 16 and 24&#x02009;h.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="SM2288" position="float" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplemental Material</title></caption><media xlink:href="KVIR_A_2275493_SM2288.zip"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>JBW and HL were supported by the Hatch Project Accession No. 1015969 from the USDA National Institute of Food and Agriculture (<ext-link xlink:href="https://nifa.usda.gov/apply-grant" ext-link-type="uri">https://nifa.usda.gov/apply-grant</ext-link>) awarded to RJS. The funders had no role in the study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or manuscript preparation.</p></ack><bio id="b0001"><p><bold><italic toggle="yes">J.W.</italic></bold> Data analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Experimental design. H. L. L. Investigation, Methodology, Experimental design, Data curation. H.S Investigation. R.J.S. Conceptualization, Data analysis, Experimental design, Manuscript preparation. All authors reviewed and edited the manuscript.</p></bio><sec sec-type="COI-statement" disp-level="1" id="s0005"><title>Disclosure statement</title><p>No potential conflict of interest was reported by the authors.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" disp-level="1" id="s0006"><title>Data Availability statement</title><p>The authors confirm that data supporting the findings of this study are available within the article and its supplementary materials.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" disp-level="1" id="s0007"><title>Supplemental data</title><p>Supplemental data for this article can be accessed online at <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1080/21505594.2023.2275493" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.1080/21505594.2023.2275493</ext-link></p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="cit0001"><label>[1]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Barrett</surname>
<given-names>LG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kniskern</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bodenhausen</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Continua of specificity and virulence in plant host&#x02013;pathogen interactions: causes and consequences</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>183</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>513</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2009.02927.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19563451</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0002"><label>[2]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Fisher</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Henk</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Briggs</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Emerging fungal threats to animal, plant and ecosystem health</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>484</volume>(<issue>7393</issue>):<fpage>186</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>194</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature10947</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22498624</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0003"><label>[3]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kniskern</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barrett</surname>
<given-names>LG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bergelson</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Maladaptation in wild populations of the generalist plant pathogen pseudomonas syringae</article-title>. <source>Evolution (N Y)</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>65</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>818</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>830</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1558-5646.2010.01157.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0004"><label>[4]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>McGonigle</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leit&#x000e3;o</surname>
<given-names>AB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ommeslag</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Parallel and costly changes to cellular immunity underlie the evolution of parasitoid resistance in three Drosophila species</article-title>. <source>PLOS Pathog</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>e1006683</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1006683</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29049362</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0005"><label>[5]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>HL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>St Leger</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <year>2016</year>
<part-title>Insect immunity to entomopathogenic fungi</part-title>. In: <person-group person-group-type="editor"><string-name><surname>Lovett</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, and <string-name><given-names>R</given-names>
<surname>St Leger</surname></string-name></person-group>, editors. <source>Advances in Genetics</source>
<volume>94</volume> (pp. <fpage>251</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>285</lpage>). <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Academic Press</publisher-name>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/bs.adgen.2015.11.002</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0006"><label>[6]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lazzaro</surname>
<given-names>BP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Little</surname>
<given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Immunity in a variable world</article-title>. <source>Philos Trans R Soc B</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>364</volume>(<issue>1513</issue>):<fpage>15</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>26</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2008.0141</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0007"><label>[7]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>HL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>St Leger</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>The genetic basis for variation in resistance to infection in the Drosophila melanogaster genetic reference panel</article-title>. <source>PLOS Pathog</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>e1006260</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1006260</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28257468</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0008"><label>[8]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Elya</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>St Leger</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Genetic variation for resistance to the specific fly pathogen entomophtora muscae</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>). doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-71262-w</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0009"><label>[9]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Roberts</surname>
<given-names>DW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>St Leger</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Metarhizium spp., cosmopolitan insect-pathogenic fungi: Mycological aspects</article-title>. <source>Adv Appl Microbiol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15251275</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0010"><label>[10]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>St</surname>
<given-names>LR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Metarhizium: jack of all trades, master of many</article-title>. <source>Open Biol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<fpage>10</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsob.200307</pub-id>
<volume>10</volume>
<issue>12</issue></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0011"><label>[11]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>St Leger</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Genetic engineering of fungal biocontrol agents to achieve greater efficacy against insect pests</article-title>. <source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source> Internet. <year>2010</year>
<month>Jan</month>;<volume>85</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>901</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>907</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-009-2306-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19862514</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0012"><label>[12]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Feng</surname>
<given-names>MG</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Advances in fundamental and applied studies in China of fungal biocontrol agents for use against arthropod pests</article-title>. <source>Biol Control</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>68</volume>:<fpage>129</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>135</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biocontrol.2013.06.017</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0013"><label>[13]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xiao</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zheng</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Trajectory and genomic determinants of fungal-pathogen speciation and host adaptation</article-title>. <source>Proc Nat Acad Sci</source>
<comment>[Internet]</comment>. <year>2014</year>
<month>Nov</month>;<volume>111</volume>(<issue>47</issue>):<fpage>16796</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16801</lpage>. <date-in-citation>[cited 2014 <month>Nov</month>
<day>25</day>]</date-in-citation>. <ext-link xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4250126/" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4250126/</ext-link>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25368161</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0014"><label>[14]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rombach</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Humber</surname>
<given-names>RA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Evans</surname>
<given-names>HC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Metarhizium album, a fungal pathogen of leaf- and planthoppers of rice</article-title>. <source>Transactions Of The British Mycological Society</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>88</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>451</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>459</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0007-1536(87)80028-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0015"><label>[15]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kang</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>Y.</given-names></string-name></person-group> et al. <article-title>Unveiling the biosynthetic puzzle of destruxins in Metarhizium species</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>109</volume>: <fpage>1287</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1292</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.111598309</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22232661</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0016"><label>[16]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Fang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Insertion of an esterase gene into a specific locust pathogen (Metarhizium acridum) enables it to infect caterpillars</article-title>. <source>PLOS Pathog</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e1002097</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1002097</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21731492</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0017"><label>[17]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>St Leger</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Developmental and transcriptional responses to host and nonhost cuticles by the specific locust pathogen Metarhizium anisopliae var. acridum</article-title>. <source>Eukaryot Cell</source>. <year>2005</year>
<month>May</month>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>937</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>947</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/EC.4.5.937-947.2005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15879528</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0018"><label>[18]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>St Leger</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roberts</surname>
<given-names>DW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Staples</surname>
<given-names>RC</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>A model to explain differentiation of appressoria by germlings of Metarhizium anisopliae</article-title>. <source>Journal Of Invertebrate Pathology</source>. <year>1991</year>
<month>May</month>;<volume>57</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>299</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>310</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0022-2011(91)90134-C</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0019"><label>[19]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>St Leger</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>A collagenous protective coat enables Metarhizium anisopliae to evade insect immune responses</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source> Internet. <year>2006</year>
<month>Apr</month>
<date-in-citation>[cited 2014 <month>Nov</month>
<day>17</day>]</date-in-citation>;<volume>103</volume>(<issue>17</issue>):<fpage>6647</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6652</lpage> doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0601951103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16614065</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0020"><label>[20]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Butt</surname>
<given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Coates</surname>
<given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dubovskiy</surname>
<given-names>IM.</given-names></string-name></person-group> et al. <article-title>Entomopathogenic fungi: new insights into host-pathogen interactions</article-title>. <source>Adv Genet</source>. <year>2016</year>; <volume>94</volume>: <fpage>307</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>364</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27131329</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0021"><label>[21]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lovett</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>St Leger</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The secretome and chemistry of Metarhizium; a genus of entomopathogenic fungi</article-title>. <source>Fungal Ecol</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>38</volume>:<fpage>7</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.funeco.2018.04.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0022"><label>[22]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gao</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jin</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ying</surname>
<given-names>SHH</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Genome sequencing and comparative transcriptomics of the model entomopathogenic fungi Metarhizium anisopliae and M. acridum</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>. <year>2011</year>
<month>Jan</month>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e1001264</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001264</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21253567</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0023"><label>[23]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>St Leger</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>May</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Allee</surname>
<given-names>LL</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Genetic differences in allozymes and in formation of infection structures among isolates of the entomopathogenic fungus Metarhizium anisopliae</article-title>. <source>Journal Of Invertebrate Pathology</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>60</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>89</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>101</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0022-2011(92)90159-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0024"><label>[24]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Samuels</surname>
<given-names>RI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Charnley</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reynolds</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The role of destruxins in the pathogenicity of 3 strains of Metarhizium anisopliae for the tobacco hornworm Manduca sexta</article-title>. <source>Mycopathologia</source>. <year>1988</year>;<volume>104</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>51</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>58</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00437924</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0025"><label>[25]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Igboin</surname>
<given-names>CO</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Griffen</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Leys</surname>
<given-names>EJ</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The Drosophila melanogaster host model</article-title>. <source>J Oral Microbiol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>10368</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3402/jom.v4i0.10368</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0026"><label>[26]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Govind</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Innate immunity in Drosophila: pathogens and pathways</article-title>. <source>Insect Sci</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>29</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>43</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1744-7917.2008.00185.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20485470</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0027"><label>[27]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Stokes</surname>
<given-names>BA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yadav</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shokal</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Bacterial and fungal pattern recognition receptors in homologous innate signaling pathways of insects and mammals</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>6</volume>: doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2015.00019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0028"><label>[28]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Issa</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Guillaumot</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lauret</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>The circulating protease Persephone is an immune sensor for microbial proteolytic activities upstream of the Drosophila Toll pathway</article-title>. <source>Mol Cell</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>69</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>539</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>550.e6</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molcel.2018.01.029</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29452635</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0029"><label>[29]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gottar</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gobert</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matskevich</surname>
<given-names>AA</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Dual detection of fungal infections in Drosophila via recognition of glucans and sensing of virulence factors</article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>127</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1425</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1437</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2006.10.046</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17190605</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0030"><label>[30]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>HL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>JB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brown</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Identification of Drosophila mutants affecting defense to an entomopathogenic fungus</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source> Internet. <year>2015</year>
<month>Jul</month>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>12350</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep12350</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26202798</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0031"><label>[31]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Leggett</surname>
<given-names>HC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cornwallis</surname>
<given-names>CK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Buckling</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Growth rate, transmission mode and virulence in human pathogens</article-title>. <source>Philos Trans R Soc B</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>372</volume>(<issue>1719</issue>):<fpage>20160094</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rstb.2016.0094</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0032"><label>[32]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sharififard</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mossadegh</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vazirianzadeh</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of temperature and humidity on the pathogenicity of the entomopathogenic fungi in control of the house fly, Musca domestica L. (Diptera: muscidae) under laboratory conditions</article-title>. <source>Journal Of Entomology</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>282</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>288</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3923/je.2012.282.288</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0033"><label>[33]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Taylor</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kimbrell</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Host immune response and differential survival of the sexes in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Fly (Austin)</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>1</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>197</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>204</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4161/fly.5082</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18820477</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0034"><label>[34]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bidochka</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>St Leger</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Roberts</surname>
<given-names>DW</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Mechanisms of deuteromycete fungal infections in grasshoppers and locusts: an overview</article-title>. <source>Mem Entomol Soc Can</source>. <year>1997</year>;<volume>129</volume>(<issue>S171</issue>):<fpage>213</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>224</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4039/entm129171213-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0035"><label>[35]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Pal</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>St Leger</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wu</surname>
<given-names>LP</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Fungal peptide destruxin a plays a specific role in suppressing the innate immune response in Drosophila melanogaster</article-title>. <source>Journal Of Biological Chemistry</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>282</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>8969</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8977</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M605927200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17227774</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0036"><label>[36]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Golo</surname>
<given-names>PS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gardner</surname>
<given-names>DR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grilley</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Production of destruxins from Metarhizium spp. Fungi in Artificial medium and in endophytically colonized cowpea plants</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<comment>[Internet]</comment>. <year>2014</year>
<month>Aug</month>
<day>15</day>
<date-in-citation>[cited 2022 <month>Mar</month>
<day>6</day>]</date-in-citation>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>e104946</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104946</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25127450</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0037"><label>[37]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Donzelli</surname>
<given-names>BGG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Krasnoff</surname>
<given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sun-Moon</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Hydrophobin genes of the entomopathogenic fungus, Metarhizium brunneum, are differentially expressed and corresponding mutants are decreased in virulence</article-title>. <source>Curr Genet</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>58</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>79</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>92</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00294-012-0366-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22388867</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0038"><label>[38]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Dudzic</surname>
<given-names>JP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hanson</surname>
<given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Iatsenko</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>More than black or white: melanization and Toll share regulatory serine proteases in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Cell Rep</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1050</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1061.e3</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2019.03.101</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31018123</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0039"><label>[39]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Le Bourg</surname>
<given-names>&#x000c9;</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The NF-kB like factor DIF has weaker effects on Drosophila melanogaster immune defenses than previously thought</article-title>. <source>J Comp Physiol B</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>181</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>741</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>750</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00360-011-0567-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21424695</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0040"><label>[40]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Valanne</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wang</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ramet</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The Drosophila Toll signaling pathway</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>186</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>649</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>656</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.1002302</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21209287</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0041"><label>[41]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Clemmons</surname>
<given-names>AW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lindsay</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wasserman</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>An effector peptide family required for Drosophila Toll-mediated immunity</article-title>. <source>PLOS Pathog</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e1004876</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1004876</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25915418</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0042"><label>[42]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lindsay</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lin</surname>
<given-names>SJH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wasserman</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Short-Form Bomanins Mediate Humoral Immunity in <bold><italic toggle="yes">Drosophila</italic></bold></article-title>. <source>J Innate Immun</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>306</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>314</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000489831</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29920489</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0043"><label>[43]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Shahrestani</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chambers</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vandenberg</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Sexual dimorphism in Drosophila melanogaster survival of Beauveria bassiana infection depends on core immune signaling</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>). doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-018-30527-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0044"><label>[44]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Duneau</surname>
<given-names>DF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kondolf</surname>
<given-names>HC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Im</surname>
<given-names>JH</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>The Toll pathway underlies host sexual dimorphism in resistance to both Gram-negative and Gram-positive bacteria in mated Drosophila</article-title>. <source>BMC Biol</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>). doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12915-017-0466-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0045"><label>[45]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>de Gregorio</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spellman</surname>
<given-names>PT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tzou</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>The Toll and Imd pathways are the major regulators of the immune response in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>2568</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2579</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/21.11.2568</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12032070</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0046"><label>[46]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Meyer</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Stewart</surname>
<given-names>TE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clement</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The quick and the deadly: growth vs virulence in a seed bank pathogen</article-title>. <source>New Phytol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>187</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>209</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>216</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2010.03255.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20406404</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0047"><label>[47]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Watson</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Joyce</surname>
<given-names>SA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Spencer</surname>
<given-names>GV</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>The exbD gene of photorhabdus temperata is required for full virulence in insects and symbiosis with the nematode Heterorhabditis</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>56</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>763</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>773</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2005.04574.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15819630</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0048"><label>[48]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Valero-Jim&#x000e9;nez</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Debets</surname>
<given-names>AJM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>van Kan</surname>
<given-names>JAL</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Natural variation in virulence of the entomopathogenic fungus Beauveria bassiana against malaria mosquitoes</article-title>. <source>Malar J</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>). doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1475-2875-13-479</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0049"><label>[49]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Talaei-Hassanloui</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kharazi-Pakdel</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goettel</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Variation in virulence of Beauveria bassiana isolates and its relatedness to some morphological characteristics</article-title>. <source>Biocontrol Sci Technol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>525</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>534</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/09583150500532758</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0050"><label>[50]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zhan</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xie</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhu</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Linear correlation analysis of Zymoseptoria tritici aggressiveness with in vitro growth rate</article-title>. <source>Phytopathology&#x000ae;</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>106</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>1255</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1261</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PHYTO-12-15-0338-R</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27348342</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0051"><label>[51]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Thrall</surname>
<given-names>PH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Barrett</surname>
<given-names>LG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burdon</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Variation in pathogen aggressiveness within a metapopulation of the Cakile maritima &#x02013; Alternaria brassicicola host&#x02013;pathogen association</article-title>. <source>Plant Pathol</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>265</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>274</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-3059.2005.01190.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0052"><label>[52]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rutschmann</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jung</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hetru</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>The rel protein DIF mediates the antifungal but not the antibacterial host defense in Drosophila</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>569</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>580</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1074-7613(00)80208-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10843389</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0053"><label>[53]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Xiao</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ying</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zheng</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Genomic perspectives on the evolution of fungal entomopathogenicity in Beauveria bassiana</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. <year>2012</year>
<month>Jan</month>;<volume>2</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>483</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep00483</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22761991</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0054"><label>[54]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname>
<given-names>XR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hu</surname>
<given-names>QB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>XQ</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Effects of destruxins on free calcium and hydrogen ions in insect hemocytes</article-title>. <source>Insect Sci</source>. <year>2014</year>
<month>Feb</month>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>31</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1744-7917.12028</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23956215</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0055"><label>[55]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Tzou</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Reichhart</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lemaitre</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Constitutive expression of a single antimicrobial peptide can restore wild-type resistance to infection in immunodeficient Drosophila mutants</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>99</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>2152</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2157</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.042411999</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11854512</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0056"><label>[56]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Fang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vega-Rodr&#x000ed;guez</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ghosh</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Development of transgenic fungi that kill human malaria parasites in mosquitoes</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>1979</year>;<volume>2011</volume>(<issue>6020</issue>):<fpage>1074</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1077</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1199115</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0057"><label>[57]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Binggeli</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Neyen</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Poidevin</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Prophenoloxidase activation is required for survival to microbial infections in Drosophila. Schneider DS, editor</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog [Internet]</source>. <year>2014</year>
<month>May</month>
<day>1</day>
<date-in-citation>[cited 2019 <month>Oct</month>
<day>3</day>]</date-in-citation>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e1004067</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1004067</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24788090</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0058"><label>[58]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>St Leger</surname>
<given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Butt</surname>
<given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Goettel</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Production in vitro of appressoria by the entomopathogenic fungusMetarhizium anisopliae</article-title>. <source>Exp Mycol</source>. <year>1989</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>274</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>288</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0147-5975(89)90049-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0059"><label>[59]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Fang</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lu</surname>
<given-names>HL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>King</surname>
<given-names>GF</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Construction of a hypervirulent and specific mycoinsecticide for locust control</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>). doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep07345</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0060"><label>[60]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ferrandon</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jung</surname>
<given-names>AC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Criqui</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>A drosomycin-GFP reporter transgene reveals a local immune response in Drosophila that is not dependent on the Toll pathway</article-title>. <source>EMBO J</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1217</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1227</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/17.5.1217</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9482719</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0061"><label>[61]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cohen</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Moran</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sharon</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Drosomycin, an innate immunity peptide of Drosophila melanogaster, interacts with the fly voltage-gated sodium channel</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>284</volume>(<issue>35</issue>):<fpage>23558</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23563</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M109.023358</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19574227</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
