<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLOS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC10732418</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0293146</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-23-19061</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>People and Places</subject><subj-group><subject>Geographical Locations</subject><subj-group><subject>Asia</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Medicine and Health Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Epidemiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Medical Risk Factors</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>People and Places</subject><subj-group><subject>Geographical Locations</subject><subj-group><subject>Asia</subject><subj-group><subject>Pakistan</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Ecology and Environmental Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Environmental Impacts</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Engineering and Technology</subject><subj-group><subject>Civil Engineering</subject><subj-group><subject>Transportation Infrastructure</subject><subj-group><subject>Roads</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Engineering and Technology</subject><subj-group><subject>Transportation</subject><subj-group><subject>Transportation Infrastructure</subject><subj-group><subject>Roads</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>People and Places</subject><subj-group><subject>Geographical Locations</subject><subj-group><subject>Europe</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Sociology</subject><subj-group><subject>Culture</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Agriculture</subject><subj-group><subject>Agricultural Economics</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Social Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Economics</subject><subj-group><subject>Agricultural Economics</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Assessing financial risks of foreign agricultural investment in belt and road countries: A risk index approach and VHSD-EM model analysis</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Assessing financial risks of foreign agricultural investment in belt and Road countries</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Ying</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/">Conceptualization</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/">Data curation</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/formal-analysis/">Formal analysis</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/funding-acquisition/">Funding acquisition</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/">Methodology</role><xref rid="aff001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8037-208X</contrib-id><name><surname>Tunio</surname><given-names>Fayaz Hussain</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/">Investigation</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/resources/">Resources</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/validation/">Validation</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/">Writing &#x02013; original draft</role><role content-type="http://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/">Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing</role><xref rid="aff002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001"><label>1</label>
<addr-line>Institute of Agricultural Economics and Development, Chinese Academ y of Agricultural Sciences, Beijing, China</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff002"><label>2</label>
<addr-line>Department of Law, Shaheed Zulfiqar Ali Bhutto University of Law, Karachi, Pakistan</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Jakovljevic</surname><given-names>Mihajlo</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref rid="edit1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>Hosei University: Hosei Daigaku, JAPAN</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>fayaztunio@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>18</volume><issue>12</issue><elocation-id>e0293146</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>5</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2023 Tian, Tunio</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Tian, Tunio</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="pone.0293146.pdf"/><abstract><p>This study establishes a risk index system to evaluate the financial risks of foreign agricultural investment in Belt and Road countries. Agricultural foreign investment risk prevention has emerged as a crucial concern across various sectors globally. We assess the four key dimensions such as political and military risk, economic market risk, social and cultural risk, and resource and environmental risk. We employ the Vertical and Horizontal Leveling Method and Entropy Weighting Method (VHSD-EM) for measuring and analyzing foreign agricultural investment risk levels in Belt and Road countries from 2014 to 2021. Moreover, we used spatial correlation analysis, the Getis-Ord Gi* statistic, to identify hot and cold spots of agricultural foreign investment risks. First political &#x00026; military, and environmental risks are the main influencing factors of agricultural foreign investment risk. The average AFDI level exceeded in Southeast and South Asia, and certain spillover effects were found in Southeast Asia. Second, the Belt and Road" initiative effectively reduces the risk of AFDI and helps to weaken the spillover effect among fellow countries. A significant spillover effect in AFDI from neighboring countries can lead to high-risk areas for sustained AFDI formation. Third to address such challenges, the Chinese government has prerequisites to enhance foreign agricultural investments in Belt and Road countries and establish a measurement index for agricultural investment risks. Government needs to establish a public service system to enhance the development of large-scale multinational agricultural enterprises. Foreign cooperation is essential for multi and bilateral investment negotiation and optimizing the financial tools to mitigate agricultural foreign direct investment risk in Belt and Road countries.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>The authors received no specific funding for this work.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="1"/><table-count count="4"/><page-count count="15"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>All relevant data are within the manuscript and its <xref rid="sec013" ref-type="sec">Supporting information</xref> files.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>All relevant data are within the manuscript and its <xref rid="sec013" ref-type="sec">Supporting information</xref> files.</p></notes></front><body><sec id="sec001"><title>1. Introduction and literature review</title><p>The Belt and Road cooperation initiative has launched a series of work with economic construction as the core, which brings not only great opportunities for Chinese agricultural enterprises to invest abroad but encourages Chinese enterprises to invest more in foreign agriculture in Belt and Road countries and also promotes Chinese enterprises to increase the amount of foreign direct agricultural investment. After China launched the Belt and Road initiative in 2013, China&#x02019;s foreign direct investment rapidly grew in member countries. Among them, foreign investment in agriculture increased from US $3.956 billion in 2013 to US $27.115 billion in 2021. As a proactive global agricultural resource allocation behavior, agricultural investment can help developing countries solve funding shortages for agricultural development, ensure a stable domestic food supply, and promote the agricultural development of host countries. China&#x02019;s agriculture has important practical significance globally in the Belt and Road initiative context. It can enhance the international pricing power of agricultural products, improve agricultural production efficiency, alleviate the pressure on domestic agricultural resources, and promote the structural reform of the agricultural supply side.</p><p>The uncertainty of the international economic and trade environment is increasing sharply. The United States and other Western countries continue to implement the policy of "De-Sinicization," tighten the review system of foreign investment, and issue the Act on Promoting Agricultural Security and Safety. The risks of foreign investment in China&#x02019;s transnational agricultural enterprises will continue to expand. The launch of the "Blue Dot Network" program of the United States has disrupted China&#x02019;s strategic layout of the Belt and Road, further increasing the uncertainty of agricultural investment risks in Belt and Road countries. However, China&#x02019;s agriculture is expand globally but facing practical challenges, such as insufficient agricultural technology, the small scale of overseas agricultural investment, and the high risk of overseas agricultural investment. A complex and changeable investment environment creates the difference in interest demands of Belt and Road countries. It raises the risk of failure in agricultural investment for Chinese firms. The spatial correlation of China&#x02019;s direct investment in Belt and Road countries objectively exists, and spatial distribution is not completely random but has significant spatial dependence on high spatial agglomeration characteristics [<xref rid="pone.0293146.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Any economy&#x02019;s outward agricultural investment depends on its investment needs and some essential conditions likewise political &#x00026; military, economic market, social &#x00026; cultural, and resource &#x00026; environment of the host country. By the end of 2021, China&#x02019;s agricultural investment projects, i.e., Belt and Road, have reached 13.68 billion US dollars, recorded for 7.50% of the total. Excessive investment risks have directly affected China&#x02019;s investment in Belt and Road countries. How is the Belt and Road initiative effective and sustainable in reducing agricultural investment risks? Do any investment risks relate to Belt and Road countries in construction spatially? The examination of these issues serves to enhance our comprehension of the evolving dynamics surrounding agricultural investment as a pivotal convergence point for countries along the Belt and Road initiative, fostering a shared community of interests and a collective vision for the future. This analysis also holds profound practical implications and a catalytic role in advancing China&#x02019;s proactive pursuit of agricultural globalization, expediting the maturation of contemporary agricultural practices, enhancing agricultural productivity and effectiveness, and bolstering international competitiveness. Investment risks along the Belt and Road are mainly divided into two categories; (i) descriptive research, and existing studies have used risk assessment methods such as the "difference-in-differences" analysis [<xref rid="pone.0293146.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], the method of moments analysis [<xref rid="pone.0293146.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], and the comprehensive evaluation method [<xref rid="pone.0293146.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], spatial autocorrelation, principal component analysis [<xref rid="pone.0293146.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>], grey correlation method [<xref rid="pone.0293146.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], and entropy method [<xref rid="pone.0293146.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] to conduct in-depth analysis from political, economic, and social perspectives. (ii) This empirical investigation employs econometric models in quantitative research, consistently indicating that emerging economies hold greater allure for China&#x02019;s Outward Foreign Direct Investment (OFDI).</p><p>Within the realm of foreign direct investment (FDI), the influence of political risks has garnered the attention of scholars. [<xref rid="pone.0293146.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] have postulated that political risk can serve as an attractive magnet for foreign direct investment inflows. In contrast, an opposing school of thought argues that reduced political risks do not necessarily foster favorable conditions for foreign direct investment. [<xref rid="pone.0293146.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>] have provided empirical evidence suggesting that political risks tend to displace foreign direct investment. Furthermore, they have highlighted the growing significance of the Bilateral Investment Treaty system, particularly in relation to the proportion of foreign direct investment outflow within a national economy.</p><p>Extending the analysis to spatial dimensions, [<xref rid="pone.0293146.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] incorporated a spatial weight matrix in their research to examine the impact of geopolitical risks on the geographical distribution of China&#x02019;s direct investment in Belt and Road countries. Their findings underscored a significant spatial correlation between China&#x02019;s investment patterns and the Belt and Road initiative. Notably, violent geopolitical risks were found to exert a pronounced adverse effect on China&#x02019;s foreign direct investment. [<xref rid="pone.0293146.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] adopting diverse measurement methodologies, explored overseas investment risk factors. Their investigation revealed that a company&#x02019;s overseas investment is influenced by social conditions and the business environment, whereas a country&#x02019;s investment risk is shaped by the intricate interplay of political and economic factors.</p><p>Furthermore, [<xref rid="pone.0293146.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] assessed the investment risk levels of 50 Belt and Road countries from 2014 to 2017. They accomplished this by constructing an investment risk system specific to Belt and Road countries and employing the VHSD-EM model. While their study provided insights into the evolving trends of investment risk within these countries and regions over a four-year span, it did not delve into the spatial correlation analysis of investment risks along the Belt and Road initiative. Additionally, the study did not further investigate the distribution of cold and hot spots regarding agricultural foreign investment risks. Research in the domain of agricultural outward investment has undertaken comprehensive investigations into various related facets, such as agricultural investment risks [<xref rid="pone.0293146.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], food security [<xref rid="pone.0293146.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], issues pertinent to agricultural outward investment [<xref rid="pone.0293146.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], factors influencing agricultural investment [<xref rid="pone.0293146.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], and global agricultural resource utilization [<xref rid="pone.0293146.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. However, the focus on China&#x02019;s agricultural outward investment remains relatively limited. A majority of these studies center on the current landscape of China&#x02019;s agricultural globalization efforts [<xref rid="pone.0293146.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], the agricultural investment environment in countries along the "Belt and Road" initiative [<xref rid="pone.0293146.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], risk assessment for agricultural investments along the "Belt and Road" [<xref rid="pone.0293146.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], location choices for China&#x02019;s agricultural investment cooperation with countries along the "Belt and Road" [<xref rid="pone.0293146.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], and strategies for mitigating agricultural investment risks [<xref rid="pone.0293146.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p><p>[<xref rid="pone.0293146.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0293146.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] discovered that China&#x02019;s Outward Foreign Direct Investment (OFDI) primarily gravitates toward high-risk countries within the "Belt and Road" initiative. Risk preference is discernible across political, military, and socio-cultural dimensions, while risk aversion manifests itself within economic and financial domains. [<xref rid="pone.0293146.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] developed indicators to quantitatively assess the evolving trends and risk levels of agricultural investment and financial risk within countries along the Belt and Road, considering four dimensions: political, economic, social, and industrial. However, they did not directly measure investment risk. It&#x02019;s important to note that this methodology relies on matrices to determine weights, limiting its ability to fully capture the information encapsulated within each indicator. [<xref rid="pone.0293146.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] examined agricultural investment risks associated with China&#x02019;s engagement with ASEAN countries using fuzzy comprehensive evaluation and grey correlation methods. Their findings indicated that major ASEAN countries exhibit higher agricultural investment risks, whereas countries such as Laos, Malaysia, and Indonesia demonstrate relatively lower levels of risk.</p><p>In general, previous studies on the influencing factors of investment in Belt and Road countries are relatively rich but lack measurement and spatial analysis on the risk of foreign agricultural investment. Therefore, by building a comprehensive risk assessment index system, we analyze the temporal and spatial evolution characteristics of four types of risks in Belt and Road countries from 2014 to 2021 using spatial autocorrelation, cold and hot spot analysis and provide some reference for China to prevent agricultural investment risks in Belt and Road countries.</p><p>First contribution of this research lies in its comprehensive exploration of effective methodologies for evaluating the agricultural investment risk prevalent among countries participating in the Belt and Road initiative. Utilizing the "VHSD-EM" model, this study assesses agricultural investment risk, allowing for a nuanced understanding of its dynamic evolution patterns over time. Furthermore, the article advances strategic recommendations and suggestions aimed at enhancing the measurement techniques for assessing foreign agricultural investment risk. This endeavor seeks to establish a dynamic rating system and early warning mechanism while fortifying enterprises&#x02019; capabilities to manage and withstand risks effectively.</p><p>Second, extending its purview beyond risk measurement in outward agricultural investments, this paper employs spatial correlation and cold and hot spot analyses to evaluate the spatial characteristics of investment risks within 51 Belt and Road countries. Through this analysis, it identifies nations marked by a sustained concentration of agricultural outward investment risks, thereby providing valuable decision-making insights for the accurate identification of high-risk regions and the strategic dispersion of enterprise investments.</p></sec><sec id="sec002"><title>2. Risk measurement and assessment of agricultural outward investment</title><sec id="sec003"><title>2.1 Index system of agricultural foreign investment risk of belt and road countries</title><p>Considering the availability and completeness of data, the 51 Belt and Road countries: Brunei, India, Indonesia, Laos, Malaysia, the Philippines, Singapore, Thailand, Albania, Bulgaria, the Czech Republic, Hungary, Latvia, Macedonia, Montenegro, Poland, Romania, Serbia, Slovakia, Slovenia, Ukraine, Kazakhstan, Kyrgyzstan Tajikistan, Uzbekistan, Algeria, Armenia, Azerbaijan, Egypt, Georgia, Iran, Iraq, Israel, Jordan, Kuwait, Lebanon, Morocco, Oman, Qatar, Saudi Arabia, Tunisia, United Arab Emirates, Yemen, Bangladesh, Maldives, Nepal, Pakistan, Sri Lanka, Vietnam, Mongolia, Russia. The time span is from 2014 to 2021.</p><p>After removing the sample of countries with missing economic and financial risk data in some years, the missing data are interpolated by linear interpolation. To cover the indicator information as comprehensively as possible, this paper, based on the principles of comprehensiveness, practicality, representativeness, and operability, constructs a risk measurement system for countries along the " Belt and Road" covering four perspective dimensions, political &#x00026; military risks, economic market risks, social &#x00026; cultural risks, and resource &#x00026; environmental risks, with a total of 21 basic indicators, as shown in <xref rid="pone.0293146.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="pone.0293146.t001"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0293146.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Agricultural investment risk index system of belt and road countries.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0293146.t001" id="pone.0293146.t001g" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Risk category</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Risk indicators</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Indicator Description</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Data sources</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Attribute</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weight</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" rowspan="5" colspan="1">
<bold>Political &#x00026; Military Risks</bold>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Political Stability</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The political situation remains stable, and lake of violence or terrorism</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WBGI</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.040</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Government Effectiveness</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The efficiency of government policy formulation and implementation, as well as the credibility of commitments</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WBGI</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Regulatory Quality</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The ability of the government to establish sound regulations to promote the development of private enterprises</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WBGI</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.086</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Military Intervention in Politics</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The level of military involvement in host country government affairs</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICRG Political Risk Index</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.035</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Corruption Control</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The degree of government control over corruption and abuse of public power within the political system</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WBGI</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="5" colspan="1">
<bold>Economic Market Risk</bold>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inflation Rate</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reflect changes in a country&#x02019;s price level</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WBDI</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.082</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Per Capita GDP</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Per capita production capacity</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WBDI</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.084</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Economic Volatility</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The fluctuation of economic growth rate in the past five years reflects the long-term stability of the economy</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WBDI</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.061</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unemployment Rate</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unemployment situation in the host country</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WBDI</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.105</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dependence on Foreign Trade</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reflect the degree of dependence of a country&#x02019;s national economy on foreign trade</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WBDI</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.023</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="6" colspan="1">
<bold>Social &#x00026; Cultural Risks</bold>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">National education level</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average length of education</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UNESCO</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">positive</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.106</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Public Security Order</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of murders per 100000 people per year</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">United Nations Office on Drugs and Crime</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">reverse</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Labor Market Regulation Situation</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimum wage standards and working hours regulations for hiring and dismissing labor force</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">World Economic freedom Index</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">positive</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.067</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Business Regulation Situation</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The difficulty of establishing a business, the restrictions on obtaining a business license, etc</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">World Economic freedom Index</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">positive</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.060</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geographical Distance</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Longitude and latitude distance between capitals</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CEPII Gravity Dataset</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.040</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gini Coefficient</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Social wealth gap</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">World Bank, CIA</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reverse</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.032</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="4" colspan="1">
<bold>Resource &#x00026; Environmental Risks</bold>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Infrastructure Quality</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The quality level of infrastructure in the host country</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Global Competitiveness Report</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.053</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average Water Resource Ownership</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total freshwater resources/cultivated land area</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The United Nations and Sustainable Development and Water Resources</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Agricultural Mechanization Level</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of tractors per 100 square kilometers of cultivated land</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WDI</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.024</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Per Capita Cultivated Land Area</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Agricultural land area/total population</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WDI</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.020</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t001fn001"><p>Note: The larger the value of the "positive" indicator, the smaller the risk; the smaller the value of the "reverse" indicator, the smaller the risk.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The outcomes derived from the Pearson correlation test exhibit a remarkable alignment with the findings obtained through the vertical and horizontal scaling method, as well as the entropy weighting method. Consequently, it can be inferred that the VHSD-EM model, which has been meticulously established, this research, demonstrates a noteworthy degree of accuracy. It is through this methodology that the ultimate weights assigned to each individual indicator have been determined.</p></sec><sec id="sec004"><title>2.2 Construction and measurement of the risk index of foreign agricultural investment of Belt and Road, countries</title><sec id="sec005"><title>2.2.1. Vertical and Horizontal Leveling Method (VHSD)</title><p>According to the time series function, the data of p countries, q basic indicators, and L years involved in the risk of outward agricultural investment can be arranged into a matrix, as shown below:
<disp-formula id="pone.0293146.e001">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0293146.e001.jpg" id="pone.0293146.e001g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M1" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1,2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022ef;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1,2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022ef;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1,2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022ef;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(1)</label>
</disp-formula>
Where <italic toggle="yes">D</italic> = <italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">ij</italic></sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>l</sub>) represents the <italic toggle="yes">j</italic>th indicator value of the <italic toggle="yes">i</italic>-th country in year <italic toggle="yes">l</italic>. The time-series three-dimensional data of agricultural foreign investment risks of Belt and Road countries are shown in <xref rid="pone.0293146.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. Among them, <italic toggle="yes">c</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub> represents the <italic toggle="yes">i</italic>-th country.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="pone.0293146.t002"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0293146.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Time series three-dimensional data of agricultural foreign investment risk of Belt and Road countries.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0293146.t002" id="pone.0293146.t002g" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">country</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>
<sub>1</sub>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>
<sub>2</sub>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x022ef;</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">t</italic>
<sub>
<italic toggle="yes">L</italic>
</sub>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub>1</sub>
<italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub>2</sub> &#x022ef; <italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">q</italic></sub></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub>1</sub>
<italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub>2</sub> &#x022ef; <italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">q</italic></sub></td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x022ef;</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub>1</sub>
<italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub>2</sub> &#x022ef; <italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">q</italic></sub></td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">c</italic>
</bold>
<sub>
<bold>1</bold>
</sub>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub>11</sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>1</sub>)<italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub>12</sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>1</sub>) &#x022ef; <italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub>1<italic toggle="yes">q</italic></sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>1</sub>)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub>11</sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>2</sub>)<italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub>12</sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>2</sub>) &#x022ef; <italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub>1<italic toggle="yes">q</italic></sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>2</sub>)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x022ef;</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub>11</sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">L</italic></sub>)<italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub>12</sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>2</sub>) &#x022ef; <italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub>1<italic toggle="yes">q</italic></sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">L</italic></sub>)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">c</italic>
</bold>
<sub>
<bold>2</bold>
</sub>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub>21</sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>1</sub>)<italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub>22</sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>1</sub>) &#x022ef; <italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub>2<italic toggle="yes">q</italic></sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>1</sub>)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub>21</sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>2</sub>)<italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub>22</sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>2</sub>) &#x022ef; <italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub>2<italic toggle="yes">q</italic></sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>2</sub>)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x022ef;</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub>21</sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">L</italic></sub>)<italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub>22</sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">L</italic></sub>) &#x022ef; <italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub>2<italic toggle="yes">q</italic></sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">L</italic></sub>)</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x022ee;</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x022ef;</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x022ef;</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x022ef;</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x022ef;</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">c</italic>
</bold>
<sub>
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>
</bold>
</sub>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>1</sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>1</sub>)<italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>2</sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>1</sub>) &#x022ef; <italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">pq</italic></sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>1</sub>)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>1</sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>2</sub>)<italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>2</sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>2</sub>) &#x022ef; <italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">pq</italic></sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>2</sub>)</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>&#x022ef;</bold>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>1</sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">L</italic></sub>)<italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>2</sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">L</italic></sub>) &#x022ef; <italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">pq</italic></sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">L</italic></sub>)</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><disp-formula id="pone.0293146.e002">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0293146.e002.jpg" id="pone.0293146.e002g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M2" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1,2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022ef;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1,2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022ef;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1,2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022ef;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(2)</label>
</disp-formula><p>Firstly, the value of the <italic toggle="yes">j</italic>th indicator in the <italic toggle="yes">i</italic>-th country in year <italic toggle="yes">l</italic> is standardized to obtain <italic toggle="yes">y</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">ijl</italic></sub>, taking the mean and standard deviation of the <italic toggle="yes">j</italic>th indicator from all countries in year <italic toggle="yes">l</italic>, obtains <inline-formula id="pone.0293146.e003"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0293146.e003.jpg" id="pone.0293146.e003g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M3" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> and <inline-formula id="pone.0293146.e004"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0293146.e004.jpg" id="pone.0293146.e004g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M4" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>.</p><p>Secondly, the risk function for agricultural outward investment is set as:
<disp-formula id="pone.0293146.e005">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0293146.e005.jpg" id="pone.0293146.e005g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M5" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(3)</label>
</disp-formula></p><p>In the equation, <italic toggle="yes">&#x003bc;</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub> is the indicator weight, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">i</italic></sub>(<italic toggle="yes">t</italic><sub>l</sub>) is the comprehensive risk value of country <italic toggle="yes">i</italic> in year <italic toggle="yes">l</italic>. Determine the indicator weight using formula (<xref rid="pone.0293146.e006" ref-type="disp-formula">4</xref>).</p><disp-formula id="pone.0293146.e006">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0293146.e006.jpg" id="pone.0293146.e006g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M6" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(4)</label>
</disp-formula><p>Among them, <italic toggle="yes">&#x003bc;</italic> = (<italic toggle="yes">&#x003bc;</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic toggle="yes">&#x003bc;</italic><sub>2</sub>, &#x022ef;, <italic toggle="yes">&#x003bc;</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">p</italic></sub>)<sup><italic toggle="yes">T</italic></sup>, <inline-formula id="pone.0293146.e007"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0293146.e007.jpg" id="pone.0293146.e007g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M7" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>A</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> is a <italic toggle="yes">p</italic> order Symmetric matrix, <inline-formula id="pone.0293146.e008"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0293146.e008.jpg" id="pone.0293146.e008g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M8" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>B</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, <italic toggle="yes">l</italic> = 1, 2, &#x022ef;,<italic toggle="yes">L</italic>.</p><p>When <italic toggle="yes">&#x003bc;</italic><sup><italic toggle="yes">T</italic></sup>
<italic toggle="yes">&#x003bc;</italic> = 1 and taking the eigenvector corresponding to the maximum value of A, <italic toggle="yes">&#x003c3;</italic><sup>2</sup> reaches a maximum value, the weight vector <italic toggle="yes">&#x003bc;</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub> is obtained by normalizing the feature vectors.</p></sec><sec id="sec006"><title>2.2.2. Entropy Weighting Method (EM)</title><p>Using range standardization to process indicator data, if <italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">ijl</italic></sub> is a positive value, then</p><p><inline-formula id="pone.0293146.e009"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0293146.e009.jpg" id="pone.0293146.e009g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M9" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>; If <italic toggle="yes">h</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">ijl</italic></sub> is a negative value, then
<disp-formula id="pone.0293146.e010">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0293146.e010.jpg" id="pone.0293146.e010g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M10" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1,2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022ef;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1,2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022ef;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>;</mml:mo><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1,2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x022ef;</mml:mo><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(5)</label>
</disp-formula></p><p>Among them, the <italic toggle="yes">j</italic>th indicator of the <italic toggle="yes">i</italic>-th country obtained <italic toggle="yes">y</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">ijl</italic></sub> After range normalization of the indicator value in the <italic toggle="yes">l</italic>-th year.</p><p>Calculate the degree of variation of indicator values:
<disp-formula id="pone.0293146.e011">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0293146.e011.jpg" id="pone.0293146.e011g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M11" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(6)</label>
</disp-formula></p><p>Among them, the characteristic proportion of the <italic toggle="yes">i</italic>-th country in the <italic toggle="yes">l</italic>-th year under the <italic toggle="yes">j</italic>th indicator is expressed as <italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">ijl</italic></sub>.</p><p>From this, calculate the EM value of the <italic toggle="yes">j</italic>th indicator, <inline-formula id="pone.0293146.e012"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0293146.e012.jpg" id="pone.0293146.e012g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M12" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula>, Among them, when <italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">ijl</italic></sub> = 0 or 1, set <italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">ijl</italic></sub>
<italic toggle="yes">ln</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">v</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">ijl</italic></sub>) = 0.</p><p>Make the coefficient of difference of the indicator <italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">jl</italic></sub>, then <italic toggle="yes">F</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">jl</italic></sub> = 1 &#x02212; <italic toggle="yes">E</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">jl</italic></sub>.</p><p>The formula for calculating the weight of indicator EM is:
<disp-formula id="pone.0293146.e013">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0293146.e013.jpg" id="pone.0293146.e013g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M13" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(7)</label>
</disp-formula></p></sec><sec id="sec007"><title>2.2.3. Basic principles and verification of the VHSD-EM model</title><p>VHSD-EM analysis combines the indicator weights calculated by the VHSD model and the EM model to obtain the final weights and calculate the comprehensive risk value of each indicator. Use MATLAB 16.0 software to perform Spearman correlation tests on the results of VHSD and EM methods.</p><p>Weights to be determined by VHSD and EM methods <italic toggle="yes">&#x003bc;</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub> and <italic toggle="yes">&#x003c6;</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">jl</italic></sub> Consists of the following matrix:
<disp-formula id="pone.0293146.e014">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0293146.e014.jpg" id="pone.0293146.e014g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M14" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#x022ee;</mml:mo></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#x022ee;</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>q</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(8)</label>
</disp-formula></p><p>The final weight of each indicator <italic toggle="yes">W</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">jl</italic></sub> is created by the arithmetic mean of each row of elements in <italic toggle="yes">C</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">jl</italic></sub> Namely
<disp-formula id="pone.0293146.e015">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0293146.e015.jpg" id="pone.0293146.e015g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M15" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>&#x003c6;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(9)</label>
</disp-formula></p><p>The specific score for each indicator is recorded as
<disp-formula id="pone.0293146.e016">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0293146.e016.jpg" id="pone.0293146.e016g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M16" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>y</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(10)</label>
</disp-formula></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec008"><title>2.3Analysis of the overall measurement results of the investment risk level of Belt and Road countries</title><p>From the time dimension, the countries&#x02019; average agricultural investment risk level shows the fluctuation in downward-upward trend, from 7.4944 in 2014 to 7.3340 in 2021, with the decrease of 2.14%. Throughout the sampling period, notable regional disparities in agricultural investment risk levels were observed among the six regions encompassed by the "Belt and Road" initiative. Specifically, the agricultural investment risk within Central and Eastern Europe, West Asia, and North Africa exhibited a distinctive temporal pattern characterized by successive phases of escalation, de-escalation, resurgence, re-escalation, and subsequent de-escalation. In contrast, the agricultural investment risk within Central Asia, Southeast Asia, and South Asia followed a discernible trend characterized by cyclical fluctuations, involving phases of decline, resurgence, decline, resurgence, and once more, decline.</p><p>In the year 2021, an intriguing observation emerged within the Belt and Road initiative as it pertains to agricultural investment risk. Specifically, four regions&#x02014;Central Asia, Central and Eastern Europe, and Northeast Asia&#x02014;recorded higher agricultural investment risk levels compared to the regional averages. This phenomenon implies the presence of an agglomeration effect associated with China&#x02019;s outward agricultural investment risk. It&#x02019;s noteworthy that, in 2021, Central Asia exhibited notably higher average agricultural investment risk levels compared to the other regions, underscoring regional variations in risk.</p><p>Moreover, substantial disparities were evident when examining the agricultural investment risk levels among the 51 countries along the Belt and Road initiative in 2021. Pakistan emerged as the country with the highest agricultural investment risk level, while Brunei ranked as the country with the lowest risk level. Notably, the disparity in the agricultural investment risk scores between these two countries was 1.80 times, signifying a significant divergence in the risk profiles of agricultural investments across different nations.</p><p>Within each region, specific countries stood out in terms of their agricultural investment risk levels. For instance, Macedonia ranked first in Central and Eastern Europe, Tajikistan claimed the top spot in Central Asia, Morocco led the pack in West Asia and North Africa, Pakistan took the lead in South Asia, Thailand held the highest rank in Southeast Asia, and Russia garnered the top position in Northeast Asia regarding agricultural investment risk levels. These regional and country-specific variations contribute to a more nuanced understanding of the complexities surrounding agricultural investment risks within the Belt and Road initiative.</p><p>Further, this paper conducts a multi-dimensional analysis of the agricultural investment risks from the perspective of temporal changes and accelerating political &#x00026; military risk. At the national level, countries with higher political risks mainly include Albania and Macedonia, two Central and Eastern European countries, Southeast Asian countries such as Indonesia, and West Asian and North African countries such as Jordan. Countries in these regions generally face risks such as political instability, inefficient government, and feeble rule of law.</p><p>The economic market risk shows an increasing and deceasing trend from the national perspective, countries with high economic market risks mainly include Southeast Asian countries such as Laos and the Philippines, Central and Eastern European countries include Poland and Romania, and South Asian countries contains Vietnam and Pakistan. Among them, the fluctuations in risk levels in 2019 were mainly due to reduced inflation risk, while the decrease in risk in 2020 was mainly due to exchange rate fluctuations, that some extent indicates the economic situation along the route is quite complex and unstable factors.</p><p>The assessment of social and cultural risks within countries along the Belt and Road initiative reveals a discernible pattern characterized by an initial decline, followed by an upswing, and subsequently another decline. When viewed through a national lens, it becomes evident that countries exhibiting heightened social and cultural risks primarily encompass West Asian and North African nations, such as Morocco, Iraq, Lebanon, and Tunisia, South Asian countries, including Pakistan and India, Southeast Asian nations such as Thailand and Indonesia, and Central and Eastern European countries like Ukraine.</p><p>These countries with elevated social and cultural risks face multifaceted challenges, stemming from both internal and external sources. For instance, India and Pakistan grapple with territorial disputes, resulting in internal and external conflicts. Ukraine has been entangled in military conflicts attributable to foreign interference. Meanwhile, Iraq contends with a proclivity towards social violence and crime. The common thread among these high-risk nation lies in their intricate and evolving social landscapes, marked by disparities in social development and frequent conflicts triggered by a multitude of factors, including race, religion, and culture. These complexities underscore the importance of considering social and cultural dimensions when assessing risk within the Belt and Road initiative. The resources and environment risk shows initial rising and then relatively flat trend from a national perspective, countries with high resource and environmental risks mainly include West Asian and North African countries such as Algeria, Iraq, and Yemen, likewise South Asian countries contains Maldives, Nepal, Bangladesh, Pakistan, and Central Asian countries such as Uzbekistan. The countries with high resource and environmental risks in these countries are mainly lagging with transportation infrastructure, scarce water resources, and a small proportion of agricultural land. Such countries have weak demand for agricultural development, disadvantaged agricultural resources, and hindered overall agricultural production development, resulting in significant resource and environmental risks.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec009"><title>3. Analysis of spatial characteristics of risks in outward agricultural investment</title><sec id="sec010"><title>3.1 Spatial correlation test</title><p>The distribution of risks in outward agricultural investment among countries is not isolated due to the strategic interaction between neighboring countries there is a significant spatial correlation in outward agricultural investment between neighboring countries. Once this spatial correlation is solidified, it may gradually form a risk accumulation area, which deserves attention. We deeply explore the spatial distribution characteristics of agricultural outward investment risks of Belt and Road countries. This paper uses <italic toggle="yes">Moran&#x02019; s I</italic> to test the spatial correlation of relevant indicators of agricultural outward investment risks. According to Tobler&#x02019;s first law of geography, regions closer to each other are more closely related. Therefore, we first build a spatial weight matrix W with the following elements:
<disp-formula id="pone.0293146.e017">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0293146.e017.jpg" id="pone.0293146.e017g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M17" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(11)</label>
</disp-formula></p><p>Among them, <italic toggle="yes">d</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">ij</italic></sub> represents the geographical distance between country i and country j. Under this setting, the spatial matrix elements corresponding to distant countries are relatively small, which can identify the correlation between neighboring regions. After the spatial weight matrix is standardized, the calculation formula of Moran&#x02019;s I can be expressed as:
<disp-formula id="pone.0293146.e018">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0293146.e018.jpg" id="pone.0293146.e018g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M18" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">'</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="2pt"/><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mfenced separators="|"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>-</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(12)</label>
</disp-formula>
Where, x refers to the risk indicators of agricultural foreign investment of Belt and Road countries. If I is a positive value, it represents a positive spatial correlation between the risks of outward agricultural investment in neighboring countries, and the larger the value, the stronger the correlation; If I is a negative value, it indicates that the risk of outward agricultural investment in neighboring countries is spatially negatively correlated. The smaller the value, the greater the difference; If I is significantly 0, it indicates no spatial correlation. The Moran&#x02019;s I value calculated using STATA16.0 is shown in <xref rid="pone.0293146.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="pone.0293146.t003"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0293146.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Global Moran&#x02019;s I in the sample period.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0293146.t003" id="pone.0293146.t003g" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Year</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">I</italic>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">E</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">I</italic>)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">sd</italic>(<italic toggle="yes">I</italic>)</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic toggle="yes">z</italic>
</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic toggle="yes">p</italic>*</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2014</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.048</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.020</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.110</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.618</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.268</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2015</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.184</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.020</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.110</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.861</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.031</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2016</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.211</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.020</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.110</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.104</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.018</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2017</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.268</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.020</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.110</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.621</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2018</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.283</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.020</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.110</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.751</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2019</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.293</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.020</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.111</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.835</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2020</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.272</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.020</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.110</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.659</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td></tr><tr><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2021</bold>
</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.249</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.020</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.110</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.454</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.007</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>For the identification of spatial correlation, this paper tests the global spatial correlation of China&#x02019;s agricultural outward investment risks to 51 Belt and Road countries by calculating Moran&#x02019;s I index under the spatial weight matrix.</p><p>From the changing trend of China&#x02019;s Moran&#x02019;s I index of outward agricultural investment in the 51 countries in <xref rid="pone.0293146.t003" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>, we can find that: first, although China&#x02019;s Moran&#x02019;s I index of investment in the " Belt and Road" shows a relatively sharp upward and downward fluctuation trend, it is generally positive, which indicates that China&#x02019;s agricultural outward investment in the "the Belt and Road" has a positive spatial correlation. Secondly, from the trend of the Moran&#x02019;s I index over time, with 2019 as a turning point, the Moran&#x02019;s I index showed a clear upward trend from 2014 to 2019 while showing a clear downward trend after 2019. It shows that before 2019, China&#x02019;s spatial dependence on the overall investment in countries has gradually increased. Since 2019, this dependence has begun to weaken, and from 2021, its spatial dependence has risen again.</p><p>According to Moran&#x02019;s I, the countries along the "Belt and Road" have a strong spatial agglomeration in the sample period, and there is a positive correlation between countries. After 2018, the Sample space correlation has partially increased.</p><p>In order to further observe the spatial agglomeration characteristics of China&#x02019;s agricultural outward investment in countries along the "Belt and Road,&#x0201d; this paper draws Moran&#x02019;s I scatter diagram of outward agricultural investment under the spatial weight of geographical distance, as shown in <xref rid="pone.0293146.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="pone.0293146.g001"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0293146.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>Moran scatter agricultural foreign investment risk.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0293146.g001" position="float"/></fig><p>It can be seen from <xref rid="pone.0293146.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref> that 34 countries are located in the first and third quadrants under the spatial weight of geographical distance, which further indicates that the spatial distribution of China&#x02019;s agricultural outward investment in countries along the "Belt and Road" is not completely random, but highly spatial dependent. Therefore, when studying the risks of foreign investment in countries&#x02019; agriculture, we should not ignore its spatial dependence, or it will lead to biased estimates.</p></sec><sec id="sec011"><title>3.2 Analysis of spatial agglomeration</title><p>Due to the obvious regional characteristics of Belt and Road countries, the spatial characteristics of agricultural outward investment risks in different based on countries heterogeneous. Although Moran&#x02019;s I can be used to measure spatial correlation, it is difficult to identify local characteristics of space and make an in-depth analysis from the national level. Therefore, this section further introduces the Getis-Ord statistic. <inline-formula id="pone.0293146.e019"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0293146.e019.jpg" id="pone.0293146.e019g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M19" display="inline" overflow="scroll"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>*</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:math></alternatives></inline-formula> Constructed by Order et al. Getis (1995), used to identify the local concentration of risks of countries along the "Belt and Road". The advantage of this unified measurement is that it can identify hot spots and cold spots in the countries, thereby describing spatial heterogeneity. The calculation formula is:
<disp-formula id="pone.0293146.e020">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0293146.e020.jpg" id="pone.0293146.e020g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M20" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>G</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">*</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>w</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>z</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(13)</label>
</disp-formula>
Where i and j represent countries, d represents geographical distance, and <italic toggle="yes">w</italic><sub>ij</sub>(<italic toggle="yes">d</italic>) is the spatial weight matrix element defined according to the distance rule, <italic toggle="yes">z</italic><sub><italic toggle="yes">j</italic></sub> is the observed value of country j. The geographical distance is calculated according to countries&#x02019; longitude and latitude coordinates. The average distance between countries along the "Belt and Road" is found to be 5946.42 km. considering the radiation range of countries, d is set as 836 km. Therefore, <italic toggle="yes">w</italic><sub>ij</sub>(<italic toggle="yes">d</italic>) can be expressed as:
<disp-formula id="pone.0293146.e021">
<alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0293146.e021.jpg" id="pone.0293146.e021g" position="anchor"/><mml:math id="M21" display="block" overflow="scroll"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mfenced><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced close="" open="{"><mml:mrow><mml:mtable columnalign="left" equalcolumns="true" equalrows="true"><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="2pt"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>836</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="2pt"/><mml:mtext>km</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr columnalign="left"><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd><mml:mtd columnalign="left"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="2pt"/><mml:msub><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>j</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo><mml:mn>836</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="2pt"/><mml:mtext>km</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives>
<label>(14)</label>
</disp-formula></p><p>In <xref rid="pone.0293146.e005" ref-type="disp-formula">Eq (3)</xref>, the numerator represents the sum of values within a radius of 836 kilometers from the center point of country i, and the denominator represents the sum of values for all countries. Therefore, this unified measurement measures whether country i and its surrounding countries (i.e. countries within a radius of d kilometers) have relatively large or small ratios compared to all countries. If the statistic is high (low) at a significance level of 5%, the region is identified as a hot (cold) point. From this, spatial clustering identification of agricultural investment risks can be carried out in 51 countries.</p><p><xref rid="pone.0293146.t004" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref> depicted political and military risks within the context of the Belt and Road initiative reveals certain consistent trends. Over five consecutive years, five countries have consistently been designated as hot spots: Yemen, Iraq, Thailand, Pakistan, and Algeria. Conversely, six countries have consistently been designated as cold spots during the same period: Slovakia, Czech Republic, United Arab Emirates, Latvia, Brunei, and Sri Lanka.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="pone.0293146.t004"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0293146.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Identification of hot and cold countries.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0293146.t004" id="pone.0293146.t004g" position="float"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Risk Indicators</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2014</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2015</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2016</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2017</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2018</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2019</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2020</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2021</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Last Five Years</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Last Two Years</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center" colspan="11" rowspan="1">
<bold>Number of Hot spot Countries</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Political &#x00026; Military Risk</bold>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Economic Market Risk</bold>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Social &#x00026; Cultural Risk</bold>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Resource &#x00026; Environmental Risk</bold>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="11" rowspan="1">
<bold>Number of Cold spot Countries</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Political &#x00026; Military Risk</bold>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Economic Market Risk</bold>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Social &#x00026; Cultural Risk</bold>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Resource &#x00026; Environmental Risk</bold>
</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>With the advancement of the Belt and Road initiative, seven countries have emerged as hot spots in recent years. These include Yemen, Iraq, Iran, Lebanon, Albania, Thailand, and Pakistan. Simultaneously, ten countries have transitioned into cold spots, such as Slovakia, Brunei, Czech Republic, United Arab Emirates, Latvia, Sri Lanka, Romania, Israel, Slovenia, and Qatar.</p><p>Evaluating economic market risks, five countries have sustained hot spot status for five consecutive years: Laos, the Philippines, Vietnam, Romania, and Poland. In contrast, four countries have consistently been identified as cold spots: Jordan, Armenia, Montenegro, and Tunisia.</p><p>In recent years, with the promotion of the Belt and Road initiative, eight countries have become hot spots, including Laos, the Philippines, Romania, Poland, Vietnam, Pakistan, Oman, and the Czech Republic. Meanwhile, seven countries have transitioned into cold spots, namely Iraq, Iran, Lebanon, Tunisia, Montenegro, Jordan, and Armenia.</p><p>Assessing social and cultural risks, three countries&#x02014;Morocco, Pakistan, and India&#x02014;have maintained hot spot status for five consecutive years. Concurrently, three countries&#x02014;Slovakia, Kazakhstan, and the United Arab Emirates&#x02014;have remained cold spots for the same duration.</p><p>With the advancement of the Belt and Road initiative, five countries have become hot spots in recent years: Morocco, Pakistan, India, Iraq, and Lebanon. In contrast, six countries have transitioned into cold spots, including Brunei, Slovakia, Kazakhstan, the United Arab Emirates, Kyrgyzstan, and the Czech Republic.</p><p>Finally, in the realm of resource and environmental risks, four countries have consistently been identified as hot spots for five years: Yemen, Iraq, Nepal, and Bangladesh. In contrast, two countries, Slovakia and the United Arab Emirates, have consistently been designated as cold spots.</p><p>With the progression of the Belt and Road initiative, seven countries have become hot spots in recent years, namely Iraq, Yemen, Algeria, Maldives, Nepal, Bangladesh, and Uzbekistan. Simultaneously, six countries have transitioned into cold spots, including Slovakia, United Arab Emirates, Hungary, Slovenia, Czech Republic, and Oman.</p><p>The distribution of agricultural investments within countries along the Belt and Road initiative exhibits a pronounced spatial agglomeration. This manifests as a core hot spot for political and military risk in West Asia and North Africa and a core cold spot for political and military risk in Central and Eastern Europe. This spatial distribution underscores the elevated overall risk levels in Belt and Road countries, particularly in terms of political and military risks.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec012"><title>4. Conclusion and discussion</title><p>This study focuses on the measurement and spatial characteristics analysis of agricultural investment risks in countries participating in the Belt and Road initiative. Firstly, it is observed that the agricultural investment risks in member countries have generally decreased over time. Political &#x00026; military risks, as well as resource &#x00026; environmental risks, emerge as the primary factors influencing agricultural foreign investment risks. Secondly, significant variations exist in the levels of agricultural investment risks among the six major sectors within the Belt and Road region. These sectors exhibit investment risks that surpass the average levels observed in Northeast Asia, Central and Eastern Europe, and Central Asia. Furthermore, the average risk level of agricultural investment between 2014 and 2021 far exceeds to Southeast and South Asia, although agricultural investment risks in Southeast Asia demonstrate a certain degree of spillover effect. Thirdly, there are notable discrepancies in the risk levels of agricultural investment among Belt and Road countries. In 2021, Macedonia, Tajikistan, Morocco, Pakistan, Thailand, and Russia rank highest in terms of agricultural investment risks within their respective regions. The ability of agricultural investment to withstand risks will face severe tests due to ongoing factors such as global inflation, power struggles among major countries, and the COVID-19 pandemic&#x02019;s impact on the global economy. The aforementioned analysis demonstrates that the "Belt and Road" initiative effectively reduces the risks associated with agricultural investment and helps to mitigate spillover effects among neighboring countries. Finally, due to strategic interactivity in the behavior of neighboring countries, a significant spatial correlation exists in outward agricultural investment, displaying distinct spatial agglomeration characteristics. Agricultural investment from neighboring countries exhibits a substantial spillover effect, which can contribute to the formation of high-risk areas for sustained agricultural investment.</p><p>Based on the aforementioned research findings, this paper presents countermeasures and recommendations encompassing four key aspects. Firstly, it is proposed to enhance agricultural investment in countries participating in the Belt and Road initiative. China should bolster foreign agricultural cooperation with these countries, actively establish a dynamic rating and early warning mechanism for Belt and Road countries, and effectively strengthen China&#x02019;s agricultural foreign-funded enterprises&#x02019; investments in these countries. To enhance investment efficiency and mitigate systematic risks, China should concentrate to optimizing the agricultural investment environment, and reinforcing the "five links" in agriculture, that facilitating the upgrade of the agricultural product supply chain, and fostering high-quality development of bilateral and multilateral cooperation. Moreover, for countries that facing distinct type risks, China needs to conduct an in-depth consultation and exchange risk affected countries. This necessitates the formulation of diverse strategic collaboration models and the enhancement of infrastructure development in conjunction with these countries. Moreover, the establishment of a cooperative mechanism to foster coordination among countries and the facilitation of the exploitation of synergistic strengths between Chinese enterprises and those in Belt and Road countries are of paramount importance.</p><p>This research proposes the creation of an index designed to evaluate agricultural investment risks within Belt and Road countries, coupled with the periodic release of rating reports on China&#x02019;s Agricultural Overseas Investment Risk Index. The comprehensive evaluation of agricultural investment risks in Belt and Road countries should encompass a multitude of risk categories, encompassing political and military risks, economic and market risks, social and cultural risks, as well as resource and environmental risks. This evaluation should not only account for the aggregate level of these risks but also dissect their respective compositions and structures. Establishing a risk management model and constructing a measurement index for agricultural investment risks in countries are crucial, along with the regular release of risk measurement index reports. Simultaneously, an internal evaluation mechanism should be established to assess national risk management in host countries, emphasizing the effective combination of domestic and external evaluations within these host countries. The evaluation mechanism for national risk management should be enhanced to promote a comprehensive service platform that offers 24/7 early warning and evaluation of overseas project risks. This platform should dynamically select a blacklist of multinational agricultural investment risk enterprises and provide timely warnings and regular assessments. Collaborative mechanisms should be fostered to safeguard the interests and ensure the safety of overseas agricultural enterprises.</p><p>In order to effectively mitigate the elevated agricultural investment risks prevalent in Central and Eastern European countries, it is imperative to harness the catalytic potential of the "17+1" cooperation mechanism that exists between China and these regions. Recognizing the disparities in agricultural investment landscapes among individual nations, it becomes essential to delve into specific key industries and products tailored to each country&#x02019;s unique context. Expanding the purview of agricultural cooperation is vital in order to establish a multifaceted framework for collaborative endeavors. The government should proactively facilitate national-level cooperation and explore projects in science, technology, education, and other fields under the "17+1" mechanism. Leveraging scientific and technological advancements in agricultural investment and trade, such as seed research and development, agricultural machinery innovation, and pest control, can play a administrative role in promoting agricultural investment. Furthermore, it is important to fully utilize the coordinating and promotional capabilities of agricultural cooperation mechanisms to deepen investment cooperation between China and Central and Eastern Europe. From the corporate perspective, Chinese enterprises should be encouraged to pursue global expansion and engage in investment cooperation with prominent local agricultural companies, fostering mutually beneficial outcomes. Additionally, China Import and Export Credit Insurance Corporation should consider implementing various crop insurance projects overseas to effectively address potential agricultural investment risks, including measures related to war, riots, exchange restrictions, and other challenges.</p><p>One limitation of this study is the absence of a comprehensive consideration of both macro and micro-level risks, including factors like China&#x02019;s diplomatic relations and the intricacies of enterprise operations, within the framework of the risk assessment system. Furthermore, the wide-ranging and intricate nature of investment risks, coupled with the challenges in acquiring accurate and comprehensive data, has constrained our ability to provide more precise statistics at this time. As the "Belt and Road" initiative continues to gain momentum, there is an expectation that the evaluation system for risk indicators in outbound agricultural investment will undergo progressive refinement. In the future, this evolution is anticipated to facilitate more precise predictions of agricultural investment risks in countries along the "Belt and Road." Such advancements hold promise for providing decision-makers with robust support as they steer China&#x02019;s high-quality development within the context of the "Belt and Road" initiative and the broader strategy of globalizing China&#x02019;s agricultural sector.</p></sec><sec id="sec013" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supporting information</title><supplementary-material id="pone.0293146.s001" position="float" content-type="local-data"><label>S1 File</label><caption><p>(RAR)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0293146.s001.rar"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0293146.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wenge</surname><given-names>Liu</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shiyun</surname><given-names>Fu</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Huang</given-names></name>. <article-title>Geopolitical Risks and the Spatial Distribution of China&#x02019;s Foreign Direct Investment&#x02014;Taking the countries along the "the Belt and Road" as an example</article-title> [J]. <source>West Forum</source>, <year>2019</year>, <volume>29</volume> (<issue>01</issue>): <fpage>84</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>97</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0293146.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lacroix</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>M&#x000e9;on</surname><given-names>P.-G.</given-names></name>, &#x00026; <name><surname>Sekkat</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>. <article-title>Democratic transitions can attract foreign direct investment: Effect, trajectories, and the role of political risk</article-title>[J]. <source>Journal of Comparative Economics</source>. <year>2020</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0293146.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Haftel</surname><given-names>YZ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bassannygate</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>.<article-title>High-Income Developing Countries, FDI Outflows and the International Investment Agreement Regime</article-title>[J]. <source>World Trade Review</source>, <year>2022</year>, <volume>21</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0293146.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ha&#x00161;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fiala</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A fuzzy approach for the estimation of foreign investment risk based on values of rating indices</article-title>[J]. <source>Risk Manag</source>, <year>2019</year>,<volume>21</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>183</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>199</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0293146.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Analysis on the Evaluation of Suburban Real Estate Investment Environment&#x02014;Taking Guangzhou as an Example</article-title>[J]. <source>Modern Economy</source>, <year>2019</year>,<volume>10</volume>(<issue>3</issue>): <fpage>914</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>930</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0293146.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yanwen</surname><given-names>Tan</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huasheng</surname><given-names>Zeng</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Congxi</surname><given-names>Li</given-names></name>. <article-title>Risk Assessment and Country Priorities of China&#x02019;s Investment in ASEAN Agriculture</article-title> [J].<source>Issues in Agricultural Economy</source>, <year>2017</year>,<volume>38</volume>(<issue>08</issue>):<fpage>76</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>85</lpage>+<fpage>111</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0293146.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>,<name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Investment Environment Assessment and Strategic Policy for Subjects of Federation in Russia</article-title>[J]. <source>Chin. Geogr. Sci</source>. <year>2019</year>,<volume>29</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>887</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>904</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0293146.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>, <article-title>Investment risk assessment of coal-fired power plants in countries along the Belt and Road initiative based on ANP-Entropy-TODIM method</article-title>[J].<source>Energy</source>,<year>2019</year>,<volume>176</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>623</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>640</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0293146.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xiaobin</surname><given-names>Tang</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yanan</surname><given-names>Wang</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>Zhang</given-names></name>
<article-title>Research on Investment Risk Measurement of Countries along the "the Belt and Road"</article-title> [J]. <source>Journal of Quantitative &#x00026; Technological Economics</source>, <year>2020</year>,<volume>37</volume> (<issue>08</issue>): <fpage>140</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>158</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0293146.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Banglu</surname><given-names>He</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xiumin</surname><given-names>Wu</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rui</surname><given-names>Ji</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>. <article-title>Risk Avoidance VS Risk Preference: Does the Risk of Agricultural Investment in the Host Country Affect China&#x02019;s Foreign Agricultural Direct Investment?</article-title>[J]. <source>World Agriculture</source>,<year>2023</year> (<issue>09</issue>):<fpage>31</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>. <comment>doi: </comment><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.13856/j.cn11-1097/s.2023.09.003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0293146.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zhao Yongzhi,and Chen Yangfen."Global Patterns of Agricultural Investment and Food Security: Evidence from the fDi Markets Database." Foods (Basel, Switzerland) 12.9(2023).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0293146.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhi</surname><given-names>Li</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dongyang</surname><given-names>Wang</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhiquan</surname><given-names>Hu</given-names></name>. <article-title>The current situation, difficulties and countermeasures of Chinese agricultural enterprises&#x02019; "going global" under the "the Belt and Road" initiative</article-title> [J]. <source>Issues in Agricultural Economy</source>, <year>2020</year> (<issue>03</issue>): <fpage>93</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>101</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0293146.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jing</surname><given-names>Li</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wen</surname><given-names>Tian</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lingli</surname><given-names>Xiao</given-names></name>. <article-title>Spatial correlation and influencing factors of agricultural investment growth in China</article-title> [J]. <source>Statistics &#x00026; Decision</source>, <year>2020</year>,<volume>36</volume> (<issue>10</issue>): <fpage>59</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0293146.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Panna</surname><given-names>Jia</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Aimin</surname><given-names>Liu</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shengkui</surname><given-names>Cheng</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wenli</surname><given-names>Qiang</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liang</surname><given-names>Wu</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>Li</given-names></name>. <article-title>Changes in China&#x02019;s agricultural product trade pattern and strategies for overseas agricultural resource utilization</article-title> [J]. <source>Journal of Natural Resources</source>, <year>2019</year>,<volume>34</volume> (<issue>07</issue>): <fpage>1357</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1364</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0293146.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jie</surname><given-names>Zhao</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yangfen</surname><given-names>Chen</given-names></name>. <article-title>Mode Selection of Chinese Enterprises&#x02019; Investment in Central Asia&#x02019;s Agriculture&#x02014;Comparative Analysis Based on the "the Belt and Road" Investment Environment</article-title> [J]. <source>World Agriculture</source>, <year>2021</year> (<issue>09</issue>): <fpage>24</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>36</lpage>+<fpage>122</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>123</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0293146.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jie</surname><given-names>Zhao</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xiaoyu</surname><given-names>Jiang</given-names></name>, <article-title>Chen Yangfen Agricultural Investment Risk Assessment of the "the Belt and Road" and Its Implications for Agriculture&#x02019;s "Going Global"</article-title> [J].<source>Research of Agricultural Modernization</source>, <year>2020</year>,<volume>41</volume> (<issue>04</issue>): <fpage>599</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>607</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0293146.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Junjiang</surname><given-names>Li</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jiexi</surname><given-names>Zhu</given-names></name>. <article-title>Risk of countries along the "the Belt and Road", bilateral investment agreements and China&#x02019;s OFDI location choice: an empirical study based on PLS-PM and BP neural network models</article-title> [J]. <source>Journal of Harbin University of Commerce(Social Science Edition)</source>, <year>2022</year> (<issue>04</issue>): <fpage>3</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0293146.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zichen</surname><given-names>Xue</given-names></name>. <article-title>China&#x02019;s Agricultural Investment in Southeast Asia and Risk Prevention</article-title> [J]. <source>Contemporary International Relations</source>, <year>2022</year>, <volume>389</volume> (<issue>03</issue>): <fpage>17</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0293146.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zia</surname><given-names>ULLLAH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tan Xiao</surname><given-names>FEN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fayaz</surname><given-names>Hussain</given-names></name>, <name><surname>TUNIO</surname><given-names>Imran ULLAH</given-names></name>, <article-title>Impact of CO<sub>2</sub> Emissions, Exchange Rate Regimes, and Political Stability on Currency Crises: Evidence from South Asian Countries</article-title>, <source>Journal of Asian Finance, Economics and Business</source>, <year>2022</year>, <volume>Vol 9</volume>
<issue>No 2</issue>, <fpage>0029</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>0036</lpage></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
