<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="methods-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Public Health</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Public Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2296-2565</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38125843</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC10732307</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2023.1153149</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Public Health</subject><subj-group><subject>Study Protocol</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Developing Climate Change and Health Impact Monitoring with eHealth at the South East Asia Community Observatory and Health and Demographic Surveillance Site, Malaysia (CHIMES)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Barteit</surname><given-names>Sandra</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1711868/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Colmar</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2424023/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nellis</surname><given-names>Syahrul</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thu</surname><given-names>Min</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Watterson</surname><given-names>Jessica</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gouwanda</surname><given-names>Darwin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/234717/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x000e4;rnighausen</surname><given-names>Till</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff6" ref-type="aff">
<sup>6</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1438746/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Tin Tin</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/925765/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Heidelberg Institute of Global Health (HIGH), Faculty of Medicine and University Hospital, Heidelberg University</institution>, <addr-line>Heidelberg</addr-line>, <country>Germany</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>South East Asia Community Observatory (SEACO) and Global Public Health, Jeffrey Cheah School of Medicine and Health Sciences, Monash University Malaysia</institution>, <addr-line>Bandar Sunway</addr-line>, <country>Malaysia</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Jeffrey Cheah School of Medicine and Health Sciences, Monash University Malaysia</institution>, <addr-line>Bandar Sunway</addr-line>, <country>Malaysia</country></aff><aff id="aff4"><sup>4</sup><institution>School of Engineering (Mechanical), Monash University Malaysia</institution>, <addr-line>Bandar Sunway</addr-line>, <country>Malaysia</country></aff><aff id="aff5"><sup>5</sup><institution>Department of Global Health and Population, Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health</institution>, <addr-line>Boston</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><aff id="aff6"><sup>6</sup><institution>Harvard Center for Population and Development Studies, Harvard T.H. Chan School of Public Health</institution>, <addr-line>Cambridge, MA</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0002"><p>Edited by: Javier Prieto, University of Salamanca, Spain</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0003"><p>Reviewed by: Kirti Sundar Sahu, Canadian Red Cross, Canada; Paolo Tieri, National Research Council (CNR), Italy; Miran Taha, University of Sulaymaniyah, Iraq</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Sandra Barteit, <email>barteit@uni-heidelberg.de</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>01</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>1153149</elocation-id><history>
<date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>1</month><year>2023</year></date>
<date date-type="accepted"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date>
</history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2023 Barteit, Colmar, Nellis, Thu, Watterson, Gouwanda, B&#x000e4;rnighausen and Su.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Barteit, Colmar, Nellis, Thu, Watterson, Gouwanda, B&#x000e4;rnighausen and Su</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec id="sec1"><title>Background</title><p>Malaysia is projected to experience an increase in heat, rainfall, rainfall variability, dry spells, thunderstorms, and high winds due to climate change. This may lead to a rise in heat-related mortality, reduced nutritional security, and potential migration due to uninhabitable land. Currently, there is limited data regarding the health implications of climate change on the Malaysian populace, which hinders informed decision-making and interventions.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Objective</title><p>This study aims to assess the feasibility and reliability of using sensor-based devices to enhance climate change and health research within the SEACO health and demographic surveillance site (HDSS) in Malaysia. We will particularly focus on the effects of climate-sensitive diseases, emphasizing lung conditions like chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) and asthma.</p></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Methods</title><p>In our mixed-methods approach, 120 participants (&#x0003e;18&#x02009;years) from the SEACO HDSS in Segamat, Malaysia, will be engaged over three cycles, each lasting 3&#x02009;weeks. Participants will use wearables to monitor heart rate, activity, and sleep. Indoor sensors will measure temperature in indoor living spaces, while 3D-printed weather stations will track indoor temperature and humidity. In each cycle, a minimum of 10 participants at high risk for COPD or asthma will be identified. Through interviews and questionnaires, we will evaluate the devices&#x02019; reliability, the prevalence of climate-sensitive lung diseases, and their correlation with environmental factors, like heat and humidity.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Results</title><p>We anticipate that the sensor-based measurements will offer a comprehensive understanding of the interplay between climate-sensitive diseases and weather variables. The data is expected to reveal correlations between health impacts and weather exposures like heat. Participant feedback will offer perspectives on the usability and feasibility of these digital tools.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>Our study within the SEACO HDSS in Malaysia will evaluate the potential of sensor-based digital technologies in monitoring the interplay between climate change and health, particularly for climate-sensitive diseases like COPD and asthma. The data generated will likely provide details on health profiles in relation to weather exposures. Feedback will indicate the acceptability of these tools for broader health surveillance. As climate change continues to impact global health, evaluating the potential of such digital technologies is crucial to understand its potential to inform policy and intervention strategies in vulnerable regions.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>climate change</kwd><kwd>fitness trackers</kwd><kwd>wearables</kwd><kwd>weather stations</kwd><kwd>3D-print</kwd><kwd>global health</kwd><kwd>Malaysia</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>The study was funded by independent institutional resources available to Heidelberg Institute of Global Health and Monash University Malaysia.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="3"/><table-count count="4"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="78"/><page-count count="12"/><word-count count="9258"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Digital Public Health</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec6"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><sec id="sec7"><label>1.1</label><title>Malaysia and climate change-induced exposures</title><p>In recent decades, extreme weather events have become increasingly frequent and severe in Southeast Asia (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). According to the fourth Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) assessment report (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>), the mean surface air temperature in Southeast Asia has been rising for several decades, with a 0.1&#x02013;0.3&#x000b0;C increase in each decade between 1951 and 2000 (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). This includes more heat waves (hot days and nights and fewer cold days and nights), an increase in severe rainstorms, and an increase in tropical cyclones. In 2018, more than 12,000 Malaysians were displaced by floods in four states (Johor, Terengganu, Pahang, and Sabah); more recently, in 2021, over 50 people died in a flood in Selangor with nearly four meters of water, and over 400,000 people were evacuated (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). In Malaysia, heat-related mortality is anticipated to increase, along with an increase in vector-borne diseases (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Additionally, other forecasts indicate that under a 400&#x02013;800&#x02009;ppm level of CO<sub>2</sub>, rice yield could reduce by 4.6 to 6.1% for every 1&#x000b0;C increase in temperature (<xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). As agriculture is dependent on weather conditions, climate change is a significant concern (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Furthermore, coastal erosion and the loss of mangrove trees are directly attributable to the high waves caused by a rise in sea level, which are exacerbated by warmer sea temperatures that may impact fish livelihoods by causing more fish-threatening algal blooms and coral reef bleaching, thereby endangering small-scale as well as food security (<xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>).</p><p>In Malaysia, the health paradigm has transitioned from infectious to non-communicable diseases, including asthma, diabetes (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>), and other cardiometabolic and respiratory conditions (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>). Elevated temperatures have been consistently linked to adverse pulmonary outcomes (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>), yet their impact on climate-sensitive populations in Malaysia remains underexplored. D&#x02019;Amato et al. highlighted that increasing temperatures and associated heat stress can induce or intensify respiratory disease manifestations (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). Notably, heat-exacerbated respiratory conditions such as asthma and COPD appear to be prevalent in Malaysia (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>).</p><p>This transition is further complicated by the diverse challenges posed by climate change. At the same time, Malaysia is faced with an ageing population, particularly in rural regions. Older individuals often exhibit reduced heat resilience, especially when they have pre-existing conditions such as cardiovascular disorders (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). Furthermore, age-related cognitive decline or impairment may reduce behavioral adaptive capacity (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Specifically, rural Malaysian areas, characterized by lower socioeconomic status, substandard housing, and limited access to cooling devices like air conditioning, are particularly vulnerable (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Rural subdistricts in Malaysia exhibit a distinct demographic profile compared to the national average, largely due to prevalent rural-to-urban youth migration (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>).</p><p>Despite a global uptick in political and research efforts (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>), studies on climate change adaptation and mitigation remain limited in Malaysia (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>).</p><p>Empirical research on the health implications of climate change, as well as adaptation strategies and interventions for marginalized and rural communities, remains limited (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Adaptation to climate change is vital for climate-vulnerable populations in emerging economies to cope with rising average temperatures and extreme heat events caused by climate change.</p></sec><sec id="sec8"><label>1.2</label><title>South East Asia Community Observatory, Malaysia, as an ideal infrastructure for climate change and health research</title><p>Health and Demographic Surveillance Systems (HDSSs) are operational in more than 56 health cohorts throughout Africa and Asia, with some systems tracking population dynamics&#x02014;including births, deaths, and migrations&#x02014;for over six decades (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). The INDEPTH network streamlines HDSS implementation in LMICs. HDSS data has enabled a better understanding of infectious diseases, amongst others, such as malaria, HIV/AIDS, and tuberculosis, and the efficacy of interventions (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Especially in countries without comprehensive health systems, HDSSs provide crucial health data, capturing demographic and health trends (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>).</p><p>In 2011, Monash University Malaysia launched the South East Asia Community Observatory (SEACO HDSS) in Segamat, Johor&#x02019;s northernmost district. Operating within five semi-rural sub-districts&#x02014;Sungai Segamat, Chaah, Bekok, Gemereh, and Jabi&#x02014;this surveillance site spans around 1,250&#x02009;km<sup>2</sup>, encompassing nearly 13,000 households and approximately 40,000 individuals (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). The SEACO HDSS operates successful community engagement strategies including regular community consultation meetings. It has hosted numerous research studies on infectious diseases (dengue) (<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>), non-communicable diseases (diabetes, hypertension, stroke, multi-morbidity) (<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>, <xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>), as well as lifestyle and health behavior research (<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>) in order to assess the disease burden of the population.</p><p>With the Climate Change and Health Impact Monitoring with eHealth system (CHIMES) we will implement a system for the continuous monitoring of health and climate metrics within the SEACO HDSS, Malaysia, adopting modules from the Climate Change and Health Evaluation and Response System (CHEERS) (<xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>). This study centers on three tiers of data collection (individual, household, and community) using digital, sensor-based devices.</p><p>Our main objectives are as following:</p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>1. Establish and explore best approaches for sensor-based measurements for climate change and health research in the SEACO HDSS:</p></list-item><list-item><p>a. Establish acceptability of sensor-based devices.</p></list-item><list-item><p>b.Determine the reliability of sensor-based devices.</p></list-item><list-item><p>c. Evaluate long-term technical performance of sensor-based devices.</p></list-item><list-item><p>2. Assess the burden of climate-sensitive diseases in populations of the SEACO HDSS:</p></list-item></list><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>a. Establish the feasibility of measuring heat strain indicators: lung disease variables, heart rate, activity, sleep.</p></list-item><list-item><p>b. Determine adequacy and usefulness of lung disease measures as heat strain indicator.</p></list-item><list-item><p>c. Investigate the correlation between weather variables, especially temperature and humidity, and lung disease variables.</p></list-item></list></sec></sec><sec id="sec9"><label>2</label><title>Methods and analysis</title><sec id="sec10"><label>2.1</label><title>Study design</title><p>The study will employ a convergent mixed-methods approach (<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Both qualitative and quantitative data will be collected at the same time. Qualitative data will be gathered through semi-structured in-depth interviews (IDIs), providing insights into experiences and perceptions. Quantitative data is sourced from log system data, and Likert-scaled questionnaires, and structured activity diaries, offering measurable and statistical information. After the data collection phase, both sets of data are first analyzed separately. Subsequently, they are merged in the interpretation phase, where results from both data types are synthesized, compared, and contrasted. This process allows us to identify areas of convergence, where qualitative and quantitative findings align, as well as areas of divergence, where they might offer different perspectives or insights.</p></sec><sec id="sec11"><label>2.2</label><title>Study 1: feasibility and acceptability study for sensor-based measurements for climate change and health research (individual-, home-, and community-based sensors)</title><p>Employing the locally-hosted SurveyCTO platform (<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>), we will administer questionnaires to gather insights on participants&#x02019; usage and experiences with the Garmin vivosmart 5 wearable device (<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>), the SwitchBot Meter for indoor temperature and humidity measurements (<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>), and the 3D-printed weather stations (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). We will collect feedback from a group of SEACO HDSS stakeholders, which includes field supervisors, technical staff, and fieldworkers. In-depth interviews (IDIs) will also be conducted with key personnel from SEACO HDSS, such as the director, selected scientists, community representatives, and fieldworkers, to ensure a holistic understanding and comprehensive feedback. We anticipate data saturation for these stakeholder interviews based on the 10&#x02009;+&#x02009;3 criterion (<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>).</p><p>Quantitative data will be collected from routine device usage and their diagnostic logs to evaluate the reliability of these sensor-based tools. This data will be juxtaposed with fieldworker questionnaire responses. We will employ five metrics to evaluate device reliability: (i) failure rate of temperature sensors (how often do they fail to make a measurement?), (ii) replacement rate (how often do the sensors technically fail so they need to be fully replaced?), (iii) maximum battery-energy intervals (how often do the devices battery run out of power, especially under heat and humidity stress?), (iv) maximum data collection intervals (how often does data need to be synchronized?), and (v) failure rate of data synchronization (how frequently are data synchronization challenges that result in inaccurate or missing data encountered?).</p><p>Data obtained from 3D-printed weather stations will be validated by comparison with data from weather stations in the study area, managed by the Meteorological Service of Malaysia (<xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>), focusing on temperature, humidity and rainfall.</p></sec><sec id="sec12"><label>2.3</label><title>Study 2: burden of climate-sensitive diseases in climate-vulnerable semi-urban and rural populations in the SEACO HDSS</title><p>Within our mixed-methods approach, we will conduct an observational panel study to evaluate the feasibility and acceptance of digital spirometry measurements, focusing on lung diseases as potential indicators of heat strain. To identify individuals at an increased risk of lung disease symptoms, specifically chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) and asthma, we will utilize validated questionnaires, administered by fieldworkers using offline tablets, for initial population screening. Lung function assessments will be conducted in participants&#x02019; homes using hand-held, digital spirometers, specifically the Medical International Research (MIR) Spirobank Smart Spirometer. To further understand participants&#x02019; self-perceived health burden, we will administer weekly questionnaires comprising Likert-scaled, multiple-choice, and open-ended questions (the complete questionnaire is provided in the <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec13"><label>2.4</label><title>Study setting</title><p>The SEACO HDSS, located in Segamat, a district in the southern peninsular state of Johor, Malaysia, is managed by Monash University Malaysia and primarily funded by Monash University&#x02019;s Malaysian and Australian branches. Since 2011, SEACO HDSS has offered longitudinal data on socio-demographics, health, and population (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). The SEACO HDSS encompasses five of 11 sub-districts of Segamat with a total area of roughly 1,250&#x02009;km<sup>2</sup> (see <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>) and a population of around 40,000 individuals from different cultural and ethnic backgrounds. The demographic profile of SEACO HDSS reflects the ethnic composition of Malaysia: Malay (62.4%), Chinese (17.9%), Indian (9.5%), Orang Asli (2.2%), and other groups (<xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Overview of the SEACO HDSS located in the Segamat region, Malaysia, with its five sub-districts: Sungai (SG) Segamat, Gemereh, Chaah, Bekok, and Jabi.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpubh-11-1153149-g001" position="float"/></fig><p>While Malaysia generally experiences light, variable winds, there are four distinct seasons influenced by wind direction: the northeast monsoon, the southwest monsoon, and two inter-monsoon periods (<xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). The El Ni&#x000f1;o Southern Oscillation (ENSO) affects rainfall distribution, with El Ni&#x000f1;o years often being the hottest (<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). In 2019, the average temperature was 27.63&#x000b0;C, with peaks at around 33&#x000b0;C and lows at around 24&#x000b0;C (<xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>). Annual precipitation averages 3,085.5&#x02009;mm, ranging from 200&#x02009;mm in mid-year to 350&#x02009;mm towards year-end, with consistent levels year-round (<xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec14"><label>2.5</label><title>Study participants and recruitment</title><p>Eligible participants for this study are individuals aged 18 and above who reside within one of the five SEACO HDSS sub-districts. Our recruitment strategy will reflect the demographic composition of the Segamat District, taking into account age, and gender. The SEACO data manager will spearhead the identification of potential participants. Participation is entirely voluntary, and due to the study&#x02019;s data collection methods, it will not be anonymous. To ensure a diverse representation, only one member from each household will be selected. Before any study-related activities commence, participants must provide their written informed consent. If at any point a participant decides to withdraw or is lost to follow-up, their participation will be terminated without any repercussions.</p><p>Given the possibility of dropouts or refusals, we will adopt an oversampling approach. Our aim is to engage <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;100 participants for the three study cycles. However, factoring in an estimated refusal rate of 50%, we anticipate a final sample size of <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;120 participants. Each study cycle will be dedicated to a specific sub-district: Jabi, Chaah, or Sungai Segamat.</p><p>The study will span nine weeks. While participants might not derive direct benefits from their involvement, the insights gleaned from this research are expected to inform and shape broader initiatives that could benefit the larger community.</p></sec><sec id="sec15"><label>2.6</label><title>Sample size calculation</title><p>As the true problem probability is unknown in our study population, we will employ the methodology proposed by Viechtbauer et al. to determine the sample size, using a lower bound for the problem probability (<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). Specifically, we aim to be 95% confident in detecting any prevalent problem at 8% (probability 0.08), necessitating a sample size of <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;36 participants (refer to the online calculator for pilot study sample sizes (<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>)). Consequently, our study will comprise three cohorts of <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;40 participants each, with every cohort participating for a three-week duration.</p></sec><sec id="sec16"><label>2.7</label><title>Sensor-based devices (individual, home-, and community-based)</title><p>Data in this study is stored securely on encrypted, password-protected devices. Initial sensor data is saved on encrypted tablets used by fieldworkers. The SEACO HDSS, ensures encrypted data transfer to the German research team, complying with Monash University Malaysia&#x02019;s data protection standards. The study timeline, analysis, and results dissemination are detailed in <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Timeline of study stages.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Agenda Item</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="12" rowspan="1">Month</th></tr><tr><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Develop protocol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obtain ethical clearance</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Publish protocol paper</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conduct feasibility study<break/><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Setting up sensor-based measurements (individual, home-based, community-based)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Sensor-based data collection</p></list-item></list></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Data analysis</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Prepare and publish feasibility study manuscript</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Design full study based on feasibility study findings</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>SEACO HDSS data resides in PostgreSQL databases, structured according to the HDSS Reference Data Model, which includes individual, social group, and event data. The database administrator, guided by the HDSS steering committee, oversees data access and linkage. SEACO HDSS employs SurveyCTO for data collection and stores data on the ARCD Nectar Research Cloud (<xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>).</p><sec id="sec17"><label>2.7.1</label><title>Individual sensors</title><sec id="sec18"><label>2.7.1.1</label><title>Garmin VivoSmart 5 wearable device</title><p>The Garmin vivosmart 5 (see <xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> for details) is a wrist-worn wearable device (worn 24&#x02009;h per day by study participants). The data is synchronized with the field worker&#x02019;s tablet through Bluetooth, and the field worker visits the participant&#x02019;s home every 5&#x02013;7&#x02009;days. The wearable device stores up to 14&#x02009;days of data and has a 7-day battery life. The following variables will be collected:</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Overview of sensor-based devices (individual and home-based sensors) employed as part of this feasibility, acceptability, and reliability study.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Individual sensor</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Individual sensor</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Home-based sensor</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Image</td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-graphic xlink:href="fpubh-11-1153149-i001.jpg"/></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-graphic xlink:href="fpubh-11-1153149-i002.jpg"/></td><td align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<inline-graphic xlink:href="fpubh-11-1153149-i003.jpg"/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensor name and type</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Garmin vivosmart 5</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MIR Spirobank Smart Oxi Spirometer</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SwitchBot Meter</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Measurements</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Heart Rate (beats per minute)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Activity Time (in steps)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Sleep Time (hours)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Blood Oxygen Saturation (SpO2)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Max. volume of oxygen (VO2)</p></list-item></list></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lung capacity variables:<break/><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Functional Vital Capacity (FVC)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Forced Expiratory Volume in 1&#x02009;s (FEV<sub>1</sub>)</p></list-item><list-item><p>FEV1% (Predicted Forced Expiratory Volume in 1&#x02009;s)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Peak Expiratory Flow Rate</p></list-item><list-item><p>Forced Expiratory Flow, average between 25 and 75% of expiration</p></list-item><list-item><p>Forced Expiratory Time</p></list-item></list></td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Ambient Air Temperature (degrees Celsius)</p></list-item><list-item><p>Relative Air Humidity (%)</p></list-item></list></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>daily activity (measured as steps, distance, calories; measured with an accelerometer sensor based on amplitude and periodic pattern)</p></list-item><list-item><p>heart rate (routinely measured every 10&#x02009;min with a photoplethysmography sensor; heart rate measured every 1&#x02009;s only in workout mode (manually enabled) or after 2&#x02009;min of running)</p></list-item><list-item><p>sleep (wearable automatically detects sleep and monitors movement during sleep; sleep data include total hours of sleep, sleep stages, sleep movement, and sleep score)</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="sec19"><label>2.7.1.2</label><title>Spirobank smart spirometer</title><p>The MIR Spirobank Smart spirometer uses a flow sensor (bi-directional digital turbine) to assess a number of lung function parameters in individuals (see <xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The tablet-based application (app), which shows the test quality and results of the spirometer test in real-time, receives the measured lung function parameters through Bluetooth. Individual participant data can also be exported in PDF or CSV format. The production company suggests the operating conditions suitable between 5 and 40&#x000b0;C, and humidity of 10&#x02013;93% Relative Humidity (RH).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec20"><label>2.7.2</label><title>Home-based sensor: SwitchBot meter</title><p>The SwitchBot Meter is a smart, consumer-grade indoor sensor that measures the ambient air temperature (&#x000b0;C) and relative humidity (see <xref rid="tab2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The sensor is mounted to the participant&#x02019;s living room wall or ceiling. The SwitchBot Meter samples data every 4&#x02009;s, saves up to 5&#x02009;weeks collected data, and the batteries (removable) are estimated to last around 1&#x02009;year. The production company specifies the temperature accuracy as +/&#x02212; 0.7&#x000b0;F, the humidity accuracy as +/&#x02212; 4% RH, and the working environment as &#x02212;10 to 60&#x000b0;C and 20&#x02013;85% RH.</p></sec><sec id="sec21"><label>2.7.3</label><title>Community-based sensor: 3D-printed weather stations</title><p>Weather stations will be 3D-printed in alignment with the guidelines and validated blueprints provided by the 3D-Printed Automatic Weather Station (3D-PAWS) initiative (<xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). The designed weather station is equipped to measure parameters such as wind speed, wind direction, rainfall, air temperature, relative humidity, solar radiation, and air pressure. A solar panel, requiring a 5 Volt input, powers the station. Components essential for the construction of these stations are procurable from local hardware vendors in Malaysia. For the 3D-printing process, we will employ the Prusa MINI+ 3D-printer, augmented with a Bond Tec dual extruder to enhance the precision of Acrylic Styrene Acrylonitrile (ASA) printing (refer to <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref> for details).</p><fig position="float" id="fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Test 3D-printed parts of the weather station (anemometer, wind vane, weather radiation shield). Image on left hand side shows the 3D-printed parts (in white), on the right-hand side shows the solar radiation shield (printed in black as a test print) on the build platform of the Prusa MINI+ 3D-printer.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpubh-11-1153149-g002" position="float"/></fig><p>ASA filament is known for its UV resistance and ability to withstand high temperatures up to 93&#x000b0;C (<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). However, it can experience warping due to rapid cooling of filament layers (<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). Additionally, ASA emits fumes during printing, necessitating well-ventilated ambient conditions (<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). To counter these issues, we use a flame-resistant pressboard enclosure for the 3D-printer (see <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>) to maintain stable internal temperatures and reduce fume exposure. Given ASA&#x02019;s tendency to absorb moisture, a filament dryer is also utilized to prevent moisture-related printing anomalies.</p><fig position="float" id="fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Ventilated, portable enclosure constructed from flame-resistant pressboard for the 3D-printer as seen from the front (left image), the padded view showing the ventilator (middle image), and the provision for the filament spool and power cord (right image).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpubh-11-1153149-g003" position="float"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="sec22"><label>2.8</label><title>Study proceedings</title><sec id="sec23"><label>2.8.1</label><title>Evaluating the feasibility, acceptability and validity of individual- and home-based sensors as routine measurements and to measure effects of heat stress</title><p>In this study, field staff will receive a 2-day training on using sensor-based devices, administering questionnaires, understanding study goals, and following safety protocols.</p><p>Our team will consist of 4&#x02013;6 fieldworkers collecting data over three weeks in selected sub-study regions: Jabi, Chaah, and Segamat. These regions capture the study population&#x02019;s diversity. Fieldworkers, selected based on experience, area familiarity, and training, ensure data consistency.</p><p>At each cycle&#x02019;s start, fieldworkers gather participant details, measure height and weight, and administer a pre-screening questionnaire for potential lung diseases, including COPD and asthma [COPD questionnaire: incorporates the population-based screening questionnaire &#x0201c;Could it be COPD?&#x0201d; (<xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>) which was adopted from the Global Initiative for Chronic Obstructive Lung Disease consisting out of five question items; asthma questionnaire: incorporates the symptom-based questionnaire for predicting the presence of asthma questionnaire (Asthma Screening Questionnaire (ASQ) consisting out of six question items (<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>), refer to <xref rid="tab3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>)]. If the lung disease questionnaire outcome shows a high likelihood of study participants&#x02019; having a lung disease with a device cutoff ratio of &#x0003c;74% (0.74) forced expiratory volume in 1&#x02009;s to forced vital capacity ratios [FEV<sub>1</sub>/FVC; ideal cutoff based on a population-health study conducted in Taiwan with the same spirometer device (<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>)], the field worker conducts a spirometry assessment with those study participants. We measure with the spirometer forced expiratory volume in 1&#x02009;s to forced vital capacity ratios (FEV<sub>1</sub>/FVC) to identify lung airflow restrictions.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>At the time of baseline data collection, screening questionnaires for chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) and asthma are administered to determine the likelihood that study participants have COPD or asthma.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Questionnaire: Could it be COPD</th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Question item</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Response options</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Do you cough several times most days?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Yes</p></list-item><list-item><p>No</p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Do you bring up phlegm or mucus most days?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Yes</p></list-item><list-item><p>No</p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Do you get out of breath more easily than others your age?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Yes</p></list-item><list-item><p>No</p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Are you older than 40&#x02009;years?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Yes</p></list-item><list-item><p>No</p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Are you a current smoker or an ex-smoker?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Yes</p></list-item><list-item><p>No</p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Asthma Screening Questionnaire (ASQ)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Question item</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Response options</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Do you cough more than the average person?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Yes</p></list-item><list-item><p>No</p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Do you have a cough that comes mainly from your chest and NOT from your throat?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Yes</p></list-item><list-item><p>No</p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Do you have worsening of the following symptoms when you lie down to sleep?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Yes</p></list-item><list-item><p>No</p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Do you have worsening of the following symptoms after exercise or physical activity?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Yes</p></list-item><list-item><p>No</p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Do you have worsening of the following symptoms after laughing or crying?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Yes</p></list-item><list-item><p>No</p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Do you have worsening of the following symptoms after talking on the phone?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Yes</p></list-item><list-item><p>No</p></list-item></list></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Fieldworkers visit weekly to administer questionnaires, gather daily activity data, and check devices.</p><p>After the 21-day study, devices are collected, deregistered, cleaned, and data synchronized. Post the nine-week study, in-depth interviews (IDIs) are conducted with fieldworkers, participants, and SEACO HDSS stakeholders to gather feedback on the devices (refer to <xref rid="sec41" ref-type="sec">Supplemenatry material</xref>, questionnaire CHIMES).</p></sec><sec id="sec24"><label>2.8.2</label><title>Feasibility, acceptability, and reliability of community-based, 3D-printed weather stations in the semi-rural context of the SEACO HDSS</title><p>Within the SEACO HDSS, we will install two 3D-printed weather stations. Over a nine-week duration, a field worker will conduct weekly visual inspections of the weather station and its immediate environment, subsequently filling out a structured questionnaire to record the station&#x02019;s condition (refer to <xref rid="tab4" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>). The data gathered from the 3D-printed weather stations will be cross-referenced with measurements from the closest meteorological station operated by the Malaysian meteorological service.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Structured questionnaire for evaluating 3D-printed weather stations in the SEACO HDSS.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" colspan="2" rowspan="1">3D-printed weather station structured questionnaire</th></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Question item</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Response</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Date of inspection.</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Input of current date.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Location of weather station.</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Input of GPS coordinates of weather station location.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Please take pictures of the weather station and surroundings.</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Taking pictures with tablet of weather station surroundings.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Have you noticed any visible damages when inspecting the weather station?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Yes</p></list-item><list-item><p>No</p></list-item></list></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Please describe in detail the damages of the weather station</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Written text typed in tablet.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">What have people said about the weather station?</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Written text typed in tablet.</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Note down any other comments regarding the weather station.</td><td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Written text typed in tablet.</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="sec25"><label>2.9</label><title>Data analysis</title><p>Upon completion of data collection, both quantitative and qualitative results will be merged and analyzed to discern any convergence or divergence. Questionnaire data will undergo cleaning, categorization, and thematic analysis. All other statistical analyses will be conducted using the R software. The normality of the data will be assessed using the Shapiro&#x02013;Wilk test. The Welch-t test will be employed to compare participants based on gender and study arm. Analyses will further categorize participants by gender, socio-economic status, age, and lung status. For error estimation, 95% confidence intervals (CIs) will be reported.</p><sec id="sec26"><label>2.9.1</label><title>Feasibility of sensor-based devices (individual, household-, and community-based)</title><sec id="sec27"><label>2.9.1.1</label><title>Reliability</title><p>We will monitor reliability of sensor-based devices using five key performance indicators: (i) failure rate, (ii) replacement rate, (iii) maximum battery-energy intervals, (iv) maximum data downloading intervals and (v) failure rate of data synchronization.</p><p>The cumulative instances when data was not collected will serve as a measure of reliability. Established metrics, such as the intra-cluster correlation coefficient (ICC) and the Bland&#x02013;Altman plot (<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>), will be employed to further evaluate the reliability of the sensor-based devices.</p></sec><sec id="sec28"><label>2.9.1.2</label><title>Data validity</title><p>We will descriptively present data on sleep duration, day- and nighttime heart rate, calorie consumption, activity, spirometer and indoor temperature and humidity. A threshold of &#x02265;20&#x02009;h of measurements per day will be set for step count and calorie consumption to be considered valid (<xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>). Indoor temperatures and humidity levels will be compared with outdoor temperatures and humidity levels, and we will compute the standard error of the mean (SEM), root mean square error (RMSE), average difference, and the minimum and maximum values.</p><p>For the validation of the 3D-printed weather stations, we will obtain data from verified weather stations under the Malaysian Meteorological Department located near our 3D-printed stations. A comparative analysis will be conducted to ascertain the validity and reliability of the measurements from the 3D-printed stations (<xref rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>). Metrics such as SEM, RMSE, average difference, minimum and maximum values will be computed, and a monthly breakdown of RMSE and correlation coefficients will be provided for the entire deployment duration of the weather station.</p></sec><sec id="sec29"><label>2.9.1.3</label><title>Data completeness</title><p>Completeness of the data will be evaluated based on the consistency of measurements during predetermined intervals (<xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>). To determine the validity of the data from sensor-based devices, specific criteria will be set for each sensor, drawing from prior research and best practices (<xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>, <xref rid="ref56" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>). As highlighted by Huhn et al. (<xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>), we will consider the manufacturer-specified measurement interval for non-continuously monitoring sensors, amplified by a factor of 1.5 (<xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec30"><label>2.9.1.4</label><title>Data usability</title><p>We will descriptively analyze the weather characteristics captured by the 3D-printed weather stations. This includes assessing the occurrence of severe weather events, focusing on rainfall and heat events, and their potential impact on the health of participants, as measured by the wearable device and spirometer. For defining weather extremes, we will utilize the indices provided by the Expert Team on Climate Change Detection and Indices (ETCCDI) (<xref rid="ref58" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>). Our analysis will encompass mean and min-max daily temperatures, as well as average and maximum daily wet bulb globe temperature (WBGT). We will also correlate sleep duration and night time heart rate with minimum night time temperature and the heat index, and step count with heavy rainfall events.</p><p>We will employ a linear mixed-effects model to explore the relationship between weather exposures and daily metrics like activity (steps), sleep, and nighttime heart rate. Covariates in the model will include the minimum nighttime heat index for sleep and nighttime HR, the maximum daytime WBGT for daily activities (steps), daily precipitation, type of day (weekend or workday), age group, gender, and body mass index (BMI) group of the participant. Additionally, we will investigate if patterns identified from the wearable device align with the self-reported activities of the participants.</p><p>We will also correlate lung function values, as determined by the spirometer at three distinct times for each cohort. This includes activity levels, sleep patterns, heart rate, and both indoor and outdoor temperature and humidity measurements, as well as the self-perceived burden of disease.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec31"><label>2.9.2</label><title>Acceptability of sensor-based devices</title><p>We will analyze both qualitative (derived from IDIs, open-ended questions, and feedback sessions with stakeholders and field workers) and quantitative data (from Likert-scaled and other structured questionnaire items of the acceptability questionnaire, as well as sensor-based log data). This convergent approach seeks to offer a holistic understanding of the collected data. Descriptive analysis will be applied to responses from Likert-scaled and other structured questionnaire items. For open-ended questions, a thematic coding approach will be employed (<xref rid="ref59" ref-type="bibr">59&#x02013;61</xref>). Our analysis will adhere to the steps of &#x0201c;compiling, disassembling, reassembling, interpreting, and concluding&#x0201d; as outlined by (<xref rid="ref62" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec32"><label>2.9.3</label><title>Feasibility of measuring the effects of heat stress</title><p>We will employ a two-way fixed effects regression (TWFE) to explore the relationships between weather-related variables, specifically heat and humidity, and lung function. Additionally, we will juxtapose these relationships with the correlations between weather-related variables and other indicators of heat stress, such as activity, sleep, and heart rate. By incorporating individual-level fixed effects, we aim to account for both observed and unobserved time-invariant individual confounders. Meanwhile, calendar time fixed effects, our &#x02018;second method&#x02019; of fixed effects, will adjust for temporal changes shared across all study participants (<xref rid="ref63" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>, <xref rid="ref64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>). Recognizing that the impact of climate variables on lung function and other heat strain measures might differ, we will leverage recent advancements in TWFE analysis that yield unbiased estimates even amidst heterogeneous effect sizes (<xref rid="ref65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>, <xref rid="ref66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>). For this analysis, we will utilize the DIDmultiplegt package in R (<xref rid="ref67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec33"><label>2.10</label><title>Ethical considerations</title><p>The Heidelberg University Hospital Ethics Committee and MONASH University Ethics Committee granted ethical approval for this study in January 2023.</p><p>For details on informed consent, please refer to <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material 2</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec34"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><p>We aim to establish the feasibility, reliability and validity of the sensor-based devices used within the SEACO HDSS. Metrics, including failure rate and data synchronization, will offer insight into the devices&#x02019; operational performance. By comparing data from 3D-printed weather stations with data of the Malaysian Meteorological Department, we seek to validate the accuracy and consistency of the weather measurements.</p><p>Our two-way fixed effects regression is anticipated to identify correlations between specific weather variables, including temperature and humidity, and lung function. Additionally, we anticipate to determine correlations between these weather variables and various measures of individual heat strain, such as activity levels, sleep patterns, and heart rate, which will provide insights into the direct and indirect impacts of weather variables on health outcomes.</p><p>Employing a mixed-methods approach, we expect to obtain qualitative data from participants, which will offer insights into experiences and perceptions regarding sensor-based devices. This feedback will be pivotal in guiding the optimal use of such devices at both individual and homebased levels, and refining the study design to leverage the wearable and indoor temperature and humidity measurement for future research for broader climate-health studies in larger populations.</p><p>With our data collection protocols and the digital devices employed, we expect a high degree of data completeness. Any gaps or inconsistencies in the data will be valuable in identifying areas for improvement in data collection methodologies.</p><p>Given the diverse demographic and cultural composition of the SEACO HDSS population, we anticipate diverse insights on how different subgroups perceive and experience the effects of heat. Such findings will be crucial for tailoring interventions and policies to meet specific community needs.</p><p>In conclusion, this study aims to delineate the potential of sensor-based technologies in capturing granular data that elucidates the nexus between weather variables and individual health impacts within the SEACO HDSS community. The outcomes will not only enrich the scientific discourse but also have potential implications for shaping public health strategies and interventions.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec35"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p>In our study, we aim to identify optimal methods for integrating advanced data generation tools to enhance data granularity in climate change and health research, utilizing state-of-the-art sensor-based devices. We will also evaluate how such monitoring can seamlessly fit into the routine data collection of health and demographic surveillance sites. These devices will range from individual wearables tracking activity, sleep, heart rate, and lung function, to home-based instruments measuring indoor temperatures and humidity, and up to community-focused sensors like 3D-printed weather stations. A key objective will be to determine the prevalence of lung diseases sensitive and to understand impacts of heat, within the population.</p><p>Health and Demographic Surveillance Systems (HDSSs) are invaluable tools for research at the intersection of climate change and health. These systems provide a robust framework, collecting detailed data across large populations over extended durations. In over 56 Low- and Middle-Income Countries (LMICs) spanning Africa, Asia, and Oceania, HDSSs bridge the gap in population-health data, playing a crucial role in evidence-based decision-making (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="ref68" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>). Significantly, many of these LMICs with HDSSs bear the brunt of climate change impacts (<xref rid="ref69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>).</p><p>By enhancing the SEACO HDSS with additional climate metrics and health indicators, both self-reported and measured, we will likely be able to delve deeper into individual behaviors and exposures in their domestic and wider environments, supported by data from 3D-printed weather stations. This detailed data integration will elucidate individual exposures and their health implications, setting the stage for tailored population-level health interventions. Such a comprehensive dataset will likely offer a holistic view of health against the backdrop of climate change, deepening our grasp of the complex interplay between weather exposures and health outcomes.</p><p>The increasing frequency of severe and extreme weather events, driven by climate change, poses direct and indirect threats to human health, such as heat exposures and disruptions in food supply (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="ref69" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>). Integrating sensor-based measurements into existing HDSSs offers a promising avenue for individual-level research, with the potential for scalability to encompass broader populations (<xref rid="ref70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>). In even resource-constrained environments, consumer-grade wearables can deliver detailed individual data, capturing metrics like activity, sleep, and vital signs (<xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>). This continuous monitoring provides a detailed view of population movement and related exposures, such as heat, especially pertinent given the projected decrease in work capacity due to climate-related exposures (<xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>). Analyzing correlations between wearable data and weather exposures can yield novel insights into the ongoing and long-term health impacts of climate change. Remote sensing techniques can enhance this approach by offering deeper insights, such as household crop yields, which can be correlated with individual data collected via wearables to understand more complex impacts on work capacity and nutritional outcomes. This method, leveraging satellite imagery, vegetation indices, and weather station data, may enhance our comprehension of nutritional security (<xref rid="ref71" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>, <xref rid="ref72" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>).</p><p>Wearable devices have been effectively utilized in large-scale research to evaluate the health impacts of weather exposures related to climate change (<xref rid="ref73" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>). Most existing studies predominantly target high-income countries, often neglecting populations already affected by climate-sensitive diseases, as underscored by Huhn et al. (<xref rid="ref74" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>). Extreme heat poses risks in rural areas where residents often have limited financial resources, reside in inadequate housing, and lack air conditioning. The growing population of older adults is especially vulnerable due to common co-morbidities like cardiovascular diseases, reducing their heat resilience. Understanding the indoor exposures to heat and humidity, especially nighttime temperatures that influence sleep, is vital (<xref rid="ref75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>). Obradovich et al. highlighted that sleep disruptions from climate-driven nocturnal heat have pronounced physiological and psychological effects, especially on economically disadvantaged and older populations (<xref rid="ref75" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>).</p><p>We aim to evaluate the feasibility of incorporating lung function evaluations into population health data collection. The burden of noncommunicable diseases (NCDs) seems to rise in the context of increased exposure to heat in many contexts, yet research remains limited in contexts, like Malaysia. However, there is limited research on the climate-related effects on NCDs, especially respiratory conditions like asthma and COPD, within the Malaysian context (<xref rid="ref76" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>). The Spirobank spirometer, which we will use in our study, has received validation in several studies (<xref rid="ref77" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>), including its effectiveness in early COPD detection (<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). Lin et al. effectively employed the Spirobank spirometer to detect undiagnosed COPD cases within high-risk groups in Taiwan (<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>). This portable spirometer, integrated with an app, has been pivotal in identifying undiagnosed COPD in at-risk individuals (<xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>).</p><p>3D-printed weather stations, priced at approximately $1,000 per unit, may offer a cost-effective alternative to professional weather stations, which can cost around $10,000 and often have to be imported. Professional weather stations not only come with high initial costs but also pose long-term maintenance challenges, especially in countries where spare parts are hard to come by. Additionally, there is the ever-present risk of these parts becoming obsolete. 3D-printed weather stations allow for local printing of replacement parts, promoting durability and sustainability. The capability to print multiple stations with a single 3D printer further cuts down on costs and fosters local ownership, as these stations can be printed and assembled on-site. The affordability and sustainability of 3D-printed weather stations might make them a compelling choice for enhancing HDSSs or similar research infrastructures. This could lead to a more extensive network of weather stations, yielding finer-grained weather data. Such detailed data is pivotal for climate change and health research, as well as for programs like weather index-based crop insurance, designed to alleviate the challenges farmers face from erratic weather patterns (<xref rid="ref78" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>). Collecting detailed health and climate data to inform interventions is crucial. Our study aims to bolster this effort by generating robust climate and health data, enhancing the attractiveness of existing HDSSs for potential research funding.</p><p>We chose sensor-based devices, including wearables, spirometers, and home-based sensors, prioritizing a balance between quality and affordability. This approach ensures data reliability while considering scalability to encompass larger populations. Ease of data collection was also a primary factor in our selection. The devices we opted for, equipped with user-friendly interfaces and Bluetooth capabilities, streamline the data collection process. Our decision to use the Garmin wearable sensor was informed by its proven efficacy in population health studies in Burkina Faso and Kenya, as highlighted by Barteit et al. (<xref rid="ref70" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>). The integration of the spirometer and home sensors was cost-effective and validated by their application in similar research settings.</p></sec><sec id="sec36"><label>5</label><title>Limitations</title><p>This study primarily serves as a feasibility assessment with a relatively small cohort of <italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;120 participants. Such a limited sample size inherently limits the generalizability of our findings and the depth of insights for broader investigations. Furthermore, potential inaccuracies in sensor-based measurements should be acknowledged. Heart rate measurements might be affected by individual physiological variations, device fit, and the type and intensity of physical activity.</p><p>It is essential to highlight that the devices used in this study, including the spirometer and the wearable device (measuring lung function, heart rate, steps and sleep), are intended for recreational rather than medical purposes. They are not certified for diagnosing, monitoring, treating, or alleviating any medical condition or disease. Additionally, extended wear of the device might lead to skin discomfort, particularly for those with sensitive skin or allergies.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ethics-statement" id="sec37"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>The studies involving humans were approved by Heidelberg University Hospital Ethics Committee and Monash University Malaysia. The studies were conducted in accordance with the local legislation and institutional requirements. Written informed consent for participation in this study was provided by the participants&#x02019; legal guardians/next of kin. Written informed consent was obtained from the individual(s) for the publication of any potentially identifiable images or data included in this article.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="sec38"><title>Author contributions</title><p>SB wrote the first draft of the study protocol with the assistance of DC. The initial study design was developed by TB, TS, and SB. SN, MT, DG, and DC contributed to the development of the detailed study design. Data collection and local study management are locally managed and conducted by SN, MT, TS, and DG supervised by TS. The acquired data will be statistically analyzed by SN, MT, and SB. All authors contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><title>Abbreviations</title><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>3D-PAWS, 3D-Printed Automatic Weather Station; ASA, Acrylic Styrene Acrylonitrile; CHIMES, Climate Change and Health Impact Monitoring through eHealth at the South East Asia Community Observatory and Health and Demographic Surveillance Site, Malaysia; COPD, Chronic obstructive pulmonary disease; ENSO, El Ni&#x000f1;o Southern Oscillation; FEV<sub>1</sub>, Forced expiratory volume in 1 s; FVC, Forced vital capacity; HDSS, Health and demographic surveillance site; IDIs, In-depth interviews; IPCC, Intergovernmental panel on climate change; LMICs, Low- and middle-income countries; RH, Relative humidity; SEACO, South East Asia Community Observatory; TWFE, Two-way fixed effects regressions.</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec40"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="sec100"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec41"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>The Supplementary material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpubh.2023.1153149/full#supplementary-material" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpubh.2023.1153149/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material id="SM1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.PDF"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM2" position="float" content-type="local-data"><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_2.PDF"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM3" position="float" content-type="local-data"><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_3.PDF"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Drought under global warming: a review</article-title>. <source>Wiley Interdiscip Rev Clim Chang</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>45</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>65</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/wcc.81</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X-X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Heat wave trends in Southeast Asia during 1979&#x02013;2018: the impact of humidity</article-title>. <source>Sci Total Environ</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>721</volume>:<fpage>137664</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.137664</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32182463</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pachauri</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reisinger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2007</year>). IPCC fourth assessment report. IPCC Geneva 2007.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bank</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2009</year>). The economics of climate change in Southeast Asia: A regional review. Asian Development Bank; Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.adb.org/publications/economics-climate-change-southeast-asia-regional-review" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.adb.org/publications/economics-climate-change-southeast-asia-regional-review</ext-link> [Accessed May 26, 2022]</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>KHD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Climate change in Malaysia: trends, contributors, impacts, mitigation and adaptations</article-title>. <source>Sci Total Environ</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>650</volume>:<fpage>1858</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.09.316</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30290336</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2022</year>). Malaysia&#x02019;s floods of December 2021: can future disasters be avoided? ISEAS - Yusof Ishak Inst Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.iseas.edu.sg/articles-commentaries/iseas-perspective/2022-26-malaysias-floods-of-december-2021-can-future-disasters-be-avoided-by-serina-rahman/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.iseas.edu.sg/articles-commentaries/iseas-perspective/2022-26-malaysias-floods-of-december-2021-can-future-disasters-be-avoided-by-serina-rahman/</ext-link> [Accessed December 9, 2022]</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll1">The World Bank Group and the Asian, Development Bank, World Bank</collab></person-group>. (<year>2021</year>). Climate risk country profile Malaysia. Asian Development Bank; Available from: <ext-link xlink:href="https://climateknowledgeportal.worldbank.org/sites/default/files/2021-08/15868-WB_Malaysia%20Country%20Profile-WEB.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://climateknowledgeportal.worldbank.org/sites/default/files/2021-08/15868-WB_Malaysia%20Country%20Profile-WEB.pdf</ext-link> [Accessed November 3, 2023].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Al-Amin</surname><given-names>AQ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Filho</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>An overview of prospects and challenges in the field of climate change in Malaysia</article-title>. <source>Int J Glob Warm</source>. (<year>2011</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>390</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>402</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1504/IJGW.2011.044402</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shaffril</surname><given-names>HAM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abu Samah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>D&#x02019;Silva</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Adapting towards climate change impacts: strategies for small-scale fishermen in Malaysia</article-title>. <source>Mar Policy</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>81</volume>:<fpage>196</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>201</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.marpol.2017.03.032</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>YY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Teh</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yeo</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kee</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Lifestyle, chronic diseases and self-rated health among Malaysian adults: results from the 2011 National Health and morbidity survey (NHMS)</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>754</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-015-2080-z</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26246019</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdul-Razak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Azzopardi</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Patton</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mokdad</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sawyer</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Child and adolescent mortality across Malaysia&#x02019;s epidemiological transition: a systematic analysis of global burden of disease data</article-title>. <source>J Adolesc Health</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>61</volume>:<fpage>424</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jadohealth.2017.05.014</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28838752</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noor</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Megat Muzafar</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Romadan Khalidi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2022</year>). Health of the nation: Measuring burden of disease. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.krinstitute.org/Working_Paper-@-Health_of_the_Nation-;_Measuring_Burden_of_Disease.aspx" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.krinstitute.org/Working_Paper-@-Health_of_the_Nation-;_Measuring_Burden_of_Disease.aspx</ext-link> [Accessed November 29, 2022]</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Folinsbee</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Horvath</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Raven</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bedi</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Drinkwater</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Influence of exercise and heat stress on pulmonary function during ozone exposure</article-title>. <source>J Appl Physiol</source>. (<year>1977</year>) <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>409</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/jappl.1977.43.3.409</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">914710</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kahle</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Neas</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Devlin</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Case</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schmitt</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Madden</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Interaction effects of temperature and ozone on lung function and markers of systemic inflammation, coagulation, and fibrinolysis: a crossover study of healthy young volunteers</article-title>. <source>Environ Health Perspect NLM-Export</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>123</volume>:<fpage>310</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1289/ehp.1307986</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25514459</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>D&#x02019;Amato</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cecchi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>D&#x02019;Amato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Annesi-Maesano</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Climate change and respiratory diseases</article-title>. <source>Eur Respiratory Soc</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>161</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1183/09059180.00001714</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vos</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abbafati</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abbas</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abbasi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abbasifard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Global burden of 369 diseases and injuries in 204 countries and territories, 1990&#x02013;2019: a systematic analysis for the global burden of disease study 2019</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>396</volume>:<fpage>1204</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30925-9</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33069326</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hairi</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bulgiba</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cumming</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Naganathan</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mudla</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence and correlates of physical disability and functional limitation among community dwelling older people in rural Malaysia, a middle income country</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>492</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2458-10-492</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20716377</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bunker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wildenhain</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Vandenbergh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Henschke</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rockl&#x000f6;v</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hajat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effects of air temperature on climate-sensitive mortality and morbidity outcomes in the elderly; a systematic review and Meta-analysis of epidemiological evidence</article-title>. <source>EBioMedicine</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>258</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>68</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ebiom.2016.02.034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27211569</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raichlen</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Adaptive capacity: an evolutionary neuroscience model linking exercise, cognition, and brain health</article-title>. <source>Trends Neurosci</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>408</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tins.2017.05.001</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28610948</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thangiah</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Said</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Majid</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reidpath</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Income inequality in quality of life among rural communities in Malaysia: a Case for immediate policy consideration</article-title>. <source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>17</volume>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph17238731</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33255397</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rongen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>ZA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lanjouw</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Simler</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2021</year>). Trends in Malaysian poverty and income dynamics: Do regional inequalities trump ethnic disparities? Mimeo. Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sinha</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kautish</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Examining the impacts of economic and demographic aspects on the ecological footprint in south and southeast Asian countries</article-title>. <source>Environ Sci Pollut Res</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>36970</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>82</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11356-020-09659-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watts</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Amann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Arnell</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ayeb-Karlsson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Beagley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Belesova</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The 2020 report of the lancet countdown on health and climate change: responding to converging crises</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>397</volume>:<fpage>129</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(20)32290-X</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33278353</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hashim</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hashim</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Climate change, extreme weather events, and human health implications in the Asia Pacific region</article-title>. <source>Asia Pac J Public Health</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>28</volume>:<fpage>8S</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14S</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1010539515599030</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herbst</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Juvekar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jasseh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Berhane</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chuc</surname><given-names>NTK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Seeley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Health and demographic surveillance systems in low-and middle-income countries: history, state of the art and future prospects</article-title>. <source>Glob Health Action</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>1974676</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/16549716.2021.1974676</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35377288</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sankoh</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Byass</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The INDEPTH network: filling vital gaps in global epidemiology</article-title>. <source>Int J Epidemiol</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>41</volume>:<fpage>579</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>88</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/dys081</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22798690</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Partap</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Allotey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Soyiri</surname><given-names>IN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jahan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Komahan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>HDSS profile: the South East Asia community observatory health and demographic surveillance system (SEACO HDSS)</article-title>. <source>Int J Epidemiol</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>1370</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1371g</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/dyx113</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29024948</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jahan</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dhanoa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ming</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Reidpath</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A community-based prospective cohort study of dengue viral infection in Malaysia: the study protocol</article-title>. <source>Infect Dis Poverty</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>5</volume>:<fpage>76</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40249-016-0172-3</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27510731</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reidpath</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Allotey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The burden is great and the money little: changing chronic disease management in low&#x02013;and middle&#x02013;income countries</article-title>. <source>JOGH</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>2</volume>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7189/jogh.02.020301</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pell</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Allotey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hardon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Imelda</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Soyiri</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Coming of age, becoming obese: a cross-sectional analysis of obesity among adolescents and young adults in Malaysia</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health BioMed Central</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-016-3746-x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salway</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>TT</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Glynis Armstrong</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The impact of COVID-19 movement restrictions on physical activity in a low-income semi-rural population in Malaysia: a longitudinal study</article-title>. <source>J Glob Health</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>05029</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7189/jogh.11.05029</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35003716</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McGrattan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mohan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hussin</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Soh</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Alawad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Feasibility and acceptability of a dietary intervention study to reduce salt intake and increase high-nitrate vegetable consumption among middle-aged and older Malaysian adults with elevated blood pressure: a study protocol</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>e035453</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2019-035453</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barteit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Si&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zabr&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Traor&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ou&#x000e9;draogo</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boudo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Widening the lens of population-based health research to climate change impacts and adaptation: the climate change and health evaluation and response system (CHEERS)</article-title>. <source>Front Public Health</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1153559</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2023.1153559</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37304117</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Creswell</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2015</year>). A concise introduction to mixed methods research.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll2">SurveyCTO</collab></person-group> (<fpage>2022</fpage>). Because your data is worth it. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.surveycto.com/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.surveycto.com/</ext-link> [Accessed December 8, 2022]</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll3">Garmin vivosmart&#x000ae; 5</collab></person-group> (<year>2022</year>). | Fitness Activity Tracker. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.garmin.com/en-CA/p/782585" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.garmin.com/en-CA/p/782585</ext-link> [Accessed December 8, 2022]</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll4">SwitchBot Meter</collab></person-group> (<year>2022</year>). SwitchBot EU. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://eu.switch-bot.com/pages/switchbot-meter" ext-link-type="uri">https://eu.switch-bot.com/pages/switchbot-meter</ext-link> [Accessed December 8, 2022]</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><label>38.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll5">3D-PAWS</collab></person-group> (<year>2022</year>). Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://sites.google.com/ucar.edu/3dpaws" ext-link-type="uri">https://sites.google.com/ucar.edu/3dpaws</ext-link> [Accessed December 8, 2022]</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Johnston</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Glidewell</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Entwistle</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Eccles</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>What is an adequate sample size? Operationalising data saturation for theory-based interview studies</article-title>. <source>Psychol Health</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>25</volume>:<fpage>1229</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>45</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/08870440903194015</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20204937</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll6">METMalaysia &#x02013; Home</collab></person-group> (<year>2022</year>). Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.met.gov.my/en/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.met.gov.my/en/</ext-link> [Accessed December 8, 2022]</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll7">MetMalaysia</collab></person-group> (<year>2022</year>). Malaysia&#x02019;s Climate. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.met.gov.my/en/pendidikan/iklim-malaysia/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.met.gov.my/en/pendidikan/iklim-malaysia/</ext-link> [Accessed January 11, 2023]</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll8">Jabatan Meteorologi Malaysia</collab></person-group> (<year>2022</year>). Met Malaysia annual report 2019. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.met.gov.my/assets/content/penerbitan/pdf/laporantahunan2019.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.met.gov.my/assets/content/penerbitan/pdf/laporantahunan2019.pdf</ext-link> [Accessed December 9, 2022]</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><label>43.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll9">World Bank</collab></person-group> (<year>2022</year>). World Bank climate change knowledge portal. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://climateknowledgeportal.worldbank.org/" ext-link-type="uri">https://climateknowledgeportal.worldbank.org/</ext-link> [Accessed January 11, 2023]</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><label>44.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Viechtbauer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smits</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kotz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bud&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spigt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Serroyen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A simple formula for the calculation of sample size in pilot studies</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>68</volume>:<fpage>1375</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2015.04.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26146089</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><label>45.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll10">Calculation of sample size in pilot studies</collab></person-group> (<year>2022</year>). Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.crutzen.net/n.htm" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.crutzen.net/n.htm</ext-link> [Accessed December 8, 2022]</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><label>46.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll11">ARDC Nectar Research Cloud | ARDC</collab></person-group> (<year>2022</year>). Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://ardc.edu.au/services/ardc-nectar-research-cloud/" ext-link-type="uri">https://ardc.edu.au/services/ardc-nectar-research-cloud/</ext-link> [Accessed December 8, 2022]</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><label>47.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll12">ASA</collab></person-group> (<year>2022</year>). Prusa Knowledge Base. Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://help.prusa3d.com/article/asa_1809" ext-link-type="uri">https://help.prusa3d.com/article/asa_1809</ext-link> [Accessed December 2, 2022]</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calverley</surname><given-names>PMA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nordyke</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Halbert</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Isonaka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nonikov</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Development of a population-based screening questionnaire for COPD</article-title>. <source>J Chronic Obstr Pulm Dis</source>. (<year>2005</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>225</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1081/COPD-57594</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>S-J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ledford</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lockey</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A new symptom-based questionnaire for predicting the presence of asthma</article-title>. <source>J Investig Allergol Clin Immunol</source>. (<year>2010</year>) <volume>20</volume>:<fpage>27</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage>. PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20232771</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><label>50.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>C-H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>S-L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H-C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>W-H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K-Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Perng</surname><given-names>D-W</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Novel app-based portable spirometer for the early detection of COPD</article-title>. <source>Diagnostics Multidiscip</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>785</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/diagnostics11050785</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33925463</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Stoltzfus</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Bland&#x02013;Altman plot: a brief overview</article-title>. <source>Int J Acad Med</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>110</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/IJAM.IJAM_54_17</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref52"><label>52.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>WY</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>SH-S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Associations of weather conditions with adolescents&#x02019; daily physical activity, sedentary time, and sleep duration</article-title>. <source>Appl Physiol Nutr Metab</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>44</volume>:<fpage>1339</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>44</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/apnm-2019-0309</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31063697</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Theisen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ungar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sheridan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Illston</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>More science with less: Evaluation of a 3D-printed weather station</article-title>. <source>Atmospheric Meas Tech</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>4699</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>713</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5194/amt-13-4699-2020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Woolley</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oniani</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pandyan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Quantifying Missingness in wearable heart rate recordings</article-title>. <source>Stud Health Technol Inform</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>281</volume>:<fpage>1077</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3233/SHTI210352</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34042845</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sallis</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cerin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pratt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Physical activity in relation to urban environments in 14 cities worldwide: a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>387</volume>:<fpage>2207</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(15)01284-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27045735</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Troiano</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Berrigan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dodd</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name>
<name><surname>M&#x000e2;sse</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tilert</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mcdowell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Physical activity in the United States measured by accelerometer</article-title>. <source>Med Sci Sports Exerc</source>. (<year>2008</year>) <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>181</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1249/mss.0b013e31815a51b3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18091006</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huhn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Matzke</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gunga</surname><given-names>H-C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maggioni</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Si&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Using wearable devices to generate real world, individual-level data in rural, low-resource contexts in Burkina-Faso, Africa: a case study</article-title>. <source>Front Public Health</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>972177</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2022.972177</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36249225</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll13">Expert Team on Climate Change Detection and Indices</collab></person-group> (<year>2022</year>). Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.wcrp-climate.org/data-etccdi" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.wcrp-climate.org/data-etccdi</ext-link> [Accessed December 8, 2022]</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref59"><label>59.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sandelowski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Qualitative analysis: what it is and how to begin</article-title>. <source>Res Nurs Health</source>. (<year>1995</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>371</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/nur.4770180411</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7624531</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref60"><label>60.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bengtsson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>How to plan and perform a qualitative study using content analysis</article-title>. <source>Nursing Plus Open</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>2</volume>:<fpage>8</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.npls.2016.01.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vaughn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Decoding via coding: analyzing qualitative text data through thematic coding and survey methodologies</article-title>. <source>J Libr Adm</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>56</volume>:<fpage>41</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>51</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01930826.2015.1105035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castleberry</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nolen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Thematic analysis of qualitative research data: is it as easy as it sounds?</article-title>
<source>Curr Pharm Teach Learn</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>807</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cptl.2018.03.019</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30025784</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref63"><label>63.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>B&#x000e4;rnighausen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Oldenburg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tugwell</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bommer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ebert</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Barreto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Quasi-experimental study designs series&#x02014;paper 7: assessing the assumptions</article-title>. <source>J Clin Epidemiol</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>89</volume>:<fpage>53</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>66</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclinepi.2017.02.017</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28365306</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gunasekara</surname><given-names>FI</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Blakely</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Fixed effects analysis of repeated measures data</article-title>. <source>Int J Epidemiol</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>264</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ije/dyt221</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24366487</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref65"><label>65.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Chaisemartin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>D&#x02019;haultf&#x00153;uille</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Two-way fixed effects and differences-in-differences estimators with several treatments</article-title>. <source>J. Econom.</source> (<year>2023</year>) <volume>236</volume>:<fpage>105480</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Estimating dynamic treatment effects in event studies with heterogeneous treatment effects</article-title>. <source>J Econ</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>225</volume>:<fpage>175</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>99</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jeconom.2020.09.006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref67"><label>67.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab id="coll14">Estimation in DID with Multiple Groups and Periods [R package DIDmultiplegt version 0.1.0]</collab></person-group> (<year>2020</year>). Comprehensive R archive network (CRAN). Available at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=DIDmultiplegt" ext-link-type="uri">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=DIDmultiplegt</ext-link> [Accessed December 1, 2022]</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref68"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herbst</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Juvekar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bhattacharjee</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bangha</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Patharia</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tei</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The INDEPTH data repository: An international resource for longitudinal population and health data from health and demographic surveillance systems</article-title>. <source>J Empir Res Hum Res Ethics</source>. (<year>2015</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>324</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1556264615594600</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26297754</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref69"><label>69.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>P&#x000f6;rtner</surname><given-names>H-O</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aldunce</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <source>Climate change 2022: Impacts, adaptation and vulnerability</source>. <publisher-loc>The Netherlands</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>IPCC Sixth Assess Rep IPCC Geneva</publisher-name> (<year>2022</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref70"><label>70.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barteit</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Boudo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ouedraogo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zabr&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ouremi</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Si&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Feasibility, acceptability and validation of wearable devices for climate change and health research in the low-resource contexts of Burkina Faso and Kenya: study protocol</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>e0257170</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0257170</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34591893</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref71"><label>71.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karst</surname><given-names>IG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mank</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Traor&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sorgho</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>St&#x000fc;ckemann</surname><given-names>K-J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Simboro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Estimating yields of household fields in rural subsistence farming systems to study food security in Burkina Faso</article-title>. <source>Remote Sens Multidiscip</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>12</volume>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/rs12111717</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref72"><label>72.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ou&#x000e9;draogo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Traor&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Satellite-based multi-annual yield models for major food crops at the household field level for nutrition and health research: a case study from the Nouna HDSS, Burkina Faso</article-title>. <source>Int J Appl Earth Obs Geoinf</source>. (<year>2023</year>) <volume>117</volume>:<fpage>103203</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jag.2023.103203</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref73"><label>73.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Matzke</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Huhn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gunga</surname><given-names>H-C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maggioni</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Munga</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Wearables for measuring health effects of climate change-induced weather extremes: scoping review</article-title>. <source>JMIR Mhealth Uhealth</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>e39532</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/39532</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36083624</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref74"><label>74.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huhn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Axt</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gunga</surname><given-names>H-C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maggioni</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Munga</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Obor</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The impact of wearable technologies in health research: scoping review</article-title>. <source>JMIR MHealth UHealth</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>e34384</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2196/34384</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35076409</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref75"><label>75.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Obradovich</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Migliorini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Mednick</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fowler</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Nighttime temperature and human sleep loss in a changing climate</article-title>. <source>Sci Adv</source>. (<year>2017</year>) <volume>3</volume>:<fpage>e1601555</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciadv.1601555</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28560320</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref76"><label>76.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Insija</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jemin</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Valamparampil</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pillai</surname><given-names>HKG</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name>
<etal/></person-group>. <article-title>COPD, asthma and pneumothorax as climate sensitive health outcomes</article-title>. <source>J Compr Health</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>82</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.53553/JCH.v06i02.006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref77"><label>77.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Degryse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Buffels</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Van Dijck</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Decramer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nemery</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Accuracy of office spirometry performed by trained primary-care physicians using the MIR Spirobank hand-held spirometer</article-title>. <source>Respiration</source>. (<year>2012</year>) <volume>83</volume>:<fpage>543</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>52</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000334907</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22269344</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref78"><label>78.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fonta</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sanfo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kedir</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thiam</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Estimating farmers&#x02019; willingness to pay for weather index-based crop insurance uptake in West Africa: insight from a pilot initiative in southwestern Burkina Faso</article-title>. <source>Agric Food Econ</source>. (<year>2018</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>11</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40100-018-0104-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
