<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="case-report"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="issn">2168-8184</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cureus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2168-8184</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cureus</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Palo Alto (CA)</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38125216</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC10732472</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.49126</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Dermatology</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>General Surgery</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Oncology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Sebaceous Adenoma: A Dermoscopic Case Perspective</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Muacevic</surname><given-names>Alexander</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>John R</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez-Ortega</surname><given-names>Jesus Ivan</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Perez Hernandez</surname><given-names>Felipe de Jesus</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Flores-Reyes</surname><given-names>Itzel Anayn</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Qui&#x000f1;ones-Venega</surname><given-names>Ricardo</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Reyna</surname><given-names>Ilse</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Valdivieso-Jimenez</surname><given-names>Jorge Arturo</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label>
Department of Dermatology, Dermatological Institute of Jalisco "Dr. Jos&#x000e9; Barba Rubio", Zapopan, MEX </aff><aff id="aff-2">
<label>2</label>
Department of Internal Medicine, Regional High-Specialty Hospital of the Yucatan Peninsula, M&#x000e9;rida, MEX </aff><aff id="aff-3">
<label>3</label>
Department of Internal Medicine, Hospital General "Dr. Agustin O'Horan", M&#x000e9;rida, MEX </aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
Felipe de Jesus Perez Hernandez <email>felipephz7@gmail.com</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>20</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><month>11</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e49126</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>18</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2023, Martinez-Ortega et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Martinez-Ortega et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License CC-BY 4.0., which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://www.cureus.com/articles/178919-sebaceous-adenoma-a-dermoscopic-case-perspective">This article is available from https://www.cureus.com/articles/178919-sebaceous-adenoma-a-dermoscopic-case-perspective</self-uri><abstract><p>This report focuses on sebaceous skin tumors, specifically sebaceous adenoma, sebaceoma, and sebaceous carcinoma, along with their association with Muir-Torre syndrome (MTS). A clinical case of a 25-year-old male with a suspected sebaceous neoplasm based on dermoscopy appearance is presented. The histopathological examination confirmed the diagnosis and surgical management resulted in successful treatment. The report highlights the importance of considering differential diagnoses and utilizing dermoscopy for accurate evaluation of these rare skin tumors.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>skin tumor</kwd><kwd>rainbow like image</kwd><kwd>dermoscopy</kwd><kwd>muir-torre syndrome</kwd><kwd>sebaceous adenoma</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>Sebaceous skin tumors can be classified into three types: sebaceous adenoma, sebaceoma, and sebaceous carcinoma. These tumors are uncommon [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. In this case study, we present a clinical case with suspected characteristics based on dermoscopy appearance. Although these tumors are generally benign, it is crucial to carefully consider the differential histopathological diagnosis and their potential association with Muir-Torre syndrome (MTS). Moreover, the significance of dermoscopy in evaluating this neoplasm should not be underestimated.</p></sec><sec sec-type="cases"><title>Case presentation</title><p>A 25-year-old male presented with a "lump" in the lower right eyelid that had been present for approximately four years. The patient reported discomfort when closing the eye. There was no relevant medical history or previous treatments. On physical examination, a dome-shaped neoformation measuring 1.3x0.9x0.3 cm was observed. It exhibited light yellow and skin-colored areas, a pearly appearance, and telangiectasias on the surface. The lesion had well-defined, raised edges on the lower right eyelid (Figure <xref rid="FIG1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Clinical lesion on the right lower eyelid</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0015-00000049126-i01" position="float"/></fig><p>Dermoscopy revealed a non-melanocytic lesion with arborizing vessels, whitish structures resembling cotton flakes, a yellow-orange background typical of sebaceous components, and hints of a rainbow-like image. (Figure <xref rid="FIG2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Dermoscopy of the lesion</title><p>The lesion exhibits non-melanocytic features, including arborizing vessels (blue arrows), whitish structures resembling cotton flakes (dark blue stars), a yellow-orange background typical of sebaceous components (black circles), and subtle hints of a rainbow-like image (dotted rectangle).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0015-00000049126-i02" position="float"/></fig><p>Histopathological examination using hematoxylin and eosin staining showed acanthosis on the epidermis, hyperpigmentation within the basal layer, and a proliferation of epithelial cells with sebaceous differentiation, confirming the diagnosis of sebaceous adenoma (Figure <xref rid="FIG3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Hematoxylin and eosin stain</title><p>The dermis shows multiple well-circumscribed lobules comprising an admixture of basaloid cells (indicated by red arrows) and mature sebocytes (indicated by black arrows).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0015-00000049126-i03" position="float"/></fig><p>These cells were grouped and exhibited an irregular shape and size, resembling a grape (Figure <xref rid="FIG4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>) [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].</p><fig position="anchor" fig-type="figure" id="FIG4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><title>Hematoxylin and eosin stain at 40x</title><p>Magnified view at 40x showing the basaloid cells (red arrow) and mature sebocytes (black arrow).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="cureus-0015-00000049126-i04" position="float"/></fig><p>The patient underwent surgical management, which involved a wedge resection of the eyelid with a 3 mm safety margin of healthy skin. The defect was repaired using an advancement flap. During the three-month post-surgery follow-up, there was no recurrence.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Sebaceous tumors present challenges in comprehending their pathogenesis and genetic profile, as these aspects remain limited. However, a widely accepted theory suggests that alterations in the Wnt/beta-catenin signaling pathway play a crucial role in their development. Studies on transgenic mice, expressing a defective beta-catenin binding site in the lymphoid enhancer-binding factor (LEF-1) transcription factor, have demonstrated the spontaneous development of sebaceous skin tumors. Mutations in the LEF-1gene have been observed in sebaceomas and sebaceous adenomas, while sebaceous carcinomas may exhibit complete silencing of the LEF-1 gene [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].</p><p>In individuals with MTS and sebaceous gland neoplasias, germline mutations in DNA mismatch repair genes, particularly MSH2, have been reported. However, there seems to be no direct correlation between the presence of LEF-1 mutations and the loss of MSH2 expression, suggesting that they are not directly linked [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><p>Sebaceous adenoma is the most common sebaceous tumor associated with MTS [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. These rare benign neoplasms originate from the epithelial tissue and are characterized by well-defined irregular lobules within the papillary dermis. Clinically, they usually emerge in the head and neck region, appearing as small erythematous or yellowish lesions, sometimes with crusting or an umbilicated appearance. In the eyelids, they can involve the glands of Zeiss or the meibomian glands. Sebaceous adenomas typically manifest around the age of 60 and usually measure approximately 5 mm in their greatest dimension [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Dermatoscopic features of sebaceous adenoma are still limited in the literature. However, one study involving 18 cases suggested two possible dermatoscopic patterns. The first pattern is characterized by tumors with a central crater, exhibiting elongated radial telangiectasias (crown vessels) surrounding an opaque structureless ovoid white-yellow center, which can sometimes be covered by blood crusts. The second pattern is observed in tumors without a central crater, revealing branching but unfocused arborizing vessels over a white-to-yellow background, with a few loosely arranged yellow comedo-like globules. These yellow ovoid structures correspond histopathologically to dermal conglomerations of enlarged sebaceous glands, a feature shared by all sebaceous lesions [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In addition, these comedo-like globules may vary in form; in our case, they resemble more "cotton flakes", but both represent the enlargement of sebaceous glands. Furthermore, we propose that the rainbow-like image observed on dermoscopy corresponds to the basaloid cell component. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first time the term "cotton flakes" has been used in the dermoscopy description of a sebaceous adenoma, and our report represents the first instance of a rainbow-like image observed on dermoscopy for this neoplasm. While clinical and dermoscopic features may give rise to suspicion of sebaceous adenoma/sebaceoma, a definitive histopathologic diagnosis is crucial for accurate identification [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].</p><p>On a histological level, sebaceous adenoma tumor lobules exhibit varying layers of germinative, immature sebocytes at the periphery. These sebocytes show mitotic activity but lack significant cell atypia. Sebaceous adenomas also demonstrate variably expanded basaloid cells, exceeding the typical two-cell layers observed in sebaceous glands and sebaceous hyperplasia. The differential diagnosis of sebaceous adenoma involves distinguishing it from clear cell variants of eccrine, melanocytic, keratinocytic, or xanthomatous lesions, as well as renal cell carcinoma [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>-<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p><p>Typically located in the superficial dermis, sebaceous adenoma can raise suspicion for well-differentiated sebaceous carcinoma if it extends into the deep dermis, exhibits high mitotic activity, and mild cytologic atypia [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Differentiating well-differentiated sebaceous carcinoma from sebaceous adenoma can be challenging in rare cases. When in doubt, complete excision of any sebaceous tumor is recommended. The cystic variant of sebaceous adenoma serves as a marker for MTS and should be stained for mismatch-repair (MMR) protein deficiency proteins and immunohistochemical markers (MSH2, mismatch repair gene). The diagnosis of the syndrome is based on the presence of at least one sebaceous neoplasm and a visceral malignancy or, alternatively, multiple keratoacanthomas associated with visceral malignancies as&#x000a0;colorectal, genitourinary, and breast carcinomas and a family history of MTS&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p><p>Traditionally, sebaceous adenomas are not linked to significant local recurrence, aggressive behavior, or metastasis. Most practitioners prefer a conservative but complete excision of these lesions, which appears to be an appropriate therapeutic approach [<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>This case&#x000a0;emphasizes the significance of dermoscopy in aiding clinical diagnosis and underscores the association of these tumors with MTS. Early identification and appropriate management, including complete excision, play a crucial role in ensuring favorable outcomes.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>To colleagues at the Instituto Dermatol&#x000f3;gico de Jalisco "Dr. Jos&#x000e9; Barba Rubio".</p></ack><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Human Ethics</title><fn fn-type="other"><p>Consent was obtained or waived by all participants in this study</p></fn></fn-group><notes><fn-group content-type="competing-interests"><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn></fn-group></notes><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="REF1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Sebaceous neoplasms</article-title><source>Surg Pathol Clin</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Flux</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>382</lpage><volume>10</volume><year>2017</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28477886</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Human sebaceous tumors harbor inactivating mutations in LEF1</article-title><source>Nat Med</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Takeda</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lyle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lazar</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Zouboulis</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Smyth</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Watt</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>395</fpage><lpage>397</lpage><volume>12</volume><year>2006</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16565724</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Frequency of microsatellite instability in unselected sebaceous gland neoplasias and hyperplasias</article-title><source>J Invest Dermatol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Kruse</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>R&#x000fc;tten</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Schweiger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>858</fpage><lpage>864</lpage><volume>120</volume><year>2003</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12713593</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Penile sebaceous adenoma</article-title><source>J Am Acad Dermatol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Terrell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wetter</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Fraga</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kestenbaum</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Aires</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>0</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><volume>57</volume><year>2007</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>A case of sebaceous adenoma of the eyelid showing excessively rapid growth</article-title><source>Clin Ophthalmol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Takayama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Usui</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Takeuchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>667</fpage><lpage>670</lpage><volume>7</volume><year>2013</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23579539</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Clinical, dermoscopic and reflectance confocal microscopy features of sebaceous neoplasms in Muir-Torre syndrome</article-title><source>J Eur Acad Dermatol Venereol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Moscarella</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Argenziano</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Longo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>699</fpage><lpage>705</lpage><volume>27</volume><year>2013</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22471909</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Sebaceous neoplasia and the Muir-Torre syndrome: important connections with clinical implications</article-title><source>Histopathology</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Shalin</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lyle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Calonje</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lazar</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>147</lpage><volume>56</volume><year>2010</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20055911</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Sebaceous neoplasia and Torre-Muir syndrome</article-title><source>Curr Diagn Pathol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Lazar</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Lyle</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Calonje</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>319</lpage><volume>13</volume><year>2007</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18670585</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Differential diagnostics of sebaceous tumors [Article in German]</article-title><source>Pathologe</source><person-group>
<name><surname>B&#x000f6;er-Auer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>455</lpage><volume>35</volume><year>2014</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25103328</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Sebaceous neoplasms and the immunoprofile of mismatch-repair proteins as a screening target for syndromic cases</article-title><source>Pathol Res Pract</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Boennelycke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Thomsen</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Holck</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>78</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><volume>211</volume><year>2015</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25457183</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
