<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Microbiol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Microbiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-302X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38125563</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC10732508</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2023.1285229</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The extracellular polysaccharide determine the physico-chemical surface properties of <italic>Microcystis</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Haijian</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1104922/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/formal-analysis"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/software"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Denghua</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Hua</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1031243/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Chunxiang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/funding-acquisition"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Key Laboratory of Algal Biology, Institute of Hydrobiology, Chinese Academy of Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Wuhan</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>University of Chinese Academy of Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0001"><p>Edited by: Man Xiao, Chinese Academy of Sciences (CAS), China</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by" id="fn0002"><p>Reviewed by: Ganyu Feng, Tongji University, China; Ming Li, Northwest A&#x00026;F University, China</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Chunxiang Hu, <email>cxhu@ihb.ac.cn</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>05</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>1285229</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>8</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2023 Yang, Wu, Li and Hu.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Yang, Wu, Li and Hu</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p><italic>Microcystis</italic> possesses the capacity to form colonies and blooms in lakes and reservoirs worldwide, causing significant ecological challenges in aquatic ecosystems. However, little is known about the determining factors of physico-chemical surface properties that govern the competitive advantage of <italic>Microcystis</italic>. Here, The physico-chemical surface properties of <italic>Microcystis wesenbergii</italic> and <italic>Microcystis aeruginosa</italic>, including specific surface area (SSA), hydrophobicity, zeta potential, and functional groups were investigated. Additionally, the extracellular polysaccharide (EPS) were analyzed. Laboratory-cultured <italic>Microcystis</italic> exhibited hydrophilic, a negative zeta potential and negatively charged. Furthermore, no significant relationship was shown between these properties and the cultivation stage. <italic>Microcystis wesenbergii</italic> exhibited low free energy of cohesion, high surface free energy, high growth rate, and high EPS content during the logarithmic phase. On the other hand, <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic> displayed lower free energy of cohesion, high surface free energy, high EPS content, and high growth rate during the stationary phase. These characteristics contribute to their respective competitive advantage. Furthermore, the relationship between EPS and surface properties was investigated. The polysaccharide component of EPS primarily influenced the SSA and total surface energy of <italic>Microcystis</italic>. Likewise, the protein component of EPS influenced hydrophobicity and surface tension. The polysaccharide composition, including glucuronic acid, xylose, and fructose, mainly influenced surface properties. Additionally, hydrophilic groups such as O&#x02013;H and P&#x02013;O&#x02013;P played a crucial role in determining hydrophobicity in <italic>Microcystis</italic>. This study elucidates that EPS influenced the SSA, hydrophobicity, and surface free energy of <italic>Microcystis</italic> cells, which in turn impact the formation of <italic>Microcystis</italic> blooms and the collection.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic>Microcystis</italic></kwd><kwd>cell surface</kwd><kwd>extracellular polysaccharide</kwd><kwd>monosaccharide composition</kwd><kwd>hydrophobicity</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>The author(s) declare financial support was received for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. This work was funded by the Featured Institute Service Projects from the Institute of Hydrobiology, Chinese Academy of Sciences (Y85Z061601), the Knowledge Innovation Program of Wuhan-Basic Research (2022020801010142), National Key R&#x00026;D Program of China (2021YFE0112000), and Natural Science Foundation for Distinguished Young Scholars of Hubei Province (2022CFA105).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="1"/><equation-count count="5"/><ref-count count="65"/><page-count count="13"/><word-count count="10257"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Aquatic Microbiology</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Cyanobacterial blooms are a significant environmental issue in aquatic ecosystems (<xref rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr">Qu et al., 2014</xref>). Common genera that form blooms include <italic>Microcystis</italic>, <italic>Anabaena</italic> (or <italic>Dolichospermum</italic>), <italic>Aphanizomenon</italic>, <italic>Cylindrospermopsis</italic> and others (<xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">Huisman et al., 2018</xref>). Among these, <italic>Microcystis</italic> is the dominant genus in eutrophic freshwaters worldwide (<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">Xiao et al., 2018</xref>). Every year, freshwater lakes with important ecological functions in China, such as Taihu Lake, Chaohu Lake and Dianchi Lake, experience varying degrees of cyanobacterial blooms, with <italic>Microcystis</italic> as the predominant species (<xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">Tang et al., 2018</xref>). <italic>Microcystis</italic> exhibits a competitive advantage over other organisms in aquatic environments due to its buoyancy regulation, specialized storage strategies, efficient nitrogen uptake, and resistance to zooplankton (<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">Xiao et al., 2018</xref>).</p><p>In several lakes and reservoirs, the predominant species responsible for the formation of blooms were <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> and <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic>, among other common <italic>Microcystis</italic> species such as <italic>M. ichthyoblabe</italic> (<xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et al., 2016</xref>)<italic>. Microcystis wesenbergii</italic> and <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic> exhibit alternating blooms in different seasons or depths in the water column, indicating a strong competitive advantage between these two <italic>Microcystis</italic> species (<xref rid="ref65" ref-type="bibr">Zhu et al., 2015</xref>). In Lake Taihu, <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> dominated at water temperatures above 27&#x000b0;C, while <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic> dominated at temperature between 22&#x000b0;C and 25&#x000b0;C (<xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr">Otten and Paerl, 2011</xref>). Numerous studies have investigated the relationship among light, temperature, and nutrient competition in <italic>Microcystis</italic> spp. (Yue et al., <xref rid="ref56" ref-type="bibr">2014a</xref>,<xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>). For instance, the growth rate of <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> from Japan remained relatively stable within a temperature range of 20&#x000b0;C&#x02013;35&#x000b0;C. On the other hand, the growth rate of <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic> showed an increase as the temperature rose. Furthermore, no significant difference in the growth rate between <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic> and <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> was observed under the same light conditions (<xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Imai et al., 2009</xref>). The algal-bacterial relationships of different microcystic algae in nature have also been studied (<xref rid="ref61" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2021</xref>; <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">Le et al., 2022</xref>). Additionally, the surface characteristics of cells, including EPS, charge, and hydrophobicity play a crucial role in non-specific adhesion of <italic>Microcystis</italic> to various biotic and abiotic surfaces (colony formation) and competitive advantage. However, the surface characteristics of <italic>Microcystis</italic> have received little attention.</p><p>Physicochemical properties of microbial cell surfaces such as hydrophobicity, surface tension, contact angle, and surface energy had been studied extensively (<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr">Barros et al., 2019</xref>). Previous researches have primarily focused on energy microalgae, with the aim of efficient harvesting through flocculation (<xref rid="ref59" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2012</xref>). However, limited research has been conducted on cyanobacteria. <xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">Liu L. et al. (2016)</xref> reported that laboratory-cultured <italic>Microcystis</italic> exists single cells, while wild <italic>Microcystis</italic> forms colonies based on the zeta potential and hydrophobicity. Additionally, the surface features of cells and colony formation are directly influenced by the characteristics of cyanobacterial extracellular polymeric substances (EPS; <xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2018</xref>). The content, composition, and monosaccharide components of EPS directly determine the surface properties of cells, including the presence of non-sugar components such as uronic acids, pyruvic acid, phosphate, and acyl groups. These non-sugar components contribute to the overall negative charge of EPS and provide binding and adsorption properties to these types of polymers (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Gupta and Diwan, 2017</xref>). Surface adhesions a key factor in determining the self-aggregation capacity of cells (<xref rid="ref63" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2020</xref>), and also affects the collection efficiency of cells (<xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">Yu et al., 2018</xref>). However, the surface characteristics of <italic>Microcystis</italic> are still poorly understood.</p><p>This study aimed to examine the cell surface properties of <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> and <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic>, specifically focusing on cell surface area, hydrophobicity, zeta potential, and surface free energy. Additionally, we investigated the variations in EPS contents and composition at different cultured stages. Our analysis focused on understanding the interactions between cell surface characteristics and EPS. The findings of this study contribute to our understanding of bloom formation (<italic>Microcystis</italic> aggregation) and shed light on the competitive advantage of these two strains. Furthermore, the insights gained from this research may have implications for the development of flocculation collection techniques, such as co-coagulation flotation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec2"><label>2</label><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="sec3"><label>2.1</label><title><italic>Microcystis</italic> and cultivation</title><p><italic>Microcystis aeruginosa</italic> and <italic>Microcystis wesenbergii</italic> were isolated from water samples collected from Meiliang Bay Meiliang Bay in Lake Taihu in June and November 2008 (<italic>M. aeruginosa</italic> was isolated by Yue Tao, and <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> was isolated by Li Renhui), which are typical of single populations with different morphotypes. Single colonies were isolated using a light microscopy (Leica, Leica Microsystems, Wetzler, Germany) and purified using a series of BG-11 agar plates until the cultures were axenic. Subsequently, they were identified through 16S rRNA and gvpA-gvpC ITS sequence analysis (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 5</xref>). These colonies were then maintained aseptically in BG11 medium in our laboratory (<xref rid="ref56" ref-type="bibr">Yue et al., 2014a</xref>,<xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>). The stock cultures were maintained in a sterilized BG11 medium containing 1.5 g NaNO<sub>3</sub>, 40 mg K<sub>2</sub>HPO<sub>4</sub>, 75 mg MgSO<sub>4</sub> &#x022c5; 7H<sub>2</sub>O, 20 mg Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>, 36 mg CaCl<sub>2</sub> &#x022c5; 2H<sub>2</sub>O, 6 mg ammonium ferric citrate, 6 mg ammonium citrate monohydrate, 1 mg EDTA, 2.86 &#x003bc;g H<sub>3</sub>BO<sub>3</sub>, 1.81 &#x003bc;g MnCl<sub>2</sub> &#x022c5; 4H<sub>2</sub>O, 0.222 &#x003bc;g ZnSO<sub>4</sub> &#x022c5; 7H<sub>2</sub>O, 0.39 &#x003bc;g Na<sub>2</sub>MoO<sub>4</sub> &#x022c5; 2H<sub>2</sub>O, 0.079 &#x003bc;g CuSO<sub>4</sub> &#x022c5; 5H<sub>2</sub>O, 0.050 &#x003bc;g CoCl<sub>2</sub> &#x022c5; 6H<sub>2</sub>O in 1 L water. <italic>Microcystis</italic> spp. were cultivated in 5 L Erlenmeyer flasks containing 4 L with continuous illumination under 40 &#x003bc;mol m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> in a temperature-controlled incubator (25&#x000b0;C&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2&#x000b0;C). The initial inoculum biomass was controlled at about 0.5 mg L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> of Chlorophyll a (<italic>Chl.a</italic>) with a continuous aeration at 0.5 L min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. All the experiments were conducted in triplicate. The microalgal cells were harvested at logarithmic phase after 30-day cultivation and stationary phase after 60-day, and used for the subsequential analyses.</p><p><italic>Microcystis</italic> colonies in the field were isolated and obtained from Lake Taihu in September 2023. The samples were collected using a plankton net positioned approximately 0.5 m above the water surface. Morphological classification using a light microscope was used to identify the <italic>Microcystis</italic> algal strains. Only individual <italic>Microcystis</italic> populations that were free of visible impurities and stray algae were selected. These populations were then rinsed with sterile water and inoculated in test tubes containing BG11 medium at 25&#x000b0;C. After 15 days of incubation, samples were taken for zeta potential and contact angle determination.</p></sec><sec id="sec4"><label>2.2</label><title>Physiology analysis</title><p>A 10 mL suspension of microalgal cells was centrifuged at 12,000 rpm for 5 min. The cells sediment was mechanically broken in a mortar with the addition of quartz sand and then resuspended in 2 mL 95% (v/v) ethanol. This suspension was kept in the dark at 4&#x000b0;C for 12 h. Subsequently, the cell suspension was centrifuged for 5 min at 10,000 rpm. The absorbencies of 663, 490, and 384 nm were measured by spectrophotometer, and the content of pigment (mg L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) was calculated using the following equations: <italic>Chl.a</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1,000&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;(1.02&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;A663 &#x02212; 0.027&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;A384+ 0.01&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;A490)/92.5.</p><p>Cell diameters (d) were measured using a microscope (Nikon ECLIPSE 80i, Japan) and dry weight (DW, g L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) was measured by difference method. The Donnan volume (DV, m<sup>3</sup> g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) was calculated using the following equations: DV&#x02009;=&#x02009;1/DW&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;1,000. The specific surface area (SSA, m<sup>2</sup> g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) was calculated using the following equations: SSA&#x02009;=&#x02009;S/m&#x02009;=&#x02009;dv&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;S/V&#x02009;=&#x02009;dv&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;4&#x003c0;r<sup>2</sup>/(4/3&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;&#x003c0;r<sup>3</sup>)&#x02009;=&#x02009;6&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;DV/d&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>6</sup>. The surface area per cell (CSA, &#x003bc;m<sup>2</sup> cell<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) were calculated using basic geometric shapes as described by <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Henderson R. et al. (2008)</xref> and dry weight.</p></sec><sec id="sec5"><label>2.3</label><title>Monosaccharide composition and EPS analysis</title><p>The EPS matrix was fractionated into the soluble EPS (sEPS, or released polymeric substance, RPS) and bound EPS (bEPS, or capsular polymeric substance, CPS), which are released into the surrounding environment, and which are tightly bound to the cell surface (<xref rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr">De Philippis, 1998</xref>). The bEPS was also fractionated into the loosely bound EPS (LB-EPS) and tightly bound EPS (TB-EPS). To extract the algae cells and supernatant, 1,000 mL of algal solution was centrifuged at 8000 rpm for 10 min. The algae cells were then washed three times with distilled water and vacuum freeze-dried (Christ ALPHA 1-2 LD plus, Germany) to obtain dry algae. The CPS were extracted from the dry algae (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material</xref>; <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figures 1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">3</xref>) with less debris. 100 mg of cells was added into 10 mL of 0.05% NaCl solution, maintained at 60&#x000b0;C for 60 min, and then passed through GF/C Whatman glass microfiber filters (Whatman International Ltd., Maidstone, United Kingdom). Microscopic observation was conducted by staining with India ink to ensure the extract has not been contaminated from intracellular or extracellular substances. Then, the supernatant was dialyzed with distilled water in a Spectrapor dialysis tube with a molecular weight cut-off of 3,500 Daltons (Spectrum China, Shanghai, China). The polysaccharide and protein content in RPS were determined from the supernatant. EPS content refers to the total (mg g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) of RPS and CPS content (<xref rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr">Ge et al., 2014</xref>). The polysaccharide content was determined using the phenol sulfuric acid method, with glucose as the standard sample, while the protein content was determined using the Bradford assay using bovine serum albumin. The CPS and RPS liquid was isolated to neutral part, acidic I polymers and acidic II polymers (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material</xref>; <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 4</xref>).</p><p>The monosaccharide composition of EPS was measured using the method by <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr">Hokputsa et al. (2003)</xref>. In briefly, 1 mg of dry weight CPS and RPS samples were subjected to methanolysis using 4 M hydrochloric acid in anhydrous methanol at 80&#x000b0;C for 24 h. To ensure accurate measurements, mannitol was added as an internal standard prior to performing trimethylsilylation. The trimethylsilylated samples were analyzed using gas chromatographic analysis (GC-Orbitrap-MS, Thermo Scientific TRACE 1310-EXACIVE GC). The content of each monosaccharide was calculated based on its content in CPS and RPS.</p></sec><sec id="sec6"><label>2.4</label><title>Surface physicochemical parameters</title><sec id="sec7"><label>2.4.1</label><title>Zeta potentials analysis</title><p>A 10 mL suspension of microalgal cells was prepared by centrifuging at 2,000 g for 20 min. The resulting pellet was washed three times with wate. The pellet was then resuspended in a 0.1 M NaNO<sub>3</sub> solution and the pH was adjusted from 2 to 8. The zeta potential was determined using a &#x003b6;-potential analyzer (Malvern, Zetasizer Nano, ZS90) at room temperature, and the value obtained represents the zeta potential in millivolts (mV).</p></sec><sec id="sec8"><label>2.4.2</label><title>Hydrophobicity characterization</title><p>The hydrophobicity of the cell surface was evaluated using the method described by <xref rid="ref40" ref-type="bibr">Rosenberg et al. (1980)</xref>. The initial content of chlorophyll a (<italic>chl.a</italic> 0) was determined using a 10 mL suspension of microalgal cells. The cells were then resuspended in a phosphate buffer. Subsequently, 2 mL of organic solvents (hexane, ethyl acetate, chloroform) were added to 8 mL of cell suspension. The two-phase system was vortexed for 2 min and allowed to settle for 20 min. The chlorophyll a content of the algal cells in the organic phase was measured as <italic>Chl.a</italic>. The percentage hydrophobicity (H) was calculated as <xref rid="EQ1" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (1)</xref>:</p><disp-formula id="EQ1">
<label>(1)</label>
<mml:math id="M1" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo stretchy="true">/</mml:mo><mml:mi>C</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mspace width="0.25em"/><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mo>%</mml:mo></mml:math>
</disp-formula></sec><sec id="sec9"><label>2.4.3</label><title>Contact angles determinations</title><p>The cells were suspended in ultrapure water and filtered through a glass fiber membrane with a pore size of 0.45 &#x003bc;m. The membranes were then stored in agar petri dishes containing 1% (w/v) 10% (v/v) glycerol for 2 h to ensure consistent moisture content. Afterward, the membranes were then air-dried for 60 min to achieve a relatively stable contact angle. The contact angle was determined using water (&#x003b8;<sub>W</sub>), diiodomethane (&#x003b8;<sub>D</sub>) and formamide (&#x003b8;<sub>F</sub>) as reference liquids, following the according the method described by <xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr">Williams et al. (2011)</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="sec10"><label>2.4.4</label><title>Free energy of adhesion determinations</title><p>The surface free energy of the algae lawns was calculated using the Lifshitz-van Waals/acid&#x02013;base approach (the LW/AB method). This method decomposes the surface free energy (&#x003b3;) into two components: Lifshitz-van der Waals component (&#x003b3;<sup>LW</sup>) and Lewis acid&#x02013;base component (&#x003b3;<sup>AB</sup>), which further splits into a Lewis acid component (&#x003b3;<sup>+</sup>) and a Lewis base component (&#x003b3;<sup>&#x02212;</sup>). The LW/AB method can be mathematically expressed as <xref rid="EQ2" ref-type="disp-formula">Equations (2)&#x02013;(4)</xref>:</p><disp-formula id="EQ2">
<label>(2)</label>
<mml:math id="M2" overflow="scroll"><mml:msub><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">cos&#x003b8;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msqrt><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msqrt><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msqrt><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:msqrt></mml:math>
</disp-formula><disp-formula id="EQ3">
<label>(3)</label>
<mml:math id="M3" overflow="scroll"><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">AB</mml:mi></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msqrt><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:msqrt></mml:math>
</disp-formula><disp-formula id="EQ4">
<label>(4)</label>
<mml:math id="M4" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">AB</mml:mi></mml:msup></mml:math>
</disp-formula><p>where &#x003b8; is the contact angle, subscripts of &#x0201c;s&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;l&#x0201d; refer to the surface and probe liquid, respectively. In <xref rid="EQ2" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (2)</xref>, the contact angle of the apolar liquid, diiodomethane, was used to quantify the apolar surface energy component &#x003b3;<sub>s</sub><sup>LW</sup>, since &#x003b3;<sub>l</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> and &#x003b3;<sub>l</sub><sup>+</sup> are both equal to zero (<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">van Oss, 1993</xref>). Additionally, the contact angles measured with the other two probe liquids, water and formamide, were utilized to calculate the remaining two unknown surface energy parameters, &#x003b3;<sub>s</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup> and &#x003b3;<sub>s</sub><sup>+</sup>.</p><p>According to the Derjaguin, Landau, Verwey, and Overbeek (DLVO) theory, the degree of hydrophilicity and hydrophobicity of the algae surfaces were determined by evaluating their free energy of cohesion (&#x00394;Gcoh), as described in <xref rid="EQ5" ref-type="disp-formula">Equation (5)</xref>:</p><disp-formula id="EQ5">
<label>(5)</label>
<mml:math id="M5" overflow="scroll"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x00394;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>G</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mfenced open="(" close=")"><mml:mrow><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt></mml:mrow></mml:mfenced></mml:math>
</disp-formula><p>where subscripts s and l, respectively, refer to the surface and water. If &#x00394;Gcoh &#x0003c; 0, the surface&#x02013;surface interaction is stronger than the interaction of the surface with water, and the material is treated as hydrophobic. In contrast, the material is hydrophilic if &#x00394;Gcoh &#x0003e; 0. Additionally, the free interfacial energy (or total surface tension, G<sup>TOT</sup>) was calculated based on the extended Derjaguin&#x02212;Landau&#x02212;Verwey&#x02212;Overbeek (XDLVO) theory (<xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">van Oss, 1993</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec11"><label>2.4.5</label><title>Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy</title><p>A 10 mL algal solution was centrifuged at 5,000 rpm for 10 min to collect the algal cells. The cells were then vacuum freeze-dried and mixed with KBr powder (1:100, wt/wt). The mixture was processed by pressing and the transmission infrared spectra were recorded using an infrared spectrometer (NEXUS, Thermo Nicolet). The spectrometer had a scanning range of 4,000 to 500 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and a resolution of 2 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The recorded spectra were analyzed using OMNIC software.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec12"><label>2.5</label><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Results are averages of triplicates, and the values in each graph and table are shown with 5% error bars. t test was performed using SPSS 24.0 package (SPSS, Chicago, IL), with values of 0.05 selected as significance.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec13"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="sec14"><label>3.1</label><title>Microalgal growth and cells physico-chemical characterization</title><sec id="sec15"><label>3.1.1</label><title>Microalgal growth and morphology</title><p><italic>Microcystis</italic> cells are spherical or sub-spherical in shape and are enveloped by a layer of uniform, non-layered, transparent and colorless glue at different stages (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). As the culture time increased, the size of the cells also tended to increase. Both strains of <italic>Microcystis</italic> exhibited the similar growth rate. <italic>Microcystis wesenbergii</italic> exhibited a higher growth rate during the early stage of logarithmic growth, whereas <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic> exhibited a higher the growth rate during the late logarithmic growth stage. These findings indicated that both strains of <italic>Microcystis</italic> possess relatively strong competitiveness. The SSA and CSV of both strains of <italic>Microcystis</italic> decreased with culture time (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1D</xref>). For <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic>, the SSA decreased from 4902.95 to 710.27 m<sup>2</sup> g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (a decrease of 85.5%) and for <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic>, the SSA decreased from 5963.65 to 1532.95 m<sup>2</sup> g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (a decrease of 74.3%). The CSV decreased by 16.5 and 10.7% for <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> and <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic>, respectively. These results highlight the significant influence of biomass on SSA.</p><fig position="float" id="fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Growth and morphology of <italic>Microcystis</italic>. <bold>(A)</bold>
<italic>Microcystis wesenbergii</italic>. <bold>(B)</bold>
<italic>Microcystis aeruginosa</italic>. <bold>(C)</bold> Growth curves of <italic>Microcystis</italic>. <bold>(D)</bold> Key cell characterization data for <italic>Microcystis</italic>. L, Logarithmic phase; S, Stationary phases.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-14-1285229-g001" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec16"><label>3.1.2</label><title>Cell surface hydrophobicity</title><p><xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref> illustrates the hydrophobicity of <italic>Microcystis</italic> in different solvents, namely hexane (a non-polar solvent), ethyl acetate (a polar alkaline solvent), and chloroform (a polar acidic solvent). In polar solvents, the hydrophobicity of <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> increased with culture time, while in polar alkaline solvents, the hydrophobicity decreased. On the other hand, the hydrophobicity of <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic> showed the opposite trend. During the logarithmic phase, the hydrophobicity of <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> in non-polar solvents was significantly lower than that of <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic>. However, during the stationary phase, the hydrophobicity of <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> in non-polar solvents was significantly higher than that of <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic>. Additionally, <italic>Microcystis</italic> had a lower affinity for chloroform (a polar acidic solvent) compared to ethyl acetate (a polar alkaline solvent). The hydrophobicity of <italic>Microcystis</italic> cell surface in hexane was less than 50%, indicating that the cell surface of <italic>Microcystis</italic> was hydrophilic.</p><fig position="float" id="fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>The hydrophobicity of the <italic>Microcystis</italic> cells under different growth phases.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-14-1285229-g002" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec17"><label>3.1.3</label><title>Contact angle and surface free energy</title><p>Contact angle and surface free energy could directly influence the hydrophobicity. As shown in <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, the contact angles with water (&#x003b8;<sub>W</sub>), formamide (&#x003b8;<sub>F</sub>), and diiodomethane (&#x003b8;<sub>D</sub>) on <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> increased with culture time. For <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic>, &#x003b8;<sub>w</sub> increased with culture time, while &#x003b8;<sub>F</sub> and &#x003b8;<sub>D</sub> decreased. During the logarithmic phase, &#x003b8;<sub>w</sub> on <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> was significantly higher than that of <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic>, whereas &#x003b8;<sub>F</sub> and &#x003b8;<sub>D</sub> on <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> were significantly lower than those on <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic>. Conversely, during the stationary phase, &#x003b8;<sub>w</sub> on <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> was not significantly different from that on <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic>, but &#x003b8;<sub>F</sub> and &#x003b8;<sub>D</sub> were significantly higher. In conclusion, the water contact angles on <italic>Microcystis</italic> were always less than 90&#x000b0;. Additionally, the change of &#x003b8;<sub>W</sub> in <italic>Microcystis</italic> from logarithmic phase to stationary phase was more than that of other algal strains (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 6</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Contact angles and surface physicochemical properties determined for cyanobacteria.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Contact angles of the probe liquids (&#x000b0;)</th><th align="center" valign="top" colspan="6" rowspan="1">Free energy components (mJ m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>)</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zeta (mV)</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Microalgae stain</th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b8;<sub>w</sub></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b8;<sub>F</sub></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b8;<sub>D</sub></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b3;<sub>s</sub><sup>LW</sup></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b3;<sub>s</sub><sup>AB</sup></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b3;<sub>s</sub></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b3;<sub>s</sub><sup>+</sup></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b3;<sub>s</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x00394;G<sub>coh</sub></th><th align="center" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b6;</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">References</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Microcystis wesenbergii</italic> (L)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.2</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;12.07&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> (S)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.8</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;11.93&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.57</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Microcystis aeruginosa</italic> (L)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.6</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;11.32&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M. aeruginosa</italic> (S)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.2</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.5</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;11.85&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.21</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">This study</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>M. aeruginosa</italic> LEGE 91344 (L)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.5</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.6</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.4</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.7</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.8</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.6</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.6</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.4&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;15.5</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Gon&#x000e7;alves et al. (2015)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>S. salina</italic> LEGE 06079 (L)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;8.0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.1</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.8</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.2</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;10.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.6</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Synechococcus</italic> sp. ATCC 27184 (L)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.3</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.3</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.7</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.9</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;32.2</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">Ozkan and Berberoglu (2013)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>A. variabilis</italic> ATCC 29413 (L)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">114</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;94.9</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;16.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>A. variabilis</italic> (S)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.5</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.1 a</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3 b</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.19</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.19</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.47</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;55.85</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;11.00</td><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Hao et al. (2017)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Synechocystis</italic> sp.</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.3</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.2</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.4</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.2</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">Volpe and Siboni (1997)</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>A. variabilis</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">37</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="center" valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;100.3</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>A</sup>contact angle with glycol; <sup>b</sup>contact angle with glycerol; L, Logarithmic phase; S, Stationary phases; &#x003b8;<sub>W</sub>, contact angle with water; &#x003b8;<sub>F</sub>, contact angle with formamide; &#x003b8;<sub>D</sub>, contact angle with diiodomethane; &#x003b3;<sub>s</sub><sup>LW</sup>, Lifshitz-van der Waals component of the surface free energy; &#x003b3;<sub>s</sub><sup>AB</sup>, Lewis acid&#x02013;base component of the surface free energy; &#x003b3;<sub>s</sub>, surface free energy; &#x003b3;<sub>s</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup>, electron donor component; &#x003b3;<sub>s</sub><sup>+</sup>, electron acceptor component; &#x00394;G<sub>coh</sub>, the free energy of cohesion; AB, refers to acid&#x02013;base, i.e., polar component; LW, refers to Lifshitz-van der Waals, i.e., dispersive component; +, refers to electron acceptor parameter; &#x02212;, refers to electron donor parameter; &#x003be;, Zeta potential (mV).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>According to <xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr">van Oss (1993)</xref>, microalgae cells were considered hydrophobic when &#x003b3;<sub>s</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup>&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;28.3 mJ m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> or &#x00394;G<sub>coh</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0, and hydrophilic when &#x003b3;<sub>s</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;28.3 mJ m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup> or &#x00394;G<sub>coh</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0. <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> shows that the surface of <italic>Microcystis</italic> cells was hydrophilic, which was not directly related to the culture stage. The &#x00394;G<sub>coh</sub> of <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> and <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic> decreased with culture time, indicating that cells tended to gather into colonies during the stationary phase. In this phase, the hydrophobicity degree of <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> (high &#x00394;G<sub>coh</sub> value) was significantly higher than that of <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic>. However, the change pattern of hydrophilicity reversed in the logarithmic phase. In terms of &#x003b3;<sub>s</sub>, the &#x003b3;<sub>s</sub> values of <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic> increased with culture time, while the &#x003b3;<sub>s</sub> values of <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> decreased. Moreover, the &#x003b3;<sub>s</sub> values of both strains of <italic>Microcystis</italic> during the stationary phase were smaller than those during the logarithmic phase. The surface free energy of <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic> was lower than that of <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> during the logarithmic phase. However, during the stationary phase, the opposite was observed. The nonpolar surface free energy (&#x003b3;<sub>s</sub><sup>LW</sup>) of <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic> remained constant throughout the culture time, with no significant difference in &#x003b3;<sub>s</sub><sup>LW</sup> between <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> and <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic>. These findings suggest that the overall surface free energy and adhesion free energy of <italic>Microcystis</italic> are determined by the polar surface free energy. Additionally, the <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 6</xref> shown that <italic>Microcystis</italic> differed significantly from other algal strains in &#x00394;Gcoh and zeta. However, the surface of colonial <italic>Microcystis</italic> cells was hydrophobic (&#x00394;G<sub>coh</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0; <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 7</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec18"><label>3.1.4</label><title>Physical intercellular interactions</title><p>The surface charge of microalgae is an important characteristic of the cell surface. The zeta potential, which refers to the potential of the shear layer on the surface of charged particles, is widely used to describe the electrostatic interaction between colloidal particles and is an important indicator of the stability of colloidal systems. The surface charge of microalgae is influenced by the surface structure and EPS of the cells (<xref rid="ref64" ref-type="bibr">Zheng et al., 2019</xref>). Microalgal cells produce a significant amount of proteins and sugars both inside and outside the cell membrane, leading to an increase in the negative charges of microalgae. This increase in the absolute value of zeta potential enhances the electrostatic repulsion between microalgae cells, making it difficult for them to coagulate and promoting a more even distribution in the medium. Therefore, the absolute value of the zeta potential can serve as an indicator of the stability of the cell suspension.</p><p><xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref> shown the zeta potential of <italic>Microcystis</italic> cells at different growth stages and pH levels. The zeta potentials of <italic>Microcystis</italic> were consistently negative throughout different growth stages, indicating the presence of negative charges. Additionally, according to the theory of electric double layer structure (<xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Felix et al., 2014</xref>), the binding of OH<sup>&#x02212;</sup> ions (and/or release of H<sup>+</sup> ions) is the main mechanism for charging the particle surface. The negative charges initially increased and then remained stable as the pH levels increased. And, the negative charges of <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic> and <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> showed no significant change (&#x02212;11.32~&#x02212;12.07) from the logarithmic phase to the stationary phase. Thus, the negative charges of <italic>Microcystis</italic> remain relatively stable and do not vary with the duration of growth. Furthermore, there was no significant difference in the zeta potential between these both strains of <italic>Microcystis</italic> (<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05). However, the absolute value of zeta was higher in the colonial <italic>Microcystis</italic> compared to the unicellular cells. Additionally, the absolute value of zeta in <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> was slightly higher than that in <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic>.</p><fig position="float" id="fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>The zeta potential of <italic>Microcystis</italic> under different growth phases <bold>(A)</bold>, and pH <bold>(B)</bold>. L, Logarithmic phase; S, Stationary phases.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-14-1285229-g003" position="float"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="sec19"><label>3.2</label><title>Cell surface functional groups under different growth stage</title><p>Cell surface functional groups were analyzed using ATR-FTIR spectroscopy (<xref rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr">Ferro et al., 2019</xref>). There were no marked differences in the spectra characteristic bands of strains corresponding to lipids, including&#x02014;CH<sub>3</sub>, CH<sub>2</sub>, C&#x02013;H functional groups [3,050&#x02013;2,800 and 1,480&#x02013;1,330 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<xref rid="ref47" ref-type="bibr">Wood et al., 2008</xref>)], carbohydrates, including C&#x02013;O&#x02013;C, C&#x02013;OH, and P&#x02013;O&#x02013;P functional groups [1,200&#x02013;950 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr">Castro et al., 2010</xref>)], nucleic acid backbone conformations, including P=O [1,250&#x02013;1,000 and 1,000&#x02013;800 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>(<xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr">Liu Y. K. et al., 2016</xref>)], and amide I, II, and III, including NH, C&#x02013;N, C=O [1,660&#x02013;1,500 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, 1,385&#x02013;1,300 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">Yee et al., 2004</xref>)].</p><p>The absorption peaks of various functional groups on the surface of <italic>Microcystis</italic> cells were observed within the spectral ranges of 918&#x02013;1,737 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> and 2,855&#x02013;3,304 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>). Comparatively, the absorption peaks of groups in the stationary phase were stronger than those in the logarithmic phase, indicating the presence of more functional groups involved in cell aggregation during the stationary phase. Notably, the increase in absorption peaks of all groups on <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic> during the stationary phase was significantly higher than that on <italic>M. wesenbergii.</italic> The absorption peak of the O&#x02013;H group on <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> remained unchanged throughout the growth stages, whereas the absorption peak of the O&#x02013;H functional group on <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic> during the stationary phase was significantly higher than that during the logarithmic phase. Additionally, the content of functional groups on <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic> was lower than that on <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic>, with a reversed stability period (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Table 1</xref>). These results showed that more O&#x02013;H functional groups were present on <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic> cell surface during the stationary phase, which could result in a more negatively charged cell surface. This enhanced negative charge would promote the adsorption of metal ions in the solution, leading to the colony formation. The absorption peak of alkyl group (CH<sub>2</sub>/CH<sub>3</sub> vibrations) on <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> remained by the growth stage. However, in the case of <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic>, the alkyl absorption peak during the stationary phase was significantly higher compared to the logarithmic phase. During the logarithmic phase, the alkyl group on <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic> was lower than that on <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic>, whereas the opposite was observed during the stationary phase. The alkyl group plays a crucial role as the primary hydrophobic component. Although the entire cell surface is hydrophilic, the decrease in hydrophilicity during the stationary phase may be attributed to the increased presence of alkyl groups. The absorption peaks of carbonyl groups (C=O) were predominantly observed at 1,622&#x02013;1,657 and 1,685&#x02013;1,789 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. The range of 1,622&#x02013;1,657 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> could be assigned to the C=O double-bond stretching vibration in the amide I band, while the range of 1,685&#x02013;1,789 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> corresponds to the C=O bond stretching vibration in the free carboxyl group. Peaks representing C&#x02013;N/N&#x02013;H group were present at 1,622&#x02013;1,657 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, which were associated with the amide II band. Peaks representing P=O double-bond asymmetric stretching were observed at 1,239 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, and are characteristic of nucleic acid or phosphorylated polysaccharides. The absorption peaks corresponding to the C&#x02013;O&#x02013;C, C&#x02013;O&#x02013;P, and P&#x02013;O&#x02013;P ring vibrations of polysaccharides were mainly observed in the range of 900&#x02013;1,200 cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, which can be attributed to the mixed peaks of carbohydrates. These changes are similar to the alterations observed in the aforementioned alkyl and OH groups.</p><fig position="float" id="fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>ATR-FTIR spectrum of <italic>Microcystis wesenbergii</italic> and <italic>Microcystis aeruginosa</italic> under different growth phases.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-14-1285229-g004" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec20"><label>3.3</label><title>EPS and monosaccharide composition</title><p>EPS, a viscous substance produced by cyanobacteria cells, serves as a protective barrier against the external environment, such as drought resistance, high salt resistance, ultraviolet radiation resistance, colony formation, and protozoan predation (<xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">Pereira et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr">Sun et al., 2020</xref>). The dominance of polysaccharide content in EPS was shown in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5A</xref>. The EPS content of <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> decreased significantly with culture time, while the EPS content of <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic> increased significantly. Moreover, during the logarithmic phase, the EPS content of <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> was significantly higher than that of <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic>, but this trend reversed during the stationary phase. These observations aligned with changes in cell surface free energy and surface functional groups, but contradicts the law of cell adhesion free energy. In term of EPS fraction (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 4</xref>), the neutral fraction of CPS in <italic>Microcystis</italic> cells decreased with culture time, while acidic fractions increased, mainly acidic I polymers. Additionally, the proportion of acidic fraction in EPS was higher during the stationary phase. The main monosaccharide components of the both <italic>Microcystis</italic> strains (<xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5B</xref>; <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 8</xref>) include alduronic acid, glucose, arabinose, and galactose. The glucuronic acid abundance of EPS in <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> increased with culture time, whereas decreased in <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic>. Furthermore, the glucuronic acid abundance of EPS in <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> was significantly higher than that in <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic> during the logarithmic phase, but becomes equal during the stationary phase. On the other hand, the galacturonic acid concentration increased with culture time in both strains of <italic>Microcystis</italic>. However, the content of galacturonic acid in <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> consistently remained lower than that in <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic>, regardless of the growth phase.</p><fig position="float" id="fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>EPS contents <bold>(A)</bold> and monosaccharide composition contents of EPS <bold>(B)</bold> for <italic>Microcystis</italic> at different growth phases. GluA, glucuronic acid; GalA, galacturonic acid; Xyl, xylose; Rha, rhamnose; Man, mannose; Glu, glucose; Gal, galactose; Fuc, Fucose; Fru, fructose; Ara, arabinose. L, Logarithmic phase; S, Stationary phases.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-14-1285229-g005" position="float"/></fig><p><xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure 5B</xref> demonstrated that the total uronic acid content was notably higher during the stationary phase compared to the logarithmic phase. Furthermore, the uronic acid content in <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> consistently remained lower than that in <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic>. Conversely, the glucose and arabinose contents of EPS during the stable period were significantly lower than those during the logarithmic period. Moreover, the glucose and arabinose contents of EPS in <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> consistently remained higher than those in <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic>, which contradicted the trend observed for uronic acid. The galactose content of EPS in <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> increased with culture time, while decreased in <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic>. Moreover, the galactose content in <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> during the logarithmic phase was significantly higher than that in <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic>. In the stationary phase, the proportion of galactose in both <italic>Microcystis</italic> strains was identical, reflecting the change observed in glucuronic acid. In summary, as the culture time, the monosaccharides that significantly decreased were glucose and arabinose, while galacturonic acid showed a significant increase. Additionally, glucuronic acid and galactose increased in <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> but decreased in <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="sec21"><label>3.4</label><title>Interrelationship of EPS and functional groups with cell surface properties</title><p>The relationship between the characteristics of EPS (including content, composition, and functional groups) and the cell surface properties of <italic>Microcystis</italic> (such as SSA, charges, surface free energy, surface tension, and hydrophobicity) was depicted in <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>. Regarding hydrophobicity, the surface hydrophobicity of <italic>Microcystis</italic> was found to be negatively correlated with EPS content, mainly due to the protein content in EPS. This suggests a higher abundance of hydrophilic amino acids in the protein, along with the arabinose and glucose concentrations in EPS, as well as O&#x02013;H and P&#x02013;O&#x02013;P groups (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 9</xref>). On the other hand, the surface hydrophobicity of <italic>Microcystis</italic> showed a significant positive correlation with xylose, glucuronic acid, and fructose. Notably, <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> exhibited a significant positive correlation between hydrophobicity and most functional groups, whereas <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic> displayed the opposite trend. Finally, two hydrophilic groups, O&#x02013;H and P&#x02013;O&#x02013;P, were identified as key factors influencing the hydrophobicity of <italic>Microcystis</italic>, with P&#x02013;O&#x02013;P primarily found in lipopolysaccharides.</p><fig position="float" id="fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>The relation between cell surface characterization and EPS content, composition and functional groups for <italic>Microcystis</italic>. EPS-C, the carbohydrate content in EPS; EPS-P, the protein content in EPS. CPS-W, neutral part in CPS; CPS-1M, acidic I polymers in CPS; CPS-2M, acidic II polymers in CPS. &#x003b8;<sub>W</sub>, contact angle with water; &#x003b8;<sub>F</sub>, contact angle with formamide; &#x003b8;<sub>D</sub>, contact angle with diiodomethane; &#x003b3;<sub>s</sub><sup>LW</sup>, Lifshitz-van der Waals component of the surface free energy; &#x003b3;<sub>s</sub><sup>AB</sup>, Lewis acid&#x02013;base component of the surface free energy; &#x003b3;<sub>s</sub>, surface free energy; &#x003b3;<sub>s</sub><sup>&#x02212;</sup>, electron donor component; &#x003b3;<sub>s</sub><sup>+</sup>, electron acceptor component; &#x00394;G<sub>coh</sub>, the free energy of cohesion; AB, refers to acid&#x02013;base, i.e., polar component; LW, refers to Lifshitz-van der Waals, i.e., dispersive component; +, refers to electron acceptor parameter; &#x02212;, refers to electron donor parameter; &#x003be;, Zeta potential (mV).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fmicb-14-1285229-g006" position="float"/></fig><p>The SSA of <italic>Microcystis</italic> showed a significant positive correlation with the polysaccharide content in EPS and neutral fraction of CPS, as well as with arabinose and galactose concentrations in EPS. Meanwhile, SSA of <italic>Microcystis</italic> exhibited a significant negative correlation with most relevant functional groups and acidic fractions of CPS, as well as with the presence of rhamnose and mannose. The relationship between the surface tension of <italic>Microcystis</italic> and the protein content in EPS, as well as the most relevant functional groups, was found to be significantly positive. On the other hand, there were significant negative correlations with the monosaccharide composition of fructose, xylose, and glucuronic acid. The adhesion free energy of <italic>Microcystis</italic> and G<sup>TOT</sup> showed a significant positive correlation with the polysaccharide content in EPS, as well as with the monosaccharide composition of fructose, galactose, xylose, and glucuronic acid. On the other hand, there was a significant negative correlation with rhamnose and most functional groups. Therefore, the presence of polysaccharides in EPS primarily influenced the SSA and total surface energy of <italic>Microcystis</italic> cells, while proteins in EPS influenced hydrophobicity and surface tension. Glucuronic acid, xylose, and fructose in the polysaccharide composition mainly impacted the surface properties. The hydrophilic groups O&#x02013;H and P&#x02013;O&#x02013;P were identified as key factors influencing the hydrophobicity of <italic>Microcystis</italic>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec22"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p><italic>Microcystis</italic> sp. is a unicellular microorganism with remarkable phenotypic plasticity, which frequently causes the formation of colonies and algal blooms in lakes and reservoirs worldwide (<xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">Xiao et al., 2018</xref>). In addition to particular adaptation characteristics like buoyancy regulation, cell surface charge and hydrophobicity, notably EPS, also play a role in the development of <italic>Microcystis</italic> colonies or blooms. Additionally, different morphologies of <italic>Microcystis</italic> can result in successional blooms in lakes. This begs the question of how <italic>Microcystis</italic> achieves a competitive edge.</p><sec id="sec23"><label>4.1</label><title>Physico-chemical surface properties of <italic>Microcystis</italic></title><p>In terms of cell growth, size and morphology, <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> had a higher growth rate in the pre-logarithmic phase and a lower growth rate in the late-logarithmic phase. Additionally, biomass had a significant impact on SSA. The SSA of <italic>Microcystis</italic> was 50 times more than that of the unicellular <italic>Synechococcus</italic> sp. (76 and 88 m<sup>2</sup> g<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; <xref rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr">Dittrich and Sibler, 2005</xref>). The CSV values of the two <italic>Microcystis</italic> strains were similar to those reported by <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Henderson R. et al. (2008)</xref>, indicating that the large SSA can enhance the ability of <italic>Microcystis</italic> to adsorb substances in the liquid phase (<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr">Cheng et al., 2019</xref>). The SSA was widely recognized as an initial parameter for evaluating the flocculation potential. In the context of <italic>Microcystis</italic> removal through flocculation, a higher SSA value indicates a greater demand for flocculant dosage (<xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Henderson R. et al., 2008</xref>). The analysis of contact angle, adhesion free energy, and surface free energy (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) revealed that both strains of <italic>Microcystis</italic> cultivated in the laboratory exhibit hydrophilic characteristics. However, there were noticeable variations in hydrophobicity between <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> and <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic>, especially in the composition of the non-polar region of the cell surface. The discrepancy may contribute to the differential occurrence of <italic>Microcystis</italic> blooms in different seasons. Notably, during the logarithmic phase, the contact angles of <italic>Microcystis</italic> with solvent were smaller than that of <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic> LEGE 91344 (less than 90&#x000b0;; <xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Gon&#x000e7;alves et al., 2015</xref>), and <italic>A. variabilis</italic> (greater than 90&#x000b0;; <xref rid="ref45" ref-type="bibr">Volpe and Siboni, 1997</xref>; <xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">Ozkan and Berberoglu, 2013</xref>; <xref rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr">Hao et al., 2017</xref>). Compared with other freshwater cyanobacteria, <italic>S. salina</italic> LEGE 06079, <italic>Synechocystis</italic> sp., and <italic>A. variabilis</italic> are all hydrophobic (<xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><p>Cell-to-cell interactions can be evaluated using the free energy of adhesion (&#x00394;G<sub>coh</sub>; <xref rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr">Yu et al., 2018</xref>), which measures the change in free energy before and after adhesion. A higher &#x00394;Gcoh suggest a weaker adhesion effect, indicating a stronger repulsive force (or higher mutual absorption) between cells. In this study, <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> exhibited a lower free energy of adhesion during the logarithmic phase, leading to a higher likelihood of adsorbing substrate and cells. Similarly, <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic> exhibited a lower free energy of adhesion during the stationary phase, making it more prone to adsorb substrate and cells. Both species displayed distinct competitive advantages in this study.</p><p>In this study, the zeta potential of <italic>Microcystis</italic> cells remained negative during throughout the cultivation stage and under different pH conditions. This finding is consistent with previous studies on various algal strains, including eukaryotic freshwater single-celled green algae and cyanobacteria (<xref rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr">Gon&#x000e7;alves et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr">Xia et al., 2016</xref>), marine green algae and diatoms (<xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">Ozkan and Berberoglu, 2013</xref>), and field <italic>Microcystis</italic> algae (<xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">Liu L. et al., 2016</xref>). These findings further support the notion that <italic>Microcystis</italic> cells can maintain a stable electronegativity, and that the electrostatic interactions can promote the surface adhesion of cells and metal cations to <italic>Microcystis</italic> cells. However, <xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr">Liu L. et al. (2016)</xref> observed that the absolute value of the zeta potential on the cell surface of <italic>Microcystis</italic> algae was higher during the stationary phase compared to the logarithmic phase, and this difference was influenced by pH. Nonetheless, no significant difference in the absolute values of the zeta potential was observed between the two algal strains during the cultivation period (pH range of from 7 to 8).</p></sec><sec id="sec24"><label>4.2</label><title>EPS and functional groups of <italic>Microcystis</italic></title><p>The cell surface functional groups of <italic>Microcystis</italic> were determined by the composition and content of EPS secreted by the cells. Ionizable functional groups in EPS, such as carboxyl, phosphorus, amino, and hydroxyl groups, can serve as binding sites for divalent cations. These functional groups play a crucial role in determining the properties of the cell surface (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Bhunia et al., 2018</xref>). The content of hydrophilic groups (including amino groups, hydroxyl groups, carboxyl groups, sulfonic acid groups, aldehyde groups, and phosphoric acid groups) increased during the stationary phase. Similarly, the hydrophobic groups (including hydrocarbon groups, ester groups, and alkanes) also undergo similar changes. These results indicated that the hydrophilicity of the both <italic>Microcystis</italic> strains decreased with culture time. Therefore, the hydrophobic groups play a significant role in the change of hydrophilicity of the algal strains during the culture time. <xref rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr">Pringle and Fletcher (1983)</xref> demonstrated that an increase in the surface hydrophobicity of microorganisms promoted their mutual approach, facilitating adsorption between microorganisms or with adsorption carriers. In our study, the hydrophobic group contents of <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic> were significantly lower than those of <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> during the logarithmic phase. However, this trend reversed during the stationary phase, with <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> exhibiting lower adhesion free energy during the logarithmic phase, making cells easier to adsorb matrix and cells. Conversely, <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic> had lower free adhesion energy during the stationary phase, making cells easier to adsorb matrix and cells. These findings suggested that both strains of <italic>Microcystis</italic> have competitive advantages at different growth stages.</p><p>The types of EPS components, such as uronic acid, phosphate, and sulfate (P=O functional group, <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>), along with unique connection to sugar groups, give EPS important characteristics (<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr">Bhunia et al., 2018</xref>). Uronic acids, phosphates, and acetylated sugars primarily contribute to the overall negative charge of EPS, which give EPS its binding and adsorption properties (<xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Gupta and Diwan, 2017</xref>). During the stationary phase, the concentration of uronic acid significantly increased, usually in the form of glycosidic bonds. Additionally, the EPS monosaccharide profiles in <italic>Microcystis</italic> were influenced by different culture conditions of distinct algal strains (<xref rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr">Forni et al., 1997</xref>). However, the polysaccharide content in EPS consistently exceeds that of protein in EPS (<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">Costa et al., 2018</xref>). Notably, galacturonic acid was prevalent in <italic>M. flos-aquae</italic>. Among the neutral sugars, fucose, mannose, rhamnose, glucose, uronic acid, and xylose are present in the EPS of <italic>M. flos-aquae</italic>, <italic>M. viridis</italic>, and <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic>, while <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> contains only uronic acid (<xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">Le et al., 2022</xref>). The variation in growth rate and the variability in EPS content could potentially shed light on the seasonal succession of <italic>Microcystis</italic>. This may also explain why <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic> blooms were both the larger and last longer in the lake, as well as its predominance in terms of abundance and frequency (<xref rid="ref58" ref-type="bibr">Zhai et al., 2013</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec25"><label>4.3</label><title>Determinants of surface properties of <italic>Microcystis</italic></title><p>The protein content in EPS of unicellular <italic>Microcystis</italic> was hydrophilic in this study. Previous research have shown that an increase in C&#x02212;(O, N) group content indicated the presence of polysaccharides, which can reduce cell hydrophobicity and increase cell surface energy. Conversely, an increase in C&#x02212;(C, H) group content indicated the presence of hydrocarbons, which can increase cell hydrophobicity and decrease cell surface energy. Other studies have also demonstrated a relationship between the abundance of phosphodiester-linked and the exposure of hydrophobic regions on the cell surface (<xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr">Masuoka and Hazen, 1997</xref>). In this study, it was found that the C&#x02212;(O, N) group could effectively reduced the hydrophobicity of <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic>, but had no impact on the hydrophobicity of <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic>. Meanwhile, the C&#x02212;(C, H) group increased the hydrophobicity of <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic>, but did not have the same effect on <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic>. These findings suggest that the changes in hydrophobicity during different growth stages vary between <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> and <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic>, and the functional groups involved in these changes also differ. Furthermore, as depicted in <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary Figure 5</xref>, the O&#x02013;H and P&#x02013;O&#x02013;P groups are shown to play a significant role in influencing the hydrophobicity of <italic>Microcystis</italic>.</p><p>The surface free energy of microorganisms is a reflection of the intermolecular force on the surface of microorganisms. It provides insight into the inherent characteristics of microorganisms and serves as a measure of the adhesion between cells and substrates or between cells themselves. Changes in cell surface components and chemical groups can result in alterations in cell free energy. Various substances [such as protein, peptidoglycan, teichoic acid, lipopolysaccharide, EPS, etc. (<xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al., 2011</xref>; <xref rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr">Li et al., 2014</xref>)] facilitate the interaction of the cell surface with other substances through Lewis acid&#x02013;base interactions, electrostatic interactions, and hydrophobic interactions. These interactions ultimately influence cell adhesion. Among these components, EPS has been found to have the most significant impact, as supported by numerous studies. For example, EPS can inhibit the adhesion of <italic>Rhodococcus</italic>, while the protein-rich EPS on the surfaces of strains <italic>Sphingobium</italic> and <italic>Micrococcus</italic> has minimal effect on bacterial adhesion to silicone oil (<xref rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr">Iwabuchi et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="ref62" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2011</xref>). <xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr">Sheng and Yu (2006)</xref> demonstrated a positive correlation between the &#x003b3;<sub>b</sub><sup>AB</sup> and &#x003b3;b of <italic>Rhodopseudomonas acidophila</italic> with EPS content, as well as a positive correlation with protein/polysaccharide content. In our study, we also observed positive correlations between the &#x003b3;<sub>s</sub><sup>AB</sup> and &#x003b3;<sub>s</sub> values and the EPS content on <italic>Microcystis</italic>. Additionally, we found positive correlations between the &#x003b3;<sub>s</sub><sup>AB</sup> and &#x003b3;<sub>s</sub> values and the polysaccharide content in EPS on <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic>, as well as a positive correlation with the protein content in EPS on <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic>. Previous studies have already demonstrated the impact of EPS on the formation of <italic>Microcystis</italic> blooms (<xref rid="ref60" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al., 2018</xref>; <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr">Le et al., 2022</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec26"><label>4.4</label><title>Determinants of surface properties on colony formation and the contribution of <italic>Microcystis</italic> ecology</title><p><xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">Xiao et al. (2017)</xref> demonstrated that <italic>Microcystis</italic> colonies formation involves two mechanisms: cell division formation (e.g., <italic>M. ichthyoblabe</italic> colonies formation), and cell adhesion (e.g., <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> colonies formation). However, cell adhesion leads to faster colony formation. The surface properties of <italic>Microcystis</italic>, such as zeta potential, hydrophobicity, and EPS, play a crucial role in cell adhesion. These properties have a significant impact on the morphology, structure, and function of cyanobacterial colonies (<xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr">Devasia et al., 1993</xref>). Algal cell surface have a negatively charged (zeta &#x0003c; 0), making somewhat hydrophobicity. In the field of <italic>Microcystis</italic> removal, cations are commonly employed as flocculants, due to neutralize the negative surface charge of <italic>Microcystis</italic>. Therefore, Zeta potential as an important index to characterize the surface charge has been applied in wastewater treatment (<xref rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr">Henderson R. K. et al., 2008</xref>). Furthermore, cations are a factor in the colony formation of <italic>Microcystis</italic>. In addition to neutralize the negative surface charge, divalent Ca<sup>2+</sup> and Mg<sup>2+</sup> exhibited a strong binding capability with phenolic &#x02212;OH, aromatic C&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;C, and polysaccharide C&#x02009;&#x02212;&#x02009;O groups to promote forming colonies (<xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr">Masumoto et al., 2023</xref>). Thus, EPS plays a crucial role in population formation, especially TB-EPS (<xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2014</xref>). Meanwhile, a study indicated that most organic matters were located in the TB&#x02013;EPS (<xref rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr">Xu et al., 2013</xref>). This finding aligns with the results of our study, which also observed a higher content of bEPS compared to sEPS, particularly in terms of polysaccharides. <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">Duan et al. (2022)</xref> further explain that the protein component of EPS has a negative effect on colony formation, while the sugar component has a positive effect.</p><p>The surface properties of colonial <italic>Microcystis</italic> differ from those of unicellular <italic>Microcystis</italic>, and the colonial <italic>Microcystis</italic> cells produce more EPS, which is more conducive to the stabilization of the colonies. Additionally, when <italic>Microcystis</italic> cells form a colony, various environmental factors can influence the physical and chemical properties of the colony. For instance, light and temperature not only impact the photosynthesis of <italic>Microcystis</italic> cells, but also influence parameters such as dissolved oxygen (DO), pH, and Eh (oxidation&#x02013;reduction potential) of the colony. Then, these factors affect the buoyancy of the colony, where Eh represents the Zeta potential of the colony (<xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">Fang et al., 2014</xref>). Additionally, influencing factors (nutrient limits and turbulent shear) can induce structural changes within the colonies, enabling to acquire survival strategies (<xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr">Feng et al., 2020</xref>). This study further elucidates that EPS influences the SSA, hydrophobicity, and surface free energy, thereby affecting the formation of <italic>Microcystis</italic> bloom colonies and the efficiency of algal cell collection.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec27"><label>5</label><title>Conclusion</title><p>This study examines the factors that influence the physico-chemical surface properties of <italic>Microcystis</italic>, including EPS polysaccharides, monosaccharide composition and functional groups. The polysaccharide in EPS primarily impacts the surface area and total surface energy of <italic>Microcystis</italic> cells, while the protein in EPS affects hydrophobicity and surface tension. The composition of EPS, specifically glucuronic acid, xylose, and fructose, plays a significant role in determining surface properties. Additionally, during the stationary phase, the content of hydrophilic groups (including amino groups, hydroxyl groups, carboxyl groups, sulfonic acid groups, aldehyde groups, and phosphoric acid groups) increased. Similarly, the hydrophobic groups (including hydrocarbon groups, ester groups, and alkanes) also exhibited similar changes. The hydrophilic group O&#x02013;H and P&#x02013;O&#x02013;P were identified as key groups that influence the hydrophobicity of <italic>Microcystis.</italic> Variations in growth rate, surface properties, and EPS between <italic>M. wesenbergii</italic> and <italic>M. aeruginosa</italic> provide a competitive advantage.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="sec28"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material</xref>, further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding author.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="sec29"><title>Author contributions</title><p>HY: Formal analysis, Writing &#x02013; original draft, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing, Data curation, Software. DW: Data curation, Writing &#x02013; original draft. HL: Supervision, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing. CH: Conceptualization, Funding acquisition, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors would like to thank Yanxia Zuo at The Analysis and Testing Center of Institute of Hydrobiology, Chinese Academy of Sciences for her assistance with monosaccharide composition analysis.</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="sec31"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="sec100"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec32"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>The Supplementary material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fmicb.2023.1285229/full#supplementary-material" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fmicb.2023.1285229/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material id="SM1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barros</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goncalves</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Simoes</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Microalgal/cyanobacterial biofilm formation on selected surfaces: the effects of surface physicochemical properties and culture media composition</article-title>. <source>J. Appl. Phycol.</source>
<volume>31</volume>, <fpage>375</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>387</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10811-018-1582-3</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bhunia</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prasad Uday</surname><given-names>U. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oinam</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mondal</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bandyopadhyay</surname><given-names>T. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiwari</surname><given-names>O. N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Characterization, genetic regulation and production of cyanobacterial exopolysaccharides and its applicability for heavy metal removal</article-title>. <source>Carbohydr. Polym.</source>
<volume>179</volume>, <fpage>228</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>243</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.carbpol.2017.09.091</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29111047</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>F. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sedman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Asadishad</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tufenkji</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Effect of dissolved oxygen on two bacterial pathogens examined using ATR-FTIR spectroscopy, microelectrophoresis, and potentiometric titration</article-title>. <source>Environ. Sci. Technol.</source>
<volume>44</volume>, <fpage>4136</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4141</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/es903692u</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20438073</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kennes</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Differences of cell surface characteristics between the bacterium <italic>pseudomonas veronii</italic> and fungus <italic>Ophiostoma stenoceras</italic> and their different adsorption properties to hydrophobic organic compounds</article-title>. <source>Sci. Total Environ.</source>
<volume>650</volume>, <fpage>2095</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2106</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.09.337</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30290351</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>O. Y. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Raaijmakers</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuramae</surname><given-names>E. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Microbial extracellular polymeric substances: ecological function and impact on soil aggregation</article-title>. <source>Front. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1636</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.01636</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30083145</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Philippis</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Exocellular polysaccharides from cyanobacteria and their possible applications</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol. Rev.</source>
<volume>22</volume>, <fpage>151</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>175</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/s0168-6445(98)00012-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Devasia</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Natarajan</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sathyanarayana</surname><given-names>D. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Surface chemistry of <italic>Thiobacillus ferrooxidans</italic> relevant to adhesion on mineral surfaces</article-title>. <source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>59</volume>, <fpage>4051</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4055</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/aem.59.12.4051-4055.1993</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16349107</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dittrich</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sibler</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Cell surface groups of two picocyanobacteria strains studied by zeta potential investigations, potentiometric titration, and infrared spectroscopy</article-title>. <source>J. Colloid Interface Sci.</source>
<volume>286</volume>, <fpage>487</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>495</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcis.2005.01.029</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15897062</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2022</year>). <article-title>Key physiological traits and chemical properties of extracellular polymeric substances determining colony formation in a cyanobacterium</article-title>. <source>J. Oceanol. Limnol.</source>
<volume>40</volume>, <fpage>1720</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1731</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00343-022-1353-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>DO, pH, and eh microprofiles in cyanobacterial granules from Lake Taihu under different environmental conditions</article-title>. <source>J. Appl. Phycol.</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>1689</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1699</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10811-013-0211-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Felix</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yaroshchuk</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasupathi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollet</surname><given-names>B. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bondarenko</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovalchuk</surname><given-names>V. I.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Electrophoresis and stability of nano-colloids: history, theory and experimental examples</article-title>. <source>Adv. Colloid. Interfac.</source>
<volume>211</volume>, <fpage>77</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>92</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cis.2014.06.005</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24997868</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Structural variations increase the upper limit of colony size of <italic>Microcystis</italic>: implications from laboratory cultures and field investigations</article-title>. <source>J. Phycol.</source>
<volume>56</volume>, <fpage>1676</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1686</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jpy.13054</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33448389</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferro</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gojkovic</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorzsas</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Funk</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>Statistical methods for rapid quantification of proteins, lipids, and carbohydrates in nordic microalgal species using ATR&#x02013;FTIR spectroscopy</article-title>. <source>Molecules</source>
<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>3237</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules24183237</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31492012</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Forni</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Telo</surname><given-names>F. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Caiola</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Comparative analysis of the polysaccharides produced by different species of <italic>Microcystis</italic> (Chroococcales, Cyanophyta)</article-title>. <source>Phycologia</source>
<volume>36</volume>, <fpage>181</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>185</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2216/i0031-8884-36-3-181.1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>C. X.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Effects of light intensity on components and topographical structures of extracellular polymeric substances from <italic>Microcoleus vaginatus</italic> (Cyanophyceae)</article-title>. <source>Phycologia</source>
<volume>53</volume>, <fpage>167</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>173</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2216/13-163.1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gon&#x000e7;alves</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Loureiro</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pires</surname><given-names>J. C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sim&#x000f5;es</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Surface physicochemical properties of selected single and mixed cultures of microalgae and cyanobacteria and their relationship with sedimentation kinetics</article-title>. <source>Bioresourc Bioprocess</source>
<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>21</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s40643-015-0051-y</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diwan</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Bacterial exopolysaccharide mediated heavy metal removal: a review on biosynthesis, mechanism and remediation strategies</article-title>. <source>Biotechnol. Rep.</source>
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>58</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.btre.2016.12.006</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28352564</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yanpeng</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiangying</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wenjun</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jun</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Surface characteristics of microalgae and their effects on harvesting performance by air flotation</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Agr. Biol. Eng.</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>125</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>133</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3965/j.ijabe.20171001.2698</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jefferson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>The impact of algal properties and pre-oxidation on solid-liquid separation of algae</article-title>. <source>Water Res.</source>
<volume>42</volume>, <fpage>1827</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1845</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2007.11.039</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18261761</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>R. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsons</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jefferson</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Successful removal of algae through the control of zeta potential</article-title>. <source>Sep. Sci. Technol.</source>
<volume>43</volume>, <fpage>1653</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1666</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01496390801973771</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hokputsa</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>C. X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulsen</surname><given-names>B. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harding</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>A physico-chemical comparative study on extracellular carbohydrate polymers from five desert algae</article-title>. <source>Carbohydr. Polym.</source>
<volume>54</volume>, <fpage>27</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0144-8617(03)00136-X</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huisman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Codd</surname><given-names>G. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paerl</surname><given-names>H. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibelings</surname><given-names>B. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verspagen</surname><given-names>J. M. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Visser</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Cyanobacterial blooms</article-title>. <source>Nat. Rev. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>16</volume>, <fpage>471</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>483</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41579-018-0040-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29946124</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Imai</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>K.-H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakano</surname><given-names>S.-I.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). &#x0201c;<article-title>Growth responses of harmful algal species <italic>Microcystis</italic> (Cyanophyceae) under various environmental conditions</article-title>&#x0201d; in <source>Interdisciplinary studies on environmental chemistry&#x02014;Environmental research in Asia</source>. eds. <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Obayashi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Isobe</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Subramanian</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanabe</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Tokyo, Japan</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>TerraPub</publisher-name>), <fpage>269</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>275</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iwabuchi</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunairi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anzai</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morisaki</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Relationships among colony morphotypes, cell-surface properties and bacterial adhesion to substrata in <italic>Rhodococcus</italic></article-title>. <source>Colloid. Surface. B.</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>51</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0927-7765(03)00036-5</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Le</surname><given-names>V. V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ko</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>C. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2022</year>). <article-title><italic>Microcystis</italic> colony formation: extracellular polymeric substance, associated microorganisms, and its application</article-title>. <source>Bioresour. Technol.</source>
<volume>360</volume>:<fpage>127610</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2022.127610</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35840029</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rietveld</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Comparison of the effects of extracellular and intracellular organic matter extracted from <italic>Microcystis aeruginosa</italic> on ultrafiltration membrane fouling: dynamics and mechanisms</article-title>. <source>Environ. Sci. Technol.</source>
<volume>48</volume>, <fpage>14549</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14557</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/es5035365</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25402823</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Morphospecies-dependent disaggregation of colonies of the cyanobacterium <italic>Microcystis</italic> under high turbulent mixing</article-title>. <source>Water Res.</source>
<volume>141</volume>, <fpage>340</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>348</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2018.05.017</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29804020</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y. X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alessi</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Owttrim</surname><given-names>G. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kenney</surname><given-names>J. P. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Q. X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lalonde</surname><given-names>S. V.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Cell surface acid-base properties of the cyanobacterium <italic>Synechococcus</italic>: influences of nitrogen source, growth phase and N:P ratios</article-title>. <source>Geochim. Cosmochim. Acta</source>
<volume>187</volume>, <fpage>179</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>194</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gca.2016.05.023</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L. Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>B. Q.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Characteristics and roles of <italic>Microcystis</italic> extracellular polymeric substances (EPS) in cyanobacterial blooms: a short review</article-title>. <source>J. Freshwater Ecol.</source>
<volume>33</volume>, <fpage>183</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>193</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02705060.2017.1391722</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Characterizing cell surface of blooming <italic>Microcystis</italic> in Lake Taihu, China</article-title>. <source>Water Sci. Technol.</source>
<volume>73</volume>, <fpage>2731</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2738</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2166/wst.2016.069</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27232410</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>X. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shang</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M. X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Relationship between surface physicochemical properties and its demulsifying ability of an alkaliphilic strain of <italic>Alcaligenes</italic> sp. S-XJ-1</article-title>. <source>Process Biochem.</source>
<volume>46</volume>, <fpage>1456</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1461</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.procbio.2011.03.018</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masumoto</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amano</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Machida</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2023</year>). <article-title>Enhancement of cyanobacterial blooms buoyancy by controlling extracellular polysaccharides content and cation concentration under light-limited condition</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Environ. Sci. Technol.</source> doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13762-023-05014-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masuoka</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hazen</surname><given-names>K. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Cell wall protein mannosylation determines <italic>Candida albicans</italic> cell surface hydrophobicity</article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source>
<volume>143</volume>, <fpage>3015</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3021</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/00221287-143-9-3015</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9308183</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Otten</surname><given-names>T. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paerl</surname><given-names>H. W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Phylogenetic inference of colony isolates comprising seasonal <italic>Microcystis</italic> blooms in Lake Taihu, China</article-title>. <source>Microb. Ecol.</source>
<volume>62</volume>, <fpage>907</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>918</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00248-011-9884-x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21667196</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ozkan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berberoglu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Physico-chemical surface properties of microalgae</article-title>. <source>Colloid. Surface. B.</source>
<volume>112</volume>, <fpage>287</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>293</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.colsurfb.2013.08.001</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24001448</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zille</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Micheletti</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moradas-Ferreira</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Philippis</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamagnini</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Complexity of cyanobacterial exopolysaccharides: composition, structures, inducing factors and putative genes involved in their biosynthesis and assembly</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol. Rev.</source>
<volume>33</volume>, <fpage>917</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>941</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6976.2009.00183.x</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19453747</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pringle</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1983</year>). <article-title>Influence of substratum wettability on attachment of freshwater bacteria to solid surfaces</article-title>. <source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>45</volume>, <fpage>811</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>817</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/aem.45.3.811-817.1983</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16346243</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lefebvre</surname><given-names>D. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Algal blooms: proactive strategy</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>346</volume>, <fpage>175</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>176</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.346.6206.175-b</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25301608</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gutnick</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenberg</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1980</year>). <article-title>Adherence of bacteria to hydrocarbons: a simple method for measuring cell-surface hydrophobicity</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol. Lett.</source>
<volume>9</volume>, <fpage>29</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>33</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0378-1097(80)90106-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sheng</surname><given-names>G. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H. Q.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Relationship between the extracellular polymeric substances and surface characteristics of <italic>Rhodopseudomonas acidophila</italic></article-title>. <source>Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>72</volume>, <fpage>126</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>131</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-005-0225-1</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16292527</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pan</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>The influence of extracellular polymeric substances on the coagulation process of cyanobacteria</article-title>. <source>Sci. Total Environ.</source>
<volume>720</volume>:<fpage>137573</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.137573</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32143047</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krausfeldt</surname><given-names>L. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>LeCleir</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stough</surname><given-names>J. M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Seasonal gene expression and the Ecophysiological implications of toxic <italic>Microcystis aeruginosa</italic> blooms in Lake Taihu</article-title>. <source>Environ. Sci. Technol.</source>
<volume>52</volume>, <fpage>11049</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11059</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.est.8b01066</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30168717</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>van Oss</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Acid&#x02014;base interfacial interactions in aqueous media</article-title>. <source>Colloids Surf. A Physicochem. Eng. Asp.</source>
<volume>78</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>49</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0927-7757(93)80308-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Volpe</surname><given-names>C. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Siboni</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Some reflections on Acid&#x02013;Base solid surface free energy theories</article-title>. <source>J. Colloid Interface Sci.</source>
<volume>195</volume>, <fpage>121</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>136</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/jcis.1997.5124</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9441613</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhn</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Bryon</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Konarik</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huskey</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Contact angle measurements using cellphone cameras to implement the Bikerman method</article-title>. <source>Galvanotechnik</source>
<volume>102</volume>, <fpage>1718</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1725</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>B. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chernenko</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Matth&#x000e4;us</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Diem</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernhard</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Shedding new light on the molecular architecture of oocytes using a combination of synchrotron Fourier transform-infrared and Raman spectroscopic mapping</article-title>. <source>Anal. Chem.</source>
<volume>80</volume>, <fpage>9065</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9072</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ac8015483</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18983174</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H. Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>S. X.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Cell surface characterization of some oleaginous green algae</article-title>. <source>J. Appl. Phycol.</source>
<volume>28</volume>, <fpage>2323</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2332</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10811-015-0768-1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reynolds</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Colony formation in the cyanobacterium <italic>Microcystis</italic></article-title>. <source>Biol. Rev. Camb. Philos. Soc.</source>
<volume>93</volume>, <fpage>1399</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1420</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/brv.12401</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29473286</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Willis</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burford</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Review: a meta-analysis comparing cell-division and cell-adhesion in <italic>Microcystis</italic> colony formation</article-title>. <source>Harmful Algae</source>
<volume>67</volume>, <fpage>85</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.hal.2017.06.007</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28755723</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Towards understanding the role of extracellular polymeric substances in cyanobacterial <italic>Microcystis</italic> aggregation and mucilaginous bloom formation</article-title>. <source>Chemosphere</source>
<volume>117</volume>, <fpage>815</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>822</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2014.10.061</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25465953</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Electrolyte cations binding with extracellular polymeric substances enhanced <italic>Microcystis</italic> aggregation: implication for <italic>Microcystis</italic> bloom formation in eutrophic freshwater lakes</article-title>. <source>Environ. Sci. Technol.</source>
<volume>50</volume>, <fpage>9034</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9043</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.est.6b00129</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27502019</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Investigation on extracellular polymeric substances from mucilaginous cyanobacterial blooms in eutrophic freshwater lakes</article-title>. <source>Chemosphere</source>
<volume>93</volume>, <fpage>75</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>81</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2013.04.077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23726883</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yee</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benning</surname><given-names>L. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Phoenix</surname><given-names>V. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferris</surname><given-names>F. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Characterization of metal-cyanobacteria sorption reactions: a combined macroscopic and infrared spectroscopic investigation</article-title>. <source>Environ. Sci. Technol.</source>
<volume>38</volume>, <fpage>775</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>782</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/es0346680</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14968864</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>A novel integrated method for quantification of interfacial interactions between two rough bioparticles</article-title>. <source>J. Colloid Interface Sci.</source>
<volume>516</volume>, <fpage>295</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>303</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcis.2018.01.075</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29408116</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>C. X.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014a</year>). <article-title>Utilization of phosphorus in four forms of the three dominant <italic>Microcystis</italic> morphospecies in Lake Taihu</article-title>. <source>J. Lake Sci.</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>379</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>384</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.18307/2014.0307</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>C. X.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014b</year>). <article-title>Comparative studies on phosphate utilization of two bloom-forming <italic>Microcystis</italic> spp</article-title>. <comment>(cyanobacteria) isolated from Lake Taihu (China)</comment>. <source>J. Appl. Phycol.</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>333</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>339</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10811-013-0067-7</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhai</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>C. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xue</surname><given-names>Y. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>The mechanism of competition between two bloom-forming <italic>Microcystis</italic> species</article-title>. <source>Freshw. Biol.</source>
<volume>58</volume>, <fpage>1831</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1839</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/fwb.12172</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amendola</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hewson</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sommerfeld</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Influence of growth phase on harvesting of Chlorella zofingiensis by dissolved air flotation</article-title>. <source>Bioresour. Technol.</source>
<volume>116</volume>, <fpage>477</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>484</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2012.04.002</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22541950</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>P. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>M. Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P. F.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Autoaggregation and adhesion abilities in bacteria associated with colonies of <italic>Microcystis</italic></article-title>. <source>Hydrobiologia</source>
<volume>823</volume>, <fpage>205</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>216</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10750-018-3706-9</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J. Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nawaz</surname><given-names>M. Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alghamdi</surname><given-names>H. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Z. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2021</year>). <article-title>Diversity, seasonal succession and host specificity of bacteria associated with cyanobacterial aggregates in a freshwater lake</article-title>. <source>Environ. Technol. Innov.</source>
<volume>24</volume>:<fpage>101988</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eti.2021.101988</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kengara</surname><given-names>F. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hong</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Extracellular polymeric substances enhanced mass transfer of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons in the two-liquid-phase system for biodegradation</article-title>. <source>Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol.</source>
<volume>90</volume>, <fpage>1063</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1071</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-011-3134-5</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21327962</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2020</year>). <article-title>Cell surface energy affects the structure of microalgal biofilm</article-title>. <source>Langmuir</source>
<volume>36</volume>, <fpage>3057</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3063</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.langmuir.0c00274</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32160744</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qian</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2019</year>). <article-title>A rapid inoculation method for microalgae biofilm cultivation based on microalgae-microalgae co-flocculation and zeta-potential adjustment</article-title>. <source>Bioresour. Technol.</source>
<volume>278</volume>, <fpage>272</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>278</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biortech.2019.01.083</pub-id>, PMID: <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30708330</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dai</surname><given-names>X. X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Differences in vertical distribution of <italic>Microcystis</italic> morphospecies composition in a shallow hypertrophic Lake (lake Taihu, China)</article-title>. <source>Environ. Earth Sci.</source>
<volume>73</volume>, <fpage>5721</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5730</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s12665-014-3826-0</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>High nutrient concentration and temperature alleviated formation of large colonies of <italic>Microcystis</italic>: Evidence from field investigations and laboratory experiments</article-title>. <source>Water Res.</source>
<volume>101</volume>, <fpage>167</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>175</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.watres.2016.05.080</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27262121</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
