<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Transl Int Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Transl Int Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jtim</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">jtim</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Translational Internal Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2450-131X</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2224-4018</issn><publisher><publisher-name>De Gruyter</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC10732491</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">jtim-2023-0002</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2478/jtim-2023-0002</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A pan-cancer analysis of the oncogenic role of Golgi transport 1B in human tumors</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>Bo</given-names></name><xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_aff_001" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>Yanan</given-names></name><xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_aff_001" ref-type="aff"/><xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_aff_002" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Ye</given-names></name><xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_aff_001" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>Qianqian</given-names></name><xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_aff_001" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xin</surname><given-names>Lei</given-names></name><xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_aff_001" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Chang</given-names></name><xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_aff_001" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Xin</given-names></name><xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_aff_001" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Yilin</given-names></name><xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_aff_003" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Zhaoshen</given-names></name><xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_aff_001" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Han</given-names><prefix>Dr.</prefix></name><email xlink:href="mailto:babyhan831@aliyun.com">babyhan831@aliyun.com</email><xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_aff_001" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Luowei</given-names><prefix>Dr.</prefix></name><email xlink:href="mailto:wangluoweimd@126.com">wangluoweimd@126.com</email><xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_aff_001" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><aff id="j_jtim-2023-0002_aff_001"><institution>Department of Gastroenterology, Changhai Hospital, Naval Medical University</institution>, <city>Shanghai</city>
<postal-code>200433</postal-code>, <country country="CN">China</country></aff><aff id="j_jtim-2023-0002_aff_002"><institution>Shanghai Institute of Pancreatic Diseases</institution>, <city>Shanghai</city>
<postal-code>200433</postal-code>, <country country="CN">China</country></aff><aff id="j_jtim-2023-0002_aff_003"><institution>Georgetown Preparatory School</institution>, <city>North Bethesda</city>
<postal-code>20852, MD</postal-code>, <country country="US">USA</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><fn><p><sup>#</sup>These authors have contributed equally to this work.</p></fn><corresp>Dr. Luowei Wang, Department of Gastroenterology, Changhai Hospital, Naval Medical University, No. 168 Changhai Road, Yangpu District, Shanghai 200433, China.</corresp><corresp>Dr. Han Lin, Department of Gastroenterology, Changhai Hospital, Naval Medical University, No. 168 Changhai Road, Yangpu District, Shanghai 200433, China.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>20</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><month>12</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>433</fpage><lpage>448</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2023 Bo Tian, Yanan Pang, Ye Gao, Qianqian Meng, Lei Xin, Chang Sun, Xin Tang, Yilin Wang, Zhaoshen Li, Han Lin, Luowei Wang, published by De Gruyter on behalf of Scholar Media Publishing</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Bo Tian, Yanan Pang, Ye Gao, Qianqian Meng, Lei Xin, Chang Sun, Xin Tang, Yilin Wang, Zhaoshen Li, Han Lin, Luowei Wang, published by De Gruyter on behalf of Scholar Media Publishing</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><title>Abstract</title><sec id="j_jtim-2023-0002_s_006"><title>Background</title><p>Owing to the aggressiveness and treatment-refractory nature of cancer, ideal candidates for early diagnosis and treatment are needed. Golgi transport 1B (<italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic>) has been associated with cellular malignant behaviors and immune responses in colorectal and lung cancer, but a systematic pan-cancer analysis on <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> has not been conducted.</p></sec><sec id="j_jtim-2023-0002_s_007"><title>Methods</title><p>The expression status and clinical association of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> in The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA) were analyzed. Genetic and methylation alterations in <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> were explored. The relationship between <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> and immune cell infiltration was also investigated. Genes related to <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> expression were selected and analyzed.</p></sec><sec id="j_jtim-2023-0002_s_008"><title>Results</title><p><italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> was highly expressed in most tumors, and there was a positive correlation between <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> expression and clinical pathological parameters. High expression levels of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> have been associated with poor prognosis of most cancers. Copy number amplification was the primary type of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> genetic alterations, which was related to the prognosis of pan-cancer cases. There were different levels of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> promoter methylation across cancer types. The methylation level of the probe cg07371838 and cg25816357 was closely associated with prognosis in diverse cancers. There was also a positive correlation between <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> genetic alterations and CD4+ T lymphocytes, especially the Th2 subset, as well as between <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> expression and the estimated infiltration value of cancer-associated fibroblasts. Serine/threonine kinase receptor-associated protein (<italic toggle="yes">STRAP</italic>), integrator complex subunit 13 (<italic toggle="yes">INTS13</italic>), and ethanolamine kinase 1 (<italic toggle="yes">ETNK1</italic>) were the most relevant genes for <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> expression, and their interactions with <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> were involved in regulating the transforming growth factor (TGF)-&#x003b2; receptor signaling pathway and epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT).</p></sec><sec id="j_jtim-2023-0002_s_009"><title>Conclusions</title><p>This pan-cancer analysis provided a comprehensive understanding of the oncogenic role of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic>, highlighting a potential mechanism whereby <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> influences the tumor microenvironment, as well as cancer immunotherapy.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><title>Key words</title><kwd>pan-cancer</kwd><kwd>bioinformatics</kwd><kwd>Golgi transport 1B</kwd><kwd>prognosis</kwd><kwd>immune infiltration</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China under Grant (No. 82103268); Shanghai Sailing Program under Grant (No. 21YF1459100); China Postdoctoral Science Foundation under Grant (No. 48067); the start-up funds for postdoctoral in Second Military Medical University; and the start-up Scientific Research Fund of Young Teachers in Changhai Hospital (No. 2019QNB01); Shanghai Science and Technology Innovation Action Program (No. 21Y31900100), and 234 clinical research fund of Changhai hospital (No. 2019YXK006).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="16"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="j_jtim-2023-0002_s_001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Globally, cancer is one of the primary causes of morbidity and mortality. Oncogenesis is a multistep and multilayered process, in which initiation and development are concomitant with aberrant biological activities of multiple proteins and lipids. Changeable structure and regulatory diversity of these functional molecules pose great challenges when exploring valuable prognostic biomarkers and effective therapeutic targets.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]</sup> As a central hub in trafficking, sorting, and modifying proteins and lipids, the Golgi apparatus (GA) plays a major role in maintaining cellular homeostasis while regulating cell differentiation and development.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]</sup> This organelle is characterized by a dynamic stacked ribbon-like structure and a complex multi-compartment system. Based on the sophisticated constitution, the fine-tuned regulatory mechanism of GA ensures efficacy and accuracy in its normal biological functions, such as post-translational protein modification, vesicular transportation, and cisternal maturation.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]</sup> Structural changes and functional disorganization of GA contribute to a number of pathophysiological changes, including oncogenesis.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]</sup> These disorders include Golgi fragmentation, aberrant Golgi glycosylation, and membrane trafficking perturbations resulting in disrupted Golgi pH homeostasis, which are frequently related to mutations in Golgi resident proteins.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]</sup></p><p>Membrane trafficking defects resulting from anomalous changes in resident proteins are closely associated with cell signaling communication, dissociation and invasion, immune regulation, and metastasis in cancer.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]</sup> Golgi transport 1B (<italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic>) is a member of the GOT1 family, and abnormal expressions of proteins in this family are associated with GA membrane trafficking disorders and cellular malignant behaviors.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]</sup> The GOT1 family consists of two primary members, <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1A</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic>. High expression of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1A</italic> has been correlated with poor prognosis and resistance to endocrine therapy in breast cancer.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]</sup> The <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1A-KISS1</italic> fusion transcript was shown to be a biomarker of adenoid cystic carcinoma metastasis.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> is located primarily in early Golgi cisternae, the absence of which induces a substantial reduction in the endoplasmic reticulum (ER)-Golgi transport efficiency.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]</sup> The amplification of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> is correlated with poor prognosis in lung cancer.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> contributes to epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT) in colorectal cancer (CRC) by activating WNT signaling, influencing the secretion of interferon (IFN)-&#x003b3;, and apoptosis of tumor-infiltrating T lymphocytes.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]</sup> Nevertheless, previous studies have only assessed <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> in selected types of cancer, and the potential mechanism by which <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> promotes tumorigenesis in divergent tumor types remains unclear.</p><p>Pan-cancer analyses enable the investigation of the differential expression of target genes and the corresponding abnormal regulatory mechanisms essential for tumorigenesis and progression across multiple layers of alterations.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]</sup> To our knowledge, this is the first pan-cancer study regarding the oncogenic role of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> by comprehensively assessing gene expression, clinical association, survival status, DNA methylation, genetic alterations, immune infiltration, and relevant molecular mechanisms.</p></sec><sec id="j_jtim-2023-0002_s_002"><title>Methods</title><sec id="j_jtim-2023-0002_s_002_s_001"><title>Oncomine</title><p>The mRNA levels of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> in diverse cancer types were analyzed in Oncomine, a publicly available online database providing genome-wide expression analysis with cancer microarray information.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]</sup> In the present study, the statistical significance thresholds were set to <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01, fold change of 1.5, and gene rank in the top 10%. The difference in the expression of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> between cancer and normal tissues was analyzed using Student&#x02019;s t-test.</p></sec><sec id="j_jtim-2023-0002_s_002_s_002"><title>Tumor immune estimation resource, version 2</title><p>Tumor immune estimation resource, version 2 (TIMER2) is a web tool for the systematic evaluation of gene expression differences, the correlation with immune cell infiltration, as well as relevant clinical impacts.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]</sup> We input <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> in the &#x0201c;Gene_DE&#x0201d; module of TIMER2 and further observed the expression difference of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> between tumor and adjacent normal tissues for the specific tumor subtypes of the TCGA project. Additionally, we used the &#x0201c;immune association&#x0201d; module of TIMER2 to explore the mutation frequency and somatic copy number alteration (sCNA) status of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> across multiple cancers by inputting <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> in the &#x0201c;Mutation&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;sCNA&#x0201d; boxes. We applied the &#x0201c;Immune-Gene&#x0201d; module of the TIMER2 web server to explore the association between <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> expression and immune infiltration across all TCGA tumors.</p></sec><sec id="j_jtim-2023-0002_s_002_s_003"><title>Gene Expression Profiling Interactive Analysis 2</title><p>The Gene Expression Profiling Interactive Analysis 2 (GEPIA2) database is used for cancer and normal gene expression and interactive analysis based on genotype-tissue expression (GTEx) and TCGA data.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]</sup> We used the &#x0201c;expression analysis box plots&#x0201d; module of the GEPIA2 to obtain box plots of the expression difference between these tumor tissues and the corresponding normal tissues of the GTEx database, under the settings of <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value cutoff = 0.01, log<sup>2</sup>fold change (FC) cutoff = 1, and &#x0201c;Match TCGA normal and GTEx data.&#x0201d; We obtained violin plots of the <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> expression in different pathological stages of all TCGA tumors <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> the &#x0201c;pathological stage plot&#x0201d; module of GEPIA2. Moreover, the &#x0201c;survival map&#x0201d; module of GEPIA2 was applied to obtain the OS and DFS significance map data of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic>. The log-rank test was used and the survival plots were also obtained through the &#x0201c;survival analysis&#x0201d; module of GEPIA2. Furthermore, we applied the &#x0201c;correlation analysis&#x0201d; module of GEPIA2 to perform a pairwise gene Pearson correlation analysis of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> and selected genes.</p></sec><sec id="j_jtim-2023-0002_s_002_s_004"><title>The University of ALabama at Birmingham CANcer data analysis Portal (UALCAN)</title><p>The UALCAN database is an online resource for gene analysis based on OMICS data (TCGA, MET500, and Clinical proteomic tumor analysis consortium [CPTAC]).<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]</sup> In our study, UALCAN was used to investigate the associations between the protein expression of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> and cancer-related clinical factors. We used the CPTAC data set in the UALCAN portal to explore the protein expression level of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> between primary tumor and normal tissues by entering &#x0201c;<italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic>.&#x0201d; The promoter methylation level of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> was also analyzed by applying the &#x0201c;expression analysis box plots&#x0201d; module. Statistical differences were assessed by using Student&#x02019;s t-test, and the statistical significance threshold was set at <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05.</p></sec><sec id="j_jtim-2023-0002_s_002_s_005"><title>cBioPortal</title><p>cBioPortal is an online resource with visual and multidimensional cancer genomic data.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]</sup> We chose the &#x0201c;TCGA Pan-Cancer Atlas Studies&#x0201d; in the &#x0201c;Quick select&#x0201d; section and entered &#x0201c;<italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic>&#x0201d; for queries of the genetic alteration characteristics of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic>. The &#x0201c;plots&#x0201d; module was used to analyze the correlation of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> mRNA and <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> Log2 copy-number values. The results of the alteration frequency, mutation type, and sCNA across all TCGA tumors were explored in the &#x0201c;cancer types summary&#x0201d; module. Additionally, we used the &#x0201c;comparison/survival&#x0201d; module to obtain the data on the overall, disease-free, progression-free, and disease-free survival differences for the TCGA cancer cases with or without <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> genetic alteration. Kaplan-Meier plots with log-rank <italic toggle="yes">P</italic>-value were obtained as well. The cellular pathways of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> genetic alteration were explored in the &#x0201c;pathways&#x0201d; module.</p></sec><sec id="j_jtim-2023-0002_s_002_s_006"><title>MethSurv</title><p>MethSurv, a web tool for assessing DNA methylation, expression, and clinical data visualization.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]</sup> This tool was used to perform the survival analysis by establishing Cox proportional hazards models for CpGs located in or around the proximity of the targeted genes across different types of cancer. We entered <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> in the searching box in &#x0201c;all cancers&#x0201d; module to perform survival analysis for a CpG located in or around the proximity of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic>. In order to evaluate the differences in survival analysis, the methylation levels of patients were divided into higher (the methylation &#x003b2; value higher than the cut-off point) and lower groups (the methylation &#x003b2; value lower than the cut-off point). <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05 was considered statistically significant.</p></sec><sec id="j_jtim-2023-0002_s_002_s_007"><title>String</title><p>STRING is a protein interaction website aiming to establish a global network of unique computational predictions.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]</sup> We searched the STRING website by using the query of a single protein name (&#x0201c;<italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic>&#x0201d;) and organism (&#x0201c;Homo sapiens&#x0201d;). Subsequently, we set the following main parameters: minimum required interaction score (&#x0201c;low confidence [0.150]&#x0201d;), meaning of network edges (&#x0201c;evidence&#x0201d;), max number of interactors to show (&#x0201c;no more than 50 interactors&#x0201d; in 1st shell), and active interaction sources (&#x0201c;experiments&#x0201d;). Finally, the available experimentally determined <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic>-binding proteins were obtained, and protein&#x02013;protein interaction network was performed.</p></sec><sec id="j_jtim-2023-0002_s_002_s_008"><title>GeneMANIA</title><p>GeneMANIA contains information on genes and prioritizes genes for functional assays with a highly accurate prediction algorithm.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]</sup> We input <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic>-related genes in the searching box of GeneMANIA and obtained the protein&#x02013;protein interaction network map and relevant functional assays in the &#x0201c;functions data&#x0201d; module.</p></sec><sec id="j_jtim-2023-0002_s_002_s_009"><title>Kyoto encyclopedia of genes and genomes/gene ontology analysis</title><p>The &#x0201c;similar gene detection&#x0201d; module of GEPIA2 was used to obtain the top 100 <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic>-correlated genes. We combined the two sets of genes (GEPIA2 and STRING) to perform Kyoto encyclopedia of genes and genomes (KEGG) pathway analysis and gene ontology (GO) enrichment analysis. The KEGG pathway and GO analyses were performed to determine the pan-cancer biological and molecular functions of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> by virtue of the R packages of ClusterProfiler and org.Hs.eg.db. The R package of ggplot2 was used to visualize the enriched pathways.</p></sec></sec><sec id="j_jtim-2023-0002_s_003"><title>Results</title><sec id="j_jtim-2023-0002_s_003_s_001"><title>The pan-cancer expression profiles of GOLT1B</title><p><italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> mRNA expression levels in different types of cancer were analyzed in Oncomine (<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A)</xref>. The pooled analysis confirmed that, compared with normal tissues, the transcriptional levels of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> were significantly elevated in tumor tissues. TIMER2 results also demonstrated that the expression levels of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> were upregulated in the tumor tissues of 15 cancer types, including bladder urothelial carcinoma (BLCA), cholangiocarcinoma (CHOL), breast invasive carcinoma (BRCA), colon adenocarcinoma (COAD), esophageal carcinoma (ESCA), head and neck squamous cell carcinoma (HNSC), glioblastoma multiforme (GBM), kidney renal clear cell carcinoma (KIRC), kidney renal papillary cell carcinoma (KIRP), liver hepatocellular carcinoma (LIHC), lung squamous cell carcinoma (LUSC), lung adenocarcinoma (LUAD), prostate adenocarcinoma (PRAD), stomach adenocarcinoma (STAD), and thyroid carcinoma (THCA) (<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B)</xref>. Using normal tissues as the controls, the expression of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> was found to be upregulated in the GTEx data set for diffuse large B-cell lymphoma (DLBC), skin cutaneous melanoma (SKCM), testicular germ cell tumors (TGCT), and thymoma (THYM) tissues (<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1C)</xref>. However, there was no significant difference in <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> expression between tumor and normal tissues for adrenocortical carcinoma (ACC), acute myeloid leukemia (LAML), brain lower grade glioma (LGG), ovarian serous cystadenocarcinoma (OV), sarcoma (SARC), or uterine carcinosarcoma (UCS).</p><fig position="float" id="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>The expression of GOLT1B in multiple cancers. (A) Increased (red) or decreased (blue) expression of GOLT1B in different cancer tissues, compared with normal tissues in Oncomine. The number in each grid represents the amount of datasets. (B) Expression levels of GOLT1B in different cancer types from TCGA data in TIMER2. (C) Expression difference between the tumor tissues and normal tissues of the GTEx (tumors without normal tissues in TCGA). (D) The expression level of GOLT1B total protein in cancers of CPTAC data set. *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05,**<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01. (E) Based on the TCGA data, the expression levels of the GOLT1B gene were analyzed by the main pathological stages (stages I, II, III, and IV) of ACC, BLCA, LUAD, OV, and UCS. Log<sub>2</sub>(TPM +1) was applied for the log scale. ACC: adrenocortical carcinoma; BLCA: bladder urothelial carcinoma; BRCA: breast invasive carcinoma, CESC: cervical squamous cell carcinoma and endocervical adenocarcinoma; CHOL: cholangiocarcinoma; COAD: colon adenocarcinoma, DLBC: lymphoid neoplasm diffuse large B-cell lymphoma; ESCA: esophageal carcinoma; GBM: glioblastoma multiforme; HNSC: head and neck squamous cell carcinoma; KICH: kidney chromophobe; KIRC: kidney renal clear cell carcinoma; KIRP: kidney renal papillary cell carcinoma; LAML: acute myeloid leukemia; LGG: brain lower grade glioma; LIHC: liver hepatocellular carcinoma; LUAD: lung adenocarcinoma; LUSC: lung squamous cell carcinoma; MESO: mesothelioma; OV: ovarian serous cystadenocarcinoma; PAAD: pancreatic adenocarcinoma; PCPG: pheochromocytoma and paraganglioma; PRAD: prostate adenocarcinoma; READ: rectum adenocarcinoma; SARC: sarcoma; SKCM: skin cutaneous melanoma; STAD: stomach adenocarcinoma; TGCT: testicular germ cell tumors; THCA: thyroid carcinoma; THYM: thymoma; UCEC: uterine corpus endometrial carcinoma; UCS: uterine carcinosarcoma; UVM: uveal melanoma.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_001" position="float"/></fig><p>Furthermore, the protein expression profiles of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> in various tumor and normal tissues were assessed using the CPTAC database. CPTAC results showed that the protein expression of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> was higher in KIRC, COAD, HNSC, and GBM primary tissues, and lower in BRCA and UCEC primary tissues compared to the corresponding normal tissues (<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1D)</xref>. The correlation between <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> mRNA expression and the pathological stage of cancers including ACC, BLCA, LUAD, OV, and UCS was obtained (<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1E</xref>, <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05). The box plots showed that higher levels of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> expression were associated with higher tumor stages in ACC, BLCA, LUAD, and UCS. The opposite expression trend was observed in OV.</p></sec><sec id="j_jtim-2023-0002_s_003_s_002"><title>Correlation of GOLT1B expression with prognosis</title><p>The correlation between <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> expression levels and prognosis in different cancers was analyzed by using GEPIA2. The cutoff-high (50%) and cutoff-low (50%) values were used as the expression thresholds for splitting the high-expression and low-expression cohorts. As shown in <xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2A</xref>, high <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> expression was associated with poor overall survival (OS) for ACC, BLCA, BRCA, CESC, ESCA, LGG, LUAD, MESO, PAAD, and SARC within the TCGA data set. Additionally, there were significant correlations between high <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> expression and poor disease-free survival (DFS) for TCGA cases of BLCA, GBM, MESO, PAAD, and SARC (<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2B)</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Prognostic significance of GOLT1B expression in many cancers. Comparison of OS (A) and DFS (B) between high and low expression of GOLT1B in different cancer types in GEPIA2. The survival map and Kaplan-Meier curves with positive results are given. OS: overall survival; DFS: disease-free survival; ACC: adrenocortical carcinoma; BLCA: bladder urothelial carcinoma; BRCA: breast invasive carcinoma, CESC: cervical squamous cell carcinoma and endocervical adenocarcinoma; CHOL: cholangiocarcinoma; COAD: colon adenocarcinoma, DLBC: lymphoid neoplasm diffuse large B-cell lymphoma; ESCA: esophageal carcinoma; GBM: glioblastoma multiforme; HNSC: head and neck squamous cell carcinoma; KICH: kidney chromophobe; KIRC: kidney renal clear cell carcinoma; KIRP: kidney renal papillary cell carcinoma; LAML: acute myeloid leukemia; LGG: brain lower grade glioma; LIHC: liver hepatocellular carcinoma; LUAD: lung adenocarcinoma; LUSC: lung squamous cell carcinoma; MESO: mesothelioma; OV: ovarian serous cystadenocarcinoma; PAAD: pancreatic adenocarcinoma; PCPG: pheochromocytoma and paraganglioma; PRAD: prostate adenocarcinoma; READ: rectum adenocarcinoma; SARC: sarcoma; SKCM: skin cutaneous melanoma; STAD: stomach adenocarcinoma; TGCT: testicular germ cell tumors; THCA: thyroid carcinoma; THYM: thymoma; UCEC: uterine corpus endometrial carcinoma; UCS: uterine carcinosarcoma; UVM: uveal melanoma.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_002" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="j_jtim-2023-0002_s_003_s_003"><title>Genetic alteration analysis of GOLT1B</title><p>The genetic alteration status of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> in different tumor samples from TCGA cohorts was investigated by applying cBioPortal. As shown in <xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3A</xref>, the highest alteration frequency of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> (&#x0003e; 8%) was observed in patients with non-seminomatous germ cell tumors, with amplification as a unique alteration type. Copy number amplification was the primary type of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> genetic alterations, with an alteration frequency of approximately 1.9% in pan-cancer types (<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3C)</xref>. There was a positive correlation between <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> Log2 copy number and <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> mRNA expression (<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3B)</xref>. The types, sites, and case numbers of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> genetic alterations are presented in <xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3C</xref>. Missense mutation of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> is the main type of genetic mutations. The L72Wfs*6/G69C frameshift deletion alteration was detected in three cases of STAD, one case of UCEC, and one case of SCKM (<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3D)</xref>, which could induce a frameshift mutation in the <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> gene.</p><fig position="float" id="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_003" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Genetic alteration analysis of GOLT1B in cBioportal. (A) Alteration frequency of GOLT1B in different cancers. (B) GOLT1B Log2 copy number with mRNA expression. (C&#x02013;D) Types, sites, and case number of GOLT1B and genetic alteration of GOLT1B. (E) Association between genetic alteration of GOLT1B and the clinical survival prognosis of pan-cancer. OS: overall survival; DSS: disease-specific survival; PFS: progression-free survival; DFS: disease-free survival; STAD: stomach adenocarcinoma; UCEC: uterine corpus endometrial carcinoma; SKCM: skin cutaneous melanoma.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_003" position="float"/></fig><p>We further explored the association between genetic alterations in <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> and the clinical survival prognosis of pan-cancer cases. Cases with <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> genetic alterations showed significantly poorer OS (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0213) but not disease-specific survival (DSS) (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.0617), DFS (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.107), or progression-free survival (PFS) (<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> = 0.340), compared with cases without <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> alterations (<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3E)</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="j_jtim-2023-0002_s_003_s_004"><title>Methylation alteration analysis of GOLT1B</title><p>We used the methylation module of UALCAN to investigate the potential association between <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> DNA methylation and the pathogenesis of different tumors in the TCGA dataset. The level of promoter methylation was significantly lower in the primary tissues of BRCA, HNSC, LUAD, and PRAD but was higher in the primary tissues of ESCA and PAAD, compared to those in the corresponding normal tissues (<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4A)</xref>. The potential association between <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> DNA methylation sites and the prognosis of multiple cancers was investigated by using the MethSurv approach. The correlation between the methylation level of probe cg07371838 and cg25816357 of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> and the prognosis of multiple cancer cases was shown in <xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4B</xref>. The Kaplan-Meier plots in the MethSurv database showed that as for cg07371838, higher methylation level in ACC, BRCA, GBM, KIRC, and SARC cases and lower methylation level in LIHC and MESO cases were associated with poorer prognosis. As for cg25816357, the higher methylation level in ESCA and STAD cases and lower methylation level in LAML, LIHC, and SARC cases were linked with poorer prognosis.</p><fig position="float" id="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_004" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Methylation alteration analysis of GOLT1B. (A) Promoter methylation level of GOLT1B in multiple tumors <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> the UALCAN. (B) Analysis of the relationships among GOLT1B methylation levels at specific probes (cg07371838 and cg25816357) and survival time in MethSurv. ACC: adrenocortical carcinoma; BRCA: breast invasive carcinoma, ESCA: esophageal carcinoma; GBM: glioblastoma multiforme; HNSC: head and neck squamous cell carcinoma; KIRC: kidney renal clear cell carcinoma; LAML: acute myeloid leukemia; LIHC: liver hepatocellular carcinoma; LUAD: lung adenocarcinoma; MESO: mesothelioma; PAAD: pancreatic adenocarcinoma; PRAD: prostate adenocarcinoma; SARC: sarcoma; STAD: stomach adenocarcinoma. The meaning of * is " *<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, **<italic toggle="yes">P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_004" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="j_jtim-2023-0002_s_003_s_005"><title>Association between immune infiltration levels and GOLT1B genetic alterations</title><p>The potential relationship between the different levels of immune infiltration and <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> genetic alterations in diverse cancer types in TCGA was investigated using the TIMER2. The sCNA state and mutation frequency of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> for each cancer type was shown in <xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5A</xref> and <xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_005" ref-type="fig">5B</xref>. The correlation between the infiltration level of different immune cells and <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> genetic mutations was also assessed. As shown in <xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5C</xref>, there were significant correlations between the copy number of sCNA and different immune infiltration levels in OV and BRCA, which possessed appropriate alternation samples of diverse CNA states for comparison. We also explored the difference in immune cell infiltration between the mutated and wild-type tumors of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> in UCEC and STAD (<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5D)</xref>. A positive association between <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> genetic alterations and CD4+ T lymphocytes, especially the Th2 subset, was observed (<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5C</xref> and <xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_005" ref-type="fig">5D)</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_005" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Association between immune infiltration level and GOLT1B genetic alterations. (A) Somatic copy number alteration (sCNA) states of GOLT1B for all TCGA cancer types. (B) Mutation frequency of GOLT1B for each TCGA cancer type. (C) Differential immune infiltration among different sCNA status of GOLT1B in OV and BRCA-basal. (D) Differential immune infiltration in the mutated vs wild-type tumors of GOLT1B in UCEC and STAD. ACC: adrenocortical carcinoma; BLCA: bladder urothelial carcinoma; BRCA: breast invasive carcinoma, CESC: cervical squamous cell carcinoma and endocervical adenocarcinoma; CHOL: cholangiocarcinoma; COAD: colon adenocarcinoma, DLBC: lymphoid neoplasm diffuse large B-cell lymphoma; ESCA: esophageal carcinoma; GBM: glioblastoma multiforme; HNSC: head and neck squamous cell carcinoma; KICH: kidney chromophobe; KIRC: kidney renal clear cell carcinoma; KIRP: kidney renal papillary cell carcinoma; LAML: acute myeloid leukemia; LGG: brain lower grade glioma; LIHC: liver hepatocellular carcinoma; LUAD: lung adenocarcinoma; LUSC: lung squamous cell carcinoma; MESO: mesothelioma; OV: ovarian serous cystadenocarcinoma; PAAD: pancreatic adenocarcinoma; PCPG: pheochromocytoma and paraganglioma; PRAD: prostate adenocarcinoma; READ: rectum adenocarcinoma; SARC: sarcoma; SKCM: skin cutaneous melanoma; STAD: stomach adenocarcinoma; TGCT: testicular germ cell tumors; THCA: thyroid carcinoma; THYM: thymoma; UCEC: uterine corpus endometrial carcinoma; UCS: uterine carcinosarcoma; UVM: uveal melanoma.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_005" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="j_jtim-2023-0002_s_003_s_006"><title>Association between immune infiltration levels and GOLT1B expression</title><p>The associations between the immune infiltration level of CD4+ cells and cancer-associated fibroblasts with <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> expression were explored using TIMER2. There was a significant correlation between the CD4+ subsets of T cells and <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> expression in TGCT and OV, two cancer types with the highest alteration frequency of copy number of sCNA (<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6A)</xref>. Meanwhile, data from xCell revealed that the level of CD4+ memory T cell subset infiltration was positively associated with <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> expression in pan-cancer analyses, while the level of central and effector memory subset infiltration was negatively associated with <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> expression (<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6B)</xref>. Results of the CIBERSORT and CIBERSORT-ABS algorithms showed that there were positive correlations between activated CD4+ memory T cells, resting subsets, and <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> expression in most cancer types such as BRCA and SKCM (<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6B)</xref>. In addition, the heatmap of all algorithms showed a positive correlation between <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> expression and the estimated infiltration value of cancer-associated fibroblasts for most TCGA tumors, including COAD, HNSC, HNSC-HPV, and PAAD (<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6C)</xref>. Moreover, we investigated the association between the infiltration level of different CD4+ T cell subsets and clinical prognosis across different cancer types. As shown in <xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6D</xref>, a high infiltration level of the Th2 subset was correlated with poor prognosis of tumors with the largest number.</p><fig position="float" id="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_006" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Association between immune infiltration level and GOLT1B expression. (A) The potential correlation between the expression level of the GOLT1B gene and the infiltration level of T cell CD4+ diverse subsets in TGCT and OV. (B) Heatmap of correlation: GOLT1B expression and infiltration value of T cell CD4+cell. (C) Heatmap of correlation: GOLT1B expression and infiltration value of cancer-associated fibroblasts for the TCGA tumors. (D) Heatmap of prognosis: GOLT1B expression and the infiltration level of T cell CD4+ for the TCGA tumors. ACC: adrenocortical carcinoma; BLCA: bladder urothelial carcinoma; BRCA: breast invasive carcinoma, CESC: cervical squamous cell carcinoma and endocervical adenocarcinoma; CHOL: cholangiocarcinoma; COAD: colon adenocarcinoma, DLBC: lymphoid neoplasm diffuse large B-cell lymphoma; ESCA: esophageal carcinoma; GBM: glioblastoma multiforme; HNSC: head and neck squamous cell carcinoma; KICH: kidney chromophobe; KIRC: kidney renal clear cell carcinoma; KIRP: kidney renal papillary cell carcinoma; LAML: acute myeloid leukemia; LGG: brain lower grade glioma; LIHC: liver hepatocellular carcinoma; LUAD: lung adenocarcinoma; LUSC: lung squamous cell carcinoma; MESO: mesothelioma; OV: ovarian serous cystadenocarcinoma; PAAD: pancreatic adenocarcinoma; PCPG: pheochromocytoma and paraganglioma; PRAD: prostate adenocarcinoma; READ: rectum adenocarcinoma; SARC: sarcoma; SKCM: skin cutaneous melanoma; STAD: stomach adenocarcinoma; TGCT: testicular germ cell tumors; THCA: thyroid carcinoma; THYM: thymoma; UCEC: uterine corpus endometrial carcinoma; UCS: uterine carcinosarcoma; UVM: uveal melanoma.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_006" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="j_jtim-2023-0002_s_003_s_007"><title>Interactions and relevant pathways of GOLT1B-related genes</title><p>To further investigate the molecular mechanism of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> in tumorigenesis, we screened <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic>-binding proteins and genes related to <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> expression using pathway enrichment analyses. A total of 50 <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic>-binding proteins supported by experimental evidence were obtained using the STRING tool. The interaction network of these proteins is shown in <xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7A</xref>. After combining all tumor expression data from TCGA using the GEPIA2 tool, the top 100 genes associated with <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> expression were selected. GO and KEGG pathway analyses of the above targeting genes from STRING and GEPIA2, Golgi vesicle transport, and ER to Golgi vesicle-mediated transport were implicated in the effect of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> on cancer pathogenesis (<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7B</xref> and <xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_007" ref-type="fig">7C)</xref>. Venn analysis of the above two groups of target genes identified six intersection genes including integrator complex subunit 13 (<italic toggle="yes">INTS13</italic>), ethanolamine kinase 1 (<italic toggle="yes">ETNK1</italic>), serine/threonine kinase receptor-associated protein (<italic toggle="yes">STRAP</italic>), <italic toggle="yes">SEC22A</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">YIPF4</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">YIPF5</italic> (<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7D)</xref>, all of which were positively correlated with <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> expression (<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7F)</xref>. The corresponding heatmap also showed positive correlations between <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> and the above six genes in most cancer types (Supplementary <xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1A)</xref>. Furthermore, the primary oncogenic roles of the six intersection genes in most TCGA cancer types were observed in the OS and DFS prognosis maps (<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7G)</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_007" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Interactions and relevant pathways of GOLT1B-related genes. (A) Network of genes for targeting genes from STRING. (B) Bubble chart of KEGG pathway analysis for targeting genes from STRING and GEPIA2. (C) The cnetplot for the molecular function data in GO analysis. (D) Intersection genes of 50 GOLT1B-binding and interacted genes and top 100 GOLT1B-correlated genes from GEPIA2. (E) Genetic alteration frequency of six relevant genes in GOLT1B mutation alteration tumor groups of TCGA tumor. (F) Analysis of the expression correlation between GOLT1B and intersection genes in TCGA cancers of GEPIA2. (G) Survival maps of comparing high and low expression of relevant genes among different cancer types in GEPIA2. OS: overall survival; DFS: disease-free survival; ACC: adrenocortical carcinoma; BLCA: bladder urothelial carcinoma; BRCA: breast invasive carcinoma, CESC: cervical squamous cell carcinoma and endocervical adenocarcinoma; CHOL: cholangiocarcinoma; COAD: colon adenocarcinoma, DLBC: lymphoid neoplasm diffuse large B-cell lymphoma; ESCA: esophageal carcinoma; GBM: glioblastoma multiforme; HNSC: head and neck squamous cell carcinoma; KICH: kidney chromophobe; KIRC: kidney renal clear cell carcinoma; KIRP: kidney renal papillary cell carcinoma; LAML: acute myeloid leukemia; LGG: brain lower grade glioma; LIHC: liver hepatocellular carcinoma; LUAD: lung adenocarcinoma; LUSC: lung squamous cell carcinoma; MESO: mesothelioma; OV: ovarian serous cystadenocarcinoma; PAAD: pancreatic adenocarcinoma; PCPG: pheochromocytoma and paraganglioma; PRAD: prostate adenocarcinoma; READ: rectum adenocarcinoma; SARC: sarcoma; SKCM: skin cutaneous melanoma; STAD: stomach adenocarcinoma; TGCT: testicular germ cell tumors; THCA: thyroid carcinoma; THYM: thymoma; UCEC: uterine corpus endometrial carcinoma; UCS: uterine carcinosarcoma; UVM: uveal melanoma; KEGG: Kyoto encyclopedia of genes and genomes; GOLT1B: golgi transport 1B.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_007" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="j_jtim-2023-0002_s_003_s_008"><title>Association of intersection genes with prognosis and GOLT1B genetic alterations</title><p>To determine the underlying molecular mechanism of the interaction, we investigated whether the alteration frequencies of intersection genes were associated with <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic>. Both <italic toggle="yes">ETNK1</italic> and INST13 showed statistically significant differences in <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> sCNA and mutation groups, whereas <italic toggle="yes">STRAP</italic> was only identified in the <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> sCNA group (<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_007" ref-type="fig">Figure 7E)</xref>. The top 20 genes with the highest alteration frequencies in <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> sCNA and mutation groups are shown in Supplementary <xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1B</xref> and <xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_001" ref-type="fig">1C</xref>. Especially, <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic> had the highest alteration frequency in the <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> altered group. The genetic alteration types of <italic toggle="yes">STRAP</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">INTS13</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">ETNK1</italic> were further explored. High amplification was identified as the primary sCNA of each gene, and missense mutations as the primary mutation type for <italic toggle="yes">INTS13</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">ETNK1</italic> (Supplementary <xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1D)</xref>. Additionally, the associations between genetic alterations of the three genes and prognosis were analyzed (Supplementary <xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1E)</xref>. Compared with cases without <italic toggle="yes">INTS13</italic> genetic alteration, cases with <italic toggle="yes">INTS13</italic> genetic alteration were associated with poor prognosis in DSS and PFS, but not in OS or DFS.</p></sec><sec id="j_jtim-2023-0002_s_003_s_009"><title>Interaction network of relevant genes and cellular pathways of GOLT1B genetic alteration</title><p>To analyze the interaction patterns of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">STRAP</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">INTS13</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">ETNK1</italic> as well as the functions of associated molecules, a PPI network was constructed using GeneMANIA (<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_008" ref-type="fig">Figure 8A)</xref>. Functional assays showed that the corresponding molecules were primarily related to the regulation of the transforming growth factor (TGF)-&#x003b2; receptor signaling pathway and EMT according to false discovery rate (FDR) (Supplementary Table 1). With the highest relevant ranks in cBioportal, WNT, <italic toggle="yes">TP53</italic>, and TGF-&#x003b2; pathways and their primary genetic alterations were shown in <xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_008" ref-type="fig">Figure 8B</xref>.</p><fig position="float" id="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_008" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Interaction network of relevant genes and cellular pathways of GOLT1B genetic alteration. (A) Protein&#x02013;protein interaction network of relevant genes from GeneMANIA. (B) Cellular pathways of GOLT1B genetic alteration. TGF: transforming growth factor; GOLT1B: golgi transport 1B.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="j_jtim-2023-0002_fig_008" position="float"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="j_jtim-2023-0002_s_004"><title>Discussion</title><p>Owing to the aggressiveness, late diagnosis, and treatment-refractory nature of cancer, ideal candidates for biomarkerrelated early diagnosis and treatment are still being explored. The multiple functions of GA and its centrality in the intersection between exocytic and endocytic membrane trafficking routes provide potential targets for cancer diagnosis and therapy.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</sup> Diverse GA-related molecules participate in tumor development and progression <italic toggle="yes">via</italic> multilayered mechanisms and pathways.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]</sup> The present study is the first to comprehensively examine the expression of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> in a pan-cancer data set. We found that the mRNA expression of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> was upregulated in most cancer tissues and was associated with a poor prognosis of multiple cancers. Moreover, <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> was positively correlated with the Th2 subset of CD4+ cells and cancer-associated fibroblasts, playing a specific role in immune infiltration. GO/KEGG pathway analyses revealed that Golgi vesicle transport and ER to Golgi vesicle-mediated transport might be associated with the effect of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> on cancer pathogenesis. <italic toggle="yes">STRAP</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">INTS13</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">ETNK1</italic> were identified as the most relevant altered genes of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic>, and their interactions were primarily linked to the regulation of the TGF-&#x003b2; receptor signaling pathway and EMT. Our study provides insights into the application of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> as a potential prognostic biomarker in several cancers in the context of immuno-oncology and contributes to the development of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic>-targeting therapeutic strategies.</p><p><italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> is a member of the GOT1 family. Limited studies have reported the oncogenic role of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> in human cancers.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]</sup> sCNA is a major source of genomic variations driving tumor evolution, and sCNA screening may identify prognostic biomarkers. The amplification of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> has been reported to be correlated with a worse prognosis in patients with resected LUAD.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]</sup> Consistent with previous studies, our study further confirmed that high expression levels of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> are linked to poor prognosis in many types of cancer. Copy number amplification was identified as the primary type of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> genetic alteration related to the prognosis of pan-cancer cases. Moreover, it has been reported that overexpression of genes from 12p11.2 to 12p12.1 is a feature of all TGCTs and the overexpression of genes from this region, particularly in non-seminomas and seminomas with amplification, might play a key role in driving TGCT progression.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]</sup> In our study, <italic toggle="yes">STRAP</italic> (chr12:15), <italic toggle="yes">INTS13</italic> (chr12:26), and <italic toggle="yes">ETNK1</italic> (chr12:22) were the most genetic alteration-related genes for <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> (chr12:21), and were all located at 12p15-26, with amplification as the primary genetic alteration type. Furthermore, the highest amplification frequency of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> was identified in tumors of the reproductive system, particularly in nonseminomatous germ cell tumors (&#x0003e; 8%). Genetic alteration by amplification supports the prognostic potential of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic>, and large cohort validations with complete clinical data across different cancers are warranted.</p><p>DNA methylation is a major form of epigenetic modification of DNA that regulates gene expression without altering the DNA sequence. DNA methylation generally suppresses gene expression by changing chromatin structure, DNA stability, and DNA conformation.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]</sup> Hyper-methylation within the promoter regions often leads to the silencing or inactivation of tumor suppressor genes in cancerous cells. In our study, the differential status of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> promoter methylation across diverse cancers was determined. The level of promoter methylation was significantly lower in BRCA, HNSC, LUAD, and PRAD primary tissues but higher in ESCA and PAAD primary tissues, compared to corresponding normal tissues. Meanwhile, the significant association of differential methylation status of probe cg07371838 and cg25816357 with prognosis in diverse cancer cases was observed. However, our pan-cancer analysis also showed that <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> overexpression contributed negatively to prognosis in patients with ESCA and PAAD. Hyper-methylation of the <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> promoter region failed to result in gene inactivation in ESCA. There are several potential mechanisms for this phenomenon. On one hand, the heterogeneity of different tumor pathological characteristics and the methylation status of different genetic locations may affect the level of gene expression and the direction of changes in different cancers. On the other hand, the cross-talk between epigenetic mechanisms and alternative RNA processing regulation plays critical roles in cell differentiation, organ development, and disease responses.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]</sup>
<italic toggle="yes">STRAP</italic> was previously identified as a putative spliceosome-associated factor that regulates alternative splicing (AS) through preferred binding positions.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]</sup> In this study, <italic toggle="yes">STRAP</italic> was shown to have specific binding positions for <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">INTS13</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">ETNK 1</italic> transcripts, respectively, suggesting the potential of <italic toggle="yes">STRAP</italic>-related AS regulatory mechanisms with these relevant genes. Considering the general as well as cancer type-specific and subtype-specific alterations in the AS of cancer, differentiated methylation status and levels of transcript and protein expression of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> across cancer types might be elucidated.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]</sup> The physiological relevance of the cross-talk between <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> methylation and <italic toggle="yes">STRAP</italic>-regulated AS processing needs to be further investigated.</p><p>Despite some breakthroughs in cancer treatment, immunotherapy faces challenges in a successful application, while new targets and biomarkers are required to improve its efficacy.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]</sup> Dysregulations of diverse immune cells and components of the tumor microenvironment (TME) facilitate the immune escape of tumors, ultimately resulting in tumor proliferation, recurrence, and metastasis.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]</sup> GA plays an essential role in the trafficking, sorting, and modification of proteins and lipids in immune responses.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]</sup> The abnormal expression of GA-related proteins contributes to immunomodulator dysfunction, which significantly promotes cancer progression.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]</sup> Immunotherapy targeting Golgi resident proteins has entered the clinical trial stage.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]</sup> The <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> expression was found to be closely associated with the tumor microenvironment score and infiltration of immune cells in BRCA.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]</sup> In our study, there was a positive correlation between <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> expression and the infiltration level of CD4+ T lymphocytes, especially the T helper type 2 (Th2) subset, which is associated with poor prognosis in multiple cancers. As two predominant subsets of CD4+ T lymphocytes, Th1 and Th2 are characterized by the production of IFN-&#x003b3; and interleukin (IL)-4 cytokines, respectively.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]</sup> It has been reported that the Th1 to Th2 immune polarity shift serves as an important feature for tumor progression.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]</sup> The cytokines secreted from Th2 cells, including IL-4, IL-5, and IL-13, have been confirmed to promote cancer development.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]</sup> T cells in the peripheral blood collected from patients with metastatic melanoma showed shifting from cytotoxic Th1 responses toward chronic inflammatory Th2 responses, indicated by elaboration of increased levels of IL-4 and decreased levels of IFN-&#x003b3;.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]</sup> It is demonstrated that <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> promotes the expression and facilitates the membrane localization of programmed death-ligand 2 (PD-L2), which plays an important role in Th2 immunity.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]</sup> Besides, the high expression of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> might inhibit GSK3&#x003b2; phosphorylation and obstruct the secretion of IFN-&#x003b3;, further impeding the positive feedback regulation of IFN-&#x003b3; on Th1 differentiation. Consistent with previous findings, our study showed the expression of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> positively correlated with the infiltration of Th2 cells. <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> might induce immunological suppression by promoting Th1 to Th2 immune polarity shift, providing a new direction for immunotherapy. Additionally, the high expression of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> was also found to be positively associated with the infiltration of cancer-associated fibroblasts (CAFs), which were key components of the TME with diverse functions. Taken together, our results further confirmed the involvement of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> with the infiltration of different immune cells in cancers.</p><p>In addition, functional analysis revealed that the regulation of the TGF-&#x003b2; receptor signaling pathway and EMT were two critical pathways in the interaction between <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> and related genes including <italic toggle="yes">STRAP</italic>, <italic toggle="yes">INTS13</italic>, and <italic toggle="yes">ETNK1</italic>. TGF-&#x003b2; has been reported to regulate immune responses and maintain immune homeostasis by regulating the proliferation, differentiation, and survival of multiple immune cell lineages.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]</sup> Moreover, TGF-&#x003b2; supports cancer growth and progression by activating tumor angiogenesis and CAFs while enabling the tumor to evade inhibitory immune responses.<sup>[<xref rid="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]</sup> Our exploration of the signaling pathways mediated by <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> genetic alterations revealed its involvement in EMT and TGF-&#x003b2; receptor signaling pathways, providing new evidence for the exploration of the regulatory mechanism of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> on immune cell infiltration.</p></sec><sec id="j_jtim-2023-0002_s_005"><title>Conclusion</title><p>In summary, the present pan-cancer analysis, for the first time, offered a comprehensive understanding of the oncogenic role of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> across different cancers, demonstrating the potential of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> as a diagnostic biomarker and a target for cancer immunotherapy. Further studies are warranted to elucidate the specific regulatory mechanisms of <italic toggle="yes">GOLT1B</italic> in carcinogenesis to improve the efficacy of cancer diagnosis and the diverse application of immunotherapy.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material position="float" content-type="local-data"><caption><p>Supplementary material</p></caption><media xlink:href="jtim-2023-0002_sm.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ack_001"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Not applicable.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="other" id="j_jtim-2023-0002_fn_102"><p>
<bold>Author Contributions</bold>
</p><p>BT, LWW, and HL designed this study. BT, YNP, YG, and QQM collected the data and performed the analysis. LX, CS, XT, and YLW provided support in the data curation, and visualization. BT, YNP, and YG wrote the original draft. LWW, HL and ZSL reviewed and revised the manuscript. All authors contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="j_jtim-2023-0002_fn_103"><p>
<bold>Conflicts of Interest</bold>
</p><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other" id="j_jtim-2023-0002_fn_104"><p>
<bold>Data Availability Statement</bold>
</p><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article. Further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding authors.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_001"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jeggo</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearl</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Carr</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><article-title>DNA repair, genome stability and cancer: a historical perspective</article-title><source>Nat Rev Cancer</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>35</fpage><comment>&#x02013;</comment><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26667849</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_002"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chatterjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodger</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Eccles</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><article-title>Epigenetic drivers of tumourigenesis and cancer metastasis</article-title><source>Semin Cancer Biol</source><year>2018</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>149</fpage><comment>&#x02013;</comment><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28807546</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_003"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Brandizzi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Barlowe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>Organization of the ER-Golgi interface for membrane traffic control</article-title><source>Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>382</fpage><comment>&#x02013;</comment><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23698585</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_004"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Witkos</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Recognition and tethering of transport vesicles at the Golgi apparatus</article-title><source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source><year>2017</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>16</fpage><comment>&#x02013;</comment><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28237810</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_005"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gomez-Navarro</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>Protein sorting at the ER-Golgi interface</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>2016</year><volume>215</volume><fpage>769</fpage><comment>&#x02013;</comment><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27903609</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_006"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><article-title>Alterations of Golgi Structural Proteins and Glycosylation Defects in Cancer</article-title><source>Front Cell Dev Biol</source><year>2021</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>665289</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34055798</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_007"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zappa</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Failli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>De Matteis</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><article-title>The Golgi complex in disease and therapy</article-title><source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source><year>2018</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>102</fpage><comment>&#x02013;</comment><lpage>16</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29614425</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_008"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Galenkamp</surname><given-names>KMO</given-names></name><name><surname>Sosicka</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jung</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Recouvreux</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Moldenhauer</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><comment>
<italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>
</comment><article-title>Golgi Acidification by NHE7 Regulates Cytosolic pH Homeostasis in Pancreatic Cancer Cells</article-title><source>Cancer Discov</source><year>2020</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>822</fpage><comment>&#x02013;</comment><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32200349</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_009"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><article-title>The role of the Golgi apparatus in disease (Review)</article-title><source>Int J Mol Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>38</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33537825</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_010"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Ockerman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><comment>
<italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>
</comment><article-title>Regulation of glial size by eicosapentaenoic acid through a novel Golgi apparatus mechanism</article-title><source>PLoS Biol</source><year>2020</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>e3001051</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33370778</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_011"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ikeda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Horie-Inoue</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ueno</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Shigekawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><comment>
<italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>
</comment><article-title>miR-378a-3p modulates tamoxifen sensitivity in breast cancer MCF-7 cells through targeting GOLT1A</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>13170</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26255816</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_012"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zou</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lv</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><comment>
<italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>
</comment><article-title>GOLT1A-KISS1 fusion is associated with metastasis in adenoid cystic carcinomas</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source><year>2020</year><volume>526</volume><fpage>70</fpage><comment>&#x02013;</comment><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32192769</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_013"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fukuda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawagoe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Washida</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagamine</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><comment>
<italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>
</comment><article-title>The Dual Roles of the Golgi Transport 1 (GOT1B): RNA Localization to the Cortical Endoplasmic Reticulum and the Export of Proglutelin and alpha-Globulin from the Cortical ER to the Golgi</article-title><source>Plant Cell Physiol</source><year>2016</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>2380</fpage><comment>&#x02013;</comment><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27565205</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_014"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lorente-Rodriguez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Heidtman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Barlowe</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>Multicopy suppressor analysis of thermosensitive YIP1 alleles implicates GOT1 in transport from the ER</article-title><source>J Cell Sci</source><year>2009</year><volume>122</volume><fpage>1540</fpage><comment>&#x02013;</comment><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19383723</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_015"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><comment>
<italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>
</comment><article-title>Comprehensive Profiling of Gene Copy Number Alterations Predicts Patient Prognosis in Resected Stages I-III Lung Adenocarcinoma</article-title><source>Front Oncol</source><year>2019</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>556</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31448219</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_016"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><comment>
<italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>
</comment><article-title>Vesicle transporter GOLT1B mediates the cell membrane localization of DVL2 and PD-L2 and promotes colorectal cancer metastasis</article-title><source>Cancer Cell Int</source><year>2021</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>287</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34059062</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_017"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Weng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><article-title>CSCO guidelines for colorectal cancer version 2022: Updates and discussions</article-title><source>Chin J Cancer Res</source><year>2022</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>67</fpage><comment>-</comment><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35685997</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_018"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ge</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><article-title>Pan-cancer analyses demonstrate that ANKRD6 is associated with a poor prognosis and correlates with M2 macrophage infiltration in colon cancer</article-title><source>Chin J Cancer Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>93</fpage><comment>-</comment><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33707932</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_019"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rhodes</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalyana-Sundaram</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahavisno</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Varambally</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Briggs</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><comment>
<italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>
</comment><article-title>Oncomine 3.0: genes, pathways, and networks in a collection of 18,000 cancer gene expression profiles</article-title><source>Neoplasia</source><year>2007</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>166</fpage><comment>&#x02013;</comment><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17356713</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_020"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><comment>
<italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>
</comment><article-title>TIMER2.0 for analysis of tumor-infiltrating immune cells</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2020</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>W509</fpage><comment>-</comment><lpage>W14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32442275</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_021"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><article-title>GEPIA2: an enhanced web server for large-scale expression profiling and interactive analysis</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2019</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>W556</fpage><comment>&#x02013;</comment><lpage>W60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31114875</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_022"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chandrashekar</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bashel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Balasubramanya</surname><given-names>SAH</given-names></name><name><surname>Creighton</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponce-Rodriguez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Chakravarthi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><comment>
<italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>
</comment><article-title>UALCAN: A Portal for Facilitating Tumor Subgroup Gene Expression and Survival Analyses</article-title><source>Neoplasia</source><year>2017</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>649</fpage><comment>&#x02013;</comment><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28732212</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_023"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Aksoy</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dogrusoz</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Dresdner</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumer</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name><comment>
<italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>
</comment><article-title>Integrative analysis of complex cancer genomics and clinical profiles using the cBioPortal</article-title><source>Sci Signal</source><year>2013</year><volume>6</volume><comment>pl1</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_024"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cerami</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dogrusoz</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumer</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name><name><surname>Aksoy</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><comment>
<italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>
</comment><article-title>The cBio cancer genomics portal: an open platform for exploring multidimensional cancer genomics data</article-title><source>Cancer Discov</source><year>2012</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>401</fpage><comment>&#x02013;</comment><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22588877</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_025"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Modhukur</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Iljasenko</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Metsalu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lokk</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Laisk-Podar</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Vilo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>MethSurv: a web tool to perform multivariable survival analysis using DNA methylation data</article-title><source>Epigenomics</source><year>2018</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>277</fpage><comment>&#x02013;</comment><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29264942</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_026"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Szklarczyk</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gable</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Nastou</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirsch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pyysalo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><comment>
<italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>
</comment><article-title>The STRING database in 2021: customizable protein-protein networks, and functional characterization of user-uploaded gene/measurement sets</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>D605</fpage><comment>&#x02013;</comment><lpage>D12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33237311</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_027"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Warde-Farley</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Donaldson</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Comes</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Zuberi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Badrawi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><comment>
<italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>
</comment><article-title>The GeneMANIA prediction server: biological network integration for gene prioritization and predicting gene function</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2010</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>W214</fpage><comment>&#x02013;</comment><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20576703</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_028"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>QH</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><comment>
<italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>
</comment><article-title>GOLM1 Modulates EGFR/RTK Cell-Surface Recycling to Drive Hepatocellular Carcinoma Metastasis</article-title><source>Cancer Cell</source><year>2016</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>444</fpage><comment>&#x02013;</comment><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27569582</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_029"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>XC</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>YC</given-names></name><comment>
<italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>
</comment><article-title>RBFOX2/GOLIM4 Splicing Axis Activates Vesicular Transport Pathway to Promote Nasopharyngeal Carcinogenesis</article-title><source>Adv Sci (Weinh)</source><year>2021</year><fpage>e2004852</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34180133</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_030"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jafer</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Goker</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Summersgill</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zafarana</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gillis</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><comment>
<italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>
</comment><article-title>Expression profile of genes from 12p in testicular germ cell tumors of adolescents and adults associated with i(12p) and amplification at 12p11.2-p12.1</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>2003</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1880</fpage><comment>&#x02013;</comment><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12660824</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_031"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mehdi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rabbani</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><article-title>Role of Methylation in Pro- and Anti-Cancer Immunity</article-title><source>Cancers (Basel)</source><year>2021</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>545</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33535484</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_032"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Bai</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>Single-cell DNA methylome analysis of circulating tumor cells</article-title><source>Chin J Cancer Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>391</fpage><comment>-</comment><lpage>404</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34321835</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_033"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y-Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Duan</surname><given-names>C-G</given-names></name><article-title>The Crosstalk Between Epigenetic Mechanisms and Alternative RNA Processing Regulation</article-title><source>Frontiers in Genetics</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>998</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32973889</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_034"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Crossman</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Datta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mobley</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><comment>
<italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>
</comment><article-title>STRAP regulates alternative splicing fidelity during lineage commitment of mouse embryonic stem cells</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2020</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>5941</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33230114</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_035"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bonnal</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopez-Oreja</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Valcarcel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Roles and mechanisms of alternative splicing in cancer - implications for care</article-title><source>Nat Rev Clin Oncol</source><year>2020</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>457</fpage><comment>&#x02013;</comment><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32303702</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_036"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pinter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><article-title>Targeting the renin-angiotensin system to improve cancer treatment: Implications for immunotherapy</article-title><source>Sci Transl Med</source><year>2017</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>eaan5616</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28978752</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_037"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Min</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><comment>
<italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>
</comment><article-title>Tertiary lymphoid structure patterns predicted anti-PD1 therapeutic responses in gastric cancer</article-title><source>Chin J Cancer Res</source><year>2022</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>365</fpage><comment>-</comment><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36199531</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_038"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Galon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Angell</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bedognetti</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Marincola</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><article-title>The continuum of cancer immunosurveillance: prognostic, predictive, and mechanistic signatures</article-title><source>Immunity</source><year>2013</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>11</fpage><comment>&#x02013;</comment><lpage>26</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23890060</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_039"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nolte</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nolte-&#x02019;t Hoen</surname><given-names>ENM</given-names></name><name><surname>Margadant</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>Integrins Control Vesicular Trafficking; New Tricks for Old Dogs</article-title><source>Trends Biochem Sci</source><year>2021</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>124</fpage><comment>&#x02013;</comment><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33020011</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_040"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Geng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><comment>
<italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>
</comment><article-title>Tumor Microenvironment Regulation by the Endoplasmic Reticulum Stress Transmission Mediator Golgi Protein 73 in Mice</article-title><source>Hepatology</source><year>2019</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>851</fpage><comment>&#x02013;</comment><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30723919</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_041"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zucchetti</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bataille</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Carpier</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dogniaux</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>San</surname><given-names>Roman-Jouve M</given-names></name><name><surname>Maurin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><comment>
<italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>
</comment><article-title>Tethering of vesicles to the Golgi by GMAP210 controls LAT delivery to the immune synapse</article-title><source>Nat Commun</source><year>2019</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>2864</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31253807</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_042"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><comment>
<italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>
</comment><article-title>Multi-Omics Analyses Revealed GOLT1B as a Potential Prognostic Gene in Breast Cancer Probably Regulating the Immune Microenvironment</article-title><source>Front Oncol</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>805273</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35127514</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_043"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Basu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramamoorthi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Beyer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Snyder</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><comment>
<italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>
</comment><article-title>Differentiation and Regulation of TH Cells: A Balancing Act for Cancer Immunotherapy</article-title><source>Front Immunol</source><year>2021</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>669474</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34012451</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_044"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pertille</surname><given-names>Ramos MFK</given-names></name><name><surname>Dias</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardili</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>de Moraes</surname><given-names>RDR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>RRE</given-names></name><comment>
<italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>
</comment><article-title>Prognostic implications of tumor-infiltrating lymphocytes in association with programmed cell death ligand 1 expression in remnant gastric cancer</article-title><source>Chin J Cancer Res</source><year>2022</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>612</fpage><comment>-</comment><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36714339</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_045"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Block</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Nevala</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name><surname>Leontovich</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Markovic</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><article-title>Differential response of human and mouse dendritic cells to VEGF determines interspecies discrepancies in tumor-mediated TH1/TH2 polarity shift</article-title><source>Clin Cancer Res</source><year>2011</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1776</fpage><comment>&#x02013;</comment><lpage>83</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21349994</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_046"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nevala</surname><given-names>WK</given-names></name><name><surname>Vachon</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Leontovich</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Markovic</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><comment>
<italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>
</comment><article-title>Evidence of systemic Th2-driven chronic inflammation in patients with metastatic melanoma</article-title><source>Clin Cancer Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1931</fpage><comment>&#x02013;</comment><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19240164</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_047"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Okiyama</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>Immune-related adverse events in various organs caused by immune checkpoint inhibitors</article-title><source>Allergol Int</source><year>2022</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>169</fpage><comment>&#x02013;</comment><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35101349</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_048"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Moses</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><article-title>TGF-beta and immune cells: an important regulatory axis in the tumor microenvironment and progression</article-title><source>Trends Immunol</source><year>2010</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>220</fpage><comment>&#x02013;</comment><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20538542</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="j_jtim-2023-0002_ref_049"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ten Dijke</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>TGF-beta-Mediated Epithelial-Mesenchymal Transition and Cancer Metastasis</article-title><source>Int J Mol Sci</source><year>2019</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>2767</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31195692</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
