<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Emerg Microbes Infect</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Emerg Microbes Infect</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Emerging Microbes &#x00026; Infections</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2222-1751</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Taylor &#x00026; Francis</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37850324</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC10732220</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2272638</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/22221751.2023.2272638</article-id><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" vocab-term="Version of Record" article-version-type="VoR">Version of Record</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>T3SS chaperone of the CesT family is required for secretion of the anti-sigma factor BtrA in <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella pertussis</italic></article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="right-running-head">Emerging Microbes &#x00026; Infections</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">J. Dr&#x0017e;m&#x000ed;&#x00161;ek et al.</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dr&#x0017e;m&#x000ed;&#x00161;ek</surname><given-names>Jakub</given-names></name><xref rid="AF1" ref-type="aff"/><xref rid="an1" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Petr&#x000e1;&#x0010d;kov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>Denisa</given-names></name><xref rid="AF1" ref-type="aff"/><xref rid="an1" ref-type="author-notes">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dienstbier</surname><given-names>Ana</given-names></name><xref rid="AF1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>&#x0010c;urnov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>Ivana</given-names></name><xref rid="AF1" ref-type="aff"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9520-6324</contrib-id><name><surname>Ve&#x0010d;erek</surname><given-names>Branislav</given-names></name><xref rid="AF1" ref-type="aff"/><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><aff id="AF1">Laboratory of post-transcriptional control of gene expression, <institution>Institute of Microbiology of the Czech Academy of Sciences</institution>, <city>Prague</city>, <country>Czech Republic</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>CONTACT</label> Branislav Ve&#x0010d;erek <email xlink:href="vecerek@biomed.cas.cz">vecerek@biomed.cas.cz</email> Laboratory of post-transcriptional control of gene expression, <institution>Institute of Microbiology of the Czech Academy of Sciences</institution>, <city>Prague</city>
<postal-code>14220</postal-code>, <country>Czech Republic</country></corresp><fn id="an1"><label>*</label><p>J.D. and D.P. contributed equally to this article.</p></fn><fn id="fn1"><p>Supplemental data for this article can be accessed online at <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1080/22221751.2023.2272638" ext-link-type="uri">https://doi.org/10.1080/22221751.2023.2272638</ext-link>.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>1</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>1</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>12</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id seq="91">2272638</elocation-id><pub-history><event event-type="received"><date><day>30</day><month>8</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="revised"><date><day>11</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="accepted"><date><day>15</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="tagger"><event-desc>Nova techset</event-desc><date><day>18</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="build-issue-online"><event-desc>Converted to JATS 1.2 by Nova Techset</event-desc><date><day>18</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2023 The Author(s). Published by Informa UK Limited, trading as Taylor &#x00026; Francis Group, on behalf of Shanghai Shangyixun Cultural Communication Co., Ltd</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. The terms on which this article has been published allow the posting of the Accepted Manuscript in a repository by the author(s) or with their consent.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="TEMI_12_2272638.pdf"/><abstract><title>ABSTRACT</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Bordetella pertussis</italic> is a Gram-negative, strictly human re-emerging respiratory pathogen and the causative agent of whooping cough. Similar to other Gram-negative pathogens, <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> produces the type III secretion system, but its role in the pathogenesis of <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> is enigmatic and yet to be elucidated. Here, we combined RNA-seq, LC-MS/MS, and co-immunoprecipitation techniques to identify and characterize the novel CesT family T3SS chaperone BP2265. We show that this chaperone specifically interacts with the secreted T3SS regulator BtrA and represents the first non-flagellar chaperone required for the secretion of an anti-sigma factor. In its absence, secretion but not production of BtrA and most T3SS substrates is severely impaired. It appears that the role of BtrA in regulating T3SS extends beyond its activity as an antagonist of the sigma factor BtrS. Predictions made by artificial intelligence system AlphaFold support the chaperone function of BP2265 towards BtrA and outline the structural basis for the interaction of BtrA with its target BtrS. We propose to rename BP2265 to BtcB for the <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella</italic> type III chaperone of BtrA.</p><p>In addition, the absence of the BtcB chaperone results in increased expression of numerous flagellar genes and several virulence genes. While increased production of flagellar proteins and intimin BipA translated into increased biofilm formation by the mutant, enhanced production of virulence factors resulted in increased cytotoxicity towards human macrophages. We hypothesize that these phenotypic traits result indirectly from impaired secretion of BtrA and altered activity of the BtrA/BtrS regulatory node.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>KEYWORDS</title><kwd><italic toggle="yes">Bordetella pertussis</italic></kwd><kwd>T3SS</kwd><kwd>CesT chaperone</kwd><kwd>anti-sigma factor</kwd><kwd>biofilm</kwd></kwd-group><support-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Czech Science Foundation</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100001824</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This work was supported by grant 23-05634S (to B.V.) from the Czech Science Foundation (www.gacr.cz) and by funding from RVO61388971.</funding-statement></funding-group></support-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="1"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="57"/><page-count count="13"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" disp-level="1" id="S001"><title>Introduction</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Bordetella pertussis</italic> is a Gram-negative human pathogen that causes whooping cough, also known as pertussis, a highly contagious re-emerging respiratory disease. After infection, <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> colonizes the ciliated epithelium of the human upper respiratory tract and causes inflammation, activation of immune responses and damage to host tissues [<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. To efficiently colonize the respiratory tract and evade immune response, <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> produces a variety of virulence factors, including adhesins and toxins [<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">1&#x02013;3</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> also encodes the type III secretion system (T3SS), which is an important virulence factor in many other pathogenic bacteria. In the closely related <italic toggle="yes">B. bronchiseptica</italic> the T3SS is required for persistent colonization of the lower respiratory tract of mammals [<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. However, compared to <italic toggle="yes">B. bronchiseptica</italic>, the role of T3SS in the pathogenesis of <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> remains to be clarified. Previously, the T3SS was assumed to be nonfunctional in <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> because studies on Tohama I, the highly-passaged, laboratory-adapted reference strain, failed to demonstrate secretion of T3SS substrates. Nevertheless, the T3SS was later shown to be functional in fresh clinical isolates of <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> and in Tohama I cells exposed to iron or glutamate limitation or passaged in mice or human macrophages [<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6&#x02013;10</xref>]. Moreover, the activity of T3SS has been reported to be increased in the presence of CO<sub>2</sub> [<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] or upon exposure to blood or serum [<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. On the other hand, after internalization by macrophages the expression of T3SS genes in intracellular <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. bronchiseptica</italic> cells is significantly reduced [<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">14&#x02013;16</xref>]. Furthermore, our recent studies employing highly sensitive label-free proteomic analysis using liquid chromatography coupled with tandem mass spectrometry (LC-MS/MS) proved that the laboratory-adapted strain Tohama I secretes T3SS components also under standard laboratory conditions, albeit to a much lesser extent than low-passage fresh clinical isolates [<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p><p>The T3SS apparatus consists of a macromolecular injectisome that delivers effector proteins directly from the bacterial cytosol into the host cell cytosol [<xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. To date, only two effector proteins have been described in bordetellae. The effector BteA, also known as BopC, is responsible for the cytotoxicity associated with T3SS in <italic toggle="yes">B. bronchiseptica</italic> and to a lesser extent in <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> [<xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20&#x02013;23</xref>], but its mechanism of action remains unknown [<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. The other effector is the BopN protein [<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], but this has recently been crystallized and characterized as a gatekeeper protein required for targeted translocation of the BteA effector into host cells [<xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. The T3SS genes are organized in two adjacent loci: <italic toggle="yes">bsc</italic>, encoding the T3SS apparatus, and <italic toggle="yes">btr</italic>, encoding regulatory proteins [<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27&#x02013;29</xref>], while the <italic toggle="yes">bteA</italic> effector gene is expressed from a distant locus. Expression of T3SS genes in <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> is controlled by the two-component system BvgAS, which regulates hundreds of genes, including the extracytoplasmic function sigma factor BtrS encoded in the <italic toggle="yes">btr</italic> locus [<xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. BtrS in turn activates the expression of genes within the <italic toggle="yes">btr</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">bsc</italic> loci, although the expression of some genes within these loci is not dependent on BtrS [<xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. The activity of BtrS is inhibited by its cognate secreted antagonist BtrA (also called BspR), and in <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic>, both factors form a regulatory mechanism that couples the expression and function of T3SS [<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. In <italic toggle="yes">B. bronchiseptica</italic>, however, the BtrA regulon is more complex, controlling the expression of nearly 300 genes. More than 80 genes, including toxins and adhesins, are activated and over 200 genes, including flagellar genes and the T3SS operon, are repressed by BtrA [<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Another level of regulation is added by the RNA chaperone Hfq, an important post-transcriptional regulator of Gram-negative bacteria, that has been shown to be required for the expression and functionality of the T3SS in <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> [<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].</p><p>Our recent study revealed that both direct exposure to blood and passage of cells from agar plates to liquid medium had a positive effect on the expression profiles of the T3SS locus in <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> [<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. However, the response to blood exposure was not uniform, and some genes did not respond to either blood exposure or passage. Only one gene, <italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic>, was downregulated upon transfer from solid to liquid medium. This gene was previously referred to as <italic toggle="yes">orf1</italic> because its affiliation with the T3SS was not clear [<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>] and its potential role in T3SS functionality was long overlooked. According to the NCBI database, the BP2265 protein shares properties with the chaperone CesT (InterPro family IPR010261). In enteropathogenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> (EPEC) strains, CesT was shown to provide a chaperone function for the translocated intimin receptor (Tir) [<xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. Furthermore, after translocation, liberated cytosolic CesT interacts with the global translation inhibitor CsrA and antagonizes its activity [<xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>].</p><p>In this study we analysed the global regulon of the BP2265 chaperone and its requirement for T3SS functionality using multiple approaches combining omics techniques, immunoproteomics, and <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> analyses based on artificial intelligence systems. Our data suggest that BP2265 is a cognate chaperone of the secreted anti-sigma factor BtrA and demonstrate that cells lacking the <italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> gene display several phenotypic traits such as impaired secretion of T3SS substrates, increased production of biofilm and enhanced cytotoxicity.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods" disp-level="1" id="S002"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec disp-level="2" id="S002-S2001"><title>Bacterial strains and growth conditions</title><p><italic toggle="yes">Bordetella pertussis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. bronchiseptica</italic> strains listed in Supplementary Table 1 were grown on Bordet Gengou agar (BGA, Difco) supplemented with 15% defibrinated sheep blood at 37 &#x000b0;C. For planktonic cultures, bacteria were gown in Stainer-Scholte medium (SSM) supplemented with 0.1% cyclodextrin and 0.5% casamino acids at 37 &#x000b0;C. To harvest samples for transcriptomic and proteomic analyses, three independent cultivations of B1917 strain and its isogenic &#x00394;<italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> mutant were performed to collect three biological replicates. Cultures were grown overnight in SSM to mid exponential phase of growth (OD<sub>600</sub> &#x02248; 1.3-1.6). Next, cells were pelleted by centrifugation (10,000&#x02005;<italic toggle="yes">g</italic>, 4 &#x000b0;C, 10&#x02005;min) for RNA and protein isolation. For secretome analysis, culture supernatants were filtered through 0.22 &#x003bc;m filters and precipitated.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="S002-S2002"><title>Construction of the &#x00394;BP2265 deletion mutant and BP2265-triple FLAG tag fusion</title><p>The deletions were introduced into the chromosome of the <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> B1917 strain as described previously [<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. To construct the &#x00394;<italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> deletion mutant, two DNA fragments flanking the corresponding gene were amplified from the upstream region (which ends with initiation TTG codon of the <italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> gene and the <italic toggle="yes">Nhe</italic>I site) and the downstream region (which begins with the <italic toggle="yes">Nhe</italic>I site and the TAG stop codon of the <italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> gene). The resulting PCR products were ligated via a <italic toggle="yes">Nhe</italic>I site, and the ligation mixture was used as a template to generate a PCR product containing the intended deletion. In the resulting product, the start and stop codons of the corresponding gene separated by the <italic toggle="yes">Nhe</italic>I restriction site formed a markerless in-frame deletion. Similar approach was used to create chromosomal <italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic>-triple FLAG tag in-frame fusion. The upstream and downstream fragments flanking the stop codon of the <italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> gene and carrying FLAG tag sequence at 3&#x000b4;and 5&#x000b4;end, respectively, were amplified and ligated via a <italic toggle="yes">Psi</italic>I site present in the FLAG sequence. In the resulting product, the FLAG tag was inserted in-frame in front of the TAG stop codon of the <italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> gene.</p><p>For both constructs, the final PCR product was ligated into the allelic exchange plasmid pSS4245 [<xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>], the resulting plasmid was transformed into <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> SM10 strain and transferred into <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> B1917 by conjugation. After two recombination events, the strain carrying the desired mutation in <italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> was obtained and verified by sequencing of the amplified PCR product covering the adjacent chromosomal regions. The primers used in this study are listed in the Supplementary Table 2.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="S002-S2003"><title>RNA isolation, sequencing and data analysis</title><p>Cell pellets were suspended in TE buffer (10&#x02005;mM Tris, 1&#x02005;mM EDTA; pH 8.0) containing 1&#x02005;mg/ml of lysozyme (Sigma) and total RNA was isolated from lysed cells using TRI Reagent (Sigma) according to manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol. Removal of DNA was achieved by treatment of samples with TURBO DNA-free kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific). RNA quality and quantity was determined by agarose gel electrophoresis and using the Nanodrop One machine (Thermo Fisher Scientific). Furthermore, the RNA quality was assessed at sequencing facility (Institute of Advanced Biotechnology; <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.iabio.eu/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.iabio.eu/</ext-link>) on an Agilent 2100 Bioanalyzer device. All samples displayed RNA integrity numbers higher than 9.</p><p>Prior to sequencing, ribosomal RNA was depleted with NEBNext rRNA Depletion Kit (NEB). Libraries were prepared with NEBNext Ultra II Directional RNA Library Prep kit for Illumina (NEB) and sequenced on a NovaSeq 6000 platform (Illumina) using paired-end 101 base-pair read protocol at sequencing facility. RNA-seq data is deposited at the European Nucleotide Archive under project accession number PRJEB65304. Quality control of the obtained reads was done using FastQC (<ext-link xlink:href="https://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc/</ext-link>). Quality trimming and adaptor removal was performed using Trimmomatic [<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. Next, reads were mapped to <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> Tohama I transcriptome and quantified using Salmon algorithm [<xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. Prior to differential expression (DE) analysis, unwanted variations caused by batch effects or library preparation were removed from the samples using the RUVs correction method of RUVseq (version 1.20.0) [<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>] in R (version 3.6.3). DE analysis was performed using DESeq2 [<xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>], genes with a |log<sub>2</sub> fold change|&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;1 and with adjusted <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.05 were considered as significantly differentially expressed.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="S002-S2004"><title>LC-MS/MS and data analysis</title><p>Protein isolation, sample preparation and LC-MS/MS was performed as already described [<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] (for details see Supplementary methods). The proteomics data were deposited to the ProteomeXchange Consortium via the PRIDE [<xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>] partner repository with the dataset identifier PXD044487.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="S002-S2005"><title>Protein detection and immunoblotting</title><p>Samples of pelleted cells equivalent to 0.1 OD<sub>600</sub> unit or samples of secreted proteins precipitated from culture supernatants equivalent to 1.0 OD<sub>600</sub> unit were separated on 12.5% SDS-polyacrylamide gels and transferred onto a nitrocellulose membrane using Trans-Blot&#x000ae; Turbo&#x02122; system (Bio-Rad). Membranes were blocked with 5% skim milk and probed with in-house produced mouse polyclonal antibodies raised against recombinant proteins Bsp22, BopB, BopN, and BteA at a 1: 10 000 dilution followed by incubation with anti-mouse IgG antibodies conjugated with horse radish peroxidase (Cell Signalling Technology, Inc.) at a 1:10 000 dilution. The antibody&#x02013;antigen complexes were visualized using SuperSignal West Femto chemiluminescent substrate (Thermo) according to standard protocol on G:Box Chemi XRQ device (Syngene).</p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="S002-S2006"><title>Co-immunoprecipitation</title><p><italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> B1917 strain (control, non-tagged BP2265) and B1917 strain carrying FLAG-tagged BP2265 were grown in triplicates to mid-exponential phase (OD<sub>600</sub> &#x02248; 1.5). Cultures (7&#x02005;mL) were centrifuged (9,000&#x02005;g, 15&#x02005;min, 4 &#x000b0;C) and washed with 7&#x02005;mL of TBS buffer (50&#x02005;mM Tris, pH 7.5, 150&#x02005;mM NaCl). Each pellet was then resuspended in 1.4&#x02005;ml lysis buffer (TBS buffer, 1&#x02005;mM EDTA, 0.1% IGEPAL CA-630, protease inhibitors) and sonicated in Protein LoBind&#x000ae; tubes (Eppendorf). The lysate was cleared by centrifugation (9,000&#x02005;g, 10&#x02005;min, 4 &#x000b0;C) and 1.2&#x02005;ml of the lysate was mixed with pre-washed ANTI-FLAG M2 Magnetic Beads (15&#x02005;&#x000b5;l packed gel volume; Sigma-Aldrich). Co-immunoprecipitation was performed for approximately 16&#x02005;h at 4 &#x000b0;C and then the beads were washed three times in 600&#x02005;&#x000b5;l TBS, divided into two parts and separated on magnetic rack. One part of the dry beads was immediately frozen at &#x02212;80 &#x000b0;C (beads-bound fraction), and the second part of the beads was gently incubated three times in 75&#x02005;&#x000b5;l elution buffer (100&#x02005;mM glycine, pH 3) for 5&#x02005;min at room temperature. Each elution was equilibrated with 7.5&#x02005;&#x000b5;l of 10X TBS buffer, all three elutions were combined and frozen at &#x02212;80 &#x000b0;C (elution fraction).</p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="S002-S2007"><title>Motility assay</title><p>Motility assays were performed according to two already described protocols. To follow the protocol of Hoffman and colleagues [<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. bronchiseptica</italic> RB50 cultures were grown in SSM overnight for 20&#x02005;h, diluted to OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.8 and 2 &#x003bc;l of the suspension was stabbed into SSM motility agar plates. Motility agar plates were prepared freshly before assay and consisted of 15&#x02005;mL of SS medium containing 40&#x02005;mM magnesium sulphate and 0.4% agar. Alternatively, motility was determined as described by Hiramatsu <italic toggle="yes">et al</italic>. [<xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. bronchiseptica</italic> cultures grown in SSM were washed, diluted to OD<sub>600</sub> of 1.0 in Hanks&#x02019; balanced salt solution (Sigma-Aldrich) containing 20&#x02005;mM Hepes (pH 7.4) and 0.1% BSA, and incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 1&#x02005;h. One microliter of bacterial suspensions was then stabbed into motility agar based on BGA (0.45% potato infusion powder, 0.55% NaCl, 1% casein hydrolysate, 1% glycerol, 1% BSA, and 0.4% agar). In both protocols, agar plates with <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">B. bronchiseptica</italic> strains were incubated in a humidified incubator at 37 &#x000b0;C for three days.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="S002-S2008"><title>Biofilm formation assay</title><p><italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> cells grown on agar were suspended in SSM to a final OD<sub>600</sub> of 0.3. Triplicate samples of diluted cultures (200 &#x003bc;l) were inoculated in parallel into 96-well non-treated tissue culture plates. The plates were incubated at 37 &#x000b0;C for up to three days in the absence or presence of 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. At each time point (24, 48, and 72&#x02005;h), the loosly adherent and planctonic bacteria were discarded by washing the wells vigorously three times with water. Adherent cells were stained with 0.1% solution of crystal violet for 45&#x02005;min. Plates were washed with water and dried, adsorbed crystal violet was then solubilized in 200 &#x003bc;l of 95% ethanol for 15&#x02005;min. To quantify biofilm formation, 100 &#x003bc;l of stained solution was transferred to a microtitration plate and the <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub>595</sub> of the crystal violet staining was measured with a multi-well spectrophotometer Epoch (BioTek).</p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="S002-S2009"><title>Cell viability and cytotoxicity assays</title><p>Viability of infected THP-1 macrophages was determined spectrophotometrically as already described [<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] using the WST-1 assay kit (Roche). THP-1 monocytes (ATCC; TIB-202) cultured in Dulbecco&#x02032;s Modified Eagle&#x02032;s Medium (DMEM, Sigma-Aldrich) were seeded in 48-well plates (2&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>5</sup> cells per well) and differentiated into macrophages as previously described [<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. The differentiated macrophages were infected in triplicates with <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> cells diluted in 400&#x02005;&#x000b5;l DMEM at a multiplicity of infection (MOI) of 50 bacteria per macrophage. After adddition of 40&#x02005;&#x000b5;l of WST-1 substrate, the plates were centrifuged at 600&#x02005;g for 3&#x02005;min to facilitate interaction of bacteria with macrophages and incubated at 37 &#x000b0;C and 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. At indicated time points, the viability of infected and uninfected macrophages (treated in the same way and serving as controls, 100% viability) was determined as <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub>450</sub> of the formazan dye with a multi-well spectrophotometer Epoch (BioTek).</p><p>Cytotoxicity towards HeLa cells (ATCC; CCL-2) was determined essentially as already described for THP-1 macrophages [<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] using CellTox<sup>TM</sup> Green Cytotoxicity Assay (Promega). HeLa cells grown in DMEM without phenol red indicator were seeded in 96-well plate (1x 10<sup>5</sup> cells per well), allowed to attach overnight at 37 &#x000b0;C and 5% CO<sub>2</sub> and next day infected by adding 50 &#x003bc;l of a <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> suspension (5x 10<sup>6</sup> cells per well; MOI 50). After addition of 50 &#x003bc;l CellTox<sup>TM</sup> reagent, plates were shortly centrifuged (400&#x02005;g, 3&#x02005;min) and then incubated in a Tecan Spark reader (37 &#x000b0;C, 5% CO<sub>2</sub>) for 10&#x02005;h to measure the fluorescent signal.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" disp-level="1" id="S003"><title>Results</title><sec disp-level="2" id="S003-S2001"><title>The putative T3SS chaperone BP2265 is required for the secretion of T3SS substrates and T3SS-mediated cytotoxicity</title><p>First, we analysed the homology between the BP2265 protein and the CesT chaperone of <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>. While the sequence homology was rather low (18.2% identity, 29.3% similarity; see Supplementary Figure 1A), the structural homology between both proteins determined with the PyMOL tool was at 56% (Supplementary Figure 1B). To test the role of BP2265 in T3SS functionality, we first decided to construct a mutant carrying a markerless in-frame deletion of the <italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> gene in <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> strain B1917 and test its ability to produce and secrete T3SS components. Strain B1917 was isolated from a patient with pertussis disease in the Netherlands in 2000 and is representative of current isolates in Europe [<xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. In addition, for experimental tractability, it is beneficial to study T3SS function in <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> in recent low-passage clinical isolates, as they exhibit greatly increased production and secretion of T3SS components compared with the high-passage reference strain Tohama I [<xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Western blot analysis revealed that compared to the wild-type (wt) strain, the strain lacking the <italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> gene produced comparable amounts of BteA and BopN, but strongly reduced amounts of Bsp22 and BopB proteins (<xref rid="F0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>A). In addition, analysis of culture supernatants showed that the mutant strain secreted negligible amounts of all T3SS proteins tested. These results clearly demonstrated that the putative T3SS chaperone BP2265 is required for proper T3SS function in <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic>. Next, we reasoned that strongly decreased secretion of T3SS substrates, including the effector BteA, would result in reduced cytotoxicity of the mutant towards human HeLa cells, a model system sensitive to BteA activity [<xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Compared with the wt cells, infection with the &#x00394;<italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> mutant yielded strongly reduced cytotoxicity to HeLa cells determined as changes in cell membrane integrity using the CellTox Green dye (<xref rid="F0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>B).
<fig position="float" id="F0001"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>The &#x00394;<italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> strain secretes strongly reduced amounts of T3SS substrates and is less cytotoxic compared to the wt strain. (A) Samples of pelleted cells (P) equivalent to 0.1 OD<sub>600</sub> unit and precipitated supernatant proteins (S) equivalent to 1 OD<sub>600</sub> unit were separated on 12.5% SDS-PAGE and analysed by immunoblotting using antibodies against Bsp22, BopB, BopN, and BteA proteins. Only the relevant parts of the membranes are shown. (B) Cytotoxicity towards HeLa cells was determined with the wt and &#x00394;<italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> strain at MOI 50. Cells were infected in triplicates, uninfected cells served as controls. Immediately after addition of fluorescent dye, HeLa cells were incubated for 10&#x02005;h (37 &#x000b0;C, 5% CO<sub>2</sub>) in the microplate reader. During incubation, the fluorescence of the DNA-binding dye CellTox Green, which is proportional to cytotoxicity, was measured every 30&#x02005;min. The graph shows the mean values and the standard errors of the means. The result is representative of two independent experiments.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="TEMI_A_2272638_F0001_OC" content-type="color" specific-use="web-only" position="float"/><graphic xlink:href="TEMI_A_2272638_F0001_PC" content-type="color" specific-use="print-only" position="float"/></alternatives></fig></p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="S003-S2002"><title>Transcriptomic profiling of the &#x00394;BP2265 mutant</title><p>Given the structural homology of the BP2265 protein with the CesT family of chaperones and the complex role of CesT in regulating gene expression in <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic>, we hypothesized that the BP2265 protein also plays a broader role in the control of gene expression in <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic>. To test this hypothesis, we analysed and compared global transcriptomic and proteomic profiles between the <italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> mutant and the wt strain using the RNA-seq and LC-MS/MS methods, respectively.</p><p>Previously, we showed that pre-incubation with blood affects the expression and secretion of T3SS components [<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. To make our study robust and minimize blood-specific effects, we used sheep blood from three different animals to obtain three biological replicates for RNA-seq analysis. On average, 10 million reads per sample were mapped to the <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> genome. Principal component analysis revealed that despite some variability among replicates, samples of the wt strain cluster separately from samples of the mutant (Supplementary Figure 2A). Next, we performed differential expression (DE) analysis to identify the genes whose expression was affected by the deletion of the <italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> gene. The DE analysis revealed that a total of 54 genes were significantly modulated in the mutant (&#x02502;log2FC&#x02502;&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;1; adjusted <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) (Supplementary Table 3). Among the 29 upregulated genes, we found 22 genes encoding flagellar proteins, two pseudogenes, two transcriptional regulator genes <italic toggle="yes">BP0142</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">BP1496</italic>, the autotransporter gene <italic toggle="yes">BP0529</italic>, one non-coding RNA gene, and the <italic toggle="yes">bipA</italic> gene encoding an outer membrane ligand-binding protein. Among the 25 downregulated genes, we found 20 genes belonging to the T3SS operon, two pseudogenes, one IS<italic toggle="yes">481</italic> transposase gene, and two non-coding RNA genes. These results indicated that the BP2265 regulon is highly specific, consisting primarily of T3SS and flagellar genes (<xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).
<fig position="float" id="F0002"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Heatmap showing flagellar, T3SS, and virulence genes displaying significantly altered omics profiles. The graph shows significant log<sub>2</sub> fold changes (FC) in transcriptomic/proteomic profiles of genes/proteins that were downregulated (blue) or upregulated (yellow) in the &#x00394;<italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> mutant compared to the wt strain. Transcriptome; gray filled cells indicate that the change in expression of the corresponding gene was not significant. Proteome and secretome; gray filled cells indicate that the change in abundance of the corresponding protein was not significant or the protein was not detected by mass spectrometry.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="TEMI_A_2272638_F0002_OC" content-type="color" specific-use="web-only" position="float"/><graphic xlink:href="TEMI_A_2272638_F0002_PC" content-type="color" specific-use="print-only" position="float"/></alternatives></fig></p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="S003-S2003"><title>Proteomic profiling of the &#x00394;BP2265 mutant</title><p>We next tested whether the changes in gene expression profiles resulting from deletion of the <italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> gene translated into differential production and secretion of proteins. The cell-associated (bacterial pellets) and cell-free (filtered culture supernatants) fractions of wt and &#x00394;<italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> strains cultures were analysed by LC-MS/MS. PCA performed with both datasets showed some degree of variability but the samples of the wt strain clustered apart of &#x00394;<italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> samples (Supplementary Figure 2B,C). Label-free quantification of cell-associated proteins identified 221 proteins that showed significantly altered abundance (Supplementary Table 4). Interestingly, the vast majority of proteins (214 of 221; 96.8%) displayed increased abundance in the mutant. In good agreement with the transcriptomic data, we identified 7 flagellar and chemotaxis proteins and BipA protein among the 10 proteins with highest increase in quantity in the mutant (<xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). Of note, the amount of BtrA, adenylate cyclase toxin (ACT, also called CyaA) and components of its secretion system (CyaB, CyaD, CyaE), pertactin, and S5 subunit of the pertussis toxin was also significantly increased. Consistent with Western blot analysis and transcriptomic data, we found the T3SS translocon components BopB, BopD, and Bsp22 among the proteins with decreased levels (<xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).</p><p>Label-free quantification analysis of secreted proteins revealed that 47 proteins exhibited significant changes in quantity between the &#x00394;<italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> mutant and the wt strain (Supplementary Table 5). Among the 19 proteins that showed reduced amounts in culture supernatants of the mutant, we identified 9 T3SS proteins, including BopN, BteA, Bsp22, BopB, BopD, and BscE, which were significantly reduced, and proteins BtrA, BscI, BscF, and BscX, which were not detected (<xref rid="F0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>). Among the 28 proteins with increased abundance, we found predominantly putative periplasmic, membrane, and exported proteins including BipA.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="S003-S2004"><title>Immunoproteomics identifies anti-sigma factor BtrA as an interaction partner of CesT chaperone BP2265</title><p>In our next experiment, we applied immunoproteomics to identify the cognate substrate(s) of chaperone BP2265. B1917 cells producing non-tagged BP2265 protein (control) and FLAG-tagged BP2265 (serving as a &#x0201c;bait&#x0201d; protein) were grown to log phase in SSM, and cell lysates were incubated with anti-FLAG M2 magnetic beads. Western blot analysis of the proteins captured on the beads and proteins eluted from the beads revealed that a substantial portion of the BP2265 bait protein remains bound to the beads after elution (data not shown). Therefore, to obtain complete information on all possible interaction partners, we decided to analyse both fractions by the LC-MS/MS method. Both analyses yielded similar and highly specific results, as in addition to the bait protein BP2265, only the T3SS-secreted anti-sigma factor BtrA was highly enriched in both the captured and eluted (log<sub>2</sub>FC values&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;5) protein fractions compared to non-tagged controls (<xref rid="T0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Among the significantly enriched proteins bound on the beads, we also found proteins BP1556, BP2173 and BP1894 to be approximately two-fold enriched. Analysis of the eluted proteins revealed only one additional significantly enriched protein, the sigma factor BtrS, which was most likely pulled down with its interaction partner BtrA. BtrS was also found among the proteins captured on the beads, but the enrichment did not reach the two-fold threshold (<xref rid="T0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).
<table-wrap position="float" id="T0001"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Significantly enriched proteins identified by immunoproteomics.</p></caption><!--OASIS TABLE HERE--><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup><col width="1*"/><col width="1*"/><col width="1*"/><col width="1*"/><col width="1*"/><col width="1*"/></colgroup><thead valign="bottom"><tr><th rowspan="2" align="left">Protein</th><th colspan="2" align="center">Beads</th><th colspan="2" align="center">Elution</th><th align="center">&#x000a0;</th></tr><tr><th align="center">log<sub>2</sub>FC<xref rid="TF1" ref-type="table-fn"><sup>a</sup></xref></th><th align="center">q-value</th><th align="center">log<sub>2</sub>FC</th><th align="center">q-value</th><th align="center">Annotation</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">BP2265</td><td align="char" char=".">12.237</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td align="char" char=".">5.801</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td align="left">CesT family T3SS chaperone</td></tr><tr><td align="left">BtrA</td><td align="char" char=".">5.433</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td align="char" char=".">5.311</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td align="left">anti-ECF sigma factor BtrA</td></tr><tr><td align="left">BtrS</td><td align="char" char="."><italic toggle="yes">0</italic>.<italic toggle="yes">898</italic></td><td align="char" char=".">0.015</td><td align="char" char=".">1.891</td><td align="char" char=".">0.003</td><td align="left">ECF sigma factor</td></tr><tr><td align="left">BP1556</td><td align="char" char=".">1.154</td><td align="char" char=".">0</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">YrdC-like domain-containing protein</td></tr><tr><td align="left">BP2173</td><td align="char" char=".">1.121</td><td align="char" char=".">0.008</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">Putative ferredoxin</td></tr><tr><td align="left">BP1894</td><td align="char" char=".">1.072</td><td align="char" char=".">0.001</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">MarR-type domain-containing protein</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="TF1"><label><sup>a</sup></label><p>Values that did not reach the two-fold threshold are in italics.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="S003-S2005"><title>In silico modelling of protein&#x02013;protein interactions between BP2265 and BtrA</title><p>Our co-immunoprecipitation data suggested that the chaperone BP2265 interacts with BtrA. Therefore, we attempted to model this interaction using the deep learning system AlphaFold (AF) [<xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>] which has recently been trained also for multimeric inputs. This model, named AF-Multimer (AF-M), has been shown to perform reasonably well in predicting interactions between two protein chains [<xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>].</p><p>Similar to other chaperones, the CesT chaperone also functions as a dimer. Thus, we first used the AF-M system to model the BP2265 dimer yielding the typical heart-shaped structure (<xref rid="F0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>A). Next, we used the predicted structures of the BP2265 dimer and the BtrA protein (<xref rid="F0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>B) and modelled their interaction using AF-M program. The predicted structure suggests that the unstructured N-terminal region of BtrA (residues 1-40) is wrapped around the BP2265 dimer (<xref rid="F0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>C). Furthermore, the predicted BtrA structure is interrupted at residues 40 and 155, indicating structural changes in BtrA caused by interaction with the BP2265 chaperone. Consequently, the central helix (residues 136-164) is split into two separate helices (residues 136&#x02013;154 and residues 155-164). Interestingly, this model also suggests a small structural change in the outermost N-terminal part of BtrA, represented by the formation of a short &#x003b2;-sheet (residues 5-8). Because our co-IP experiments suggested a specific interaction between BtrA and BtrS proteins, we used the AF-M system to model this interaction (<xref rid="F0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>D). The predicted heterodimer suggests an &#x003b1;-helix-mediated interaction between the central helix of BtrA (residues 136-164) and the N-terminal helix of BtrS (residues 21-38).
<fig position="float" id="F0003"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p><italic toggle="yes">In silico</italic> modelling of T3SS proteins interactions. (A) Ribbon diagram of the dimer of BP2265 protein predicted by the AF-M algorithm. The monomers of BP2265 are shown in red and pink. (B) Ribbon diagram of the BtrA protein predicted by the AF system (Uniprot code Q7VWI6) with depicted N and C termini. (C) Ribbon diagram of the complex between the BP2265 dimer and the BtrA protein predicted using the AF-M system. Depicted are the N and C termini, the short N-terminal &#x003b2;-sheet, and the positions where the predicted BtrA structure is interrupted (residues 40 and 155). (D) Ribbon diagram of the BtrA-BtrS complex predicted by the AF-M system. The N and C termini of BtrA (blue) and BtrS (green) are depicted.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="TEMI_A_2272638_F0003_OC" content-type="color" specific-use="web-only" position="float"/><graphic xlink:href="TEMI_A_2272638_F0003_PC" content-type="color" specific-use="print-only" position="float"/></alternatives></fig></p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="S003-S2006"><title>Phenotypic characterization of the &#x00394;BP2265 mutant</title><p>Next, we tested the possibility that the absence of the BP2265 chaperone leads, besides aberrant secretion of T3SS components, to additional phenotypic changes. The increased production of numerous flagellar proteins suggested that the mutant will exhibit increased motility. Therefore, we examined the motility of wt and &#x00394;<italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> strains in soft SSM agar under modulatory conditions (40&#x02005;mM magnesium sulphate), which have been shown to induce motility in <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella</italic> cells [<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. To verify that our experimental setup and conditions are permissive for studying motility, we also used the motile <italic toggle="yes">B. bronchiseptica</italic> RB50 strain. As shown in <xref rid="F0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>A, unlike the control strain RB50, neither the mutant nor the wt strain were motile in our assay. Next, we tested two <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> strains that have already been shown to be motile, namely the UT-25 isolate [<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>] and strain 18323 [<xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], however, also these <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> strains were non-motile in contrast to <italic toggle="yes">B. bronchiseptica</italic> (<xref rid="F0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>A). Finally, we tested the motility of all five strains according to another protocol [<xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Again, as shown in <xref rid="F0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>B, only <italic toggle="yes">B. bronchiseptica</italic> strain RB50 exhibited motility on soft agar.
<fig position="float" id="F0004"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Motility assays. (A) Motility of <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> strains B1917, its isogenic &#x00394;<italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> mutant (upper panel), UT-25, and 18323 (lower panel) was tested together with <italic toggle="yes">B. bronchiseptica</italic> strain RB50 in 0.4% SSM motility agar containing 40&#x02005;mM magnesium sulphate. (B) Motility of <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> strains B1917, its isogenic &#x00394;<italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> mutant, UT-25, and 18323 was tested together with <italic toggle="yes">B. bronchiseptica</italic> RB50 strain in 0.4% BGA-based motility agar. In all experiments, cultures of the tested strains were stabbed into a soft agar plate and incubated at 37 &#x000b0;C for three days. All images were taken after three days of incubation. The experiment was performed four times, and the figure shows the images of a representative experiment.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="TEMI_A_2272638_F0004_OC" content-type="color" specific-use="web-only" position="float"/><graphic xlink:href="TEMI_A_2272638_F0004_PC" content-type="color" specific-use="print-only" position="float"/></alternatives></fig></p><p>Thus, we focused on another aspect of the increased production of flagellar proteins, such as biofilm formation. Indeed, flagella have been shown to be required for the initial phase of biofilm formation in several bacteria, including <italic toggle="yes">B. bronchiseptica</italic> [<xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. This observation prompted us to compare biofilm formation in the mutant and its parental strain. Both strains were incubated in SS medium without shaking, and biofilm production was monitored for several days using crystal violet method. While after one day of incubation both strains produced low but comparable amounts of biofilm, after two and three days the mutant produced significantly more biofilm than the wt strain (<xref rid="F0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>A). Expression of flagellar and chemotaxis genes in <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> has been shown to be reduced in the presence of 5% CO<sub>2</sub> [<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Compared to aerobic conditions, biofilm formation was significantly reduced in both wt and mutant strains in the presence of 5% CO<sub>2</sub> (<xref rid="F0005" ref-type="fig">Figure 5</xref>B), providing another evidence that biofilm production requires flagella.
<fig position="float" id="F0005"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>The &#x00394;<italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> strain forms increased amounts of biofilm compared to the wt strain. (A) Biofilm formation was tested in triplicate samples of the B1917 strain (wt) and its isogenic &#x00394;<italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> mutant (&#x00394;) over three days under static aerobic conditions and determined by crystal violet staining. (B) Biofilm formation was determined in triplicate samples of the wt strain (wt) and the &#x00394;<italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> mutant (&#x00394;) after two days of incubation under static conditions in the absence (-CO<sub>2</sub>) or presence of 5% CO<sub>2</sub> (+CO<sub>2</sub>) by crystal violet staining. Left panels; images of wells with crystal violet stain eluted from the biofilm formed by the corresponding strain. Right panels; graphs quantifying biofilm formation determined as <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub>595</sub> of crystal violet staining. Results are averages from three replicates, error bars represent standard deviations. Statistical analysis for panel A was performed using the two-way ANOVA test for multiple comparisons (Sidak&#x000b4;s test); ns, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05; **, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01; ****, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001. Statistical analysis for panel B was performed using the two-way ANOVA test for multiple comparisons (Tukey&#x000b4;s test); **, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01; ****, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001. Three independent experiments were performed for each panel, and one representative experiment is shown.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="TEMI_A_2272638_F0005_OC" content-type="color" specific-use="web-only" position="float"/><graphic xlink:href="TEMI_A_2272638_F0005_PC" content-type="color" specific-use="print-only" position="float"/></alternatives></fig></p><p>Finally, we examined whether increased production of virulence factors including adenylate cyclase toxin resulted in increased cytotoxicity of the mutant towards human macrophages. The viability of human monocyte-derived THP-1 macrophages infected with wt and &#x00394;<italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> strains was determined spectrophotometrically using the cell proliferation reagent WST-1 at 20, 40, 60 and 80&#x02005;min after infection. At all tested time points, the viability of macrophages infected with the mutant was significantly lower than that of macrophages infected with the wt strain (<xref rid="F0006" ref-type="fig">Figure 6</xref>).
<fig position="float" id="F0006"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Viability of THP-1 macrophages infected with &#x00394;<italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> mutant is reduced compared to the wt strain. THP-1 macrophages were infected in triplicate with the wt strain and the &#x00394;<italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> mutant at MOI of 50 bacteria per macrophage. Infection was initiated by addition of WST-1 reagent and centrifugation of bacterial cells to facilitate the interaction with macrophages. During infection, <italic toggle="yes">A</italic><sub>450</sub> of samples, which is proportional to cell viability, was determined 20, 40, 60, and 80&#x02005;min post-infection using multi-well spectrophotometer (Biotek). The absorbance of uninfected cells treated in the same manner was arbitrarily set to 100%. The dot plot shows the individual data points, and the labels above indicate statistical significance. Statistical analysis was performed using a two-way ANOVA test for multiple comparisons (Sidak&#x000b4;s test); ****, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>-value&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.0001. The result is representative of three independent experiments.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="TEMI_A_2272638_F0006_OB" content-type="black-white" specific-use="web-only" position="float"/><graphic xlink:href="TEMI_A_2272638_F0006_PC" content-type="color" specific-use="print-only" position="float"/></alternatives></fig></p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" disp-level="1" id="S004"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this work, we have focused on a relatively overlooked member of the T3SS locus of <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic>, the putative T3SS chaperone BP2265. Its high structural homology with <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> CesT, the size of 15.9&#x02005;kDa, the presence of an &#x003b1; helix in the C-terminal part, and the association with only one secreted substrate indicate that BP2265 represents a genuine class IA T3SS chaperone [<xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. To elucidate the role of the BP2265 chaperone in <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic>, we combined omics techniques, immunoproteomics, standard biochemical methods, and deep learning system. First, we demonstrate that the &#x00394;<italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> mutant shows reduced expression of most T3SS genes, secretes strongly reduced amounts of almost all T3SS substrates and, consequently, exhibits strongly reduced T3SS toxicity. Second, we show that BP2265 interacts specifically with the BtrA protein, and this interaction is supported by <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> data obtained with the AF-M program. BtrA cannot be <italic toggle="yes">bona fide</italic> considered a T3SS effector protein, and therefore BP2265 represents first non-flagellar T3SS chaperone required for the secretion of an anti-sigma factor.</p><p>Our immunoproteomic data revealed that the T3SS-specific sigma factor BtrS is co-purified with BtrA, confirming previous evidence for a specific interaction of these two proteins [<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Given the role of BtrA in inhibiting the activity of the BtrS and the poor secretion of BtrA in the &#x00394;<italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> strain, the reduced expression of most T3SS genes in the mutant was anticipated. On the other hand, the strongly reduced secretion but not production of early, intermediate, and late T3SS substrates is surprising and suggests that secretion of BtrA occurs as early as basal body formation. Our data demonstrate the pivotal role of the CesT chaperone BP2265 in BtrA secretion and indicate that its interaction with BtrA is a prerequisite for efficient assembly of the injectisome and efficient secretion of T3SS substrates. It appears that the role of BtrA in T3SS of <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> is more complex and is not limited to silencing of BtrS-mediated transcription. In support, the <italic toggle="yes">in silico</italic> modelling analysis suggests that the BP2265 homodimer binds to the N-terminal portion of BtrA, consistent with both the proposed model [<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] and previous data showing that the N-terminal part of BtrA is required for secretion [<xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Furthermore, predictions made by AF-M system indicate that BP2265 induces changes in the BtrA structure, including destabilization of the central helix, which in turn is predicted to interact with the N-terminal helix of BtrS. Thus, these observations suggest that the structural changes induced by BP2265 into the BtrA molecule prevent the interaction between BtrA and BtrS and promote secretion of BtrA. We propose to rename BP2265 as BtcB for the <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella</italic> type III chaperone of BtrA.</p><p>CesT plays a complex regulatory role in <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> due to its interaction with the global regulator CsrA [<xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. We did not identify an additional interaction partner for the chaperone BP2265, yet the BP2265 mutant exhibited altered expression profiles of numerous flagellar genes and several virulence genes. In the closely related <italic toggle="yes">B. bronchiseptica</italic>, the genes for flagella and chemotaxis are induced in the &#x00394;<italic toggle="yes">btrA</italic> strain, indicating that BtrA inhibits expression of flagella, possibly by inactivating BtrS [<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. However, this is in contrast to a recent study showing that a <italic toggle="yes">B. bronchiseptica</italic> strain lacking BtrS exhibited increased expression of flagellar genes and higher motility compared to wt [<xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. These results suggest that deletion of either the sigma factor or its antagonist may lead to similar expression pattern. The regulation of flagella expression in <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella</italic> is indeed intriguing and our data indicate that it is even more complex process, involving additional factors such as the CesT chaperone BP2265. Since our results showed that the &#x00394;<italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> strain produces increased amounts of flagellar proteins, we assumed that the mutant would exhibit increased motility. Until recently, <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> was considered non-motile bacterium, but two pieces of evidence showed that <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> produces functional flagella and can be motile [<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Unfortunately, we could not reproduce these results in our laboratory, although we used the same strains of <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis.</italic> Furthermore, <italic toggle="yes">B. bronchiseptica</italic> assayed in parallel as a positive control was motile, indicating that our experimental conditions were favourable for motility testing.</p><p>Nevertheless, we demonstrate that increased production of several flagellar proteins in the mutant leads to increased biofilm production. Flagella are known to be implicated in biofilm formation as they are required for initial attachment to the surface [<xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Mutations introduced into flagellar genes resulted in reduced biofilm formation in several bacteria, including <italic toggle="yes">B. bronchiseptica</italic> [<xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. In support, the production of biofilm was significantly increased in the &#x00394;<italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> mutant compared to the wt strain. The presence of 5% CO<sub>2</sub> significantly reduces the expression of flagellar genes in <italic toggle="yes">B. bronchiseptica</italic> [<xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] and therefore we speculated that under these conditions, flagella-dependent biofilm formation will be reduced as also shown in <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter jejuni</italic> [<xref rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Our results are congruent with this assumption, as biofilm formation was reduced in the presence of 5% CO<sub>2</sub>. In addition to the flagellar proteins, the &#x00394;<italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> mutant produced and secreted increased amounts of the intimin BipA. In pathogenic <italic toggle="yes">E. coli</italic> strains, intimins are required for the attachment to mammalian host cells [<xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Moreover, BipA is the major component of <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella pertussis</italic> biofilm [<xref rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>] and therefore, we hypothesize that the increased production of BipA provides another basis for the increased biofilm formation by the mutant.</p><p>Finally, we show that the mutant producing moderately but significantly increased levels of several virulence factors, including ACT, exhibits increased cytotoxicity towards human macrophages compared with the wt strain. In <italic toggle="yes">B. bronchiseptica</italic>, the expression of adenylate cyclase toxin gene is activated by the BtrA [<xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Thus, it is conceivable that moderately increased levels of BtrA in the &#x00394;<italic toggle="yes">BP2265</italic> mutant contribute to increased production of ACT and, consequently, increased cytotoxicity. Thus, our data suggest that the BtrA regulon in <italic toggle="yes">B. pertussis</italic> is larger and bears more similarity to <italic toggle="yes">B. bronchiseptica</italic> than previously thought.</p><p>In this work, we focused on the T3SS chaperone BP2265 of the CesT family and we demonstrate its requirement for the secretion of BtrA. We hypothesize that its chaperone activity towards the BtrA protein adds another layer in the regulatory circuit governed by the BtrA/BtrS node.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material id="SM6449" position="float" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary_methods_mass_spectroscopy</title></caption><media xlink:href="TEMI_A_2272638_SM6449.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM6447" position="float" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary_Table_5</title></caption><media xlink:href="TEMI_A_2272638_SM6447.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM6444" position="float" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary_Table_4</title></caption><media xlink:href="TEMI_A_2272638_SM6444.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM6442" position="float" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary_Table_3</title></caption><media xlink:href="TEMI_A_2272638_SM6442.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM6441" position="float" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary_Table_2</title></caption><media xlink:href="TEMI_A_2272638_SM6441.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM6440" position="float" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary_Table_1_revised</title></caption><media xlink:href="TEMI_A_2272638_SM6440.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM6438" position="float" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary_Figure_2</title></caption><media xlink:href="TEMI_A_2272638_SM6438.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM6435" position="float" content-type="local-data"><caption><title>Supplementary_Figure_1</title></caption><media xlink:href="TEMI_A_2272638_SM6435.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgment</title><p>We are grateful to Karel Harant and Pavel Talacko from the Mass Spectrometry and Proteomics Service Laboratory, Faculty of Science, Charles University for performing the LC-MS/MS runs.</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement" disp-level="1" id="S005"><title>Disclosure statement</title><p>No potential conflict of interest was reported by the author(s).</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="CIT0001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mattoo</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cherry</surname>
<given-names>JD.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Molecular pathogenesis, epidemiology, and clinical manifestations of respiratory infections due to <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella pertussis</italic> and other <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella</italic> subspecies</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>326</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>382</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.18.2.326-382.2005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15831828</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Melvin</surname>
<given-names>JA</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title><italic toggle="yes">Bordetella pertussis</italic> pathogenesis: current and future challenges</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>274</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>288</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro3235</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24608338</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Belcher</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dubois</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rivera-Millot</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Pathogenicity and virulence of <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella pertussis</italic> and its adaptation to its strictly human host</article-title>. <source>Virulence</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>2608</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2632</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/21505594.2021.1980987</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34590541</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Yuk</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Harvill</surname>
<given-names>ET</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cotter</surname>
<given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Modulation of host immune responses, induction of apoptosis and inhibition of NF-kappaB activation by the <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella</italic> type III secretion system</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>991</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1004</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.2000.01785.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10712682</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Nicholson</surname>
<given-names>TL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brockmeier</surname>
<given-names>SL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Loving</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>The <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella bronchiseptica</italic> type III secretion system is required for persistence and disease severity but not transmission in swine</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>82</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1092</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1103</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.01115-13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24366249</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Fennelly</surname>
<given-names>NK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sisti</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Higgins</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title><italic toggle="yes">Bordetella pertussis</italic> expresses a functional type III secretion system that subverts protective innate and adaptive immune responses</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>76</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1257</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1266</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.00836-07</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18195025</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gaillard</surname>
<given-names>ME</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bottero</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Castuma</surname>
<given-names>CE</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Laboratory adaptation of <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella pertussis</italic> is associated with the loss of type three secretion system functionality</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>79</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>3677</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3682</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.00136-11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21730086</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bibova</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hot</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Keidel</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Transcriptional profiling of <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella pertussis</italic> reveals requirement of RNA chaperone Hfq for Type III secretion system functionality</article-title>. <source>RNA Biol</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>175</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>185</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15476286.2015.1017237</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25674816</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Brickman</surname>
<given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cummings</surname>
<given-names>CA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Liew</surname>
<given-names>S-Y</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Transcriptional profiling of the iron starvation response in <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella pertussis</italic> provides new insights into siderophore utilization and virulence gene expression</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>193</volume>(<issue>18</issue>):<fpage>4798</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4812</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.05136-11</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21742863</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hanawa</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kamachi</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yonezawa</surname>
<given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Glutamate limitation, BvgAS activation, and (p)ppGpp regulate the expression of the <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella pertussis</italic> type 3 secretion system</article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>198</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>343</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>351</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00596-15</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26527639</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hester</surname>
<given-names>SE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lui</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nicholson</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Identification of a CO<sub>2</sub> responsive regulon in <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>e47635</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0047635</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23112828</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gestal</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rivera</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Howard</surname>
<given-names>LK</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Blood or serum exposure induce global transcriptional changes, altered antigenic profile, and increased cytotoxicity by classical <italic toggle="yes">Bordetellae</italic></article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1969</fpage>), doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.01969</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30245672</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Drzmisek</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Omics analysis of blood-responsive regulon in <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella pertussis</italic> identifies a novel essential T3SS substrate</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Sci</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>2</issue>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rivera</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Linz</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dewan</surname>
<given-names>KK</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Conservation of ancient genetic pathways for intracellular persistence Among animal pathogenic Bordetellae</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>2839</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2019.02839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31921025</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Farman</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Petr&#x000e1;&#x0010d;kov&#x000e1;</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kumar</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Avirulent phenotype promotes <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella pertussis</italic> adaptation to the intramacrophage environment</article-title>. <source>Emerg Microbes Infect</source>. <year>2023</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>e2146536</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/22221751.2022.2146536</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36357372</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Petr&#x000e1;&#x0010d;kov&#x000e1;</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Farman</surname>
<given-names>MR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Amman</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Transcriptional profiling of human macrophages during infection with <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella pertussis</italic></article-title>. <source>RNA Biol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>731</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>742</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/15476286.2020.1727694</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32070192</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Dienstbier</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Comparative integrated omics analysis of the Hfq regulon in <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella pertussis</italic></article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Sci</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>12</issue>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Dienstbier</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Amman</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Petr&#x000e1;&#x0010d;kov&#x000e1;</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Comparative omics analysis of historic and recent isolates of <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella pertussis</italic> and effects of genome rearrangements on evolution</article-title>. <source>Emerg Infect Dis</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>57</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>68</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid2701.191541</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33350934</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gal&#x000e1;n</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lara-Tejero</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Marlovits</surname>
<given-names>TC</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Bacterial type III secretion systems: specialized nanomachines for protein delivery into target cells</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Microbiol</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>68</volume>:<fpage>415</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>438</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-micro-092412-155725</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25002086</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>French</surname>
<given-names>CT</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Panina</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yeh</surname>
<given-names>SH</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>The <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella</italic> type III secretion system effector BteA contains a conserved N-terminal motif that guides bacterial virulence factors to lipid rafts</article-title>. <source>Cell Microbiol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1735</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1749</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1462-5822.2009.01361.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19650828</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kuwae</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matsuzawa</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ishikawa</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>BopC is a novel type III effector secreted by and has a critical role in type III-dependent necrotic cell death</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>281</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>6589</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6600</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M512711200</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16407269</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Stockbauer</surname>
<given-names>KE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Foreman-Wykert</surname>
<given-names>AK</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>JF.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title><italic toggle="yes">Bordetella</italic> type III secretion induces caspase 1-independent necrosis</article-title>. <source>Cell Microbiol</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>123</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>132</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1462-5822.2003.00260.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12580948</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bayram</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Malcova</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Sinkovec</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Cytotoxicity of the effector protein BteA was attenuated in <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella pertussis</italic> by insertion of an alanine residue</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>16</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>e1008512</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1008512</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32776984</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kamanova</surname>
<given-names>J.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Bordetella type III secretion injectosome and effector proteins</article-title>. <source>Front Cell Infect Microbiol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>466</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2020.00466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33014891</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Nagamatsu</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kuwae</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Konaka</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Bordetella evades the host immune system by inducing IL-10 through a type III effector, BopN</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>206</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<fpage>3073</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3088</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20090494</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20008527</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Navarrete</surname>
<given-names>KM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Bopn is a gatekeeper of the <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella</italic> type III secretion system</article-title>. <source>Microbiol Spectr</source>. <year>2023</year>: <fpage>e0411222</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37036369</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Fauconnier</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Veithen</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gueirard</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Characterization of the type III secretion locus of <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella pertussis</italic></article-title>. <source>Int J Med Microbiol</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>290</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>693</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>705</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1438-4221(01)80009-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11310448</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mattoo</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yuk</surname>
<given-names>MH</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huang</surname>
<given-names>LL</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Regulation of type III secretion in Bordetella</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>52</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1201</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1214</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2004.04053.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15130135</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ahuja</surname>
<given-names>U</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shokeen</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cheng</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Differential regulation of type III secretion and virulence genes in <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella pertussis</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella bronchiseptica</italic> by a secreted anti-sigma factor</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>113</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>2341</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2348</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1600320113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26884180</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Moon</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>The BvgAS regulon of <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella pertussis</italic></article-title>. <source>mBio</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>5</issue>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kurushima</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kuwae</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abe</surname>
<given-names>A.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>The type III secreted protein BspR regulates the virulence genes in <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella bronchiseptica</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e38925</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0038925</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22701731</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Abe</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Enteropathogenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> translocated intimin receptor, Tir, requires a specific chaperone for stable secretion</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1162</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1175</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10510231</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Elliott</surname>
<given-names>SJ</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Identification of CesT, a chaperone for the type III secretion of Tir in enteropathogenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic></article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>33</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1176</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1189</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10510232</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Katsowich</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Elbaz</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pal</surname>
<given-names>RR</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Host cell attachment elicits posttranscriptional regulation in infecting enteropathogenic bacteria</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>355</volume>(<issue>6326</issue>):<fpage>735</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>739</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aah4886</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28209897</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ye</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yang</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Molecular basis of binding between the global post-transcriptional regulator CsrA and the T3SS chaperone CesT</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1196</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-018-03625-x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29567971</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bibova</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Skopova</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Masin</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>The RNA chaperone Hfq is required for virulence of <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella pertussis</italic></article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>81</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>4081</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4090</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.00345-13</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23980112</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Inatsuka</surname>
<given-names>CS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Xu</surname>
<given-names>Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Vujkovic-Cvijin</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Pertactin is required for Bordetella species to resist neutrophil-mediated clearance</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>78</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>2901</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2909</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.00188-10</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20421378</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bolger</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lohse</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Usadel</surname>
<given-names>B.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Trimmomatic: a flexible trimmer for Illumina sequence data</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>2114</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2120</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btu170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24695404</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Patro</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Duggal</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Love</surname>
<given-names>MI</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Salmon provides fast and bias-aware quantification of transcript expression</article-title>. <source>Nat Methods</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>417</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>419</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.4197</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28263959</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Risso</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ngai</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Speed</surname>
<given-names>TP</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Normalization of RNA-Seq data using factor analysis of control genes or samples</article-title>. <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>896</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>902</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt.2931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25150836</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Love</surname>
<given-names>MI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Huber</surname>
<given-names>W</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Anders</surname>
<given-names>S.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Moderated estimation of fold change and dispersion for RNA-Seq data with DESeq2</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>550</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13059-014-0550-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25516281</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Perez-Riverol</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Csordas</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bai</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>The PRIDE database and related tools and resources in 2019: improving support for quantification data</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>D1</issue>):<fpage>D442</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>D450</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gky1106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30395289</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hoffman</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title><italic toggle="yes">Bordetella pertussis</italic> can be motile and express flagellum-like structures</article-title>. <source>mBio</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>3</issue>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hiramatsu</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nishida</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Nugraha</surname>
<given-names>DK</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Interference of flagellar rotation up-regulates the expression of small RNA contributing to <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella pertussis</italic> infection</article-title>. <source>Sci Adv</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>8</volume>(<issue>51</issue>):<fpage>eade8971</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciadv.ade8971</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36542710</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bart</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Complete genome sequences of <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella pertussis</italic> isolates B1917 and B1920, representing two predominant global lineages</article-title>. <source>Genome Announc</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>2(6)</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jumper</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Jumper</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Evans</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Highly accurate protein structure prediction with AlphaFold</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>596</volume>(<issue>7873</issue>):<fpage>583</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>589</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-021-03819-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34265844</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Evans</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group> Protein complex prediction with AlphaFold-Multimer. bioRxiv, 2021: p. 2021.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Akerley</surname>
<given-names>BJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Monack</surname>
<given-names>DM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Falkow</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>The bvgAS locus negatively controls motility and synthesis of flagella in <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella bronchiseptica</italic></article-title>. <source>J Bacteriol</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>174</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>980</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>990</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/jb.174.3.980-990.1992</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1370665</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Nicholson</surname>
<given-names>TL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Conover</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Deora</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Transcriptome profiling reveals stage-specific production and requirement of flagella during biofilm development in <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella bronchiseptica</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>7</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>e49166</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0049166</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23152870</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cornelis</surname>
<given-names>GR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Van Gijsegem</surname>
<given-names>F.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Assembly and function of type III secretory systems</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Microbiol</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>54</volume>:<fpage>735</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>774</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.micro.54.1.735</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11018143</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gestal</surname>
<given-names>MC</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Enhancement of immune response against <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella</italic> spp. by disrupting immunomodulation</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>20261</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-56652-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31889098</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Guttenplan</surname>
<given-names>SB</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kearns</surname>
<given-names>DB.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Regulation of flagellar motility during biofilm formation</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol Rev</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>37</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>849</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>871</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1574-6976.12018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23480406</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>O'Toole</surname>
<given-names>GA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kolter</surname>
<given-names>R.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Flagellar and twitching motility are necessary for Pseudomonas aeruginosa biofilm development</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>. <year>1998</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>295</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>304</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.1998.01062.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9791175</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Watnick</surname>
<given-names>PI</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lauriano</surname>
<given-names>CM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Klose</surname>
<given-names>KE</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>The absence of a flagellum leads to altered colony morphology, biofilm development and virulence in <italic toggle="yes">Vibrio cholerae</italic> O139</article-title>. <source>Mol Microbiol</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>223</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>235</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2958.2001.02195.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11136445</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Reuter</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mallett</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Pearson</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>Biofilm formation by <italic toggle="yes">Campylobacter jejuni</italic> is increased under aerobic conditions</article-title>. <source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>76</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>2122</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2128</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.01878-09</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20139307</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jerse</surname>
<given-names>AE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yu</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tall</surname>
<given-names>BD</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>A genetic locus of enteropathogenic <italic toggle="yes">Escherichia coli</italic> necessary for the production of attaching and effacing lesions on tissue culture cells</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>1990</year>;<volume>87</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<fpage>7839</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7843</lpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.87.20.7839</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2172966</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>de Gouw</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<article-title>The vaccine potential of <italic toggle="yes">Bordetella pertussis</italic> biofilm-derived membrane proteins</article-title>. <source>Emerg Microbes Infect</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>3</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>e58</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
