<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Public Health</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Public Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2296-2565</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38125848</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC10732580</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2023.1271177</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Public Health</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Dichotomous outcomes vs. survival regression models for identification of predictors of mortality among patients with severe acute respiratory illness during COVID-19 pandemics</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Tasca</surname><given-names>Karen Ingrid</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/92525/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/formal-analysis/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/project-administration/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/validation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>Camila Gon&#x000e7;alves</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/visualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Grotto</surname><given-names>Rejane Maria Tommasini</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1954413/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/validation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>de Moraes</surname><given-names>Leonardo Nazario</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/validation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Assato</surname><given-names>Patr&#x000ed;cia Akemi</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/198564/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/validation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fortaleza</surname><given-names>Carlos Magno Castelo Branco</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1611874/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/data-curation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/formal-analysis/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/methodology/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/validation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Infectious Diseases, Botucatu Medical School (FMB), S&#x000e3;o Paulo State University (Unesp), Botucatu</institution>, <addr-line>S&#x000e3;o Paulo</addr-line>, <country>Brazil</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Department of Biotechnology and Bioprocess, School of Agriculture (FCA), S&#x000e3;o Paulo State University (Unesp), Botucatu</institution>, <addr-line>S&#x000e3;o Paulo</addr-line>, <country>Brazil</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>Clinical Hospital of Botucatu Medical School (HCFMB)</institution>, <addr-line>Botucatu</addr-line>, <country>Brazil</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Gerald Stanley Zavorsky, University of California, Davis, United States</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Igor Tona Peres, Pontifical Catholic University of Rio de Janeiro, Brazil; Vasco Ricoca Peixoto, New University of Lisbon, Portugal</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Karen Ingrid Tasca <email>karen.i.tasca@unesp.br</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>1271177</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>01</day><month>8</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2023 Tasca, Alves, Grotto, de Moraes, Assato and Fortaleza.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Tasca, Alves, Grotto, de Moraes, Assato and Fortaleza</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>As the studies predicting mortality in severe acute respiratory illness (SARI) have inferred associations either from dichotomous outcomes or from time-event models, we identified some clinical-epidemiological characteristics and predictors of mortality by comparing and discussing two multivariate models.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>To identify factors associated with death among all SARI hospitalizations occurred in Botucatu (Brazil)/regardless of the infectious agent, and among the COVID-19 subgroup, from March 2020 to 2022, we used a multivariate Poisson regression model with binomial outcomes and Cox proportional hazards (time-event). The performance metrics of both models were also analyzed.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>A total of 3,995 hospitalized subjects were included, of whom 1338 (33%) tested positive for SARS-CoV-2. We identified 866 deaths, of which 371 (43%) were due to the COVID-19. In the total number of SARI cases, using both Poisson and Cox models, the predictors of mortality were the presence of neurological diseases, immunosuppression, obesity, older age, and need for invasive ventilation support. However, the Poisson test also revealed that admission to an intensive care unit and the COVID-19 diagnosis were predictors of mortality, with the female gender having a protective effect against death. Likewise, Poisson proved to be more sensitive and specific, and indeed the most suitable model for analyzing risk factors for death in patients with SARI/COVID-19.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Given these results and the acute course of SARI and COVID-19, to compare the associations and their different meanings is essential and, therefore, models with dichotomous outcomes are more appropriate than time-to-event/survival approaches.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>SARI</kwd><kwd>COVID-19</kwd><kwd>multivariable models</kwd><kwd>Poisson regression</kwd><kwd>Cox regression</kwd><kwd>clinical predictors</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn001"><institution-wrap><institution>Funda&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de Amparo &#x000e0; Pesquisa do Estado de S&#x000e3;o Paulo</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100001807</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn002"><institution-wrap><institution>Coordena&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de Aperfei&#x000e7;oamento de Pessoal de N&#x000ed;vel Superior</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100002322</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn003"><institution-wrap><institution>Conselho Nacional de Desenvolvimento Cient&#x000ed;fico e Tecnol&#x000f3;gico</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100003593</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><award-group><funding-source id="cn004"><institution-wrap><institution>Universidade Estadual Paulista</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100009568</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>The author(s) declare financial support was received for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. This research has been partly funded by Pr&#x000f3;-Reitoria de Pesquisa (PROPe-Unesp) Edital PROPe 13/2022, Coordena&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o de Aperfei&#x000e7;oamento de Pessoal de N&#x000ed;vel Superior &#x02013; Brasil (CAPES) &#x02013; Finance Code 001, The Brazilian Council for Scientific and Technological Development (CNPq) #401575/2021-7 and by S&#x000e3;o Paulo Research Foundation (FAPESP) #20/12165-8 and #22/02261-5.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="1"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="32"/><page-count count="9"/><word-count count="6455"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Infectious Diseases: Epidemiology and Prevention</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>SARS-CoV-2 was the most common&#x02013;but not the only-agent of Severe Acute Respiratory Illness (SARI) during the COVID-19 pandemic, and this syndrome is responsible for a significant number of hospital admissions and is the major cause of death and morbidity in low- and middle-income countries. Before COVID-19, etiologic agents were often undetermined due to the lack of molecular diagnostics in hospitals and clinics. Studies have focused on the impact of SARS-CoV-2 and other co-circulating viruses on the mortality of patients admitted for SARI, as well as in other predictors of unfavorable outcomes (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). This studies have emerged at a frantic pace resulting from the urgency of responses regarding disease treatment and prevention, making it difficult to interpret this abundance of results, mainly because there is a diversity of statistical methods applied for the same purpose, given this particular disease and its outcome.</p><p>Despite vaccination, COVID-19 is still killing many people worldwide. Thus, establishing mortality predictors is the key to taking steps to slow down this scenario. For this, the behavior of different variables correlated with the COVID-19 prediction as sex, age, ethnicity and socio-economic backgrounds must be considered facts that require improved mortality models (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). To use prediction models within clinical practice guidelines to make decisions is still necessary for patient care (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Considering that estimates of probabilities are rarely based on a single predictor, it is inherently multivariable. Therefore, prediction models are tools that combine multiple predictors by assigning relative weights to each predictor to obtain a risk or probability (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>).</p><p>Studies predicting mortality in SARI and/or COVID-19 have inferred associations either from dichotomous outcomes or time-event models. Although these associations seem similar, they have different meanings. For example, given that cumulative outcome at a particular point of time is simpler and can be analyzed with logistic regression, a type of multivariable analysis that is relatively easier to conduct and interpret than proportional hazards analysis, there are so many published papers using time to outcome. It is probably because clinical medicine consists more of treatment than cure or because the Cox model allows the incorporation of subjects with differing lengths of follow-up in its analysis, a common choice in longitudinal studies (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). However, probabilistic mortality models usually assume that deaths are independent, identically distributed Yes/No events. In this case, it was estimated by fitting Poisson distributions to mortality counts with known exposures, using a log link function, an improvement to standard continuous mortality models (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>).</p><p>Here we proposed to verify clinical-epidemiological characteristics and to identify mortality predictors in SARI inpatients, applying multivariate models of dichotomous (Poisson) and time-event (Cox) outcomes in a city that promoted a mass vaccination campaign against COVID-19 in its population, to compare if factor associated with death and respective risk measurements remained similar using different multivariable analysis methods.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Data source</title><p>The case definition for SARI according to Brazilian surveillance is: an individual with <sup>*</sup>Syndrome Influenza presenting dyspnea/respiratory distress, or persistent chest pressure, or O2 saturation lower than 95% on room air, or bluish coloration of lips or face. (<sup>*</sup>SG: individual with an acute respiratory condition characterized by at least two of the following signs and symptoms: fever - even if referred -, chills, sore throat, headache, cough, runny nose, smell or taste disturbances). For the purpose of notification in SIVEP-Gripe, hospitalized cases of SARS or deaths from SARS regardless of hospitalization should be considered (<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>).</p><p>Data on SARI hospitalization and death were collected from the Brazilian hospitalization database operated by the Ministry of Health-the Influenza Surveillance System Data Repository (SIVEP-Gripe), which monitors SARI hospitalization cases in Brazil. Thus, the epidemiological surveillance of Botucatu provided us the report of its citizens hospitalized for SARI on 11 April 2022.</p><p>Botucatu is a city in inner S&#x000e3;o Paulo State, with an estimated population of 142,092 (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>). The hospital admissions occurred in private and public hospitals (through the health program within Brazil's socialized Unified Health System&#x02013;SUS), including the Clinical Hospital, a university hospital that provides tertiary care for this city and surrounding municipalities.</p><p>All inpatients were obtained from the SIVEP-Gripe database from the 1st of March 2020 to the 31st of March 2022, including residents of Botucatu. After acquiring the database, the data was treated (excluding people with missing &#x0201c;final evolution/outcome&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;final classification&#x0201d; fields), and the variables were binary transformed. All vaccines were manually added to our database by consulting the State of S&#x000e3;o Paulo's Vaccination Recording System against COVID-19 (VaciVida). Sensitive data were subsequently anonymized to proceed with the statistical analyses.</p></sec><sec><title>Study design, variables, and groups</title><p>We performed a cohort retrospective analytical study with secondary data from SIVEP-Gripe.</p><p>The main outcome consisted of cure/recovery (discharge) and deaths. We considered the following predictors to identify risk factors associated with the occurrence of death: age, sex (male and female), and the presence or absence of pre-existing comorbidities (postpartum or pregnancy, cardiovascular, renal, neurological, hematological, or hepatic comorbidities, diabetes, chronic respiratory disorder, obesity, Down syndrome or immunosuppression). Clinical course was reported in terms of the need (or not) for non-invasive (NIVS) or invasive ventilation support (IVS) and the admission (or not) to an intensive care unit (ICU). For vaccination data, were included the number of doses received (none, one, two, three, or four) at the time of the SIVEP-gripe notification.</p><p>Variables regarding signs and symptoms present on admission (fever, cough, sore throat, shortness of breath, respiratory distress, gastrointestinal symptoms, and oxygen saturation) were included to the descriptive analysis. Besides, comorbidity data were also categorized according to the number of pre-existing conditions (none, one, and &#x02265;two/multimorbidity).</p><p>The first group analyzed was all SARI cases-for all hospitalization notifications contained in SIVEP-gripe that remained after applying the exclusion criteria. Then, a filter was used in the database to analyze only people with a confirmed diagnosis of SARS-CoV-2, here referred as the &#x0201c;COVID-19 subgroup.&#x0201d; It is important to emphasize that all patients were tested for SARS-CoV-2.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>We calculated descriptive statistics for inpatient characteristics. Quantitative variables were expressed as mean &#x000b1; standard deviation (SD) values, and categorical variables were expressed as absolute (<italic>n</italic>) and relative (%) frequencies values. Chi square test was used for testing relationships between categorical variables.</p><p>Poisson regression with binomial outcome estimated the crude and adjusted for the confounders variables in order to obtain relative risks (RR) and 95% confidence intervals (95% CI). The Cox proportional-hazards (time-event) model was used to estimate the death risk by the studied variables, being these associations expressed as hazard ratios (HR) with 95% CI and considering the time from hospital admission to outcome. A single-step model included demographic data, comorbidities, care needs, and vaccines. A two-sided <italic>p</italic>-value &#x02264; 0.05 was considered as statistical significance.</p><p>Besides, considering the predicted values obtained by each models, a receiver operating characteristic curve (ROC) curve was calculated in order to compare the area under the curve (AUC), specificity and sensitivity values (for death outcome).</p><p>Analyses were performed both for all SARI cases and those confirmed for COVID-19 singly, using SAS for Windows (version 9.4) software.</p></sec><sec><title>Ethical issues</title><p>The local Research Ethics Committee of Botucatu Medical School (FMB/Unesp) approved the study (CAAE: 57919122.9.0000.5411) without the need for informed consent.</p><p>Additionally, this study complied with the Resolution 466/2012 and 510/2016 of the Brazilian National Health Council and with the Strengthening the Reporting of Observational Studies in Epidemiology (STROBE) guidelines (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material 1</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><p>Out of the 3,995 hospitalized people included, 1,338 (33%) tested positive for SARS-CoV-2. Among all those hospitalized, 656 (16%) required ICU admission, and 409 (10%) required IVS. These numbers were 300 (22%) and 182 (14%), respectively, for COVID-19 patients. In total, 866 (22%) deaths were identified, 371 (28%) were in the COVID-19 group. Therefore, hospitalization for COVID-19 was more severe than other respiratory viruses (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001), and the in-hospital mortality by COVID-19 was 28%. <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref> shows these results. Therefore, the cumulative COVID-19 mortality rate in Botucatu was 3%.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Intensive care unit (ICU) admissions, invasive ventilation support (IVS) and deaths in patients residing in Botucatu/SP, hospitalized for SARI <bold>(A)</bold> and specifically the COVID-19 subgroup <bold>(B)</bold> during the period from March 2020 to March 2022. The frequencies are shown by different colors - in red: &#x0201c;yes&#x0201d; (which shows the &#x0201c;number of sample&#x0201d; right below the corresponding graph); green: &#x0201c;no.&#x0201d; Chi square test (difference in proportions) showed differences for all variables/outcomes when SARI group was compared to COVID-19 subgroup (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001). ICU comparison (<bold>A</bold> vs. <bold>B</bold>): <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0001; IVS: <italic>p</italic> = 0.0009; Death: <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpubh-11-1271177-g0001" position="float"/></fig><p>The average age of the patients was 52 (&#x000b1;25) years old in the SARI group and 59 (&#x000b1;18) in the COVID-19 subgroup. In general, we observed that almost 50% of all SARI hospitalization (and the same proportion to the COVID-19 subgroup) occurred in older people (aged 60+). For all deaths reported, 46% were older people for SARI and 70% for the COVID-19 subgroup (<xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>All cases of SARI <bold>(A)</bold> and cases of SARI by COVID-19 <bold>(B)</bold> from Botucatu/SP: hospitalizations, intensive care unit (ICU) admissions, and deaths by age groups during 2 years.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpubh-11-1271177-g0002" position="float"/></fig><p>The proportion of male patients ranged from 52% for SARI to 55% for COVID-19 subgroup. The most common clinical manifestations among all hospitalized, present in at least 50% of them, were low oxygen saturation (SpO2 &#x0003c; 95%), dyspnea, coughing, respiratory decompensation, and fever (data not showed).</p><p>Most of the individuals included in the study were unvaccinated against COVID-19; specifically in the COVID-19 subgroup, 68% (<italic>n</italic> = 912) were unvaccinated, and the vaccinated rates considering different doses received were 15% (dose 1), 12% (dose 2), 5% (dose 3) and 0.2% (dose 4). Among those vaccinated with 1 or 2 doses, most had received AstraZeneca (<italic>n</italic> = 192) or Coronavac (<italic>n</italic> = 164) (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplementary material 2</xref>).</p><p>The most common underlying illness are shown in <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>. Although we had information missing for a lot of cases, among 2,904 who had appropriately filled in these fields, 85% (<italic>n</italic> = 2,481) presented at least one comorbidity, and 33% (<italic>n</italic> = 830) were COVID-19 cases, i.e., 62% of the COVID-19 cases presented at least one comorbidity. Among all SARI inpatients, approximately 89% (<italic>n</italic> = 770) of non-survivors had some underlying disease. Multi-morbidities were present in 50% (<italic>n</italic> = 1,238) of SARI group, of which 32% (<italic>n</italic> = 400) were COVID-19 patients.</p><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Underlying diseases present in 2,481 patients hospitalized for SARI <bold>(A)</bold> and for those 800 with COVID-19 diagnosis <bold>(B)</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpubh-11-1271177-g0003" position="float"/></fig><p>Risk factors associated with in-hospital death were evaluated with multivariate Poisson regression and multivariable Cox proportional hazards regression. In the total number of SARI cases, using both Poisson and Cox models, the following were predictors of mortality: older people, presence of neurological diseases, immunosuppression, obesity, and need for IVS. However, the Poisson test also revealed that the ICU admission (RR: 1.62; 1.33&#x02013;1.98) and the COVID-19 diagnosis (RR: 1.24; 1.06&#x02013;1.46) were also indicative factors of an increased risk for mortality, with female gender having a protective effect against death (RR: 0.85; 0.73&#x02013;1.00) (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The use of Poisson distribution in this case (binary data with log link) enable to control the over/underdispersion to avoid the use of negative binomial distribution and robust estimation variance for binary outcome.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Predictors for death and protective factors (both in bold) using both Poisson and Cox Models in SARI and COVID-19 subgroup.</p></caption><table frame="box" rules="all"><thead><tr style="background-color:#919498;color:#ffffff"><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Poisson</bold>
</th><th valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" rowspan="1">
<bold>Cox</bold>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr style="background-color:#919498;color:#ffffff"><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>Predictors</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>RR</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>CI (95%)</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>
<bold>p-</bold>
</italic>
<bold>values</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>HR</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">
<bold>CI (95%)</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>
<bold>p</bold>
</italic>
<bold>-values</bold>
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#dee1e1"><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
<bold>SARI</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Older age</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1.03</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>0.000</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1.03</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>0.000</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neurological diseases</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1.47</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.20</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.79</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>0.000</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1.43</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.76</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>0.001</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Immunossupression</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1.67</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.30</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.15</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>0.000</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1.81</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.33</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>0.000</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Obesity</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1.46</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>0.018</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1.34</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>0.076</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IVS</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2.29</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.83</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>0.000</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1.77</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.40</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.24</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>0.000</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICU admission</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1.62</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.98</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>0.000</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<sup>
<bold>_</bold>
</sup>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<sup>
<bold>_</bold>
</sup>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<sup>
<bold>_</bold>
</sup>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<sup>_</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">COVID-19</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1.24</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.46</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>0.008</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<sup>
<bold>_</bold>
</sup>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<sup>
<bold>_</bold>
</sup>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<sup>
<bold>_</bold>
</sup>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<sup>_</sup>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Female gender</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.85</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>0.044</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<sup>
<bold>_</bold>
</sup>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<sup>
<bold>_</bold>
</sup>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<sup>
<bold>_</bold>
</sup>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<sup>_</sup>
</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#dee1e1"><td valign="top" align="center" colspan="9" rowspan="1">
<bold>COVID-19</bold>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Older age</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1.02</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>0.000</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1.03</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>0.000</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neurological diseases</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1.67</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.38</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>0.004</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1.41</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.98</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.03</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>0.063</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IVS</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1.81</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.44</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>0.000</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1.84</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.34</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.54</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>0.000</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ICU Admission</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>2.35</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.76</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.14</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>0.000</italic>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>1.32</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.80</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>0.074</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vaccination (doses)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<sup>
<bold>_</bold>
</sup>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<sup>
<bold>_</bold>
</sup>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<sup>
<bold>_</bold>
</sup>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<sup>_</sup>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold>0.85</bold>
</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>0.035</italic>
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>RR, relative risks; HR, Hazard ratios; CI, confidence interval; ICU, intensive care unit; IVS, invasive ventilation support. The italic values is given only to differentiate the p-value from the other values.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>In a sub-analysis for COVID-19, the predictors of mortality using both models were the following: older age, presence of neurological diseases, need for ICU and invasive ventilatory support. However, only the Cox model demonstrated that the higher number of vaccine doses was a protective factor for mortality (HR: 0.85; 0.74&#x02013;0.99) (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p><p>Additionally, considering the predicted values by each model and the calculation of a ROC curve, we showed that Poisson is the most suitable model for analyzing risk factors for death in patients with SARI/COVID-19 (<xref rid="F4" ref-type="fig">Figure 4</xref>), due to its greater AUC when compared with Cox model (0.789 vs. 0.663, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0001), and its greater specificity (0.700 vs. 0.625) and sensitivity (0.750 vs. 0.625).</p><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Two receiver operating characteristic curves (ROC) showed to compare the area under the curve (AUC), specificity and sensitivity values between Poisson and Cox models, for death outcome from predicted values obtained by each models. The comparison was made for SARI <bold>(A)</bold> and for COVID-19 <bold>(B)</bold> group. <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0001 for both.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpubh-11-1271177-g0004" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Historically, Brazil has had high adherence to previous vaccination campaigns. The mass vaccination campaign conducted in Botucatu City (on May 16 and Aug 08, 2021) was a success, allowing the immunization of 77,683 and 60,333 inhabitants (first and second dose, respectively) from a total of 92,394 adults (i.e., coverage 84 and 80%), in a record period. This resulted in a drastically reduced number of deaths especially in the pre-omicron period (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>).</p><p>Here we showed 1,338 (33%) hospital admissions for SARS-CoV-2 and 371 related deaths in Botucatu. This mortality rate of ~27% was similar to that found in other Brazilian studies (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). However, these data represent people of all ages, different variants distributed along the time, and a longer observation period (24 months) that included the months before the vaccines were made available, what is reinforced by the high frequency (69%) of unvaccinated people included here. It is well known that the benefits of vaccination are undeniable in protecting against severe COVID-19 (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>), and its effects are even more protective according to the higher number of doses received and the younger age (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>), especially due to factors related to immunosenescence (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>) reflecting in a lower vaccine response.</p><p>Regarding age, it is worth noting that about half of all hospitalizations for SARI and COVID-19 occurred in people older than 60 years in our study, which is consistent with the literature (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>) and here, the mortality rate in this older adult population specifically by COVID-19 was 40%, higher than the rate found in younger people (16%). It shows us that COVID-19 was more aggressive than any other respiratory viruses in causing hospitalization, mainly in the older adult. Other studies have found higher mortality rate in those hospitalized for SARI due to COVID-19 than non-COVID-19 cases (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Among hospitalized inpatients from our study, 2,657 (66%) admissions and 495 (19%) deaths were non-COVID-19 related. The mortality rate in the older adult and younger overall (SARI) was ~- 20 and 22%, respectively. Independently of this, other respiratory viruses also have a high impact on public health (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>), especially in the older population (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>) and policies to promote the prevention of SARI cases are, and certainly will continue to be necessary to entire population.</p><p>Several works reported a higher risk of a poor prognosis/death not only in older adult individuals, but also in those with comorbidities (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>), not differing from the findings of the current study. At least one comorbidity was present in 85% (SARI group) and 62% (COVID-19 subgroup) of inpatients, and this last rate was similar to that found by Castro et al. (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). We observed the most common underlying illnesses were cardiovascular diseases and diabetes, followed by neurological disturbs, findings shared by Santos et al. (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>) and Sousa et al. (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Multi-morbidities were present in half cases of the SARI group and COVID-19 subgroup, and it is also a factor proven to be related to a higher risk/chance of death (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>).</p><p>The clinical manifestation of COVID-19, as well as some other viral conditions, is also highly heterogeneous and depends on the characteristics of the agent (variants) (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>) and of the host. Among all hospitalized, low oxygen saturation (SpO2 &#x0003c; 95%), dyspnea, coughing, respiratory discomfort, and fever were the most expressive complaints, which converges with the literature (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). Since most of the hospitalized people in our study were from the first year of the pandemic, the most common symptoms found here, a combination of sore throat and head, were similar to those found by Prado et al. (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) in the same period. However, as the pandemic persisted and omicron became more prevalent lately, Sobral et al. (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) found respiratory discomfort and abdominal pain to be the most frequent manifestations.</p><p>As mentioned before, obtaining accurate estimates of the risk of COVID-19-related death in the population is challenging in the context of changing levels of circulating infection (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>), types of circulating variants, the population heterogeneity, and regional and social factors (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). Besides, many studies which reported potential predictors of mortality in patients with COVID-19 with different methodological analyses were found in the literature. For this reason, we proposed a comparison between two statistical analyses to verify these predictors in all SARI inpatients.</p><p>Clinical prediction for mortality in patients with COVID-19 could help to identify those patients who require the most urgent help and make numerous medical decisions based on the risk of developing a particular outcome or state of health within a specific period. This also supports the efficient use of limited medical resources, reducing the impact on the healthcare system (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). The main prediction outcomes used in the studies are death, development of severe/critical state, ICU admission/mechanical ventilation/death, survival time, and length-of-hospital stay (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Only the mortality outcome was investigated for its possible predictors in this study.</p><p>Our study showed three variables as predictors of mortality in both the SARI group and the COVID-19 subgroup, using Poisson and Cox: advanced age, SVI, and the presence of neurological disease. As mentioned above and according to the literature, the age is an important risk factor for a poor prognosis, not only for COVID-19, but also for any SARI case. These findings were from Brazilian studies using the Poisson (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>, <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>) and Cox models (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). However, Sousa et al. (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>) also considered both Poisson and Cox models, sharing very similar results-the older adult and people with comorbidities (CVD, neurological disease, lung disease) had a higher risk of dying from COVID-19. Furthermore, others (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>, <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>) performed multivariate logistic regression for their analysis, and some results were similar. Although many studies use this last methodology, we decided not to consider it because when the event is not rare, the odds ratio (OR) can be overestimated (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>).</p><p>The need for the use of IVS contributed to an increase in the probability of death, in this and in other studies, using Poisson (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>), Cox (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>) or logistic regression (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). As neurological diseases indicated high mortality, our study corroborates with several others, also using these statistical methodologies (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). In addition to these Brazilian studies, the findings of the present study are supported by the systematic review and meta-analysis conducted by Shi et al. (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>), in which the advanced age, male sex, preexisting comorbidities and complications during hospitalization are predictors of COVID-19 mortality.</p><p>Moreover, only in our SARI group other two preexisting medical conditions have predicted mortality: the presence of immunosuppression and obesity (by Poisson and Cox). Such underlying diseases have also been associated with a higher risk of death, especially in those COVID-19 cases, as reported in other studies assigning different analyses (Poisson, Cox and logistic regression) (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>). Although we did not check whether multimorbidity would be a predictor of mortality, half of our inpatients had multimorbidities and in this way, Colnago et al. (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>) by logistic regression, Mascarello et al. (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>) by Poisson, Prado et al. (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) and Oliveira Lima et al. (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>) by Cox previously demonstrated that fatality was higher among this population.</p><p>High fatality rates were observed among COVID patients admitted to the ICU admission using both Cox and Poisson. However, for SARI this predictor only appeared when using the Poisson model. Another variable that only appeared using Poisson, specifically for the SARI group, was COVID-19 infection as a mortality prediction and female gender as a protection factor. The literature (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>) showed that ICU admission could be a predictor of mortality in people with respiratory infections, especially those positive for SARS-CoV-2. Regarding gender and disease progression, similarly to our results, Bermudi et al. (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>) found that being male could be a predictor for death in these patients also using Poisson, and Colnago et al. (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>), Castro et al. (<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>), Prado et al. (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>) and Sobral et al. (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>) pointed the same using other multivariate analyses.</p><p>We noted another difference using the two proposed models: only using Cox, the presence of anti-COVID-19 booster vaccine doses appeared as a protective factor against death. This data is aligned with that reported by Colnago et al. (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>) during the Omicron wave in Brazil but using logistic regression. Jesus et al. (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>) observed greater vulnerability, especially in the older adult who have received the inactivated virus vaccine suggesting the importance of giving the additional doses to this population as a priority.</p><p>However, it is worth remembering that this vaccine platform was applied to most of the older adult population in Brazil because it was the first vaccine to be approved by the local regulatory agency, so the age factor may also influence the lower protection conferred by it.</p><p>This discussion was based on Brazilian studies on predictors of mortality in cases of SARI, and it was noticeable that even having the same purpose, the studies use different types of multivariate analysis. We focused on showing mainly those works that used Poisson and Cox models here. Thus, the remaining question is: which analysis would be the most reliable, considering that the findings may be slightly different according to the model chosen? It is necessary a reflexive thought to answer this question.</p><p>The Poisson regression model is generally used in epidemiology to analyze longitudinal studies where the response is the number of episodes of an event occurring in a given time. The Cox regression model, in turn, is generally used to analyze the time to an event. Using both robust methods for variance estimation corrects the variance overestimation and produces adequate confidence intervals. The Cox and Poisson models also behaved well with the presence of continuous covariates (<xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). It is recognized that the time to outcome has two major advantages over cumulative outcome at a particular time: it is a more sensitive measure of efficacy and it also allows inclusion of individuals with unequal lengths of follow-up (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>).</p><p>However, when we obtain relatively few results, the duration of follow-up is relatively short. Thus, fewer subjects are lost to follow-up using cumulative outcomes, and logistic regression will give similar results to using time-to-outcome and proportional hazards analysis. With Poisson regression, the outcome will be estimated to be zero or higher. In contrast to multiple linear regression the outcome can be estimated with negative values for certain subgroups of subjects-defined by independent variables&#x02013;and it is clear that clinical events cannot have negative values (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). However, assuming that we are discussing respiratory infections with the rapid outcome, how important is it to slow down the progression of a disease? From our point of view, time is not a determining factor capable of changing the outcome; therefore, the outcome analyses can be carried out in a binary manner.</p><p>Although the notification of COVID-19 hospital admissions is compulsory in Brazil and the System used for the inclusion of participants in this study (SIVEP-gripe) provides the most representative account of SARI hospitalized patients in the entire city, whose data contained are more reliable than other COVID-19 surveillance systems (e.g., E-sus notifica), it must be considered that the use of the secondary database will always run into possible study biases. First, there may be a limitation in the predictors of the existing data with an impaired patient monitoring. Second, this dataset has a restricted number of variables (comorbidities, symptoms, medical procedures) with a lack of laboratory data, including for example, confirmatory tests for underlying diseases-that are only notified according to the patient's report or perception of the medical staff at the time of admission. Additionally, data entry with free-text fields causes an understandable discrepancy in the use of medical terms and descriptions, which leads to a lack of standardization in the completion of these data by health professionals. Other limitations include the lack of an adjustment for some subjects, clinical or regional characteristics (i.e., malnutrition, unhealthy health habits, treatments applied in the hospital or those chronically used by individuals, inequities and economic development to which the individual belongs, etc.).</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s5"><title>Conclusion</title><p>The findings of dichotomous and time-event predictor models may differ, and their significance depends on the epidemiological assumptions and on the research question. Considering the short time-course of SARI-COVID, the Poisson adjustment was more appropriate, since the occurrence or not of a certain outcome (death) in this case, is more crucial than considering when it occurred (early or late, and considering the proportional risks). In other words, choosing Poisson would simplify the model and provide precise results. Besides, in addition to identifying more associations using the Poisson model than Cox model, we demonstrated that Poisson was more sensitive and specific in the metric performance analysis comparing the both models.</p><p>In this manner, older age, neurological diseases, IVS and ICU admission were the four predictors of mortality to hospitalized COVID-19 patients, using Poisson regression. To the SARI group, in addition to the above predictors, others appeared in the Poisson model, such as obesity, immunosuppression and SARS-CoV-2 infection itself.</p><p>Lastly, the present study provides additional support for using other more suitable models as alternatives to logistic regression, available in most statistical design used for epidemiological studies analyses.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s6"><title>Data availability statement</title><p>The raw data supporting the conclusions of this article will be made available by the authors, without undue reservation.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ethics-statement" id="s7"><title>Ethics statement</title><p>Research Ethics Committee of Botucatu Medical School (FMB/Unesp) approved the study (CAAE: 57919122.9.0000.5411). The studies were conducted in accordance with the local legislation and institutional requirements. The Ethics Committee/institutional review board waived the requirement of written informed consent for participation from the participants or the participants' legal guardians/next of kin because epidemiological study - secondary data.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s8"><title>Author contributions</title><p>KT: Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Project administration, Validation, Writing&#x02014;original draft. CA: Investigation, Visualization, Writing&#x02014;review &#x00026; editing. RG: Investigation, Validation, Writing&#x02014;review &#x00026; editing. LdM: Investigation, Validation, Writing&#x02014;review &#x00026; editing. PA: Investigation, Validation, Writing&#x02014;review &#x00026; editing. CF: Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Supervision, Validation, Writing&#x02014;review &#x00026; editing, Writing&#x02014;original draft.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors wish to acknowledge Prof. Dr. Jos&#x000e9; Eduardo Corrente, from Research Support Office (EAP/FMB-Unesp), who developed the statistics analysis and played an important role in our study. We are also grateful for the support provided by the staff of the EAP/FMB, Clinical Hospital (HCFMB), Public Health Research Unit (UPeSC/FMB) and Foundation for Hospital Medical Development (FAMESP) for helping to conduct this study in its several stages, and to the Botucatu Health Department for providing the database.</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s10"><title>Publisher's note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s11"><title>Supplementary material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpubh.2023.1271177/full#supplementary-material" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpubh.2023.1271177/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material id="SM1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><media xlink:href="Data_Sheet_1.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM2" position="float" content-type="local-data"><media xlink:href="Table_1.DOCX"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kothari</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Goel</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Narayanan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Goyal</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhatia</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical features and mortality in COVID-19 SARI versus non COVID-19 SARI cases from Western Rajasthan, India</article-title>. <source>J Family Med Prim Care.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>3240</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/jfmpc.jfmpc_14_21</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34760737</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Predictors of mortality in patients with coronavirus disease 2019: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>BMC Infect Dis.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>663</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12879-021-06369-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34238232</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colnago</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Benvenuto</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Casaca</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Negri</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuminato</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Risk factors associated with mortality in hospitalized patients with COVID-19 during the omicron wave in Brazil</article-title>. <source>Bioengineering</source>. (<year>2022</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>584</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/bioengineering9100584</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36290552</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prado</surname><given-names>PRD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gimenes</surname><given-names>FRE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>MVM</given-names></name><name><surname>Prado</surname><given-names>VBD</given-names></name><name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Amaral</surname><given-names>TLM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Risk factors for death due to COVID-19, in the state of Acre, Brazil, 2020: a retrospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>Epidemiol Serv Saude</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>e2020676</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/s1679-49742021000300018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34287555</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Venter</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>A Mortality Model for Pandemics Other Contagion Events (Chapter 5). From Boado-Penas MC Sahin JES, Pandemics: Insurance Social Protection</source>. <publisher-loc>Springer</publisher-loc> (ebook) (<year>2022</year>). Available online at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://library.oapen.org/bitstream/handle/20.500.12657/51459/9783030783341.pdf?sequence=1#page=93" ext-link-type="uri">https://library.oapen.org/bitstream/handle/20.500.12657/51459/9783030783341.pdf?sequence=1#page=93</ext-link> (accessed November 15, 2022).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Reitsma</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Moons</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Transparent reporting of a multivariable prediction model for individual prognosis or diagnosis (TRIPOD): the TRIPOD statement</article-title>. <source>BMJ.</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>350</volume>:<fpage>g7594</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.g7594</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25569120</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Reporting of coronavirus disease 2019 prognostic models: the transparent reporting of a multivariable prediction model for individual prognosis or diagnosis statement</article-title>. <source>Ann Transl Med.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>421</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.21037/atm-20-6933</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33842642</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katz</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Multivariale Analysis &#x02013; A Practical Guide for Clinicians, 2nd Edn</source>. <publisher-name>Cambridge Univ Press</publisher-name> (<year>2007</year>). <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1541-0420.2007.00743_8.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brasil</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Ficha de Notifica&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o SIVEP-GRIPE 2022. SIVEP-GRIPE</source>. Available online at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://prefeitura.pbh.gov.br/sites/default/files/estrutura-de-governo/saude/2022/ficha_srag_hospitalizado_19.09.2022.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">https://prefeitura.pbh.gov.br/sites/default/files/estrutura-de-governo/saude/2022/ficha_srag_hospitalizado_19.09.2022.pdf</ext-link> (accessed October 13, 2023).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seade</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <source>Popula&#x000e7;&#x000e3;o projetada</source>. (<year>2022</year>). Available online at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.seade.gov.br/" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.seade.gov.br/</ext-link> (accessed November 02, 2022).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clemens</surname><given-names>SAC</given-names></name><name><surname>Fortaleza</surname><given-names>CMCB</given-names></name><name><surname>Crowe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tasca</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name><name><surname>Grotto</surname><given-names>RMT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Safety of the fiocruz ChAdOx COVID-19 vaccine used in a mass vaccination campaign in botucatu, Brazil</article-title>. <source>Vaccine.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>6722</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2022.08.026</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36055876</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clemens</surname><given-names>SAC</given-names></name><name><surname>Fortaleza</surname><given-names>CMCB</given-names></name><name><surname>Crowe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tasca</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name><name><surname>Spadaro</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Souza-Neto</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Effectiveness of the fiocruz recombinant ChadOx1-nCoV19 against variants of SARS-CoV-2 in the municipality of botucatu-SP</article-title>. <source>Front Public Health.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>1016402</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2022.1016402</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36311567</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gurzenda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mac&#x000e1;rio</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fran&#x000e7;a</surname><given-names>GVA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Characteristics, outcomes and risk factors for mortality of 522 167 patients hospitalised with COVID-19 in Brazil: a retrospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>BMJ Open.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>e049089</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjopen-2021-049089</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33947740</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marcolino</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziegelmann</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Souza-Silva</surname><given-names>MVR</given-names></name><name><surname>Nascimento</surname><given-names>IJB</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical characteristics and outcomes of patients hospitalized with COVID-19 in Brazil: results from the Brazilian COVID-19 registry</article-title>. <source>Int J Infect Dis.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>107</volume>:<fpage>300</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2021.01.019</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33444752</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perazzo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ribeiro</surname><given-names>MPD</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreira</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Coelho</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Jalil</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>In-hospital mortality and severe outcomes after hospital discharge due to COVID-19: a prospective multicenter study from Brazil</article-title>. <source>Lancet Reg Health Am.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<fpage>100244</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.lana.2022.100300</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35434696</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Regional heterogeneity of in-hospital mortality of COVID-19 in Brazil</article-title>. <source>Infect Dis Model.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>7</volume>:<fpage>364</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.idm.2022.06.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35815243</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilkinson</surname><given-names>TMA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Respiratory viral infections in the elderly</article-title>. <source>Ther Adv Respir Dis.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>1753466621995050</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1753466621995050</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33749408</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sobral</surname><given-names>MFF</given-names></name><name><surname>Roazzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>da Penha Sobral</surname><given-names>AIG</given-names></name><name><surname>de Oliveira</surname><given-names>BRB</given-names></name><name><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>da Silva</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Retrospective cohort study of 238,000 COVID-19 hospitalizations and deaths in Brazil</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>3629</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-07538-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35256660</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sousa</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Garces</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Cestari</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Flor&#x000ea;ncio</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreira</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Mortality and survival of COVID-19</article-title>. <source>Epidemiol Infect.</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>148</volume>:<fpage>E123</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0950268820001405</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32580809</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jesus</surname><given-names>MAS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hojo-Souza</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>de Moraes</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Guidoni</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>de Souza</surname><given-names>FSH</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Profile of Brazilian inpatients with COVID-19 vaccine breakthrough infection and risk factors for unfavorable outcome</article-title>. <source>Rev Panam Salud Publica.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>46</volume>:<fpage>e106</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2022.04.12.22273589</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36016834</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Short term outcome and risk factors for mortality in adults with critical severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS)</article-title>. <source>J Huazhong Univ Sci Technolog Med Sci.</source> (<year>2004</year>) <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>514</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02831124</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15641708</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wunderink</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>MERS, SARS and other coronaviruses as causes of pneumonia</article-title>. <source>Respirology.</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>130</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/resp.13196</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29052924</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mascarello</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>ACBC</given-names></name><name><surname>Souza</surname><given-names>ASS</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcarini</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Barauna</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name><name><surname>Maciel</surname><given-names>ELN</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>COVID-19 hospitalization and death and relationship with social determinants of health and morbidities in Esp&#x000ed;rito Santo State, Brazil: a cross-sectional study</article-title>. <source>Epidemiol Serv Saude.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>30</volume>:<fpage>e2020919</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/s1679-49742021000300004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34287551</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oliveira Lima</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Campos Vieira Abib</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tavares</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>DWCL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ara&#x000fa;jo</surname><given-names>ACLF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Coronavirus disease-related in-hospital mortality: a cohort study in a private healthcare network in Brazil</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>6371</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-10343-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35430625</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucena</surname><given-names>EES</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonfada</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Vechi</surname><given-names>HT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Brazilian Older people hospitalized by COVID-19: characteristics and prognostic factors in a retrospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>J Appl Gerontol.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>40</volume>:<fpage>571</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>81</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0733464820983976</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33406963</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carabelli</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Peacock</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Thorne</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name><name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>WT</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><collab>COVID-19 Genomics UK Consortium</collab><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>SARS-CoV-2 variant biology: immune escape, transmission and fitness</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Microbiol.</source> (<year>2023</year>) <volume>21</volume>:<fpage>162</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>77</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41579-022-00841-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36653446</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>OpenSAFELY</surname><given-names>Collaborative</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tazare</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhaskaran</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Comparison of methods for predicting COVID-19-related death in the general population using the OpenSAFELY platform</article-title>. <source>Diagn Progn Res.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>6</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s41512-022-00120-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35197114</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bermudi</surname><given-names>PMM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorenz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguiar</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Failla</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrozo</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiaravalloti-Neto</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Spatiotemporal ecological study of COVID-19 mortality in the city of S&#x000e3;o Paulo, Brazil: shifting of the high mortality risk from areas with the best to those with the worst socio-economic conditions</article-title>. <source>Travel Med Infect Dis.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>39</volume>:<fpage>101945</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tmaid.2020.101945</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33278610</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jong</surname><given-names>VMT</given-names></name><name><surname>Rousset</surname><given-names>RZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Antonio-Villa</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name><surname>Buenen</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Calster</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bello-Chavolla</surname><given-names>OY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Clinical prediction models for mortality in patients with COVID-19: external validation and individual participant data meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>BMJ.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>378</volume>:<fpage>e069881</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj-2021-069881</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35820692</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sansone</surname><given-names>NMS</given-names></name><name><surname>Boschiero</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Marson</surname><given-names>FAL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Epidemiologic profile of severe acute respiratory infection in Brazil during the COVID-19 pandemic: an epidemiological study</article-title>. <source>Front Microbiol.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>13</volume>:<fpage>911036</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2022.911036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35854935</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paravidino</surname><given-names>VB</given-names></name><name><surname>Leite</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mediano</surname><given-names>MFF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sichieri</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Azevedo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Association between obesity and COVID-19 mortality and length of stay in intensive care unit patients in Brazil: a retrospective cohort study</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>12</volume>:<fpage>13737</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-022-17197-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35962010</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coutinho</surname><given-names>LMS</given-names></name><name><surname>Scazufca</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Menezes</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>M&#x000e9;todos para estimar raz&#x000e3;o de preval&#x000ea;ncia em estudos de corte transversal</article-title>. <source>Rev Sa&#x000fa;de P&#x000fa;blica.</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>42</volume>:<fpage>992</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0034-89102008000600003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19009156</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
