<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="EN" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">ACS Sustain Chem Eng</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">ACS Sustain Chem Eng</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">sc</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="coden">ascecg</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>ACS Sustainable Chemistry &#x00026; Engineering</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2168-0485</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Chemical Society</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC10732281</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acssuschemeng.3c07024</article-id><article-categories><subj-group><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Upcycling
of Poly(lactic acid) Waste: A Valuable Strategy
to Obtain Ionic Liquids</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath1"><name><surname>Raia</surname><given-names>Giovanna</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath2"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9932-9823</contrib-id><name><surname>Marullo</surname><given-names>Salvatore</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath3"><name><surname>Lazzara</surname><given-names>Giuseppe</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath4"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2145-0161</contrib-id><name><surname>Cavallaro</surname><given-names>Giuseppe</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">&#x02021;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath5"><name><surname>Marino</surname><given-names>Sefora</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">&#x000a7;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="ath6"><name><surname>Cancemi</surname><given-names>Patrizia</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">&#x000a7;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="ath7"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6171-8620</contrib-id><name><surname>D&#x02019;Anna</surname><given-names>Francesca</given-names></name><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="other">*</xref><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>&#x02020;</label>Dipartimento
STEBICEF, Sezione di Chimica, <institution>Universit&#x000e0;
degli Studi di Palermo</institution>, Viale delle Scienze Ed. 17 &#x0201c;S. Cannizzaro&#x0201d;, Palermo 90128, <country>Italy</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>&#x02021;</label>Dipartimento
di Fisica e Chimica, <institution>Universit&#x000e0; degli
Studi di Palermo</institution>, Viale delle Scienze Ed. 17 &#x0201c;S. Cannizzaro&#x0201d;, Palermo 90128, <country>Italy</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>&#x000a7;</label>Dipartimento
STEBICEF, Sezione di Biologia Cellulare, <institution>Universit&#x000e0; degli Studi di Palermo</institution>, Viale delle Scienze Ed. 16, Palermo 90128, <country>Italy</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Email: <email>francesca.danna@unipa.it</email>.</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><day>18</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>50</issue><fpage>17870</fpage><lpage>17880</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>20</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2023 The Authors. Published by American Chemical Society</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Authors</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>Permits the broadest form of re-use including for commercial purposes, provided that author attribution and integrity are maintained (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p content-type="toc-graphic"><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="sc3c07024_0012" id="ab-tgr1"/></p><p>With the aim to investigate
new strategies for upcycling
of plastic
waste, we performed aminolysis of poly(lactic acid) (PLA), using <italic>N,N</italic>-dimethylethylenediamine (DMEDA), <italic>N</italic>,<italic>N</italic>-dimethylpropylenediamine (DMPDA), and 3-aminopropylimidazole
(API) as nucleophiles. The <italic>N</italic>-substituted lactamides
obtained were alkylated by using alkyl halides differing in alkyl
chain length, obtaining organic salts that in most cases behaved as
ionic liquids (ILs). Both aminolysis of PLA and alkylation of amides
were carried out taking into consideration the basic principles of
the holistic approach to green chemistry, applied at a laboratory
scale, and carefully selecting the nature of the reaction solvent,
temperature range, and amount of reagents. Organic salts obtained
from the alkylation of <italic>N</italic>-substituted lactamides were
investigated to determine their glass or solid&#x02013;liquid transitions
and their thermal stability. Furthermore, cytotoxicity toward normal
lung fibroblasts was also assessed. Data collected show that the proposed
strategy represents a valuable protocol to upcycle plastic waste,
using it as starting material to obtain alternative solvents of potential
industrial relevance.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="short"><p>In this work,
we recycle PLA by depolymerization and then
we use the resulting lactamides to obtain safe ionic liquids.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>poly(lactic acid)</kwd><kwd>upcycling</kwd><kwd>aminolysis</kwd><kwd>lactamides</kwd><kwd>ionic liquids</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution>Ministero dell''Universit&#x000c3;&#x000a0; e della Ricerca</institution><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">10.13039/501100021856</institution-id></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>PE00000004</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>document-id-old-9</meta-name><meta-value>sc3c07024</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>document-id-new-14</meta-name><meta-value>sc3c07024</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>ccc-price</meta-name><meta-value/></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Plastic polymers represent a class of
materials that play a pivotal
role in the everyday life of modern society. The large use and different
fields of application make it unlikely that their substitution or
banning would be necessary without lowering the standards of living.
Unfortunately, the main problem directly related to the use of plastics
is the environmental impact due to both production and disposal of
these materials. Indeed, in some cases, the incorrect disposal of
plastic waste induces accumulation in landfills and oceans, and considering
that most of these synthetic polymers are designed for longevity and
performance, their persistence poses serious environmental issues.
A careful analysis of the actual plastic waste production allows foreseeing
that it will outweigh marine fish by 2050. Furthermore, as above stated,
due to the chemical inertia of plastic constituents, degradation of
existing materials requires around 250&#x02013;500 years, with the
high risk that they can enter the human food chain through crops and
animals.</p><p>Recycling is currently considered as a possible strategy
to face
the above problems. However, plastic production has increased exponentially
from 1975, with the current worldwide annual amount of approximately
380 millions of tons, of which only about 20% is recycled. Frequently,
this is a consequence of the complexity of postconsumer plastic waste
having unknown composition and presenting contaminants of different
nature.</p><p>Among alternative strategies suggested to partially
overcome the
above issues, production of biobased polymers and degradable plastics
shows great promise for a green and sustainable future.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref1">1</xref></sup> This is especially important in the case of polyesters,
considering not only their wide application but also their petroleum-based
production. Indeed, the use of biobased raw materials could contribute
to decrease the impact deriving from the production.</p><p>During
the years, among biobased polymers, polylactic acid (PLA)
has been proposed as the best replacement for petroleum-based polyesters
and its production is currently equal to 1.23 million tons per year,
representing 32% of global biodegradable plastics.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref3">3</xref></sup></p><p>PLA was produced for the first time in 1954 by Dupont,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4">4</xref></sup> and its mechanical properties allow a wide range
of applications ranging from food packaging to agricultural films.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref5">5</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref7">7</xref></sup> Unfortunately, although it is generally believed that biodegradable
plastics have a lower environmental impact, PLA degradation occurs
very slowly in the real environment, both in seawater and in soil,
producing CO<sub>2</sub>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref8">8</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref10">10</xref></sup> Like other thermoplastic polymers,
PLA can be physically recycled by melting and reforming into new shapes.
However, this kind of treatment induces a worsening of chemical and
mechanical properties of the polymer, and this is the main reason
why, also in this case, chemical recycling represents the more valuable
strategy.</p><p>Among chemical recycling methods, hydrolysis, alcoholysis,
and
aminolysis have been mainly considered. Hydrolysis represents the
best strategy for a closed loop, but this process requires harsh conditions
and produces waste for the use of a large amount of acids or bases.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref></sup></p><p>As for alcoholysis, different cases have been reported in
which
Lewis acids<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref12">12</xref></sup> or ionic liquids<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref14">14</xref></sup> have been used as catalysts. Finally, as for aminolysis, after the
first example investigating the transformation of PLA into alanine,
by treatment of the polymer in ammonia solution,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15">15</xref></sup> only few examples concerning the aminolysis of PLA, carried
out in the presence of amines, have been reported.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref></sup> The main products
of such processes are <italic>N</italic>-substituted lactamides, widely
applied in the chemical industry. These substrates are normally obtained
by dehydrative coupling reactions of lactic acid with amines, carried
out under equilibrium conditions, producing a large amount of waste
because of the removal of an acid or base catalyst.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref20">20</xref></sup> Then, the possibility to obtain these chemical intermediates, under
mild conditions and avoiding production of a large amount of waste,
represents a challenge of the current research in the field of sustainable
chemistry.</p><p>In this paper, embracing the above challenge, we
performed the
aminolysis of PLA in the presence of <italic>N,N</italic>-dimethylethylenediamine
(<bold>DMEDA</bold>), <italic>N,N</italic>-dimethylpropylenediamine
(<bold>DMPDA</bold>), and 3-aminopropylimidazole (<bold>API</bold>) (<xref rid="sch1" ref-type="scheme">Scheme <xref rid="sch1" ref-type="scheme">1</xref></xref>).</p><fig id="sch1" position="float"><label>Scheme 1</label><caption><title>Representation of Aminolysis of PLA and Amines Used</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="sc3c07024_0009" id="gr1" position="float"/></fig><p>Nucleophiles were chosen with the aim to evaluate
the effect due
to the length of the spacer between primary and tertiary nitrogens
(<bold>DMEDA</bold> and <bold>DMPDA</bold>) and the one deriving from
the aliphatic or aromatic nature of the tertiary amine function (<bold>DMPDA</bold> and <bold>API</bold>). In setting up the experimental
conditions, we considered basic principles of the holistic approach
to green chemistry,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref></sup> applied at a laboratory
scale, with the aim to minimize energy and materials consumption.</p><p>The relevance of the above approach further increases if <italic>N</italic>-substituted lactamides are subsequently used as starting
materials to obtain alternative solvents. To this aim, in this article,
we evaluated the possibility of using the products of PLA aminolysis
to prepare a new class of ionic liquids (ILs).</p><p>ILs are organic
salts with a melting point lower than 100 &#x000b0;C,
frequently liquid at room temperature and claimed as a benign and
sustainable alternative to conventional organic solvents, thanks to
their low vapor pressure and flammability. After pioneering papers
published in the past decade of the 20th century, presenting imidazolium
salts as main actors in this class of solvents, several efforts have
been carried out with the aim to prepare ILs, which combine good chemical
performance with low environmental cost and impact. In this context,
the possibility of using raw materials as building blocks for the
obtainment of ILs is a strategy widely considered in the past few
years. To this aim, some examples have been reported about the preparation
of ILs that originate from compounds normally existing in nature,
such as amino acids, carbohydrates, carboxylic acids, and choline.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref22">22</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref></sup></p><p>These compounds frequently award ILs lower toxicity and higher
biocompatibility. Furthermore, as they can be obtained also from biomass,
they also offer the dual advantage of a lower cost, which is one of
the main factors affecting ILs use on an industrial scale.</p><p>Bearing
in mind the above information and considering the structure
of <italic>N</italic>-substituted lactamides, we evaluated the possibility
of alkylating the tertiary amine function to obtain organic salts,
potentially behaving as ILs (<xref rid="sch2" ref-type="scheme">Schemes <xref rid="sch2" ref-type="scheme">2</xref></xref> and <xref rid="sch3" ref-type="scheme">3</xref>).</p><fig id="sch2" position="float"><label>Scheme 2</label><caption><title>Representation of
the Synthesis of Ammonium Salts</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="sc3c07024_0010" id="gr2" position="float"/></fig><fig id="sch3" position="float"><label>Scheme 3</label><caption><title>Representation of the Synthesis of Imidazolium Salts</title></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="sc3c07024_0011" id="gr3" position="float"/></fig><p>To this aim, the alkylation reaction was carried
out by using alkyl
iodides differing in alkyl chain length to assess the role played
by the above structural feature on the properties of the salts obtained.
Furthermore, the effect deriving from a different length of the spacer
or from the different nature of the cationic head (ammonium or imidazolium)
was also taken into consideration. We carried out synthetic procedures
considering the nature of the solvent used, the amount of reagents,
and also the reaction temperature, in the attempt to fully accomplish
green chemistry principles.</p><p>The thermal behavior of the obtained
organic salts was evaluated
by performing differential scanning calorimetry (DCS) and thermal
gravimetric analysis (TGA). Furthermore, considering the amide nature
of the organic salts and the presence of a lactate residue on the
cation structure, we also performed cytotoxicity tests by using normal
lung fibroblasts.</p><p>Previous reports in the literature demonstrate
that ammonium-based
ILs generally show a lower toxicity with respect to the corresponding
imidazolium ones. Furthermore, the toxicity of these latter can be
drastically reduced if hydroxylated chains are endowed in the cation
or anion structure.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref28">28</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref30">30</xref></sup> As a further point, it is also noteworthy that although
different examples of ILs bearing lactate anion have been reported,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref32">32</xref></sup> and they have been used for extractive desulfurization of fuels,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref33">33</xref></sup> as liquid phases for CO<sub>2</sub> and SO<sub>2</sub> capture,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref34">34</xref></sup> and as stabilizer of
metal nanoparticles,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref35">35</xref></sup> no case about the
presence of lactic acid residue on the cation structure has been reported
so far.</p><p>Results collected demonstrate that starting from PLA
waste, it
is possible to obtain lactamide-based ILs, under mild conditions and
in full compliance with the holistic approach to green chemistry.
Furthermore, our strategy demonstrates that a suitable combination
of structural features allows us to obtain ILs with good thermal stability
but very low toxicity.</p></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec id="sec2.1"><title>Aminolysis of PLA</title><p>The first experiments performed were
aimed at the setup of the experimental conditions. To this aim, we
carried out the aminolysis of PLA, using <italic>N,N</italic>-dimethylpropylenediamine
as nucleophile and evaluating the effect deriving from the increase
in the amount of nucleophile, reaction time, and reaction temperature.</p><p>The first attempts were performed using 1.5 equiv of nucleophile,
at 40 &#x000b0;C, under magnetic stirring. According to green chemistry
principles, to avoid the use of unnecessary auxiliaries, we performed
the reaction without using additional solvents.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref36">36</xref></sup> Then, we evaluated the effect of increasing reaction times,
going from 1 up to 6 h (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref></xref> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acssuschemeng.3c07024/suppl_file/sc3c07024_si_001.pdf">Table S1</ext-link>).</p><fig id="fig1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Conversion and yield
values for the aminolysis of PLA carried out,
at 40 &#x000b0;C, in the presence of <italic>N</italic>,<italic>N-</italic>dimethylpropylenediamine, as a function of time.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="sc3c07024_0001" id="gr4" position="float"/></fig><p>In all cases, the reaction proceeded with very
high selectivity,
as accounted for by comparable yield and conversion values. Furthermore,
we observed a gradual increase in yield from 17%, after 1 h, up to
60%, after 6 h.</p><p>With the aim to improve the performance of the
process, we slightly
increased the amount of nucleophile, using 2 equiv of amine at 40
&#x000b0;C. However, the modest increase in yield from 45 up to 52% induced
us to perform the process at a lower amount of nucleophile (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref></xref>).</p><p>Once we
determined the amount of nucleophile (1.5 equiv), we analyzed
the effect deriving from the increase in temperature, performing the
process in the temperature range 40&#x02013;100 &#x000b0;C (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref></xref> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acssuschemeng.3c07024/suppl_file/sc3c07024_si_001.pdf">Table S1</ext-link>).</p><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Conversion and yield values for the aminolysis of PLA carried out,
for 1 h, in the presence of <italic>N</italic>,<italic>N-</italic>dimethylpropylenediamine (1.5 equiv), as a function of the temperature.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="sc3c07024_0002" id="gr5" position="float"/></fig><p>The gradual increase in temperature induced a parallel
increase
in conversion values that ranged from 18 up to 99%. However, at the
highest temperature, we observed only a modest increase in yield that
changed from 73 up to 81%, because of a temperature increase from
70 up to 100 &#x000b0;C. Conversely, a significant decrease in selectivity
was detected, as accounted for by the significant difference between
yield and conversion value. This is the reason that further investigation
was performed at 70 &#x000b0;C.</p><p>The last parameter we took into
consideration, the temperature
being the same, was the reaction time. Interestingly, going from 1
h up to 3 h, we collected very high conversion and yield values with
excellent selectivity in the reaction (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref></xref> and <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acssuschemeng.3c07024/suppl_file/sc3c07024_si_001.pdf">Table S1</ext-link>).</p><fig id="fig3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Conversion
and yield values for the aminolysis of PLA carried out,
at 70 &#x000b0;C, in the presence of <italic>N</italic>,<italic>N</italic>-dimethylpropylenediamine (1.5 equiv), as a function of time.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="sc3c07024_0003" id="gr6" position="float"/></fig><p>With the optimized reaction conditions in hand,
we analyzed the
effect derived from the nature of the nucleophile. In particular,
besides <italic>N</italic>,<italic>N</italic>-dimethylpropylenediamine,
we also took into consideration <italic>N</italic>,<italic>N</italic>-dimethylethylenediamine and 3-aminopropylimidazole, with the aim
to explore the effect deriving from a different flexibility in the
nucleophile structure, going from the propyl to ethyl spacer and,
the spacer being the same, to assess the role played by the aliphatic
or aromatic nature of the tertiary amine (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref></xref>).</p><fig id="fig4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Conversion and yield values for the aminolysis
of PLA carried out
at 70 &#x000b0;C as a function of the nature of the nucleophile.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="sc3c07024_0004" id="gr7" position="float"/></fig><p>Surprisingly, we observed only a negligible effect
deriving from
the nucleophile flexibility, as accounted for by comparable conversion
and yield values obtained by using <italic>N</italic>,<italic>N</italic>-dimethylpropylenediamine and <italic>N</italic>,<italic>N</italic>-dimethylethylenediamine. Conversely, the presence of the aromatic
tertiary amine induced a significant worsening of the performance
of the process. Indeed, using 3-aminopropylimidazole required extending
the reaction time up to 24 h to obtain a yield higher than 89%.</p><p>As previously stated, the main aim of the present work was to perform
the aminolysis of PLA in a sustainable way and, consequently, consider
all the experimental parameters that could have repercussions on the
environmental impact of the process. To this aim, we analyzed the
results collected by using the holistic approach at green chemistry,
reported some years ago by Clark et al.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref></sup> This kind of approach can be applied at different levels, and, as
far as the laboratory scale is considered, important parameters that
must be considered are, besides reaction temperature, also conversion,
yield, and selectivity values. Flags of different color, green, yellow,
and red, respectively, are indicative of the increase of the environmental
impact of the target process. In particular, reaction temperatures
in the range 0&#x02013;70 &#x000b0;C and yield values higher than 89%
are indicative of a more sustainable process.</p><p>Results obtained
from the aminolysis of PLA performed under our
experimental conditions as a function of the different nature of the
nucleophile are reported in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acssuschemeng.3c07024/suppl_file/sc3c07024_si_001.pdf">Table S2</ext-link>. Analysis
of the results sheds light on the good performance of the process.
Indeed, in all cases, reaction temperature perfectly complies with
the guidelines of the used approach. Only in the case of 3-aminopropylimidazole,
a yield value lower than 89% was collected, giving a yellow flag to
the process. In all other cases, conversion, yield, and selectivity
values near or higher than 90% were collected, highlighting a good
compliance of the target process with the best previsions of the holistic
approach. The reaction mass efficiency ranged from 63% in the case
of <bold>[Im</bold><sub><bold>3</bold></sub><bold>-Lac]</bold> up
to 69.6% for <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>112</bold></sub><bold>&#x02013;Lac]</bold>.</p><p>To further assess the relevance of our process, we compared
our
results to some of the most recently reported papers on aminolysis
of PLA (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">1</xref></xref>).</p><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Reaction Conditions and Yields for
the Aminolysis of PLA</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="0"><colgroup><col/><col/><col/><col/><col/><col/><col/></colgroup><thead><tr><th style="border:none;" align="center"><bold>amine</bold></th><th style="border:none;" align="center"><bold>catalyst</bold></th><th style="border:none;" align="center"><italic>T</italic>&#x000a0;(&#x000b0;C)</th><th style="border:none;" align="center"><bold>reaction time (min)</bold></th><th style="border:none;" align="center"><bold>feeding ratio</bold></th><th style="border:none;" align="center">yield&#x000a0;(%)</th><th style="border:none;" align="center"><bold>reference</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td style="border:none;">DMEDA</td><td style="border:none;">none</td><td style="border:none;">70</td><td style="border:none;">180</td><td style="border:none;">1:1.5</td><td style="border:none;">88</td><td style="border:none;">this work</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;">DMPDA</td><td style="border:none;">None</td><td style="border:none;">70</td><td style="border:none;">180</td><td style="border:none;">1:1.5</td><td style="border:none;">90</td><td style="border:none;">this work</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;">API</td><td style="border:none;">none</td><td style="border:none;">70</td><td style="border:none;">24&#x000a0;h</td><td style="border:none;">1:1.5</td><td style="border:none;">83</td><td style="border:none;">this work</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;">2-aminoethanol</td><td style="border:none;">none</td><td style="border:none;">100</td><td style="border:none;">60</td><td style="border:none;">1:4</td><td style="border:none;">100</td><td style="border:none;">(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;">benzylamine</td><td style="border:none;">[FeCl<sub>2</sub>(TMG<sub>5</sub>NMe<sub>2</sub>asme)]</td><td style="border:none;">60</td><td style="border:none;">180</td><td style="border:none;">1:7</td><td style="border:none;">99</td><td style="border:none;">(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;">none</td><td style="border:none;">60</td><td style="border:none;">180</td><td style="border:none;">1:7</td><td style="border:none;">85</td><td style="border:none;">(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;">aniline</td><td style="border:none;">[N<sub>4444</sub>][Lac]</td><td style="border:none;">120</td><td style="border:none;">120</td><td style="border:none;">1:1.5</td><td style="border:none;">94</td><td style="border:none;">(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref>)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Our reaction conditions proved
to be comparable or
better than
the ones recently reported in literature. Indeed, our protocol foresees
the use of a lower amount of nucleophile, compared with data recently
reported by Zhang et al., concerning the same process carried out
in the presence of 2-aminoethanol, that gave full conversion of the
polymer at 60 &#x000b0;C, but working with a feeding ratio PLA/amine
equal to 1:4.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref18">18</xref></sup> On the other hand, our
approach also exhibited better performance than the one recently reported
by Liu et al. about the aminolysis of PLA carried out using aniline
as nucleophile.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref17">17</xref></sup> In the above case, a
yield value equal to 94% was obtained, using a comparable amount of
nucleophile (1.5 equiv) but operating at 120 &#x000b0;C. On the other
hand, our conditions proved to be significantly better than the ones
applied by Herres-Pawlis et al. that achieved a quantitative yield,
at 60 &#x000b0;C in the presence of a guanidine Iron(II) catalyst but
using the nucleophile with a feeding ratio equal to 1:7.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref16">16</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title>Alkylation of N-Substituted Lactamides</title><p>After the optimization
of the reaction conditions for the aminolysis of PLA, with the aim
to obtain products having potential industrial value, we considered
the possibility to alkylate the tertiary amine function of the amides
(<xref rid="sch2" ref-type="scheme">Schemes <xref rid="sch2" ref-type="scheme">2</xref></xref> and <xref rid="sch3" ref-type="scheme">3</xref>) for the obtainment of ammonium salts that, depending
on their melting point, could behave as ILs.</p><p>We optimized the
reaction conditions using <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>&#x02013;Lac]</bold> as substrate and butyl or dodecyl iodide
as alkylating agent to assess the effect of the alkyl chain length
on the performance of the process. We carried out the reaction at
70 &#x000b0;C, which represents a temperature value that perfectly resides
in the range 0&#x02013;70 &#x000b0;C, indicated as relatively mild conditions
according to the holistic approach.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref21">21</xref></sup></p><p>First attempts were carried out by using 1.5 equiv of alkyl halides
in solvent-free conditions. However, in all cases, reaction mixtures
appeared as biphasic systems and after 24 h (butyl iodide) or 72 h
(dodecyl iodide), we did not observe product formation. Consequently,
we used ethanol as solvent that, according to solvent selection guides,
is classified as a recommended solvent,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref37">37</xref></sup> operating in a very concentrated solution. Indeed, 100 mg of amide
was solubilized in 2 mL of EtOH and the alkyl iodide was added dropwise.
Alkylation reactions were performed changing the amount of alkyl iodide
from 1 up to 1.5 eq. (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acssuschemeng.3c07024/suppl_file/sc3c07024_si_001.pdf">Table S3</ext-link>). However,
data collected demonstrate that they proceeded with a full conversion
only using 1.5 equiv of alkyl iodide.</p><p>Taking into consideration
the above results, we changed the length
of the alkyl chain and the spacer to evaluate the effect of the above
structural parameters on the process performance<underline>.</underline> Reaction times ranged from 24 up to 72 h, in dependence of the alkyl
chain and the amide nature (see <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acssuschemeng.3c07024/suppl_file/sc3c07024_si_001.pdf">Experimental Section in the SI</ext-link>). In general, lower reaction times were used for
butyl chain and hexyl derivatives whereas the further lengthening
induced a corresponding increase in the reaction time. The longest
reaction time (2 weeks) was used in the case of <bold>[Im</bold><sub><bold>3</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]I</bold>.</p><p>In all cases, we
obtained a full conversion and yields ranging
from 83% (<bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>&#x02013;Lac-10]I</bold>) to 97% (<bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>&#x02013;Lac-6]I</bold> and <bold>[Im</bold><sub><bold>3</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]I</bold>). Results are reported in <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="other">Table <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="other">2</xref></xref>, together with reaction mass efficiency values (RMI).</p><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Yields and Reaction Mass Efficiency
(RME) for the Alkylation Reaction of the <italic>N</italic>-Lactamides</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="0"><colgroup><col/><col/><col/></colgroup><thead><tr><th style="border:none;" align="center"><bold>ammonium salt</bold></th><th style="border:none;" align="center">yield&#x000a0;(%)<xref rid="t2fn1" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref></th><th style="border:none;" align="center">RME&#x000a0;(%)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td style="border:none;"><bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>112</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]I</bold></td><td style="border:none;">92</td><td style="border:none;">72</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;"><bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]I</bold></td><td style="border:none;">95</td><td style="border:none;">75</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;"><bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-6]I</bold></td><td style="border:none;">97</td><td style="border:none;">76</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;"><bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-8]I</bold></td><td style="border:none;">98</td><td style="border:none;">76</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;"><bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-10]I</bold></td><td style="border:none;">83</td><td style="border:none;">63</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;"><bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]I</bold></td><td style="border:none;">93</td><td style="border:none;">70</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;"><bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>112</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]I</bold></td><td style="border:none;">92</td><td style="border:none;">69</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;"><bold>[Im</bold><sub><bold>3</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]I</bold></td><td style="border:none;">99</td><td style="border:none;">74</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;"><bold>[Im</bold><sub><bold>3</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]I</bold></td><td style="border:none;">97</td><td style="border:none;">79</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;"><bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]Br</bold></td><td style="border:none;">91</td><td style="border:none;">74</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;"><bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]Br</bold></td><td style="border:none;">70</td><td style="border:none;">53</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t2fn1"><label>a</label><p>Yields were reproducible within
&#x000b1;2.0%.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>With the only
exception of <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-10]I</bold>, the yield and selectivity
were higher
than 91%, giving a green flag to the process. In all cases, solvent
used to perform the reaction, as well as the ones used in the workup
procedures, can be easily recycled. Consequently, reaction mass efficiency
shows good values ranging from 70 up to 79%.</p><p>With the only exceptions
being <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]I</bold> and <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]Br</bold>, all organic salts behaved as viscous
liquids at room temperature. Some representative pictures are listed
in <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref></xref>.</p><fig id="fig5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Picture of
the obtained organic salts: (a) <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>112</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]I</bold>; (b) <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-6]I</bold>; (c) <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>112</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]I</bold>.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="sc3c07024_0005" id="gr8" position="float"/></fig><p>To have information about the effect of the nature
of the anion
on the properties of the organic salts, also butyl and dodecylbromides
of <italic>N</italic>-lactamide deriving from <italic>N,N</italic>-dimethylpropylenediamine were prepared (<bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]Br</bold> and <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]Br</bold>; <xref rid="sch2" ref-type="scheme">Scheme <xref rid="sch2" ref-type="scheme">2</xref></xref>). These were obtained under the same reaction
conditions, used for the alkylation, but only after reacting the amide
and corresponding bromides for 96 and 72 h, respectively. At the end
of the reaction time, also in this case, we recorded a full conversion
but with significantly different yield values that were equal to 70
and 91% in the case of [<bold>N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]Br</bold> and <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]Br</bold>, respectively. As a consequence of the low yield,
in the case of <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]Br</bold>, we obtained the lowest reaction mass efficiency that was equal
to 53% (<xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">Table <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="other">1</xref></xref>).</p><p>In addition, we investigated the possibility of recovering excess
halide. To this aim, we evaporated the organic phase obtained after
the washing step in the workup of the synthesis of <bold>[N<sub>113</sub>-Lac-12]I</bold>, as a representative case. The <sup>1</sup>H NMR
spectrum of the residue, reported in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acssuschemeng.3c07024/suppl_file/sc3c07024_si_001.pdf">Figure S5</ext-link>, shows that it is practically constituted by only the alkyl iodide,
suggesting the concrete possibility to recover it.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title>Thermal Behavior</title><p>Organic salts were first studied using
DSC measurements. Melting or glass transitions are reported in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acssuschemeng.3c07024/suppl_file/sc3c07024_si_001.pdf">Table S4</ext-link>, whereas DSC traces are displayed in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acssuschemeng.3c07024/suppl_file/sc3c07024_si_001.pdf">Figure S1</ext-link>. In most cases, in the used temperature
range (&#x02212;40&#x02013;60 &#x000b0;C), on heating, we did not observe
transitions, confirming the ionic liquid nature of the organic salts.
Melting processes were detected only in the case of <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>112</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]I</bold>, <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]I</bold>, <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]Br</bold>, and <bold>[Im</bold><sub><bold>3</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]I</bold>, and, among the above
cases, only <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>112</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]I</bold> and <bold>[Im</bold><sub><bold>3</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]I</bold> showed transition at temperature values lower than 100 &#x000b0;C.
Data collected clearly evidence that transition temperature increased
by increasing the spacer length (<italic>T</italic><sub>m<bold>[N113-Lac-4]I</bold></sub> &#x0003e; <italic>T</italic><sub>m<bold>[N112-Lac-4]I</bold></sub>) but also changing the anion nature (<italic>T</italic><sub>m<bold>[N113-Lac-4]Br</bold></sub> &#x0003e; <italic>T</italic><sub>m<bold>[N113-Lac-4]I</bold></sub>).</p><p>Thermal
stability of all of the organic salts was investigated by TGA measurements.
TGA traces are reported in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acssuschemeng.3c07024/suppl_file/sc3c07024_si_001.pdf">Table S1</ext-link>. With
the only exception of <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]Br</bold> and <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]Br</bold>, in all of the other cases, we observed a single-step
degradation process. In all cases, we considered the temperature corresponding
to the first degradation process, as the short-term stability limit,
as the highest temperature ILs can withstand for short periods. These
temperature values are reported in <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="other">Table <xref rid="tbl3" ref-type="other">3</xref></xref>.</p><table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Decomposition Temperatures
Obtained
for ILs</title></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="0"><colgroup><col/><col align="char" char="."/><col/><col/><col/><col align="char" char="."/></colgroup><thead><tr><th style="border:none;" align="center">&#x000a0;</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char="."><italic>T</italic><sub><bold>ons</bold></sub><bold>(1) (&#x000b0;C)</bold></th><th style="border:none;" align="center"><bold>&#x00394;</bold><italic>T</italic><bold>G peak(1) (&#x000b0;C)</bold></th><th style="border:none;" align="center"><italic>T</italic><sub><bold>ons</bold></sub><bold>(2) (&#x000b0;C)</bold></th><th style="border:none;" align="center">&#x000a0;</th><th style="border:none;" align="center" char="."><italic>T</italic><sub><bold>ons</bold></sub><bold>(1) (&#x000b0;C)</bold>(<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td style="border:none;"><bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>112</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]I</bold></td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">230.2</td><td style="border:none;">252.13</td><td style="border:none;">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;"><bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>112</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]I</bold></td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">218.23</td><td style="border:none;">250.21</td><td style="border:none;">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;"><bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>112</bold></sub><bold>-Glu-12]I</bold></td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">210.3</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;"><bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]I</bold></td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">261.01</td><td style="border:none;">295.76</td><td style="border:none;">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;"><bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Glu-4]I</bold></td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">191.7</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;"><bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-6]I</bold></td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">234.34</td><td style="border:none;">264.57</td><td style="border:none;">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;"><bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-8]I</bold></td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">238.92</td><td style="border:none;">272</td><td style="border:none;">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;"><bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-10]I</bold></td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">230.15</td><td style="border:none;">261.13</td><td style="border:none;">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;"><bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]I</bold></td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">235.17</td><td style="border:none;">263.41</td><td style="border:none;">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;"><bold>[Im</bold><sub><bold>3</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]I</bold></td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">292.05</td><td style="border:none;">320.8</td><td style="border:none;">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;"><bold><bold>[Im</bold><sub><bold>3</bold></sub>-Glu-4]I</bold></td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">197.3</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;"><bold>[Im</bold><sub><bold>3</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]I</bold></td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">274.24</td><td style="border:none;">310.33</td><td style="border:none;">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;"><bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]Br</bold></td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">251.2</td><td style="border:none;">277.9</td><td style="border:none;">457.1</td><td style="border:none;">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td style="border:none;"><bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]Br</bold></td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">226.7</td><td style="border:none;">245.3</td><td style="border:none;">466.4</td><td style="border:none;">&#x000a0;</td><td style="border:none;" align="char" char=".">&#x000a0;</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Decomposition temperatures
of ILs ranged from 245.3
(<bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]I)</bold> up to 320.8 &#x000b0;C
(<bold>[Im</bold><sub><bold>3</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]I).</bold> Thermal
stability significantly decreased by lengthening the alkyl chain.
On the other hand, alkyl chain and anion being the same, it increased
on going from <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>112</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]I</bold> to (<bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4 ]I</bold> and from <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>112</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]I</bold> to <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]I</bold>, according to the increase in the alkyl spacer length, with &#x00394;<italic>T</italic> depending on the length of the alkyl chain (&#x00394;<italic>T</italic> = 43.7 and 13.2 in the case of butyl and dodecyl derivatives,
respectively).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref></sup> This result was different
from the one we collected for <italic>N</italic>-glucosamide-based
ILs. Indeed, in that case, we observed a decrease in thermal stability
on going from an ethyl to propyl spacer.</p><p>Comparison between
data collected for bromide (<bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]Br</bold> and <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]Br</bold>) and iodide salts (<bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]Br</bold> and <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]I</bold>) evidenced
a higher thermal stability of the iodides than bromide salts. This
result perfectly accounts for the increase in thermal stability induced
by a decrease in the anion nucleophilicity previously reported for
imidazolium salts.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref38">38</xref></sup></p><p>Finally, data
were collected accounting for the higher thermal
stability of imidazolium with respect to the corresponding ammonium
salts (<italic>cfr.</italic><bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]I/[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]I</bold> and [<bold>Im</bold><sub><bold>3</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]I/</bold>[<bold>Im</bold><sub><bold>3</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-</bold><sub><bold>12</bold></sub><bold>]I</bold>), in accordance with a previous observation
in literature comparing imidazolium and ammonium salt having alkyl
chains of the same length.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref39">39</xref></sup></p><p>In order
to analyze the effect of the oxygenated chain on the thermal
stability, we compared decomposition temperatures, at 95% wt, for <italic>N</italic>-glucosamides-based ILs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref></sup> with
the one now obtained for <italic>N</italic>-lactamide-based ILs (<xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="other">Table <xref rid="tbl2" ref-type="other">2</xref></xref>). In general, the
above comparison evidenced a higher thermal stability for <italic>N</italic>-lactamides-based ILs with respect to the corresponding <italic>N</italic>-glucosamide-based ones.</p></sec><sec id="sec2.4"><title>Biological Activity of
ILs: Morphological Assessment</title><p>A morphological assessment
of human fetal lung fibroblasts (IMR-90
cells) by a phase-contrast inverted microscope was employed, monitoring
the cells under an inverted light microscope after 24 h of treatment
with different concentrations (50, 75, 100, 150 &#x003bc;M) of ILs (<xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">Figures <xref rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref></xref> and <xref rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). IMR-90 control cells maintained their original morphology
consisting of elongated and slender forms and the strikingly regular
form, with longitudinal alignment of cells. At a lower concentration
of treatments (50 &#x003bc;M), the ILs bearing short alkyl chains showed
weaker biological effectiveness compared to those with long apolar
alkyl chains in terms of morphological changes and cytotoxic effects.
This lower biological activity was maintained at higher concentrations
of treatments, especially for salts bearing butyl or hexyl chains.
The obtained results clearly indicate that, according to the specific
fields of application, the biological activity of ILs is quite tunable,
by modifying structural characteristics.</p><fig id="fig6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Micrographs performed
by inverted phase-contrast microscopy of
IMR-90 cells treated for 24 h with different concentrations (50, 75,
100, 150 &#x003bc;M) of <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]I, [N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-6]I</bold>, <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-8]I</bold>, <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-10]I</bold>, and <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]I</bold>. Magnification 200&#x000d7;.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="sc3c07024_0006" id="gr9" position="float"/></fig><fig id="fig7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Micrographs
performed by inverted phase-contrast microscopy
of
IMR-90 cells treated for 24 h with different concentrations (50, 75,
100, 150 &#x003bc;M) of <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]Br</bold>, <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]Br</bold>, <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>112</bold></sub><bold>&#x02013;Lac-4]I</bold>, <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>112</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]I, [Im</bold><sub><bold>3</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]I</bold>, and <bold>[Im</bold><sub><bold>3</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]I</bold>. Magnification 200&#x000d7;.</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="sc3c07024_0007" id="gr10" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec2.5"><title>Structure vs Cytotoxicity</title><p>The cytotoxicity of ILs was
evaluated by using a 24 h toxicity assay. The IC<sub>50</sub> values
were calculated using a dose&#x02013;response model by means of sigmoidal
fitting of curves of percent inhibition versus logarithm of tested
concentrations. In all cases, the MTT assay was performed using diluted
1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02013;3</sup> M stock solutions of salts. The results
obtained are gathered in <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acssuschemeng.3c07024/suppl_file/sc3c07024_si_001.pdf">Table S3</ext-link> and depicted
in <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref></xref>.</p><fig id="fig8" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Histograms
showing IC<sub>50</sub> values expressed as &#x003bc;M
concentration of ILs sorted for different structural characteristics:
(a) alkyl chain length in the cation (<bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]I</bold>, <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-6]I</bold>, <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-8]I</bold>, <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-10]I</bold>, and <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]I</bold>), (b) spacer length (<bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>112</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]I</bold>, <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]I</bold>, <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>112</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]I</bold>, and <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]I</bold>), (c) cation nature
(<bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]I</bold>, <bold>[Im</bold><sub><bold>3</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]I</bold>, <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]I</bold>, <bold>[Im</bold><sub><bold>3</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]I</bold>), and (d) anion nature
(<bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]Br</bold>, <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]I</bold>, <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]Br</bold>, and <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]I</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="sc3c07024_0008" id="gr11" position="float"/></fig><p>IC<sub>50</sub> values range from 6.58 &#x003bc;M
up to 94.4 &#x003bc;M.
In general, these organic salts prove to be less toxic than <italic>N</italic>-gluconamide-based ILs, which exhibited IC<sub>50</sub> values ranging from 0.06 &#x003bc;M up to 12.6 &#x003bc;m.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref></sup></p><p>Data collected will be analyzed as a function
of different structural
features of the salts.</p><p>First, as can be seen from <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref></xref>a, butyl and hexyl derivatives
represent the terms
of lower toxicity. The further increase in alkyl chain length induces
a sharp increase in cytotoxicity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref40">40</xref></sup> These
results are consistent with data previously reported in literature
and can be easily ascribed to the increase in the lipophilicity that
induces a better interaction with the phospholipid bilayers of biological
membranes.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref41">41</xref></sup></p><p>On the alkyl chain being
the same, small changes were detected
as a function of the length of the alkyl spacer. In particular, ILs
bearing the ethyl spacer are slightly less toxic than the ones featured
by the presence of the propyl spacer (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref></xref>b). This result is different from the one
we collected studying the biological activity of <italic>N</italic>-glucosamide-based ILs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref></sup></p><p>Interestingly,
the presence of the <italic>N</italic>-lactamide
unit induced comparable toxicity in imidazolium- and ammonium-based
salts, as accounted for by the comparison between IC<sub>50</sub> values
detected for <bold>[Im</bold><sub><bold>3</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]I</bold> and <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]I</bold>, as well as the ones for <bold>[Im</bold><sub><bold>3</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-12]I</bold> and <bold>[N</bold><sub><bold>113</bold></sub><bold>-Lac-4]I</bold> (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref></xref>c). This results appear quite surprising considering the frequently
claimed lower toxicity of aliphatic ILs with respect to the corresponding
aromatic ones. This finding clearly supports the one previously reported
in literature about the role played by oxygenated chains in decreasing
the IL toxicity.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref42">42</xref></sup></p><p>Finally, independently
from the cation structure, bromide salt
exhibited lower toxicity with respect to the corresponding iodide
salts (<xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">Figure <xref rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref></xref>d).
Probably, the above result can be related to the anion lipophilicity,
as accounted for by its ability to interact with water molecules.
Bromide, as a consequence of its higher charge density, should better
interact with water molecules exhibiting a lower lipophilicity and
consequently a lower ability to interact with the lipophilic membrane.
This hypothesis is also supported by data previously reported in literature
about the ability of the anion to permeate phospholipidic bilayers
and showing a higher permeation rate for the iodide anion with respect
to the bromide one.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref43">43</xref></sup></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Conclusions</title><p>With the aim to upcycle plastic waste and
to realize an open loop
that starting from waste materials allows the obtainment of products
of industrial values, like alternative solvents, we performed aminolysis
of PLA, under sustainable conditions. In particular, temperature and
time of reaction, as well as the amount and nature of nucleophile,
were carefully evaluated, to minimize the environmental impact of
the process. This allowed the obtainment of <italic>N</italic>-substituted
lactamides, avoiding harsh conditions and the use of a large amount
of acidic or basic catalysts.</p><p>A careful analysis of the <italic>N</italic>-lactamide structure
sheds light on the possibility of using them as starting materials
for the preparation of organic salts, potentially behaving as ionic
liquids. To this aim, they were successfully alkylated, using alkyl
halides differing for the alkyl chain length and the halide nature.
Proposed synthetic protocols perfectly fit the guidelines of the holistic
approach to green chemistry and allowed obtaining a green or yellow
flag for related parameters, like conversion and yield, while RMI
values ranged from 52 up to 79%.</p><p>The majority of the ammonium
salts obtained were viscous liquids
at room temperature, behaving as ILs. Properties of these solvents,
like melting temperature, thermal stability, and toxicity toward normal
lung fibroblasts, were studied as a function of different structural
features, showing good thermal stability and toxicity lower than the
one recently detected for some <italic>N</italic>-glucosamide-based
ILs.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref25">25</xref></sup> Interestingly, the results collected
demonstrate how careful modulation of structural features, like alkyl
chain and spacer length, as well as anion and cationic head nature
allows the obtainment of ILs of good thermal stability and low toxicity.
To the best of our knowledge, this is the first report about the obtainment
of ILs from plastic waste, featured by a lactate residue on the cation
structure. The presence of the above residue should award these ILs
a good coordination ability, and also thanks to the good thermal stability
and low toxicity, they could be tested, in the future, for extractive
desulfurization of fuels or as liquid phases for CO<sub>2</sub> and
SO<sub>2</sub> capture. Furthermore, according to previous reports,
iodide-based ammonium salts are frequently indicated as good corrosion
inhibitors.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref44">44</xref>&#x02212;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref46">46</xref></sup> Consequently, the proposed strategy in this work
could represent a suitable way to upcycle waste for the obtainment
of useful industrial intermediates.</p></sec></body><back><notes id="notes1" notes-type="si"><title>Supporting Information Available</title><p>The Supporting Information is
available free of charge at <ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acssuschemeng.3c07024?goto=supporting-info">https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acssuschemeng.3c07024</ext-link>. <list id="silist" list-type="simple"><list-item><p>Experimental
procedures, yields and conversions for
PLA aminolysis, IC<sub>50</sub> values, thermogravimetric curves, <sup>1</sup>H and <sup>13</sup>C NMR spectra, and FTIR spectra of lacatamide-based
ionic liquids (<ext-link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/suppl/10.1021/acssuschemeng.3c07024/suppl_file/sc3c07024_si_001.pdf">PDF</ext-link>)</p></list-item></list></p></notes><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sifile1"><media xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="sc3c07024_si_001.pdf"><caption><p>sc3c07024_si_001.pdf</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><notes notes-type="COI-statement" id="NOTES-d14e1581-autogenerated"><p>The
authors declare no
competing financial interest.</p></notes><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>This study was carried out within the MICS (Made
in Italy &#x02013; Circular and Sustainable) Extended Partnership and
received funding from the European Union Next-GenerationEU (Piano
Nazionale di Ripresa e Resilienza (PNRR) &#x02013; Missione 4 Componente
2, Investimento 1.3 &#x02013; D.D. 1551.11-10-2022, PE00000004). This
manuscript reflects only the authors&#x02019; views and opinions; neither
the European Union nor the European Commission can be considered responsible
for them. G.R. thanks PNRR, Missione 4, Componente 1 &#x0201c;Potenziamento
dell&#x02019;offerta dei servizi di istruzione: dagli asili nido all&#x02019;Universit&#x000e0;&#x0201d;
- Investimento 3.4 &#x0201c;Didattica e competenze universitarie avanzate&#x0201d;
e Investimento 4.1 &#x0201c;Estensione del numero di dottorati di ricerca
e dottorati innovativi per la pubblica amministrazione e il patrimonio
culturale&#x0201d;.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ref1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit1"><name><surname>Schneiderman</surname><given-names>D. K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hillmyer</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>
<article-title><italic>50th Anniversary
Perspective</italic>: There
Is a Great Future in Sustainable Polymers</article-title>. <source>Macromolecules</source>
<year>2017</year>, <volume>50</volume> (<issue>10</issue>), <fpage>3733</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3749</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acs.macromol.7b00293</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit2"><name><surname>Singhvi</surname><given-names>M. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zinjarde</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gokhale</surname><given-names>D. V.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Polylactic Acid: Synthesis and Biomedical
Applications</article-title>. <source>J. Appl. Microbiol.</source>
<year>2019</year>, <volume>127</volume> (<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>1612</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1626</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jam.14290</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31021482</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit3"><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Raubenheimer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Urho</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Unger</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Azoulay</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Farrelly</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sousa</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>van Asselt</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Carlini</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sekomo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Schulte</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Busch</surname><given-names>P.-O.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wienrich</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Weiand</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A Binding
Global Agreement to Address
the Life Cycle of Plastics</article-title>. <source>Science (1979)</source>
<year>2021</year>, <volume>373</volume> (<issue>6550</issue>), <fpage>43</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>47</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abi9010</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><mixed-citation publication-type="undeclared" id="cit4"><person-group person-group-type="allauthors"><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chapter 1. PLA
Synthesis. From the Monomer to the Polymer</article-title>. <source>Poly (lactic acid) science and technology: processing, properties,
additives and applications</source>; <publisher-name>Royal Society
Chemistry</publisher-name><year>2014</year>; pp <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>36</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit5"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Xing</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Quality and
Microbial Diversity of Homemade Bread Packaged in Cinnamaldehyde Loaded
Poly(Lactic Acid)/Konjac Glucomannan/Wheat Gluten Bilayer Film during
Storage</article-title>. <source>Food Chem.</source>
<year>2023</year>, <volume>402</volume>, <elocation-id>134259</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2022.134259</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36137378</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit6"><name><surname>Swetha</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bora</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Mohanrasu</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Balaji</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Raja</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ponnuchamy</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Muthusamy</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Arun</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A Comprehensive Review
on Polylactic Acid (PLA) &#x02013; Synthesis, Processing and Application
in Food Packaging</article-title>. <source>Int. J. Biol. Macromol.</source>
<year>2023</year>, <volume>234</volume>, <elocation-id>123715</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2023.123715</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36801278</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit7"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shi</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Super-Toughed
PLA Blown Film with Enhanced Gas Barrier Property Available for Packaging
and Agricultural Applications</article-title>. <source>Materials</source>
<year>2019</year>, <volume>12</volume> (<issue>10</issue>), <fpage>1663</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ma12101663</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31121860</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit8"><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>R. T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Camargo</surname><given-names>L. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Marine-Degradable
Polylactic Acid</article-title>. <source>Green Chem.</source>
<year>2014</year>, <volume>16</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>1768</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1773</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C3GC42604A</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit9"><name><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Environmental Performance
of Bio-Based and Biodegradable
Plastics: The Road Ahead</article-title>. <source>Chem. Soc. Rev.</source>
<year>2017</year>, <volume>46</volume> (<issue>22</issue>), <fpage>6855</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6871</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C7CS00149E</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28932844</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit10"><name><surname>Suyama</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tokiwa</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ouichanpagdee</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kanagawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kamagata</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Phylogenetic
Affiliation of Soil Bacteria That Degrade Aliphatic Polyesters Available
Commercially as Biodegradable Plastics</article-title>. <source>Appl.
Environ. Microbiol.</source>
<year>1998</year>, <volume>64</volume> (<issue>12</issue>), <fpage>5008</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5011</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.64.12.5008-5011.1998</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9835597</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit11"><name><surname>Piemonte</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gironi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Kinetics of Hydrolytic
Degradation of PLA</article-title>. <source>J. Polym. Environ.</source>
<year>2013</year>, <volume>21</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>313</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>318</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10924-012-0547-x</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit12"><name><surname>Piemonte</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gironi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Lactic Acid Production by Hydrolysis of Poly(Lactic
Acid) in Aqueous Solutions: An Experimental and Kinetic Study</article-title>. <source>J. Polym. Environ.</source>
<year>2013</year>, <volume>21</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>275</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>279</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10924-012-0468-8</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit13"><name><surname>Leibfarth</surname><given-names>F. A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hawker</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shand</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Transforming Polylactide
into Value-Added Materials</article-title>. <source>J. Polym. Sci.,
Part A: Polym. Chem.</source>
<year>2012</year>, <volume>50</volume> (<issue>23</issue>), <fpage>4814</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4822</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pola.26303</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit14"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Facile Synthesis
of DBU-Based Protic Ionic Liquid for Efficient Alcoholysis of Waste
Poly(Lactic Acid) to Lactate Esters</article-title>. <source>Polym.
Degrad. Stab.</source>
<year>2019</year>, <volume>167</volume>, <fpage>124</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>129</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.polymdegradstab.2019.06.028</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit15"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Converting Plastic Wastes to Naphtha
for Closing the Plastic Loop</article-title>. <source>J. Am. Chem. Soc.</source>
<year>2023</year>, <volume>145</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>1847</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1854</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jacs.2c11407</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36635072</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit16"><name><surname>Burkart</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Eith</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Herres-Pawlis</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Open Loop
Recycling &#x02013; guanidine Iron(II) Polymerization Catalyst for
the Depolymerization of Polylactide</article-title>. <source>Chem. -
Asian J.</source>
<year>2023</year>, <volume>18</volume> (<issue>5</issue>), <elocation-id>e202201195</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/asia.202201195</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36577118</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit17"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Lactate Anion
Catalyzes Aminolysis of Polyesters with Anilines</article-title>. <source>Sci. Adv.</source>
<year>2023</year>, <volume>9</volume> (<issue>5</issue>), <elocation-id>eade7971</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciadv.ade7971</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36724269</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit18"><name><surname>Shao</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Y.-C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fei</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Bliss</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A Chemical Approach for the Future
of PLA upcycling: From Plastic Wastes to New 3D Printing Materials</article-title>. <source>Green Chem.</source>
<year>2022</year>, <volume>24</volume> (<issue>22</issue>), <fpage>8716</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8724</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/D2GC01745H</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit19"><name><surname>RATCHFORD</surname><given-names>W. P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>FISHER</surname><given-names>C. H.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Preparation of n-substituted
lactamides by aminolysis
of methyl lactate</article-title>. <source>J. Org. Chem.</source>
<year>1950</year>, <volume>15</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>317</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>325</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jo01148a013</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit20"><name><surname>Fein</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Filachione</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>N-Substituted
Lactamides</article-title>. <source>J.
Am. Chem. Soc.</source>
<year>1953</year>, <volume>75</volume> (<issue>9</issue>), <fpage>2097</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2099</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ja01105a022</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit21"><name><surname>McElroy</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Constantinou</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Summerton</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Towards a Holistic
Approach to Metrics for the 21st
Century Pharmaceutical Industry</article-title>. <source>Green Chem.</source>
<year>2015</year>, <volume>17</volume> (<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>3111</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3121</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C5GC00340G</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit22"><name><surname>Ohno</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fukumoto</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Amino Acid Ionic Liquids</article-title>. <source>Acc.
Chem. Res.</source>
<year>2007</year>, <volume>40</volume> (<issue>11</issue>), <fpage>1122</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1129</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ar700053z</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17970600</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit23"><name><surname>Miao</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Atkin</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Warr</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Design and Applications of Biocompatible
choline Amino Acid Ionic Liquids</article-title>. <source>Green Chem.</source>
<year>2022</year>, <volume>24</volume> (<issue>19</issue>), <fpage>7281</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7304</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/D2GC02282F</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit24"><name><surname>Dhattarwal</surname><given-names>H. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Kashyap</surname><given-names>H. K.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Microstructures
of choline Amino Acid Based Biocompatible
Ionic Liquids</article-title>. <source>Chem. Record</source>
<year>2023</year>, <volume>23</volume>, <elocation-id>e202200295</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/tcr.202200295</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36960931</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit25"><name><surname>Billeci</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>D&#x02019;Anna</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Feroci</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cancemi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Feo</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Forlino</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tonnelli</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Seddon</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gunaratne</surname><given-names>H. Q. N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Plechkova</surname><given-names>N. V.</given-names></name>
<article-title>When Functionalization Becomes Useful: Ionic Liquids
with a &#x0201c;Sweet&#x0201d; Appended Moiety Demonstrate Drastically
Reduced Toxicological Effects</article-title>. <source>ACS Sustainable
Chem. Eng.</source>
<year>2020</year>, <volume>8</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>926</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>938</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/acssuschemeng.9b05507</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit26"><name><surname>Zullo</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Iuliano</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Guazzelli</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Sugar-Based
Ionic Liquids: Multifaceted
Challenges and Intriguing Potential</article-title>. <source>Molecules</source>
<year>2021</year>, <volume>26</volume> (<issue>7</issue>), <fpage>2052</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules26072052</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33916695</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit27"><name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gathergood</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Biodegradation
of Ionic Liquids &#x02013; a Critical
Review</article-title>. <source>Chem. Soc. Rev.</source>
<year>2015</year>, <volume>44</volume> (<issue>22</issue>), <fpage>8200</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8237</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C5CS00444F</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26239761</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit28"><name><surname>Gaida</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Brz&#x00065;&#x00328;czek-Szafran</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Insights into
the Properties and
Potential Applications of Renewable Carbohydrate-Based Ionic Liquids:
A Review</article-title>. <source>Molecules</source>
<year>2020</year>, <volume>25</volume> (<issue>14</issue>), <fpage>3285</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/molecules25143285</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32698359</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit29"><name><surname>Javed</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ullah</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Akil</surname><given-names>H. Md.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Synthesis,
Characterization and Cellulose
Dissolution Capabilities of Ammonium-Based Room Temperature Ionic
Liquids (RTILs)</article-title>. <source>Pure Appl. Chem.</source>
<year>2018</year>, <volume>90</volume> (<issue>6</issue>), <fpage>1019</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1034</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/pac-2017-0315</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit30"><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Forte</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zalewska</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tiago</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Petrovski</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Branco</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Novel Biocompatible Ionic Liquids Based on Gluconate
Anion</article-title>. <source>Green Chem. Lett. Rev.</source>
<year>2015</year>, <volume>8</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>8</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/17518253.2014.951695</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit31"><name><surname>Shawver</surname><given-names>N. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Doerr</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Long</surname><given-names>B. K.</given-names></name>
<article-title>A Perspective
on redox-switchable
Ring-opening Polymerization</article-title>. <source>J. Polym. Sci.</source>
<year>2023</year>, <volume>61</volume> (<issue>5</issue>), <fpage>361</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>371</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pol.20220585</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit32"><name><surname>Kasprzak</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>St&#x00065;&#x00328;pniak</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gali&#x00144;ski</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Acetate- and Lactate-Based Ionic
Liquids: Synthesis, Characterisation and Electrochemical Properties</article-title>. <source>J. Mol. Liq.</source>
<year>2018</year>, <volume>264</volume>, <fpage>233</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>241</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.molliq.2018.05.059</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit33"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Lei</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Deep Desulfurization
of Fuels by Extraction with 4-Dimethylaminopyridinium-Based Ionic
Liquids</article-title>. <source>Energy Fuels</source>
<year>2013</year>, <volume>27</volume> (<issue>8</issue>), <fpage>4617</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4623</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ef401015c</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit34"><name><surname>Tian</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ren</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Absorption of SO2 by
Thermal-Stable Functional Ionic Liquids with Lactate Anion</article-title>. <source>RSC Adv.</source>
<year>2013</year>, <volume>3</volume> (<issue>11</issue>), <fpage>3572</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/c3ra22450c</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit35"><name><surname>Morel</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Silarska</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Trzeciak</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pernak</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Palladium-Catalyzed
Asymmetric Heck Arylation of 2,3-Dihydrofuran &#x02013; Effect of Prolinate
Salts</article-title>. <source>Dalton Trans.</source>
<year>2013</year>, <volume>42</volume> (<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>1215</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1222</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C2DT31672B</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23135637</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit36"><name><surname>Anastas</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Eghbali</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Green Chemistry: Principles
and Practice</article-title>. <source>Chem. Soc. Rev.</source>
<year>2010</year>, <volume>39</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>301</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>312</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/B918763B</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20023854</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit37"><name><surname>Prat</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pardigon</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Flemming</surname><given-names>H.-W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Letestu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ducandas</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Isnard</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Guntrum</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Senac</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ruisseau</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Cruciani</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hosek</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Sanofi&#x02019;s
Solvent Selection
Guide: A Step Toward More Sustainable Processes</article-title>. <source>Org. Process Res. Dev.</source>
<year>2013</year>, <volume>17</volume> (<issue>12</issue>), <fpage>1517</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1525</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/op4002565</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit38"><name><surname>Kroon</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Buijs</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Witkamp</surname><given-names>G.-J.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Quantum Chemical
Aided Prediction of the Thermal Decomposition Mechanisms and Temperatures
of Ionic Liquids</article-title>. <source>Thermochim. Acta</source>
<year>2007</year>, <volume>465</volume> (<issue>1&#x02013;2</issue>), <fpage>40</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>47</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tca.2007.09.003</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit39"><name><surname>Kulkarni</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Branco</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Crespo</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nunes</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Raymundo</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Afonso</surname><given-names>C. A. M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Comparison of Physicochemical Properties of New Ionic
Liquids Based on imidazolium, Quaternary Ammonium, and Guanidinium
Cations</article-title>. <source>Chem. - Eur. J.</source>
<year>2007</year>, <volume>13</volume> (<issue>30</issue>), <fpage>8478</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8488</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/chem.200700965</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17665379</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit40"><name><surname>Cancemi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Buttacavoli</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>D&#x02019;Anna</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Feo</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Fontana</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Noto</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Sutera</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Vitale</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gallo</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The Effects
of Structural Changes on the Anti-Microbial and Anti-Proliferative
Activities of Diimidazolium Salts</article-title>. <source>New J. Chem.</source>
<year>2017</year>, <volume>41</volume> (<issue>9</issue>), <fpage>3574</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3585</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C6NJ03904A</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit41"><name><surname>Egorova</surname><given-names>K.
S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Ananikov</surname><given-names>V. P.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Toxicity
of Ionic Liquids: Eco(Cyto)Activity as Complicated,
but Unavoidable Parameter for Task-Specific Optimization</article-title>. <source>ChemSusChem</source>
<year>2014</year>, <volume>7</volume> (<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>336</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>360</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cssc.201300459</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24399804</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit42"><name><surname>Vrane&#x00161;</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Tot</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Jovanovi&#x00107;-&#x00160;anta</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Karaman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Do&#x0017e;i&#x00107;</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Te&#x00161;anovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Koji&#x00107;</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Gad&#x0017e;uri&#x00107;</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Toxicity Reduction of imidazolium-Based
Ionic Liquids by the Oxygenation of the Alkyl Substituent</article-title>. <source>RSC Adv.</source>
<year>2016</year>, <volume>6</volume> (<issue>98</issue>), <fpage>96289</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>96295</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/C6RA16182K</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit43"><name><surname>Paula</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Volkov</surname><given-names>A. G.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Deamer</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Permeation
of Halide Anions through
Phospholipid bilayers Occurs by the Solubility-Diffusion Mechanism</article-title>. <source>Biophys. J.</source>
<year>1998</year>, <volume>74</volume> (<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>319</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>327</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-3495(98)77789-6</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9449332</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit44"><name><surname>Dean</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Golding</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Pringle</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Forsyth</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Skelton</surname><given-names>B. W.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>White</surname><given-names>A. H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>MacFarlane</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The Effect
of Alkyl Chain Length
in a Series of Novel N-Alkyl-3-Benzylimidazolium Iodide Salts</article-title>. <source>CrystEngComm</source>
<year>2009</year>, <volume>11</volume> (<issue>11</issue>), <fpage>2456</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1039/b906142h</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit45"><name><surname>Branzoi</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Branzoi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Baibarac</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>
<article-title>The Inhibition of the Corrosion of
Armco Iron in HCl Solutions in the Presence of Surfactants of the
Type of N-Alkyl Quaternary Ammonium Salts</article-title>. <source>Mater.
Chem. Phys.</source>
<year>2000</year>, <volume>65</volume> (<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>288</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>297</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0254-0584(00)00260-1</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="cit46"><name><surname>Arellanes-Lozada</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>D&#x000ed;az-Jim&#x000e9;nez</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Hern&#x000e1;ndez-Cocoletzi</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Nava</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Olivares-Xometl</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>; <name><surname>Likhanova</surname><given-names>N. V.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Corrosion
Inhibition Properties of Iodide Ionic Liquids for API 5L X52 Steel
in Acid Medium</article-title>. <source>Corros. Sci.</source>
<year>2020</year>, <volume>175</volume>, <elocation-id>108888</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.corsci.2020.108888</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
