<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Temperature (Austin)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Temperature (Austin)</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Temperature: Multidisciplinary Biomedical Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2332-8940</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2332-8959</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Taylor &#x00026; Francis</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC10732613</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/23328940.2023.2208516</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2208516</article-id><article-version vocab="JAV" vocab-identifier="http://www.niso.org/publications/rp/RP-8-2008.pdf" vocab-term="Version of Record" article-version-type="VoR">Version of Record</article-version><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Seasonal influence on cognitive and psycho-physiological responses to a single 11-h day of work in outdoor mine industry workers</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">S. M. TAGGART ET AL.</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="right-running-head">TEMPERATURE</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-3815-9805</contrib-id><name><surname>Taggart</surname><given-names>Sarah M.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref><xref rid="an0001" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4797-182X</contrib-id><name><surname>Girard</surname><given-names>Olivier</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2679-4342</contrib-id><name><surname>Landers</surname><given-names>Grant J.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4743-313X</contrib-id><name><surname>Ecker</surname><given-names>Ullrich K. H.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0002" ref-type="aff">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9768-6736</contrib-id><name><surname>Wallman</surname><given-names>Karen E.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff0001" ref-type="aff">
<sup>a</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff0001"><label>a</label>School of Human Sciences (Sport Science, Exercise and Health), <institution-wrap><institution>The University of Western Australia</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Crawley</city>, <state>WA</state>, <country>Australia</country></aff><aff id="aff0002"><label>b</label>School of Psychological Science, <institution-wrap><institution>The University of Western Australia</institution></institution-wrap>, <city>Crawley</city>, <state>WA</state>, <country>Australia</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="an0001">CONTACT Sarah M. Taggart <email xlink:href="mailto:sarah.taggart@research.uwa.edu.au">sarah.taggart@research.uwa.edu.au</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>12</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>12</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage seq="8">465</fpage><lpage>478</lpage><pub-history><event event-type="tagger"><event-desc>Integra</event-desc><date><day>04</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="final"><event-desc>Integra</event-desc><date><day>04</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="received"><date><day>10</day><month>1</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="revised"><date><day>24</day><month>4</month><year>2023</year></date></event><event event-type="accepted"><date><day>25</day><month>4</month><year>2023</year></date></event></pub-history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2023 The Author(s). Published by Informa UK Limited, trading as Taylor &#x00026; Francis Group.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author(s)</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. The terms on which this article has been published allow the posting of the Accepted Manuscript in a repository by the author(s) or with their consent.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="KTMP_10_2208516.pdf"/><abstract><title>ABSTRACT</title><p>This study investigated the seasonal effects that working outdoors had on various parameters in mining industry workers over the course of a work-shift. Workers (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;27) were assessed in summer (33.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.2&#x000b0;C, 38&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;18% RH; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;13, age&#x02009;=&#x02009;46&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;14 y, BMI&#x02009;=&#x02009;29.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.7&#x02009;kg/m<sup>2</sup>) and winter (23.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.1&#x000b0;C, 39&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;20% RH; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;14, age&#x02009;=&#x02009;44&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;12 y, BMI&#x02009;=&#x02009;31.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.1&#x02009;kg/m<sup>2</sup>). Core temperature and heart-rate were measured continuously (analyzed at five time points), while perceptual measures, cognitive and manual dexterity performance were assessed at various times over an 11-h shift at the start of a 14-day swing. Hydration was assessed (urine specific gravity) pre- and post-shift. Working memory was impaired in summer compared to winter (&#x02212;10%; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.039), however did not change throughout the shift. Processing efficiency was significantly reduced at 12 pm (&#x02212;12%; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.005) and 5 pm (&#x02212;21%; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) compared to 9 am, irrespective of season (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05). Manual dexterity (dominant-hand) improved over the shift (+13%, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.002), but was not different between seasons. Perceived fatigue had no main effect of season or shift. Core temperature, heart-rate, thermal sensation and rating of perceived exertion increased throughout the shift, with only core temperature and thermal sensation showing a seasonal effect (summer: +0.33&#x000b0;C, +18%, respectively; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.002). Notably, 23% of workers in summer and 64% in winter started work significantly dehydrated, with 54% and 64% in summer and winter, respectively, finishing work with significant to serious dehydration. Impairment in working memory in summer combined with high levels of dehydration over the work-shift reinforces the need for workplace education on the importance of hydration and risk of occupation heat stress.</p><p><bold>Abbreviations:</bold> Core temperature: T<sub>c</sub>; Fly-in fly-out: FIFO; Ratings of perceived exertion: RPE; Relative humidity: RH; Urinary specific gravity: USG; Wet bulb globe temperature: WBGT.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><title>KEYWORDS</title><kwd>Heat stress</kwd><kwd>thermal strain</kwd><kwd>cognition</kwd><kwd>core temperature</kwd><kwd>occupational settings</kwd><kwd>dehydration</kwd></kwd-group><support-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>
<institution-wrap><institution>Compass Group Australia</institution></institution-wrap>
</funding-source></award-group><funding-statement>This work was support by Compass Group Australia</funding-statement></funding-group></support-group><counts><fig-count count="4"/><table-count count="2"/><ref-count count="50"/><page-count count="14"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" disp-level="1" id="s0001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Working outdoors during the summer months is a major challenge for many occupations [<xref rid="cit0001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. For instance, ambient temperatures on mine sites during summer in Australia often exceed 30&#x000b0;C wet bulb globe temperature (WBGT) [<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. This, combined with the wearing of required personal protective equipment, can result in a rising core temperature (T<sub>c</sub>), cardiovascular strain, and in some cases, significant dehydration over the course of the working day (also known as a shift [<xref rid="cit0003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]). Excessive thermal strain can lead to physical and cognitive decrements, which in turn can elevate the risk of heat-related illnesses and hence workplace accidents [<xref rid="cit0004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,<xref rid="cit0005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p>To date, only a few studies have assessed the consequences of working in extreme heat in field settings on cognitive function. For instance, Mazloumi et al. [<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] assessed workers in the steel and iron casting industry during the morning (9.00 am&#x02212;12.00 pm) of a shift, whilst working in hot (32.9&#x000b0;C WBGT) and cool (16.7&#x000b0;C WBGT) conditions. A greater number of errors and extended reaction time on cognitive tasks (Stroop test: neutral, congruent and incongruent trials) were reported in the hotter condition. However, as perceptual and physiological responses were not assessed by Mazloumi et al. [<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], it cannot be ascertained if deteriorated cognitive functioning in the heat was primarily due to higher-than-normal dehydration, physiological strain, and/or thermal discomfort. Conversely, Girard et al. [<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] reported that cognitive ability (recognition memory, executive function and working memory) was unaffected by seasonal heat stress (Summer: ~41&#x000b0;C; Winter: ~17&#x000b0;C) in oil-and-gas workers in the Middle-East. However, these authors acknowledged that all testing occurred in a temperature-controlled room (22&#x02013;24&#x000b0;C) and that participants were both living and working in warm conditions for at least 3&#x02013;4&#x02009;months prior to testing, which may have reduced the impact of heat stress on these responses.</p><p>Solar radiation is another factor to be considered when working outdoors as prolonged sun exposure can contribute to increases in T<sub>c</sub> and dehydration, in turn contributing to thermal discomfort and impaired physical work capacity [<xref rid="cit0008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. For instance, 109 construction and agricultural workers performing manual labor in the sun was associated with workers being four times more likely to experience dizziness and twice as likely to suffer heat strain symptoms compared to performing the same work in the shade [<xref rid="cit0009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. By studying the effect of simulated solar radiation on motor-cognitive performance, Piil et al. [<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] found that prolonged exposure to heat generated from simulated solar radiation (in a lab) impaired performance on simple and complex motor tasks, and combined-motor cognitive tasks. There is a need for more in-field research in occupational settings on the effect of solar radiation on cognitive performance.</p><p>Cognitive function can also be impaired by mental and physical fatigue as a result of demanding manual labor and exertion [<xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="cit0012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Indeed, fatigue-related incidents represent one of the greatest risk factors in industrial settings, with ~80% of industrial incidents likely due to human errors [<xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Reportedly, the relative risk of workplace incidents occurring during 10-h and 12-h shifts compared to an 8-h shift increased by +13% and +27%, respectively, regardless of environmental temperature [<xref rid="cit0015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Workplace fatigue, and its negative consequences on cognitive [<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] and physical performance [<xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>], can be detrimental to workers&#x02019; health and safety, as well as to their productivity [<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], if not monitored and carefully managed.</p><p>Fly-in-fly-out (FIFO) workers in the North-West of Australia typically spend one to four weeks on site at a time (described as a &#x0201c;swing&#x0201d;), interspersed with one to two weeks at home in between each swing. Little is known about cognitive and psycho-physiological responses to a typical shift in FIFO mine service workers when traveling from their residential city where ambient conditions are typically cooler than their workplace. Importantly, Donoghue et al. [<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] reported that more cases of heat exhaustion occur in miners during the first shift of their swing. One potential reason may relate to inadequate fluid intake (i.e. state of dehydration) as evidenced by raised serum osmolality, urea creatinine, and urinary specific gravity (USG) [<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. However, Donoghue et al. [<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] did not assess cognitive function, perceived fatigue, thermal discomfort, or physiological variables, rather only determined blood measures and USG once a worker experienced symptoms of heat exhaustion. Further, Piil et al. [<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>] reported that 70% of 139 workers across five industries in Europe commenced work with a USG&#x02265;1.020 (significant to serious dehydration). However, these authors also did not assess the impact that dehydration may have had on cognitive performance in the field.</p><p>Previous research has been restricted to pre- <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> post-shift comparisons and only assessed workers on one working day, not necessarily at the beginning of their swing [<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Little is known about the time-course adjustments in cognitive, manual dexterity and psycho-physiological variables over the duration of a work shift at the beginning of a swing in the heat.</p><p>Therefore, this study investigated cognitive, manual dexterity and psycho-physiological responses in outdoor FIFO mining workers at various time-points over the course of a work shift at the start of their swing during summer compared to winter months. It was hypothesized that cognitive and manual dexterity function would deteriorate over the course of a shift, accompanied by progressive increases in perceptual and physiological responses, with these changes being more pronounced in hotter conditions (summer) compared to temperate conditions (winter).</p></sec><sec disp-level="1" id="s0002"><title>Methods</title><sec disp-level="2" id="s0002-s2001"><title>Participants</title><p>A repeated measures ANOVA power calculation (a&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05, 1-&#x003b2;&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.95) was conducted with G*Power (Version 3.1.9.3) to determine a sample size based on our primary variable: cognitive performance. Based on the existing literature, the average effect size for a difference in cognitive performance, derived from a random movement generated working memory task is <italic toggle="yes">1.6</italic> [<xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. To express our results with 95% confidence, a minimum sample of 12 participants per group was calculated for this study. Therefore, a cohort of 27 male workers (summer: n&#x02009;=&#x02009;13 [grounds staff&#x02009;=&#x02009;3, electricians&#x02009;=&#x02009;2, plumbers&#x02009;=&#x02009;2, carpenters&#x02009;=&#x02009;2, refrigeration technicians&#x02009;=&#x02009;4]; winter: n&#x02009;=&#x02009;14 [grounds staff&#x02009;=&#x02009;4, electricians&#x02009;=&#x02009;2, plumbers&#x02009;=&#x02009;2, carpenters&#x02009;=&#x02009;3, refrigeration technicians&#x02009;=&#x02009;3]) volunteered for this study. Physical characteristics are described in <xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. Participants were FIFO employees working a 14-day on, 7-day at home roster on a mine site village in the Pilbara region, in the North of Western Australia. All participants resided in Perth (and surrounding areas), Western Australia when on their week at home. Participants were informed of details and requirements of the study before providing informed consent. Ethics approval was granted by the Human Research Ethics Office of the University of Western Australia (RA/4/20/4537) [<xref rid="cit0021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. <table-wrap position="float" id="t0001"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>Demographic and anthropometric characteristics of participants recruited for the Summer and Winter seasons.</p></caption><!--OASIS TABLE HERE--><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup><col width="1*" align="left"/><col width="1*" align="char" char="&#x000b1;"/><col width="1*" align="char" char="&#x000b1;"/><col width="1*" align="char" char="&#x000b1;"/><col width="1*" align="char" char="&#x000b1;"/><col width="1*" align="char" char="&#x000b1;"/><col width="1*" align="char" char="&#x000b1;"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left">&#x000a0;</th><th align="center" char="&#x000b1;">Age (y)</th><th align="center" char="&#x000b1;">Height (m)</th><th align="center" char="&#x000b1;">Body mass (kg)</th><th align="center" char="&#x000b1;">BMI (kg/m<sup>2</sup>)</th><th align="center" char="&#x000b1;">Waist to hip</th><th align="center" char="&#x000b1;">Length of employment (y)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Summer <italic toggle="yes">n=13</italic></td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;">46&#x000b1;14</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;">1.75&#x000b1;0.06</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;">88.9&#x000b1;18.3</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;">29.1&#x000b1;5.7</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;">0.94&#x000b1;0.08</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;">2.1&#x000b1;1.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Winter <italic toggle="yes">n=14</italic></td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;">44&#x000b1;12</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;">1.77&#x000b1;0.08</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;">98.4&#x000b1;18.5</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;">31.2&#x000b1;4.1</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;">0.97&#x000b1;0.07</td><td align="char" char="&#x000b1;">1.6&#x000b1;1.7</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tfn0001"><p><italic toggle="yes">Note that no significant differences (p&#x0003e;0.05) were found between summer and winter</italic> populations for any variable assessed.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="s0002-s2002"><title>Study design</title><p>Participants were assessed in respect to cognitive, manual dexterity and psycho-physiological variables over the course of a shift at the start of a swing in hot (March in late summer; average WBGT during the day: ~29.6&#x000ba;C WBGT [range: 18.8&#x02013;35.4&#x000b0;C WBGT) and temperate (July in winter; average WBGT during the day: ~20.2&#x000b0;C WBGT [range: 7.2&#x02013;25.8&#x000b0;C WBGT]) environmental conditions. Three out of 27 participants were tested during both summer and winter months due to workplace attrition rates. Participants underwent a familiarization session on the first shift (day 1) of their 14-day swing after recruitment. They were then tested over the course of a work shift on either day 2 or 3 of this swing. During their 11-h shift, T<sub>c</sub>, heart-rate, thermal sensation, thermal comfort and fatigue, were tested in participants at the start (6&#x02013;7 am), mid-morning (9&#x02013;10 am), mid-point (12&#x02013;1 pm), mid-afternoon (2&#x02013;3 pm) and end of their daily shift (5&#x02013;6 pm). Cognitive function and manual dexterity were assessed at the start, mid-point and end of each daily shift. Participants wore the same clothing for each testing session (steel cap boots, yellow-high visibility long sleeve shirt, trousers, and a hat). Food and fluid consumption for the 11-h shift were recorded in diaries, as to determine total fluid intake (i.e. water, coffee, tea, soft drink).</p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="s0002-s2003"><title>Familiarization session</title><p>Following recruitment, anthropometric measurements, including waist-to-hip ratio and body-mass index were determined (<xref rid="t0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Demographic information regarding age, home address, length of employment, occupation, smoking status, and ethnicity were collected. Participants were introduced to all the physiological equipment, and perceptual scales were carefully explained. They also performed the manual dexterity and cognitive tasks (counting span task) five times each in order to reduce any potential learning effect [<xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="s0002-s2004"><title>Protocol</title><p>Upon arrival to work, participants were fitted with a heart-rate monitor and an Actigraph. Participants provided a urine sample during the 30-min period prior to the start of their shift. Next, they attended a ~25&#x02009;min pre-work meeting where they were assigned their tasks for the day. After this meeting, participants attended baseline testing (described below), which was conducted outdoors in a seated position. The baseline test battery was replicated at mid-shift and end-of-shift time points. Throughout the workday participants conducted a broad range of tasks such as digging, carrying light to heavy loads, driving vehicles, walking, working with tools, gardening and installation of utilities. Workers conducted majority of their tasks (~80%) outdoors throughout their shift.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="s0002-s2005"><title>Testing procedures</title><p>Numerous testing stations were set up, and participants rotated through them in order to assess: (1) manual dexterity and cognitive performance, (2) fatigue, and (3) heart-rate, T<sub>c</sub>, and perceptual measures including thermal sensation, thermal comfort, and rating of perceived exertion. Tests were performed in an invariant order, for a given participant in all their testing sessions. Environmental conditions (ambient temperature, globe temperature, WBGT, and relative humidity) were monitored hourly via the QuesTEMP 32 (TSI Incorporated, USA; accuracy&#x000b1;0.5&#x000b0;C), while wind speed was measured at similar intervals via a digital anemometer (Model: AM-4203&#x02009;HA, Lutron Electronic Enterprise Co., LTD., Taiwan; accuracy&#x000b1;0.1&#x02009;km/h).</p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="s0002-s2006"><title>Physiological responses</title><p>Core temperature was recorded via an ingestible radio-telemetric thermistor using a CorTemp Data Recorder 262K device (CorTemp HQ Inc., Palmetto, USA; accuracy&#x000b1;0.1&#x000b0;C). Capsules were provided to the workers the day before with instructions to swallow it immediately before sleep time. Heart-rate was measured continuously throughout the work-shift via a chest-based monitor (Polar H7, Finland). Participants were fitted with accelerometers (Actigraph GT3&#x000d7;, Pensacola, USA) located on the hip (left side of their belt). Data was recorded continuously (epoch 30&#x02009;Hz) during the work-shift and was downloaded using ActiLife (Actilife, version 6.13.4, Pensacola, USA), with the total number of steps taken over the duration of the shift determined. Participants provided a urine sample for the measurement of USG using a hand-held refractometer (ATAGO Model URC-N<sub>E</sub>, Japan). Values for USG were defined as <italic toggle="yes">&#x0201c;well hydrated&#x0201d;</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;1.010, <italic toggle="yes">&#x0201c;minimal dehydration&#x0201d;</italic> 1.010&#x02013;1.020, <italic toggle="yes">&#x0201c;significant dehydration&#x0201d;</italic> 1.021&#x02013;1.030 and &#x0201c;<italic toggle="yes">serious dehydrated&#x0201d;</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.030 [<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>].</p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="s0002-s2007"><title>Perceptual responses</title><p>Thermal sensation (0 [very cold] to 20 [very hot]) and thermal comfort (0 [very comfortable] to 20 [very uncomfortable]) were recorded using visual analogue scales ranging from green to red and white to black, respectively [<xref rid="cit0010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The corresponding scores were only visible to the researcher, with higher thermal sensation and thermal comfort scores representing <italic toggle="yes">feeling hotter</italic> and <italic toggle="yes">less comfortable</italic>, respectively. Ratings of perceived exertion (RPE; 6 [no exertion at all] to 20 [maximal exertion]) were measured using the Borg scale (16, [<xref rid="cit0023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. The Multidimensional Fatigue Scale was used to quantify physical, mental and general fatigue as well as motivation and activity, and this scale has been previously validated in army recruits and junior doctors [<xref rid="cit0017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Briefly, responses are scored on a scale of 1 (Yes, this is true) to 5 (No, this is not true), with higher scores representing greater levels of fatigue, with each sub-dimension including four questions each.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="s0002-s2008"><title>Manual dexterity and cognitive function</title><p>The Purdue pegboard task (Model 32020, J.A Preston Corporation, New York) was used to assess manual dexterity performance (i.e. concentration, fine motor skills, and hand-eye coordination). Participants had to place as many pegs as possible in a row of holes (one at a time) in 30 s, one hand at a time. Test-retest reliability assessment of the Purdue Pegboard task has been reported by Palejwala et al. [<xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] with typical error scores and coefficients of variation of&#x000b1;0.5 and 3.1% for the dominant hand and of&#x000b1;0.7 and 4.4% for the non-dominant hand. Working memory capacity and processing efficiency was assessed using a modified version of the Counting Span task (Inquisit Lab 6, Millisecond Software, Seattle, USA) which takes~5&#x02009;min to complete [<xref rid="cit0019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. This task requires participants to count the number of green dots on cards containing yellow and green dots. After a set number of cards, participants then have to recall the sequence of count numbers in the order of the presented cards. Set size (i.e. the number of cards) thereby increases from 2 to 7 across task trials. The test terminates when two consecutive sequences are recalled incorrectly. Counting latency (time taken to count the green dots), first recall latency (time taken to recall the first number in the sequence), subsequent recall latency (time taken to recall each subsequent number), recall latency (average time taken to recall all numbers in a trial), number of cards counted correctly (correct counting responses), number of counts recalled correctly (correct recall responses) and counting span were recorded. Individual counting and recall latency times (ms) were aggregated across all trials with the same number of green dots, or within the relevant serial position, respectively. There were fewer responses for later recall positions &#x02013; especially serial positions 6 and 7 &#x02013; because there were fewer trials with these positions (whereas every trial had positions 1 and 2 and many had positions 3&#x02013;5). Data from these positions need to be interpreted with caution. To reduce any possible learning effects, different number sequences were randomly assigned such that participants never received the same sequence of numbers (i.e. dot counts) throughout their testing sessions.</p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="s0002-s2009"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Data are expressed as mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;standard deviation. Statistical analysis was conducted using R studio 1.4.1717. Linear mixed model analysis (obtained using the <italic toggle="yes">lmer</italic> function) was used to compare all dependent variables, with season (summer and winter) and shift (6 am, 9 am, 12 pm, 3 pm and 5 pm) included as fixed effects and random intercepts for participants. P-values were extracted from these mixed models using the <italic toggle="yes">Anova</italic> function in R studio. Where appropriate, post hoc comparisons using <italic toggle="yes">Tukey LSD</italic> were conducted. Statistical significance was accepted at <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05. Cohen&#x02019;s <italic toggle="yes">d</italic> effect sizes with &#x000b1;95% confidence intervals were calculated for primary variables (working memory, processing efficiency manual dexterity and fatigue) between and within seasons, with only moderate (<italic toggle="yes">0.50&#x02013;0.79</italic>) to large (<italic toggle="yes">&#x0003e;0.80</italic>) effect sizes reported. A Pearson&#x02019;s correlation was conducted to determine associations of USG with counting span, correct counting responses and correct recall responses for summer and winter separately. The correlation coefficient was interpreted as either negligible (0&#x02013;0.10), weak (0.10&#x02013;0.39), moderate (0.40&#x02013;0.69), strong (0.70&#x02013;0.89) or very strong (0.90&#x02013;1.00).</p></sec></sec><sec disp-level="1" id="s0003"><title>Results</title><p>Mean ambient temperature (33.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.2 <italic toggle="yes">vs</italic>. 23.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.1&#x000b0;C; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0001), globe temperature (42.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.1 vs. 30.9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.4&#x000b0;C), and WBGT (29.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.8 <italic toggle="yes">vs</italic>. 20.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.3&#x000b0;C; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001), but not relative humidity (38&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;18 <italic toggle="yes">vs</italic>. 39&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;20%; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.907) and wind speed (8.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.9 <italic toggle="yes">vs</italic>. 6.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.2&#x02009;km/h; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.108), were significantly greater in summer (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6) compared to winter (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;5). Maximum average temperature was recorded at 12 pm in summer (37.1&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.4&#x000b0;C) and 3 pm in winter (27.7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.1&#x000b0;C), with minimum average temperature recorded at 6 am in both summer (25.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.9&#x000b0;C) and winter (15.0&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.9&#x000b0;C).</p><sec disp-level="2" id="s0003-s2001"><title>Cognitive performance</title><sec disp-level="3" id="s0003-s2001-s3001"><title>Processing efficiency</title><sec disp-level="4" id="s0003-s2001-s3001-s4001"><title>Counting latency</title><p>There was no significant main effect of season in that counting latency scores for summer (4025&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2015&#x02009;ms) did not differ significantly from scores in winter (3492&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1630&#x02009;ms; p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.123; <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). There was a main effect of shift on counting latency (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001), with mean latency being significantly longer at 6 am (4224&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2141&#x02009;ms) compared to 12 pm (3704&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1742&#x02009;ms; p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.005) and 5 pm (3317&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1482&#x02009;ms; p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001). There was no significant interaction effect for counting latency (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.240). There was a moderate effect size for counting latency where in summer, there was a tendency for it to be longer at 6 am compared to 5 pm (<italic toggle="yes">d&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.60</italic>, [&#x02212;0.23, 1.33]).
<fig position="float" id="f0001" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Mean response latencies in the counting span task over the duration of a shift (start (6 am), middle (12 pm) and end (5 pm)). Recall latencies across serial positions (A &#x00026; B) and counting latencies across number of green dots (C &#x00026; D) in summer (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=13) and winter (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=14) over the course of a shift. Recall latency did not significantly differ (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x0003e;0.05) between seasons or over the course of a shift, however first recall latency (serial position 1) was significantly greater than subsequent recall latency (serial positions 2&#x02013;7; note that data from positions 6 and 7 are noisy). Irrespective of season, mean counting latency was significantly longer at the start of a shift compared to the middle and end of a shift (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x0003c;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="KTMP_A_2208516_F0001_B" content-type="black-white" position="float"/></fig></p></sec><sec disp-level="4" id="s0003-s2001-s3001-s4002"><title>Correct counting responses</title><p>Correct counting responses had a significant main effect for season (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.022), where more correct responses were provided in winter (49&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;9) as opposed to summer (43&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;10; <italic toggle="yes">d&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.62&#x02013;0.83</italic> [&#x02212;0.20, 1.55]; <xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). There was no significant main effect of shift (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.530). No interaction between season and shift was present for counting correct responses (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.384). There was a weak correlation between USG values (decreased) and correct counting responses (increased) in summer (r&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;0.33), whereas both of these variables increased in winter resulting in a weak correlation (r&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.11).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0002"><label>Table 2.</label><caption><p>Processing speed, working memory and manual dexterity results at the start (6 am), middle (12 pm) and end (5 pm) of shift. Counting correct responses, recall correct responses, counting span score out of 7, and manual dexterity performance for dominant and non-dominant hand (out of 25).</p></caption><!--OASIS TABLE HERE--><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup><col width="1*" align="left"/><col width="1*" align="center"/><col width="1*" align="center"/><col width="1*" align="center"/><col width="1*" align="center"/><col width="1*" align="center"/><col width="1*" align="center"/><col width="1*" align="center"/><col width="1*" align="center"/><col width="1*" align="center"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left">&#x000a0;</th><th colspan="3" align="center">Summer (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=13)<hr/></th><th colspan="3" align="center">Winter (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=14)<hr/></th><th colspan="3" align="center">ANOVA <italic toggle="yes">P</italic> - Value<hr/></th></tr><tr><th align="left">&#x000a0;</th><th align="center">6 am</th><th align="center">12 pm</th><th align="center">5 pm</th><th align="center">6 am</th><th align="center">12 pm</th><th align="center">5 pm</th><th align="center">Season</th><th align="center">Shift</th><th align="center">Interaction</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><bold>Processing speed</bold></td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Correct counting responses</td><td align="center">45&#x000b1;9</td><td align="center">41&#x000b1;12</td><td align="center">44&#x000b1;10</td><td align="center">50&#x000b1;7</td><td align="center">50&#x000b1;7</td><td align="center">47&#x000b1;12</td><td align="center">0.022</td><td align="center">0.531</td><td align="center">0.384</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Working memory</bold></td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Correct recall responses</td><td align="center">38&#x000b1;11</td><td align="center">34&#x000b1;12</td><td align="center">39&#x000b1;10</td><td align="center">43&#x000b1;10</td><td align="center">51&#x000b1;8</td><td align="center">40&#x000b1;13</td><td align="center">0.354</td><td align="center">0.120</td><td align="center">0.268</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Counting span</td><td align="center">5.09<break/>&#x000b1;1.65</td><td align="center">4.57<break/>&#x000b1;1.40</td><td align="center">5.32<break/>&#x000b1;0.87</td><td align="center">5.30<break/>&#x000b1;1.45</td><td align="center">5.71<break/>&#x000b1;0.93</td><td align="center">5.41<break/>&#x000b1;1.40</td><td align="center">0.039</td><td align="center">0.752</td><td align="center">0.167</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Manual Dexterity</bold></td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Dominant hand</td><td align="center">15&#x000b1;2</td><td align="center">16&#x000b1;2</td><td align="center">16&#x000b1;3</td><td align="center">15&#x000b1;2</td><td align="center">16&#x000b1;2</td><td align="center">17&#x000b1;2</td><td align="center">0.735</td><td align="center">0.002</td><td align="center">0.618</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Non-dominant hand</td><td align="center">14&#x000b1;3</td><td align="center">15&#x000b1;3</td><td align="center">15&#x000b1;3</td><td align="center">15&#x000b1;2</td><td align="center">16&#x000b1;2</td><td align="center">15&#x000b1;2</td><td align="center">0.343</td><td align="center">0.030</td><td align="center">0.205</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p></sec></sec><sec disp-level="3" id="s0003-s2001-s3002"><title>Working memory</title><sec disp-level="4" id="s0003-s2001-s3002-s4001"><title>Recall latency</title><p>There were no significant main effects of shift (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.181) or season (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.425) on recall latency, nor were there any significant interaction effects between season and shift for recall latency (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.972; <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig">Figure 1</xref>). First recall latency (2446&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;843&#x02009;ms) was significantly longer than subsequent response latencies (1458&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1124&#x02009;ms; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001), irrespective of season.</p></sec><sec disp-level="4" id="s0003-s2001-s3002-s4002"><title>Correct recall responses</title><p>There were no main effects for correct recall responses on shift or season (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). There was no interaction between swing and shift for correct recall responses. There was a moderate effect size for correct recall responses, where at 12 pm in winter there was a tendency for more correct responses to be recalled compared to 12 pm in summer (<italic toggle="yes">d&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.69</italic> [&#x02212;0.14, 1.41). There was a moderate negative correlation between USG values (decreased) and correct recall responses (increased/improved) in summer (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;0.50), whereas both these variables increased in winter (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.27) resulting in a weak correlation.</p></sec><sec disp-level="4" id="s0003-s2001-s3002-s4003"><title>Counting span</title><p>There was a significant main effect of season (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.039) on counting span scores, where scores were significantly lower in summer (4.99&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.35) compared to winter (5.55&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.25). Counting span did not significantly differ throughout the shift (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.752; <xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). There was no significant interaction effect between season and shift (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.167). Effect sizes were found in summer between 12 pm and 5 pm (d&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;0.64 [&#x02212;1.38, 0.19]), and between summer and winter for 12 pm scores (d&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;0.97 [&#x02212;1.68, &#x02212;0.10]). A weak correlation was found between USG values (decreased) and counting span scores (increased) in summer (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;0.34). In winter, there was a weak correlation between these variables, where both increased (<italic toggle="yes">r</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.17).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="s0003-s2002"><title>Manual dexterity</title><p>There were significant main effects of shift for the dominant and non-dominant hand (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.002 and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.030, respectively) but no effect of season (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.735 and <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.343, respectively). For the non-dominant hand, performance was overall significantly better at 12 pm (15&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2) compared to 6 am (14&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.025). Performance with the dominant hand (17&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3) was significantly better at 5 pm compared to 6 am (15&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). There were no significant interaction effects for either the dominant (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.618) or non-dominant (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.205) hand (<xref rid="t0002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). For the dominant hand, effect sizes were found in summer at 6 am to 12 pm and 5 pm (<italic toggle="yes">d=&#x02212;0.50</italic> [&#x02212;1.24, 0.32]) and in winter at 6 am to 12 pm and 5 pm (d&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;1.0 to &#x02212;0.5 [&#x02212;1.70, 0.29]), plus at 12 pm to 5 pm (d&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;0.50 [&#x02212;1.21, 0.29]). For the non-dominant hand, effect sizes were found in winter at 6 am to 12 pm (d&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;0.5 [&#x02212;1.21, 0.29]) and 12 pm to 5 pm (d&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.50 [&#x02212;0.29, 1.21]).</p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="s0003-s2003"><title>Perceived fatigue</title><p>No significant interaction effects were found for any fatigue sub-dimensions (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05) nor were there any main effects between seasons (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.263) or for shift (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.075). A large effect size for physical fatigue showed there was a tendency for fatigue at 5 pm in winter to be greater than summer (d&#x02009;=&#x02009;1 [0.13, 1.72]). For motivation, a large effect size showed that in summer there was a tendency to have more motivation at 6 am compared to in winter at 6 am (<xref rid="f0002" ref-type="fig">Figure 2</xref>) (d&#x02009;=&#x02009;&#x02212;0.78 [&#x02212;1.50, &#x02212;0.1]) .
<fig position="float" id="f0002" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Sub-dimensions of multi-dimensional fatigue scale pre- and post-shift over summer (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;13) and winter (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;14).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="KTMP_A_2208516_F0002_B" content-type="black-white" position="float"/></fig></p></sec><sec disp-level="2" id="s0003-s2004"><title>Physiological and perceptual variables</title><sec disp-level="3" id="s0003-s2004-s3001"><title>Core temperature</title><p>There was a main effect for season that demonstrated a significantly higher T<sub>c</sub> in summer (37.46&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.25&#x000b0;C; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;9) compared to winter (37.34&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.35&#x000b0;C, <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.002; <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;13). A main effect for shift demonstrated that T<sub>c</sub> increased significantly by+0.33&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.34&#x000b0;C (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) over the course of the day. Compared to 6 am (37.18&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.28&#x000b0;C), T<sub>c</sub> was globally higher at 12 pm (37.43&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.25&#x000b0;C; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001), 3 pm (37.58&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.24&#x000b0;C; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) and 5 pm (37.51&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.29&#x000b0;C; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001). There was no significant interaction effect between season and shift for T<sub>c</sub> (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.143). Peak T<sub>c</sub> in summer (37.59&#x000b0;C) occurred at 5pm, and in winter (<xref rid="f0003" ref-type="fig">Figure 3</xref>) (37.61&#x000b0;C) at 3pm.
<fig position="float" id="f0003" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Core temperature (a); heart-rate (b); thermal sensation (c); thermal comfort (d); and ratings of perceived exertion (e) over the course of a shift in summer and winter seasons.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="KTMP_A_2208516_F0003_B" content-type="black-white" position="float"/><attrib><italic toggle="yes">#, different from 6 am, irrespective of season (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05)</italic></attrib><attrib><italic toggle="yes">*, different from previous time point, irrespective of season (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) &#x00026;;, different from 6 am in summer only (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05)</italic>.</attrib></fig></p></sec><sec disp-level="3" id="s0003-s2004-s3002"><title>Heart rate</title><p>Mean heart-rate in summer (89&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;18&#x02009;bpm, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;13) was not significantly different than in winter (81&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;14&#x02009;bpm, <italic toggle="yes">n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;14; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.074). There was a significant main effect for shift (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001), with significantly higher heart-rate values at all time points when compared to 6 am. There was a significant interaction effect between season and shift for heart-rate (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.016). Post hoc analysis revealed significantly lower heart-rate in summer at 6 am (74&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;10&#x02009;bpm) compared to 12 pm (90&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;15&#x02009;bpm; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.029), 3 pm (98&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;19&#x02009;bpm; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) and 5 pm (96&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;23&#x02009;bpm; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.006).</p></sec><sec disp-level="3" id="s0003-s2004-s3003"><title>Thermal sensation</title><p>Mean thermal sensation in summer (11&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2) was significantly greater than in winter (9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). There was a significant interaction effect between season and shift for thermal sensation (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.045), as well as a significant main effect for shift (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). Thermal sensation in summer was significantly greater at 3 pm compared to 6 am (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.019) and 9 am (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.035). In winter, thermal sensation at 6 am was significantly lower than all other time points (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.016). Thermal sensation was also greater at 6 am in summer than in winter (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001).</p></sec><sec disp-level="3" id="s0003-s2004-s3004"><title>Ratings of perceived exertion</title><p>Mean RPE in summer (9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3) did not differ significantly from winter (9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.312). The main effect for shift was significant (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) where, irrespective of season, RPE values were significantly greater at all time points of the shift when compared to 6 am (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;0.001). There was no significant interaction effect between season and shift (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.063).</p></sec><sec disp-level="3" id="s0003-s2004-s3005"><title>Thermal comfort</title><p>Thermal comfort did not differ significantly (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.246) between summer (8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5) and winter (9&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4). A main effect for shift was observed (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.002) with scores for thermal comfort increasing from 6 am (7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6) and 9 am (7&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5) to 3 pm (11&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3) indicating greater discomfort. There was no significant interaction effect for thermal comfort (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.123).</p></sec><sec disp-level="3" id="s0003-s2004-s3006"><title>Urinary specific gravity</title><p>There was no significant interaction effect for USG (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.106), nor were they any main effects for season (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.070) or shift (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.389; <xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4a</xref>). Mean pre-shift USG in winter (1.022&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.004) categorized participants as <italic toggle="yes">&#x0201c;significantly dehydrated&#x0201d;</italic> and in summer (1.016&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.004) as <italic toggle="yes">&#x0201c;minimally dehydrated&#x0201d;</italic>. Post-shift values characterized participants as <italic toggle="yes">&#x0201c;significantly dehydrated&#x0201d;</italic> in winter (1.021&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.007) and <italic toggle="yes">&#x0201c;minimally dehydrated&#x0201d;</italic> in summer (1.020&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.008).
<fig position="float" id="f0004" fig-type="figure"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Urinary specific gravity changes from pre to post shift (a) and mean fluid intake over the course of a shift (b) in summer (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=13) and winter (<italic toggle="yes">n</italic>=14).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="KTMP_A_2208516_F0004_B" content-type="black-white" position="float"/><attrib><italic toggle="yes">*, significantly different between summer and winter (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05).</italic></attrib></fig></p></sec><sec disp-level="3" id="s0003-s2004-s3007"><title>Fluid intake</title><p>Total fluid intake during shift was significantly greater in summer than in winter (3.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.1 <italic toggle="yes">vs</italic>. 3.3&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.2&#x02009;L; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.025). Water intake in summer was significantly greater than in winter (3.2&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.1 <italic toggle="yes">vs</italic>. 2.6&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.3&#x02009;L; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.025; <xref rid="f0004" ref-type="fig">Figure 4b</xref>). There was a significant difference in other fluids consumed between seasons (summer: 0.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.3&#x02009;L; winter: 0.8&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.4&#x02009;L; <italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05).</p></sec><sec disp-level="3" id="s0003-s2004-s3008"><title>Activity</title><p>There was no significant difference (<italic toggle="yes">p</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.710) between the number of steps recorded in summer (7418&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2388) and winter (7725&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3311).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec disp-level="1" id="s0004"><title>Discussion</title><p>This study assessed psycho-physiological, manual dexterity and cognitive responses in FIFO workers during hot (summer) <italic toggle="yes">versus</italic> temperate (winter) environmental conditions over the course of an 11-h shift at the start of a 14-day swing. The main findings were that in summer compared to winter: (i) working memory scores were lower, (ii) perceived fatigue and manual dexterity performance did not differ, and (iii) mean T<sub>c</sub> and thermal sensation were higher. While there were no significant changes in USG values, clinical descriptors [<xref rid="cit0022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>] demonstrated that 23% of workers started work significantly dehydrated in summer with 54% concluding work significantly dehydrated. In winter, 64% started work significantly to seriously dehydrated and 64% finished work significantly dehydrated [<xref rid="cit0024" ref-type="bibr">24&#x02013;28</xref>].</p><p>Exposure to summer heat resulted in globally lower (impaired) counting span scores and correct counting responses compared to winter. These results are consistent with previous literature that reported impaired complex cognitive task performance associated with increases in T<sub>c</sub> due to heat exposure [<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] and accompanying dehydration [<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Notably, mean T<sub>c</sub> in the current study did not reach the same peak levels as those reported by Gaoua et al. [<xref rid="cit0029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] (38.60&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.1&#x000b0;C <italic toggle="yes">vs</italic> 37.46&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.25&#x000b0;C), while Jimenez-Pavon et al. [<xref rid="cit0030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>] only reported losses in body-mass as opposed to USG values, making direct comparison difficult. The difference in counting span score between seasons should however be interpreted with caution as only three participants were the same between seasons, hence the difference between performance may be due to participant differences. This promotes the possibility that changes in performance may at least partially be due to the fact that many of our participants were different people in summer compared to winter. Further, counting span scores did not differ over the course of the work shift, irrespective of season. This finding was unexpected, as previous research has reported increased errors, increased task duration and extended reaction time in cognitive tasks assessed in the heat from pre- to post-shift [<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. One potential explanation could be the lower-than-expected increase in T<sub>c</sub> in the current study over the work shift, however as Mazloumi et al. [<xref rid="cit0006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>] did not measure T<sub>c</sub> this conjecture cannot be confirmed. In addition, while recall latency was not influenced by heat exposure, counting latency performance was slower at the beginning compared to the middle and end of a shift. It is well known that T<sub>c</sub> rises throughout the day due to circadian rhythm, typically increasing by~0.5&#x000b0;C from early morning (4 am) to late afternoon (4&#x02013;6 pm) [<xref rid="cit0031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Counting latency in our study was faster in the afternoon compared to the morning, which was similar to Craig et al. [<xref rid="cit0032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>] where speed and ability to perceive stimuli were faster in the afternoon compared to the morning due to the effects of the circadian rhythm.</p><p>Performance on the manual dexterity task followed a similar pattern to recall and counting latency, whereby performance improved over the course of a shift but was not different between seasons. We hypothesized that performance would be hindered in summer compared to winter. This may not have occurred due to the smaller than expected increase in T<sub>c</sub>. The improved scores over the course of the shift may also be attributed to changes in circadian rhythm, which may have resulted in improved alertness and attention. Valdez [<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] reported that, due to changes in circadian rhythm, attention which is lowest between 7 am to 10 am, improves between 10 am and 2 pm before dipping early afternoon, then increasing again early to late evening (4 pm to 8 pm). These timings coincide with when we assessed our participants and reflect the variations in results. Although the first testing session occurred after a short meeting, participants may still have been feeling tired or lethargic from the early morning start. This may have led to diminished alertness in the morning compared to after a day of active work [<xref rid="cit0033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].</p><p>Dehydration can result in an increased T<sub>c</sub>, poor concentration and the risk of developing heat related illnesses [<xref rid="cit0034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. In our study, results for summer indicated that 9/13 (69%) workers finished their shift with a higher USG compared to pre-shift values, demonstrating increasing dehydration levels occurring over the course of the day. In winter, 8/14 (57%) of workers had a higher USG at the conclusion of their shift in winter. Our findings were consistent with previous research by Polkinghorne et al. [<xref rid="cit0036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] that reported pre-shift hydration status likely influences the outcome of hydration status at the end of a work shift, where 59% of underground miners started work with a USG&#x0003e;1.020 (significantly to seriously dehydrated), with 58% ending their shift with a value&#x0003e;1.020. This places workers at an increased risk of experiencing heat-related injury or illness that is often associated with dehydration in the workplace [<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Dehydration has also been linked to impairment in cognitive performance, which may result in workplace injuries due to deteriorated concentration [<xref rid="cit0037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Nonetheless, no significant association was observed between dehydration and cognitive performance, as evidenced by weak correlations between USG values and cognitive parameters, despite dehydration being more pronounced in winter compared to summer in the current study. Furthermore, a greater decrement was found in cognitive performance in summer when hydration levels were better. Dehydration levels reported for workers in both seasons suggest that fluid intake over the course of the day was inadequate. Pre-shift dehydration levels in winter may have been higher when compared to summer values due to the lack of stimulus to consume fluids (i.e. lower thermal sensation scores at the commencement of the shift) and/or the possible reduced emphasis to drink in cooler conditions [<xref rid="cit0038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>].</p><p>Perceived fatigue in workers did not differ between seasons or from pre- to post-shift. Comparing fatigue scores to studies in the mining industry and general population is anecdotal as most have assessed the accumulation of fatigue over the course of a swing (ranging from 7 to 28&#x02009;days) including the changeover from day shift to night shift [<xref rid="cit0039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="cit0040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>], which did not occur in the current study. Further studies that include an objective measure of fatigue or attention capacity (psychomotor vigilance tasks) and a measure of perceived fatigue and sleep may provide further insight into the consequences of fatigue on cognitive performance [<xref rid="cit0041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="cit0042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Regardless, working an 11-h shift in hot compared to temperate conditions did not result in greater sensations of fatigue in mine service workers.</p><p>Although our participants experienced a significant elevation in T<sub>c</sub> over the course of the 11-hr shift (0.33&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.34&#x000b0;C) during the summer months, while mean T<sub>c</sub> in summer (37.46&#x000b0;C) was significantly higher than in winter (37.34&#x000b0;C), this elevation could be attributed to oscillations in T<sub>c</sub> due to the circadian rhythm. Similar to findings by Girard et al. [<xref rid="cit0007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>] and Peiffer et al. [<xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], average T<sub>c</sub> values recorded in our study were below those generally associated with negative side effects of occupational heat stress and the onset of hyperthermia (T<sub>c</sub>&#x0003e;38&#x000b0;C [<xref rid="cit0043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="cit0044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Interestingly, heart-rate, thermal comfort and RPE did not differ between seasons despite a higher T<sub>c</sub> in summer. This outcome may be a result of T<sub>c</sub> not exceeding 38&#x000b0;C, thus minimizing an autonomic response designed to cool the body (i.e. increased sweating, redistribution of blood to the skin for cooling, and a consequent increase in heart-rate [<xref rid="cit0035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]), suggesting that workers were able to thermoregulate effectively in summer temperatures. Further, the higher fluid intake recorded in summer, compared to winter, would have assisted in improving hydration status [<xref rid="cit0045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] in workers as reflected by lower USG values, which in turn would have aided thermoregulation [<xref rid="cit0046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. The maintenance of T<sub>c</sub> may also have been due to the ability of the workers to self-pace [<xref rid="cit0047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. Although there was no difference in activity/steps determined in summer compared to winter, upper body work was not assessed and this may have resulted in different metabolic loads associated with self-pacing based on season. It has been noted that workers with the ability to self-pace under thermally stressful conditions were able to mitigate physiological strain [<xref rid="cit0048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,<xref rid="cit0049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>].</p><p>There were a number of limitations to this study. Due to the limited number of workers on site, our cohort consisted of a range of occupations that involved varying complexities and time spent on each job (i.e. not strictly quantified), as well as being limited to only males as there were no females in the current workforce. Therefore, it was not possible to measure productivity as work tasks can differ between and even within a specific occupation. Secondly, we did not record alcohol consumption on the night prior to their shift. The amount of alcohol consumed the night prior to work may have contributed to the dehydration status reported for workers prior to their shift commencing. This study only assessed workers on a single day at the start of a swing, future research should aim to assess workers on multiple days over the course of a swing to evaluate the effects of working on consecutive days in these environments. Future studies should include the assessment of skin as a driver of human performance/productivity. Specifically, skin temperature acts as a feedforward signal for behavioral thermoregulation (e.g. self-pacing), which can result in decreases in metabolic heat production associated with lower muscle activation [<xref rid="cit0050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. Lastly, due to attrition rates over time, not all participants were assessed in both seasons, with only three individuals assessed in both winter and summer. This could be one factor that may have accounted for differences in cognitive performance and/or T<sub>c</sub> variability between seasons, although multiple factors such as differences in aerobic fitness levels, acclimatization, or circadian rhythm may have contributed to differences. Again, this is reflective of a field-based study undertaken over the course of nearly a year.</p></sec><sec disp-level="1" id="s0005"><title>Conclusion</title><p>This was the first field-based mining study that assessed cognitive performance, manual dexterity and psycho-physiological responses in FIFO workers at the commencement of their swing in summer and winter. Working memory performance was impaired in summer compared to winter, with a high percentage of workers minimally to significantly dehydrated prior to and at the conclusion of their daily shift during both seasons. The effects of hot ambient conditions on dehydration are important considerations in respect to workers&#x02019; cognitive function, health (increased chance of kidney disease) and workplace safety. This is particularly of issue with environmental temperatures increasing due to climate change and the existence of heat waves. Workers need to remain vigilant to the symptoms of heat stress and partake in a work protocol that allows them to preserve their physiological and cognitive health, especially in the summer months.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>The authors thank all the workers who participated in the research and Compass Group Australia for their support with the project.</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement" disp-level="1" id="s0006"><title>Disclosure statement</title><p>No potential conflict of interest was reported by the authors.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="cit0001"><label>[1]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Caruso</surname>
<given-names>CC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hitchcock</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dick</surname>
<given-names>RB</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Relationship of work schedules to gastrointestinal diagnoses, symptoms, and medication use in auto factory workers</article-title>. <source>Am J Ind Med</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>46</volume>:<fpage>586</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>598</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ajim.20099</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15551368</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0002"><label>[2]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Peiffer</surname>
<given-names>JJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Abbiss</surname>
<given-names>CR.</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Thermal stress in North Western Australian iron ore mining staff</article-title>. <source>Ann Occup Hyg</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>57</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>519</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>527</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/annhyg/mes084</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23184257</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0003"><label>[3]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cheung</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McLellan</surname>
<given-names>TM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tenaglia</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The thermophysiology of uncompensable heat stress</article-title>. <source>Sports Med</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>329</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>359</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/00007256-200029050-00004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10840867</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0004"><label>[4]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Srinivasan</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Maruthy</surname>
<given-names>KN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Venugopal</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Research in occupational heat stress in India: challenges and opportunities</article-title>. <source>Indian J Occup Environ Med</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>20</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>73</fpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/0019-5278.197522</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28194079</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0005"><label>[5]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ramsey</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Burford</surname>
<given-names>CL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Beshir</surname>
<given-names>MY</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Effects of workplace thermal conditions on safe work behavior</article-title>. <source>J Safety Res</source>. <year>1983</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>105</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>114</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0022-4375(83)90021-X</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0006"><label>[6]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mazloumi</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Golbabaei</surname>
<given-names>F</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Khani</surname>
<given-names>SM</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Evaluating effects of heat stress on cognitive function among workers in a hot industry</article-title>. <source>HPP</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>240</fpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5681/hpp.2014.031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25649311</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0007"><label>[7]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Girard</surname>
<given-names>O</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gaoua</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grantham</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Effects of living and working in a hot environment on cognitive function in a quiet and temperature-controlled room: an oil and gas industry study</article-title>. <source>Temperature</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/23328940.2021.1959289</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0008"><label>[8]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Smallcombe</surname>
<given-names>JW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Foster</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hodder</surname>
<given-names>SG</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Quantifying the impact of heat on human physical work capacity; part IV: interactions between work duration and heat stress severity</article-title>. <source>Int J Biometeorol</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>66</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2463</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2476</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00484-022-02370-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36197554</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0009"><label>[9]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ioannou</surname>
<given-names>LG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tsoutsoubi</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Mantzios</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>The impacts of sun exposure on worker physiology and cognition: multi-country evidence and interventions</article-title>. <source>Int J Environ Res Public Health</source>. <year>2021</year>;<volume>18</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<fpage>7698</fpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph18147698</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34300148</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0010"><label>[10]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Piil</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Christiansen</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morris</surname>
<given-names>NB</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Direct exposure of the head to solar heat radiation impairs motor-cognitive performance</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>7812</fpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-64768-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32385322</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0011"><label>[11]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chau</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bourgkard</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bhattacherjee</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Associations of job, living conditions and lifestyle with occupational injury in working population: a population-based study</article-title>. <source>Int Arch Occup Environ Health</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>81</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>379</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>389</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00420-007-0223-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17701420</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0012"><label>[12]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lewis</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wessely</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>The epidemiology of fatigue: more questions than answers</article-title>. <source>J Epidemiol Community Health</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>92</fpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/jech.46.2.92</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1583440</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0013"><label>[13]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chan</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Fatigue: the most critical accident risk in oil and gas construction</article-title>. <source>Constr Manag Econ</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>341</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>353</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/01446193.2010.545993</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0014"><label>[14]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Theophilus</surname>
<given-names>SC</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Esenowo</surname>
<given-names>VN</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Arewa</surname>
<given-names>AO</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Human factors analysis and classification system for the oil and gas industry (HFACS-OGI)</article-title>. <source>Reliab Eng Syst</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>167</volume>:<fpage>168</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>176</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ress.2017.05.036</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0015"><label>[15]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Folkard</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lombardi</surname>
<given-names>DA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Toward a &#x0201c;risk index&#x0201d; to assess work schedules</article-title>. <source>Chronobiol Int</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1063</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1072</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1081/CBI-200036919</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15646251</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0016"><label>[16]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Fan</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>AP</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<article-title>Effects of occupational fatigue on cognitive performance of staff from a train operating company: a field study</article-title>. <source>Front Psychol</source>. <year>2020</year>;<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>558520</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33041922</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0017"><label>[17]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ioannou</surname>
<given-names>LG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Tsoutsoubi</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Samoutis</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Time-motion analysis as a novel approach for evaluating the impact of environmental heat exposure on labor loss in agriculture workers</article-title>. <source>Temperature</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>4</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>330</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>340</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/23328940.2017.1338210</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0018"><label>[18]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Donoghue</surname>
<given-names>AM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Heat exhaustion in a deep underground metalliferous mine</article-title>. <source>Occup Environ Med</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>57</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>165</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>174</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/oem.57.3.165</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10810098</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0019"><label>[19]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Piil</surname>
<given-names>JF</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lundbye-Jensen</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Christiansen</surname>
<given-names>L</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>High prevalence of hypohydration in occupations with heat stress&#x02014;Perspectives for performance in combined cognitive and motor tasks</article-title>. <source>Plos One</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>e0205321</fpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0205321</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30356308</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0020"><label>[20]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>McMorris</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Swain</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Smith</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Heat stress, plasma concentrations of adrenaline, noradrenaline, 5-hydroxytryptamine and cortisol, mood state and cognitive performance</article-title>. <source>Int J Psychophysiol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>61</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>204</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>215</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpsycho.2005.10.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16309771</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0021"><label>[21]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Saldaris</surname>
<given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Landers</surname>
<given-names>GJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Lay</surname>
<given-names>BS</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Enhanced decision making and working memory during exercise in the heat with crushed ice ingestion</article-title>. <source>Int J Sports Physiol Perform</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>15</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>503</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>510</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1123/ijspp.2019-0234</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31711038</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0022"><label>[22]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Casa</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Armstrong</surname>
<given-names>LE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hillman</surname>
<given-names>SK</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>National athletic trainers&#x02019; association position statement: fluid replacement for athletes</article-title>. <source>J Athl Train</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>35</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>212</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16558633</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0023"><label>[23]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Ioannou</surname>
<given-names>LG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Foster</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morris</surname>
<given-names>NB</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Occupational heat strain in outdoor workers: a comprehensive review and meta-analysis</article-title>. <source>Temperature</source>. <year>2022</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>67</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>102</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/23328940.2022.2030634</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0024"><label>[24]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gaoua</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grantham</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Racinais</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Sensory displeasure reduces complex cognitive performance in the heat</article-title>. <source>J Environ Psychol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>32</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>158</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>163</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jenvp.2012.01.002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0025"><label>[25]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Borg</surname>
<given-names>GA</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Psychophysical bases of perceived exertion</article-title>. <source>Med Sci Sports Exerc</source>. <year>1982</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>377</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>381</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1249/00005768-198205000-00012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7154893</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0026"><label>[26]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Smets</surname>
<given-names>EM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Garssen</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bonke</surname>
<given-names>B</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>The Multidimensional Fatigue Inventory (MFI) psychometric qualities of an instrument to assess fatigue</article-title>. <source>J Psychosom Res</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>315</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>325</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0022-3999(94)00125-O</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7636775</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0027"><label>[27]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Palejwala</surname>
<given-names>Z</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wallman</surname>
<given-names>K</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ward</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Effects of a hot ambient operating theatre on manual dexterity, psychological and physiological parameters in staff during a simulated burn surgery</article-title>. <source>Plos One</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>14</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>e0222923</fpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0222923</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31618241</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0028"><label>[28]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Conway</surname>
<given-names>AR</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kane</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bunting</surname>
<given-names>MF</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Working memory span tasks: a methodological review and user&#x02019;s guide</article-title>. <source>Psychon Bull Rev</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>769</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>786</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3758/BF03196772</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16523997</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0029"><label>[29]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Gaoua</surname>
<given-names>N</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Racinais</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Grantham</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Alterations in cognitive performance during passive hyperthermia are task dependent</article-title>. <source>Int J Hyperthermia</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3109/02656736.2010.516305</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21070137</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0030"><label>[30]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Jim&#x000e9;nez-Pav&#x000f3;n</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Romeo</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Cervantes-Borunda</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Effects of a running bout in the heat on cognitive performance</article-title>. <source>J Exerc Sci Fit</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>9</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>58</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>64</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1728-869X(11)60008-7</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0031"><label>[31]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Mackowiak</surname>
<given-names>PA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Wasserman</surname>
<given-names>SS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Levine</surname>
<given-names>MM</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>A critical appraisal of 98.6 F, the upper limit of the normal body temperature, and other legacies of carl reinhold august Wunderlich</article-title>. <source>Jama</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>268</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1578</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1580</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.1992.03490120092034</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1302471</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0032"><label>[32]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Craig</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Davies</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matthews</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Diurnal variation, task characteristics, and vigilance performance</article-title>. <source>Hum Factors</source>. <year>1987</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>675</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>684</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/001872088702900607</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3436623</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0033"><label>[33]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Valdez</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Circadian rhythms in attention</article-title>. <source>Yale J Biol Med</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>92</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>81</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>92</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07420528.2018.1543315</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30923475</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0034"><label>[34]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Armstrong</surname>
<given-names>LE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Ganio</surname>
<given-names>MS</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Casa</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Mild dehydration affects mood in healthy young women</article-title>. <source>J Nutr</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>142</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>382</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>388</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3945/jn.111.142000</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22190027</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0035"><label>[35]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>P&#x000e9;riard</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Racinais</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>Heat stress in sport and exercise</source>. <publisher-loc>Cham, Switzerland</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>; <year>2019</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0036"><label>[36]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Polkinghorne</surname>
<given-names>BG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Gopaldasani</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Furber</surname>
<given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Hydration status of underground miners in a temperate Australian region</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>426</fpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2458-13-426</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23634724</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0037"><label>[37]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Varghese</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hansen</surname>
<given-names>AL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Are workers at risk of occupational injuries due to heat exposure? A comprehensive literature review</article-title>. <source>Saf Sci</source>. <year>2018</year>;<volume>110</volume>:<fpage>380</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>392</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ssci.2018.04.027</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0038"><label>[38]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Greenleaf</surname>
<given-names>JE</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>Environmental issues that influence intake of replacement beverages</source>. <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Academies</publisher-name>; <year>1994</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0039"><label>[39]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Bazazan</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rasoulzadeh</surname>
<given-names>Y</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dianat</surname>
<given-names>I</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Occupational fatigue and mental health complaints among 8-hour shift workers of petrochemical industries in Iran</article-title>. <source>Work</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>62</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>309</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>317</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3233/WOR-192865</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30829641</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0040"><label>[40]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Muller</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Carter</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Williamson</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Epidemiological diagnosis of occupational fatigue in a fly-in&#x02013;fly-out operation of the mineral industry</article-title>. <source>Ann Occup Hyg</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>52</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>63</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/annhyg/mem058</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18065400</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0041"><label>[41]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Legault</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Clement</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Kenny</surname>
<given-names>GP</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Cognitive consequences of sleep deprivation, shiftwork, and heat exposure for underground miners</article-title>. <source>Appl Ergon</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>58</volume>:<fpage>144</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>150</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apergo.2016.06.007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27633207</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0042"><label>[42]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Riethmeister</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Matthews</surname>
<given-names>RW</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Dawson</surname>
<given-names>D</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Time-of-day and days-on-shift predict increased fatigue over two-week offshore day-shifts</article-title>. <source>Appl Ergon</source>. <year>2019</year>;<volume>78</volume>:<fpage>157</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>163</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.apergo.2019.02.010</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31046947</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0043"><label>[43]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>International Organization for Standardization</collab></person-group>. <source>Ergonomics of the thermal environment: analytical determination and interpretation of heat stress using calculation of the predicted heat</source>. <publisher-loc>Strain</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>ISO</publisher-name>; <year>2004</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0044"><label>[44]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Faulds</surname>
<given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Meekings</surname>
<given-names>T</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Temperature management in critically ill patients continuing education in anaesthesia</article-title>. <source>Critical Care &#x00026; Pain</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>13</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>75</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>79</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bjaceaccp/mks063</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0045"><label>[45]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Popkin</surname>
<given-names>BM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>D&#x02019;Anci</surname>
<given-names>KE</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Rosenberg</surname>
<given-names>IH</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Water, hydration, and health</article-title>. <source>Nutr Rev</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>68</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>439</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>458</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1753-4887.2010.00304.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20646222</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0046"><label>[46]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hardy</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Physiology of temperature regulation</article-title>. <source>Physiol Rev</source>. <year>1961</year>;<volume>41</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>521</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>606</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/physrev.1961.41.3.521</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13711528</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0047"><label>[47]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bates</surname>
<given-names>GP</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schneider</surname>
<given-names>JD</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Self-pacing as a protective mechanism against the effects of heat stress</article-title>. <source>Ann Occup Hyg</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>55</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>548</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>555</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/annhyg/mer012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21474543</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0048"><label>[48]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Brake</surname>
<given-names>R</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bates</surname>
<given-names>G</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>A valid method for comparing rational and empirical heat stress indices</article-title>. <source>Ann Occup Hyg</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>46</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>165</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>174</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/annhyg/mef030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12074026</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0049"><label>[49]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Miller</surname>
<given-names>V</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bates</surname>
<given-names>GP</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <article-title>Hydration of outdoor workers in north-west Australia</article-title>. <source>J Occup Health Saf Aust NZ</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>79</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="cit0050"><label>[50]</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Schlader</surname>
<given-names>ZJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Raman</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Morton</surname>
<given-names>RH</given-names></string-name>, et al</person-group>. <article-title>Exercise modality modulates body temperature regulation during exercise in uncompensable heat stress</article-title>. <source>Eur J Appl Physiol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>111</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>757</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>766</lpage>. DOI:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00421-010-1692-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20978782</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
