<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="review-article"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Cureus</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="issn">2168-8184</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Cureus</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2168-8184</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cureus</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Palo Alto (CA)</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38125211</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC10732328</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7759/cureus.49119</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Dentistry</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Oral Medicine</subject></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Orthopedics</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Role of Low Mineral Water Consumption in Reducing the Mineral Density of Bones and Teeth: A Narrative Review</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Muacevic</surname><given-names>Alexander</given-names></name></contrib><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>John R</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>V</surname><given-names>Kamalapriya</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Mani</surname><given-names>Rekha</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-2" ref-type="aff">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Venkatesh</surname><given-names>Vijay</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kunhikannan</surname><given-names>Seetha</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-3" ref-type="aff">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ganesh V</surname><given-names>Shyam</given-names></name><xref rid="aff-1" ref-type="aff">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff-1">
<label>1</label>
Conservative Dentistry and Endodontics, SRM Kattankulathur Dental College and Hospital, Chennai, IND </aff><aff id="aff-2">
<label>2</label>
Endodontics, SRM Kattankulathur Dental College and Hospital, Chennai, IND </aff><aff id="aff-3">
<label>3</label>
Dentistry, ICON Clinical Research Organisation, Chennai, IND </aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
Rekha Mani <email>rekham@srmist.edu.in</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>20</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="collection" publication-format="electronic"><month>11</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><issue>11</issue><elocation-id>e49119</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2023, V et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>V et al.</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License CC-BY 4.0., which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://www.cureus.com/articles/204690-the-role-of-low-mineral-water-consumption-in-reducing-the-mineral-density-of-bones-and-teeth-a-narrative-review">This article is available from https://www.cureus.com/articles/204690-the-role-of-low-mineral-water-consumption-in-reducing-the-mineral-density-of-bones-and-teeth-a-narrative-review</self-uri><abstract><p>Low mineral water has gained increasing attention due to its potential health implications concerning bone mineral density (BMD) and dental health. Reverse osmosis (RO) systems to purify water&#x000a0;are in use extensively, and these systems, in addition to removing&#x000a0;impurities from water,&#x000a0;also remove&#x000a0;92-99% of beneficial minerals like calcium, lead, fluoride, magnesium, and iron. These minerals&#x000a0;are essential for maintaining optimal&#x000a0;mineral density of teeth and bones, thereby preserving bone and teeth health. Most of these mineral components are physically larger than water molecules and are trapped by the semi-permeable membrane of RO filters when drinking water is filtered through it. The resultant water is of very poor mineral content, and studies have shown that this water, when consumed, can absorb minerals from the body and eliminate the same through urine. The combined synergistic effect of consumption of low mineral water along with minerals being excreted has been shown to cause demineralization of bones and teeth, increasing the risk of osteoporosis and dental caries. This review tries to address the ill effects of consuming low mineral water along with preventive strategies to overcome its much-concealed adverse effects.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>water</kwd><kwd>dental caries</kwd><kwd>bone mineral density</kwd><kwd>low mineral water</kwd><kwd>reverse osmosis</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction and background</title><p>Safe drinking water is vitally important for healthy living. Water that is meant for human consumption, in other words, potable water, needs to be pathogen-free, devoid of hazardous chemicals, tasty, colourless, and odourless, and therefore suitable for drinking. The traditional ways of water purification like boiling, distillation, and filtration have been replaced by advanced methods like nano-filtration and ultra-filtration, adsorption and ion exchange, chemical and ultraviolet disinfection, and reverse osmosis (RO) [<xref rid="REF1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. RO water purification technology has spread its tentacles worldwide in recent years. RO filters work by forcing water molecules across a thick RO membrane to separate the contaminants. All suspended particles, including organic waste, colloids, and bacterial and viral contaminants, are removed during the RO process, in addition to salts in the ionic state. Therefore, RO systems have been extensively used to improve the quality of the water for drinking and also guarantee a water supply in an emergency [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].</p><p>While&#x000a0;some&#x000a0;homes&#x000a0;possess RO&#x000a0;systems,&#x000a0;others&#x000a0;rely&#x000a0;on&#x000a0;commercial&#x000a0;enterprises.&#x000a0;Twenty-litre bottles of bottled water&#x000a0;are commonly used by homes for drinking and cooking.&#x000a0;People think drinking bottled or RO water is safe; however,&#x000a0;research has shown that the RO membrane virtually eliminates the water's mineral content. In India, various kinds of membranes are utilized. Membranes made of cellulose acetate, polyamide, and composite are frequently used [<xref rid="REF3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. As the global market&#x000a0;for RO devices&#x000a0;is expanding, there is still a dearth of scientific data on the ill effects of&#x000a0;drinking RO-purified water [<xref rid="REF4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Therefore, the aim of this review is to assess the effects&#x000a0;of consuming RO-purified low mineral water on bone&#x000a0;and teeth&#x000a0;health.</p></sec><sec sec-type="review"><title>Review</title><p>The working mechanism of RO filters</p><p>Through the use of an RO membrane, RO technology isolates the solvent, typically water, from the solution. External pressure is required to balance&#x000a0;the&#x000a0;water's osmotic pressure. The process is permeation rather than spontaneous infiltration. When an external pressure is applied that is less than the solution's natural osmotic pressure, the solvent moves from the diluted solution to the concentrated solution. This process&#x000a0;will successfully separate the solute and eliminate pollutants such as salt, colloid, bacteria, viruses, organic waste, and others [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. One of the world's most cutting-edge membrane separation&#x000a0;technologies is RO.&#x000a0;RO separation has a one-time desalination rate of over 95% and can remove organic materials&#x000a0;with a molecular weight of more than 150; in addition, it also removes bacteria&#x000a0;and viruses&#x000a0;from water to produce aseptic water.&#x000a0;The workflow of&#x000a0;RO&#x000a0;systems includes tap water, mechanical filters, activated carbon filters, softeners, intermediate water tanks, booster pumps, security filters, RO high-pressure pumps, ozone generators, and 0.2-micron fine filters [<xref rid="REF2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>].</p><p>RO technology eliminates most of the ions from the water, especially divalent cations and anions [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. There is abundant proof that fluoride was significantly reduced by the use of water purification systems based on RO technology. The systems based on RO, according to a study by Prabhakar et al., exhibited the largest reduction in fluoride levels, with the majority of filters completely removing fluoride from the water samples [<xref rid="REF6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. The semipermeable membrane used in RO has been shown to eliminate&#x000a0;94-98% of the calcium and magnesium. The calcium content of drinking water is therefore less than 6 mg/L in nations that use RO systems for purifying water.</p><p>In other words,&#x000a0;residential&#x000a0;filters&#x000a0;or&#x000a0;RO&#x000a0;systems&#x000a0;used&#x000a0;to&#x000a0;treat&#x000a0;drinking&#x000a0;water&#x000a0;virtually eliminate calcium content [<xref rid="REF7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Since demineralized water only contains minimal amounts of dissolved minerals like calcium and magnesium, which are the primary causes of hardness, the water produced can be&#x000a0;regarded as an extreme form of low-mineral or soft water that has not been remineralized&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. A study conducted in 1995&#x000a0;revealed that the fluoride levels were less than 0.3 ppm in 78% of the bottled water sold in Iowa City. Only 10% of samples were within the recommended optimal range of 0.7 to 1.2 ppm fluoride or exceeded it [<xref rid="REF8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. The filtration efficacy&#x000a0;of essential minerals by RO systems&#x000a0;is described in Table <xref rid="TAB1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="TAB1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Average purification efficacy of reverse osmosis (RO) systems</title><p>Adapted from&#x000a0;[<xref rid="REF9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Component</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Efficacy (%)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Calcium</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fluoride</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Magnesium</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">96</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Phosphate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sodium</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sulphate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">94</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Iron</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td></tr><tr style="background-color:#ccc"><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zinc</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Effects of drinking RO water on teeth</p><p>The effects of drinking RO&#x000a0;water on dental health are a subject of interest, particularly in&#x000a0;relation to calcium (Ca), magnesium (Mg), and fluoride (F) concentrations. Drinking water with appropriate&#x000a0;levels of Ca, Mg, and F creates an environment conducive to remineralization in oral tissues, promoting dental&#x000a0;health [<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. A study conducted by Razvan et al. [<xref rid="REF10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>] suggests that drinking water with Ca and Mg&#x000a0;levels below recommended standards may not adequately support tooth remineralization. Furthermore, studies have indicated that the presence of calcium in drinking water can decrease the development of dental caries, as measured by the decayed, missing, and filled tooth surfaces (DMF-S). According to one study, calcium-containing water increases remineralization and decreases demineralization in early caries lesions [<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p><p>This effect may be due to the relationship between calcium and fluoride levels in dental plaque, where calcium can infiltrate and provide additional sites for fluoride binding. Notably, drinking water should contain a higher proportion of free calcium compared to saliva, as saliva contains various binding agents, such as bicarbonate, proteins, and phosphorus, all contributing to significant calcium binding. Supplying water with 0.75 mg/L of fluoride and 90 mg/L of calcium, which yields a free calcium concentration over four times higher than that in saliva, can significantly reduce DMF-S while maintaining moderate concentrations of both ions [<xref rid="REF11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>].</p><p>Fluoride deficiency has been linked to an increased risk of tooth decay and a reduction in the formation of molar crowns within the dentine, which is dose-dependent. Fluoride's influence on the odontoblastic process, associated with dentine production, is facilitated through its interaction with the tubular structure and the metabolic activity of dentine. According to a study by Arvin et al., 100 mg/L of calcium has a protective effect equivalent to 0.64 mg/L of fluoride. Alternatively, the concept of calcium fluorite (CaF2) saturation is used to assess the combined impact of calcium and fluoride. Reducing calcium levels from 120 mg/L to 33 mg/L may increase the incidence of caries by as much as 46% [<xref rid="REF5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>].</p><p>An investigation conducted among school children in China found that low mineral water was associated with a slightly higher prevalence and incidence of caries on pit and fissure surfaces but slightly lower rates for smooth surfaces. This was the first promising epidemiological study to establish that drinking low mineral water increases the risk of dental caries and hypoevolutism among children in mixed dentition. The study further reported stunting among children caused by RO water consumption in their growing age [<xref rid="REF12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p><p>Effect of drinking RO water on bones</p><p>Bone modelling, the process responsible for shaping and maintaining bone structure in childhood and adolescence, heavily depends on essential nutrients like calcium (Ca). However, Ca serves multiple crucial physiological functions beyond bone mineralization. The body employs a sophisticated regulatory system involving various tissues to oversee both bone formation and resorption, along with the absorption of Ca in the intestines. This complex regulation system is necessary to keep serum Ca concentrations within a narrow range. The concentration of Ca in the bloodstream also influences the secretion of cholecalciferol, commonly known as vitamin D, by the kidneys. A surge in serum Ca levels&#x000a0;often resulting from excessive bone resorption can trigger a reduction in cholecalciferol levels. Cholecalciferol is well-established for its positive effects on bone health. As a result, continuous use of very low mineral drinking water might speed up bone resorption since it reduces cholecalciferol secretion, aggravating calcium insufficiency [<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>-<xref rid="REF15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].</p><p>Furthermore, bone mineral density (BMD) is a key indicator of bone health and susceptibility to fractures. Paradoxically, drinking water with extremely low mineral content, such as RO water, can substantially decrease overall mineral intake, potentially raising health concerns, including the risk of osteopenia. To investigate the long-term effects of consuming very low mineral drinking water on bone modelling in children, Huang et al. conducted a comprehensive retrospective cohort study spanning four years. While RO water was not the sole water source in the study, it was discovered that using water with very low mineral content significantly reduced children&#x02019;s daily mineral intake [<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p><p>This reduction in daily mineral intake had several noteworthy consequences. Due to a drop in daily magnesium intake and a decrease in the consumption of bicarbonate from water, serum magnesium (Mg) concentrations decreased. Additionally, the lack of calcium (Ca) in drinking water may make Ca deficiency worse. It is interesting to note that youngsters who drank water with very low mineral content had higher serum Ca concentrations. This rise revealed an antagonistic link between dietary calcium consumption and total daily calcium intake. Consequently, the study&#x02019;s&#x000a0;findings suggest that in cases of inadequate Ca intake through drinking water, the body&#x02019;s regulatory&#x000a0;mechanisms adapt to maintain serum Ca balance [<xref rid="REF13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>].</p><p>Intriguingly, a study conducted by Grobler et al. unveiled an association between higher BMD&#x000a0;values and elevated fluoride levels in drinking water. This suggests that as children progress in age, the minimal fluoride content in their water supply might not suffice to support increased bone density, potentially resulting in declining bone density over time [<xref rid="REF16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>].</p><p>Other health effects of drinking low mineral water</p><p>Low mineral water can lead to several health effects beyond its impact on bone health. Water with low mineral content can disrupt the body&#x02019;s ability to maintain balance, affecting both water and mineral metabolism. This disruption can result in increased excretion of critical intracellular and extracellular ions from body fluids, leading to imbalances, changes in body water levels, and alterations in the functional activity of hormones related to water management. This may manifest as enhanced diuresis or increased urine production. Notably, low mineral water significantly increases the body&#x02019;s ability to excrete sodium, potassium, chloride, calcium, and magnesium ions, along with changes in body water volume and serum sodium concentrations (typically around a 20% increase, on average) [<xref rid="REF12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].</p><p>Remineralization of RO water</p><p>To counteract the negative consequences of drinking low mineral water, the idea of remineralizing RO water has been proposed. Better hydration, greater nutritional absorption, healthy digestion, remineralization of teeth and bones, and a stronger immune system are the primary health benefits. Because RO water has a significantly lower mineral concentration than drinking water, detrimental effects on the flavour of the RO water are possible [<xref rid="REF17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].</p><p>The most popular technique for remineralizing RO permeate involves the permeate's liquid-solid interaction with a medium based on calcium carbonate and the addition of CO2. This process requires the procurement of a solid medium, together with the related difficulties of transportation and resource extraction [<xref rid="REF18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. To increase water hardness and chemical stability, RO permeate remineralization is necessary to change the concentrations of calcium and magnesium carbonate/bicarbonate. Recently, a hybrid electrodialysis method using bipolar membranes and ion exchange resins was created for RO permeate remineralization. In the investigated remineralization process, RO permeate remineralization uses a portion of the cation exchange resin regenerant stream, which is rich in primarily divalent ions [<xref rid="REF19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>].</p><p>Another strategy is to employ CO2 injection in conjunction with lime slurry, although this causes turbidity in the water and necessitates producing lime slurry on-site in a particular tank. Sodium bicarbonate and calcium sulphate can also be added to achieve remineralization; however, this approach is constrained particularly by the low solubility of calcium sulphate. Utilizing calcium bicarbonate or calcium chloride is another strategy that could be used. Other methods of remineralization include&#x000a0;adding a mineral filter to an RO system to remineralize RO water, an alkaline water pitcher with a filter that restores essential minerals to drinking water, and the addition of trace mineral drops [<xref rid="REF18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusions</title><p>Although RO water purification systems provide the safest drinking water to the human community, they also pose several adverse effects on systemic and oral health. The natural ability of the tooth to remineralize is depreciated due to the chronic consumption of RO water, which leads to the deterioration of incipient carious lesions and accelerates the development of cavitated carious lesions. RO water consumption may also be related to a declining BMD with an increased risk of osteoporosis and fracture. This is indeed alarming and is of colossal significance due to the generalized nature and chronicity of the issue, which tremendously affects human well-being.</p><p>An alternative proficient technology with remineralization of the RO water in moderate levels to meet the required daily amount of each micro and macro-mineral must be adapted to reap the benefits of the drinking water and to prevent adverse effects and ailments caused by the aforementioned. Knowledge about the mineral content of drinking water is essential to both the public and healthcare professionals. Future research in this regard can help us to overcome the health hazards of consuming low mineral water as well as develop new technologies that can provide safe drinking water while retaining its minerals.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group content-type="other"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Concept and design:</bold>&#x000a0; Rekha Mani, Kamalapriya V, Vijay Venkatesh, Shyam Ganesh V</p><p><bold>Acquisition, analysis, or interpretation of data:</bold>&#x000a0; Rekha Mani, Kamalapriya V, Seetha Kunhikannan</p><p><bold>Drafting of the manuscript:</bold>&#x000a0; Rekha Mani, Kamalapriya V, Vijay Venkatesh, Shyam Ganesh V, Seetha Kunhikannan</p><p><bold>Critical review of the manuscript for important intellectual content:</bold>&#x000a0; Rekha Mani, Kamalapriya V, Vijay Venkatesh, Shyam Ganesh V, Seetha Kunhikannan</p><p><bold>Supervision:</bold>&#x000a0; Rekha Mani, Kamalapriya V, Vijay Venkatesh, Shyam Ganesh V, Seetha Kunhikannan</p></fn></fn-group><notes><fn-group content-type="competing-interests"><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn></fn-group></notes><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="REF1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Guidance from secondary data for remineralization of RO water</article-title><source>J Indian Water Works Assoc</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Srivastava</surname><given-names>DN</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Daga</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><volume>42</volume><year>2010</year><uri xlink:href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Divesh-Srivastava-2/publication/268278718_Guidance_from_secondary_data_for_remineralization_of_RO_water/links/561e73ef08ae50795afefc4c/Guidance-from-secondary-data-for-remineralization-of-RO-water.pdf">https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Divesh-Srivastava-2/publication/268278718_Guidance_from_secondary_data_for_remineralization_of_RO_water/links/561e73ef08ae50795afefc4c/Guidance-from-secondary-data-for-remineralization-of-RO-water.pdf</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><article-title>Application of reverse osmosis in purifying drinking water</article-title><source>2018 4th International Conference on Energy Materials and Environment Engineering</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group><publisher-loc>Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia</publisher-loc><publisher-name>ICEMEE</publisher-name><year>2018</year><uri xlink:href="https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2018E3SWC..3801037J/abstract">https://ui.adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/2018E3SWC..3801037J/abstract</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Reverse osmosis units in groundwater based public water supply system in rural eastern Karnataka, India: an analysis</article-title><source>Curr Sci</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Pandit</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Khatei</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>1493</fpage><lpage>1498</lpage><volume>123</volume><year>2022</year><uri xlink:href="https://www.currentscience.ac.in/Volumes/123/12/1493.pdf">https://www.currentscience.ac.in/Volumes/123/12/1493.pdf</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Life cycle assessment of three safe drinking-water options in India: boiled water, bottled water, and water purified with a domestic reverse-osmosis device</article-title><source>Sustainability</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Garcia-Suarez</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kulak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>King</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chatterton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Saksena</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>6233</fpage><volume>11</volume><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Caries affected by calcium and fluoride in drinking water and family income</article-title><source>J Water Health</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Arvin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bardow</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spliid</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><volume>16</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29424718</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>A study of the effect of home water filtration systems on fluoride content of drinking water in Johor</article-title><source>Malays Dent J</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Loh</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Yaacob</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Andan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Omar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Jamaludin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>8</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><volume>1</volume><year>2011</year><uri xlink:href="https://web.mda.org.my/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/2011-AStudy.pdf">https://web.mda.org.my/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/2011-AStudy.pdf</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The calcium concentration of public drinking waters and bottled mineral waters in Spain and its contribution to satisfying nutritional needs</article-title><source>Nutr Hosp</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Vitoria</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Maraver</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ferreira-P&#x000ea;go</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Armijo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moreno Aznar</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Salas-Salvad&#x000f3;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>188</fpage><lpage>199</lpage><volume>30</volume><year>2014</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25137280</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><article-title>Health risks from drinking demineralised water</article-title><source>Nutrients in Drinking Water</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Kozisek</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>148</fpage><lpage>163</lpage><publisher-loc>Geneva, Switzerland</publisher-loc><publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name><year>2005</year><uri xlink:href="https://aguaenmexico.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/WHO-HEALTH-RISKS-FROM-DRINKING-DEMINERALISED-WATER.pdf">https://aguaenmexico.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/WHO-HEALTH-RISKS-FROM-DRINKING-DEMINERALISED-WATER.pdf</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Purification of contaminated water with reverse osmosis: effective solution of providing clean water for human needs in developing countries</article-title><source>Int J Emerging Technol Adv Eng</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Wimalawansa</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><volume>3</volume><year>2013</year><uri xlink:href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/284804889">https://www.researchgate.net/publication/284804889</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The correlation between the mineral drinking water composition and the relevance of dentine in health - a pilot study</article-title><source>Pak J Med Sci</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Razvan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Popa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Incze</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cristina</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>349</fpage><lpage>354</lpage><volume>36</volume><year>2020</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32292432</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Optimal drinking water composition for caries control in populations</article-title><source>J Dent Res</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Bruvo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ekstrand</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Arvin</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Spliid</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kirkeby</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bardow</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>340</fpage><lpage>343</lpage><volume>87</volume><year>2008</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18362315</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Low-mineral direct drinking water in school may retard height growth and increase dental caries in schoolchildren in China</article-title><source>Environ Int</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>104</fpage><lpage>109</lpage><volume>115</volume><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29554484</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Consumption of very low mineral water is associated with lower bone mineral content in children</article-title><source>J Nutr</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Tan</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>
<etal/>
</person-group><fpage>1994</fpage><lpage>2000</lpage><volume>149</volume><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31373351</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Long-term 1,25(OH)2 vitamin D therapy increases bone mineral density in osteopenic women. Comparison with the effect of plain vitamin D</article-title><source>Aging Clin Exp Res</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Zofkova</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>472</fpage><lpage>477</lpage><volume>19</volume><year>2007</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18172369</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>ED-71, a new active vitamin D3, increases bone mineral density regardless of serum 25(OH)D levels in osteoporotic subjects</article-title><source>J Steroid Biochem Mol Biol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kubodera</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>584</fpage><lpage>586</lpage><volume>103</volume><year>2007</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17298881</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>The relationships between two different drinking water fluoride levels, dental fluorosis and bone mineral density of children</article-title><source>Open Dent J</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Grobler</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Louw</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Chikte</surname><given-names>UM</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Rossouw</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van W Kotze</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><volume>3</volume><year>2009</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19444344</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Sensory quality of drinking water produced by reverse osmosis membrane filtration followed by remineralisation</article-title><source>Water Res</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Vingerhoeds</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Nijenhuis-de Vries</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Ruepert</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van der Laan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Bredie</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kremer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><volume>94</volume><year>2016</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26925543</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="REF18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Surface water RO permeate remineralization through minerals recovery from brines</article-title><source>Desalination</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Philibert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Filingeri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Natalello</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Moe</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Filloux</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Cipollina</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>115725</fpage><volume>531</volume><year>2022</year><uri xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.desal.2022.115725">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.desal.2022.115725</uri></element-citation></ref><ref id="REF19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Ion exchange resin - bipolar membrane electrodialysis hybrid process for reverse osmosis permeate remineralization: cation exchange resins equilibria and kinetics</article-title><source>Sep Purif Technol</source><person-group>
<name><surname>Abusultan</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Sainio</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>
<name><surname>Kemperman</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>
<name><surname>van der Meer</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name>
</person-group><fpage>123798</fpage><volume>317</volume><year>2023</year><uri xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.seppur.2023.123798">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.seppur.2023.123798</uri></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
