<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">World J Surg Oncol</journal-id><journal-title>World Journal of Surgical Oncology</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1477-7819</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15350201</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC521083</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1477-7819-2-30</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1477-7819-2-30</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Technical Innovations</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Single group study to evaluate the feasibility and complications of radiofrequency ablation and usefulness of post treatment position emission tomography in lung tumours</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>Shijun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>shijun@uic.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Rongcheng</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>rongcheng@fimmu.edu.cn</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>Wangjun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>wangjun@fimmu.edu.cn</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Hubing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>hubin@fimmu.edu.cn</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Xuelin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>xuelin@fimmu.edu.cn</email></contrib><contrib id="A6" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Meng</surname><given-names>Yuru</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>ruthmwk@yahoo.com</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Oncology, Nanfang Hospital, Guangzhou, P.R.China, 510515</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>PET Center, Nanfang Hospital, Guangzhou, P.R.China, 510515</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Medical Image Center, Nanfang Hospital, Guangzhou, P.R.China, 510515</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>6</day><month>9</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wjso.com/content/2/1/30"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>5</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>6</day><month>9</month><year>2004</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2004 Kang et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2004</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Kang et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Kang
               Shijun
               
               shijun@uic.edu
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Single group study to evaluate the feasibility and complications of radiofrequency ablation and usefulness of post treatment position emission tomography in lung tumours
         </dc:title><dc:date>2004</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>World Journal of Surgical Oncology 2(1): 30-. (2004)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1477-7819(2004)2:1&#x0003c;30&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1477-7819</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>There is genuine need to develop interventional treatment options for management of lung tumors. Radiofrequency ablation (RFA) is one such alternative being promoted to treat lung tumors recently. Larger studies should help define RFA's further development. Furthermore fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography (PET) has been reported to be an accurate indicator of treatment response in variety of tumors. This study focuses on the evaluating the feasibility of RFA and usefulness of PET scan in lung tumors after RFA procedure.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Patients and methods</title><p>Between November 1999 and May 2002, 50 patients with primary or metastasis pulmonary tumors underwent RFA procedure. The electrode was guided to the target areas using computerized tomography (CT). Tumors smaller than 3.5 cm were given single RFA, while tumors larger than 3.5 cm received RFA to multiple sites. Maximum 4 lesions or 6 target areas were treated during one operating procedure. Whole body and/or lung PET images were acquired; identical site CT images and chest X-ray were taken 1 week before and after RFA.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Of the 50 patients, 17 had single lesions while rest had multiple lesions. Tumors smaller than 3.5 cm were completely dissipated after RFA. In tumors larger than 3.5 cm, the part within 3.5 cm diameter dissipated. While CT showed that tumor image became larger 1 to 2 weeks after RFA procedure. PET demonstrated tumor destruction in 70% cases, compared to 38% in CT.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The present study shows RFA to be safe and effective treatment option for lung tumors. PET is superior to CT in evaluation the effectiveness of RFA treatment shortly after the procedure.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Lung cancer continues to be the leading cause of cancer deaths in United States [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. The overall prognosis of lung cancer is still dismal despite all current early detection and treatment efforts. Only about 20&#x02013;25% of lung cancers can potentially be cured by surgery. The majority of patients presents with locally advanced or metastatic disease, and treatments essentially rely on external beam irradiation, chemotherapy or a combination of both [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Thus other interventional palliative treatment options have been developed for these lesions.</p><p>Radiofrequency ablation (RFA), is an imaging-guided percutaneous ablative procedure, that has been suggested to be an effective treatment option for patients with non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) and metastatic disease who are not suitable candidates for surgery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Guided by computed tomography (CT), physicians are able to localize the tumor and determine the optimal approach. During RFA, current passing through tissue from the active electrode leads to ion agitation and frictional heat generation. This leads to irreparable cellular damage and coagulation necrosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Recently a number of studies reported its application in malignant lung tumours. Accurate assessment of treatment response remains one of the major problems.</p><p>PET has been reported to be an accurate indicator of treatment response in variety of tumors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. However, its use has been limited to evaluating disease stage in lung tumors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. PET imaging, provides proliferation and metabolism information, is sensitive and specific to diagnose malignant lesions from benign. Coleman and colleagues has provided substantial information in evaluating the role of PET in management of lung cancers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. In this report we focus on evaluating the feasibility of RFA, its complication and on evaluating the role of PET on RFA response in lung tumors.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Patients and methods</title><p>Between November 1999 and May 2002, 50 patients with either primary or metastatic lung tumors were enrolled in to a prospective single group trial. Patient characteristics are detailed in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>. Patients with bleeding potentials or serious heart, liver and renal failures were excluded. Antibiotics and medicines for prevention of bleeding were given regularly. Every patient underwent a chest Flurodeoxyhlucose postron emission (PET) and CT scan before procedure.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Patient characteristics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="center" colspan="3">Patients (n = 50)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Patient characteristic</td><td align="center">No</td><td></td><td align="center">%</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Age, years</td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Median</td><td></td><td align="center">51</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Range</td><td></td><td align="center">35&#x02013;74</td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Sex</td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Male</td><td align="center">32</td><td></td><td align="center">64</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Female</td><td align="center">18</td><td></td><td align="center">36</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Origins</td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Primary lung tumors</td><td align="center">23</td><td></td><td align="center">46</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Metastases from breast</td><td align="center">13</td><td></td><td align="center">26</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Metastases from colon</td><td align="center">9</td><td></td><td align="center">18</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Metastases from other places</td><td align="center">5</td><td></td><td align="center">10</td></tr><tr><td align="left">No. of patient with lesions</td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Single lesion</td><td align="center">17</td><td></td><td align="center">34</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;Multiple lesions</td><td align="center">33</td><td></td><td align="center">66</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Total lesions received RFA</td><td></td><td align="center">120</td><td></td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Patients received a chest X-ray and CT for preoperative evaluation and a repeat scan after RFA procedure. A PET scan was performed one week after the treatment.</p><p>The Radiofrequency ablation was carried out using RF-2000 generator and related software purchased from Radio Therapeutics Corporation, USA; PET imaging was done using an Advance 2 Scanner (General Electric Medical Systems, WI, USA).</p><p>Patients received general anesthesia along with local infiltration of Lidocaine. The electrodes were directed to target areas during RFA procedure using CT scan. The initial power applied was 50 W, which was subsequently increased to a maximum 90 W over several minutes. RFA continued for 5 to 15 min until roll off was achieved, which continued for 2 min to stop. Tumors smaller than 3.5 cm were given full heating energy only once, while tumors larger than 3.5 cm received multiple RFA to different areas. Maximum 4 lesions or 6 target areas were treated during one procedure.</p><p>One to two weeks after the procedure and a 4 hour fast, patients were taken for PET scan. They were made to rest for 15 min, and then received <sup>18</sup>F-FDG 296 MBq &#x02013; 440 MBq (8 mCi -12 mCi) intravenously. After another period of rest lasting for 45&#x02013;60 min, the whole body and/or lung images was acquired by PET scanner. PET was also acquired at 5&#x02013;8 bed positions, typically from the base of skull to the mid thigh, which was identical to the CT protocol used in the present study. The complications of the treatment are detailed in table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref> and results are summarized in table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Complications of Radiofrequency ablation</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="center" colspan="2">Patients (n = 50)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Complication</td><td align="center">No</td><td align="center">%</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Fever</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">20</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Congested pneumonia</td><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">12</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Pneumothorax</td><td align="center">9</td><td align="center">18</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Hemothorax</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">2</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Early effectiveness of RFA by various techniques</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="center" colspan="2">Tumor destruction demonstrated</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Technique</td><td align="center">No</td><td align="center">%</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">All 50 patients received</td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;PET</td><td align="center">35</td><td align="center">70</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;CT</td><td align="center">19</td><td align="center">38</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x02003;X-ray</td><td align="center">13</td><td align="center">26</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>After RFA procedure a number of complications were seen. Fever and/or congested pneumonia were commonest complications seen in 32% of patients; however, they were cured in a week with antibiotics treatment. Pneumothorax occurred during procedures in 18% and the patients were treated with aspiration. Five of these had small pneumothorax that did not require and treatment. One patient had hemothorax which required intercostals drainage (ICD) which was removed 2 days later. These were no life threatening events or deaths.</p><p>Post procedural PET demonstrated the effectiveness of RFA on lung tumors. Tumors smaller than 3.5 cm showed complete response after RFA (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). In tumors larger than 3.5 cm, the part within 3.5 cm diameter dissipated, while the part outside this 3.5 cm area remained (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). Damage to the normal tissue outside the tumor was not extensive in any cause.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>PET images taken before and after RFA treatments: coronal (A, B), and Sagittal (C, D) views of PET scans of lung cancer. (A, C) were taken before RFA treatment; (B, D) were taken two weeks after RFA treatment.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1477-7819-2-30-1"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>PET images taken before and after RFA treatments. This patient had a tumor size larger than 3.5 cm. PET scans were taken 1 week before (A) and 2 weeks after (B) RFA treatment.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1477-7819-2-30-2"/></fig><p>The Chest X-ray and CT showed that tumor image became larger 1 to 2 weeks after RFA procedure (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). These may result from partial tissue damages, bleeding, acute inflammation or pneumonia, and support the routing use of antibiotics and haemostatic drugs after RFA. The tumor destruction was picked up by PET much effectively when compared to CT scan or chest X-ray.</p><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>CT images taken before and after RFA treatments. The same patient PET images were shown as Figure 1. (A) was taken before RFA treatment, (B) was taken 2 week after RFA treatment.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1477-7819-2-30-3"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Since RFA ablates lung tumors directly and locally, marginal tissues surrounding the tumor are frequently partially damaged leading to occasional pneumonia. It is difficult for regular CT and/or chest X-rays to discriminate pathological-physiological tissue damage and fibrillation from the treatment effect of RFA. PET on the other hand provides information on functional and metabolic activity anatomically, and is the only available technique which can specifically diagnose tumors or necrosis after surgery and radiotherapy effectively [28]. Our experience too proves that PET is particularly superior to CT in its ability to evaluate the effectiveness of RFA treatment early after therapy.</p><p>RFA is a relatively noninvasive, well-tolerated approach. It could destruct tumor completely within the effective diameter while avoiding the surgery, side effects of radiotherapy and toxicity of high dose chemotherapy. Our observations suggest that RFA can kill lung tumors smaller than 3.5 cm after a single RFA procedure. The effect of RFA appears to be limited within 3.5 cm diameter area with the current instruments. However, this also suggests that RFA may not damage the normal tissues surrounding the small tumors. The malignant lesions dissipated in 1 to 2 weeks, while the surrounding tissue stayed intact. While at this period regular chest CT and chest X-ray may show enlarged lesion images. This is in agreement with other reports. With improvements in technology, RFA in combination with other options may further reduce the morbidity and mortality of cancer deaths [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. Though complications do occur, they are usually curable. RFA results in a higher rate of complete necrosis and requires fewer treatment cycles compared to traditional chemotherapy or radiotherapy. Besides CT guidance help to localize the tumor and determine the optimal approach further optimizes specific of targeting the tumor. For patients with non-small cell lung malignancy who are not candidates for surgery owing to poor cardio respiratory reserve, RFA alone or followed by conventional radiation therapy or chemotherapy may prove to be a treatment option [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. For patients with metastatic disease, RFA may be suitable for treatment of a small tumor or reduce symptoms caused by large tumor burden. This technique can be used as a primary technique or in conjunction with other interventional procedures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. Further randomized controlled trials comparing RFA with conventional palliative treatment are needed before RFA can be accepted as a routine treatment modality. Survival of patient and quality of life issues too need be addressed.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Despite inherent deficiency of trial design our single group study clearly demonstrates that RFA can be an effective treatment option for lung tumors. Unlike other interventional techniques, RFA provide controlled regions of coagulation necrosis with a single application to an area with 3.5 cm diameter. RFA may cure small lung tumor, reduce tumor burden in larger lesions and may be combined with external beam radiation and/or systemic chemotherapy for further improvements. PET provides functional and metabolic activity anatomically and is particularly superior to CT in evaluation the effectiveness shortly after RFA procedure. Absence of follow-up information and randomization in the current study are two major fallacies which need to be addressed in subsequent studies.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>SJK is the leading physician and drafted the manuscript.</p><p>RL, WL, HW, XZ, YM all participated in the study, patient management, literature search and preparation of manuscript.</p><p>All authors have read and approved the final version of the manuscript.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>None declared.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Sandler</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The epidemiology of lung cancer</article-title><source>Cancer Treat Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11224993</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noppen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interventional palliative treatment options for lung cancer</article-title><source>Ann Oncol</source><year>2002</year><volume>13 Suppl 4</volume><fpage>247</fpage><lpage>250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12401697</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dupuy</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayo-Smith</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbott</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name><name><surname>DiPetrillo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical applications of radio-frequency tumor ablation in the thorax</article-title><source>Radiographics</source><year>2002</year><volume>22 Spec No</volume><fpage>S259</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12376615</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chhajed</surname><given-names>PN</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamm</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Radiofrequency heat ablation for lung tumors: potential applications</article-title><source>Med Sci Monit</source><year>2003</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>ED5</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14586281</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gazelle</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldberg</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Solbiati</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Livraghi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tumor ablation with radio-frequency energy</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>2000</year><volume>217</volume><fpage>633</fpage><lpage>646</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11110923</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Salem</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Raman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gates</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name><surname>Dworkin</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluating 90Y-glass microsphere treatment response of unresectable colorectal liver metastases by [18F]FDG PET: a comparison with CT or MRI</article-title><source>Eur J Nucl Med Mol Imaging</source><year>2002</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>815</fpage><lpage>820</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12029557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00259-002-0787-4</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fazzari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tickoo</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolbert</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sgouros</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeung</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Macapinlac</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prognostic value of [18F]fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomographic scanning in patients with thyroid cancer</article-title><source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2000</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>1107</fpage><lpage>1113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10720047</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/jc.85.3.1107</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name><name><surname>Polascik</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>DeGrado</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of [18 F]fluorocholine and [18 F]fluorodeoxyglucose for positron emission tomography of androgen dependent and androgen independent prostate cancer</article-title><source>J Urol</source><year>2002</year><volume>168</volume><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>280</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12050555</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00005392-200207000-00090</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Voth</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Opfermann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Gottschild</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>[The value of fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography (FDG-PET) in differentiation of pancreatic lesions]</article-title><source>Zentralbl Chir</source><year>2003</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>375</fpage><lpage>378</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12813634</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-2003-40030</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunphy</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Varvares</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunphy</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunleavy</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonough</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Minster</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fletcher</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of chemotherapy response in patients with advanced head and neck cancer using [F-18]fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography</article-title><source>Head Neck</source><year>1997</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>666</fpage><lpage>674</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9406745</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1097-0347(199712)19:8&#x0003c;666::AID-HED4&#x0003e;3.3.CO;2-C</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peschina</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>[F-18 fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography in lung lesions]</article-title><source>Wien Med Wochenschr</source><year>2002</year><volume>152</volume><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12138653</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1563-258X.2002.02019.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berlangieri</surname><given-names>SU</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitt</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hennessy</surname><given-names>OF</given-names></name><name><surname>Tochon-Danguy</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>McKay</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>F-18 fluorodeoxyglucose positron emission tomography in the non-invasive staging of non-small cell lung cancer</article-title><source>Eur J Cardiothorac Surg</source><year>1999</year><volume>16 Suppl 1</volume><fpage>S25</fpage><lpage>30</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10536941</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamberg</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>McCloud</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischman</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dynamic T1-weighted magnetic resonance imaging and positron emission tomography in patients with lung cancer: correlating vascular physiology with glucose metabolism</article-title><source>Clin Cancer Res</source><year>1998</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>949</fpage><lpage>955</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9563889</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PET in lung cancer staging</article-title><source>Q J Nucl Med</source><year>2001</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11788815</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Value of FDG-PET scanning in management of lung cancer</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2002</year><volume>359</volume><fpage>1361</fpage><lpage>1362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11978328</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(02)08388-5</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonzalez-Stawinski</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemaire</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Merchant</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Halloran</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Harpole</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>D'Amico</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A comparative analysis of positron emission tomography and mediastinoscopy in staging non-small cell lung cancer</article-title><source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source><year>2003</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>1900</fpage><lpage>1905</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14688703</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-5223(03)01036-5</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marom</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>McAdams</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Erasmus</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Culhane</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Herndon</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Patz</surname><given-names>E. F., Jr.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Staging non-small cell lung cancer with whole-body PET</article-title><source>Radiology</source><year>1999</year><volume>212</volume><fpage>803</fpage><lpage>809</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10478250</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burt</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Humm</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kooby</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Squire</surname><given-names>OD</given-names></name><name><surname>Mastorides</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Using positron emission tomography with [(18)F]FDG to predict tumor behavior in experimental colorectal cancer</article-title><source>Neoplasia</source><year>2001</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11494112</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.neo.7900147</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>FDG imaging</article-title><source>Nucl Med Biol</source><year>2000</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>689</fpage><lpage>690</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11091113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0969-8051(00)00139-6</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liao</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigation of short-term therapy results for radiofrequency ablation by positron emission tomography</article-title><source>Di Yi Jun Yi Da Xue Xue Bao</source><year>2002</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>376</fpage><lpage>377</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12390754</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kostakoglu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldsmith</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>18F-FDG PET evaluation of the response to therapy for lymphoma and for breast, lung, and colorectal carcinoma</article-title><source>J Nucl Med</source><year>2003</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>224</fpage><lpage>239</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12571214</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akhurst</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Downey</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ginsberg</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bains</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Korst</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ginsberg</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Rusch</surname><given-names>VW</given-names></name><name><surname>Larson</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An initial experience with FDG-PET in the imaging of residual disease after induction therapy for lung cancer</article-title><source>Ann Thorac Surg</source><year>2002</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>64; discussion 264-6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11834020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0003-4975(01)03257-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herrera</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernando</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Gooding</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Buenaventura</surname><given-names>PO</given-names></name><name><surname>Christie</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><name><surname>Luketich</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Radiofrequency ablation of pulmonary malignant tumors in nonsurgical candidates</article-title><source>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg</source><year>2003</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>929</fpage><lpage>937</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12698158</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1067/mtc.2003.18</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Allegra</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Bostick</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Foshag</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bilchik</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Radiofrequency ablation: a novel primary and adjunctive ablative technique for hepatic malignancies</article-title><source>Am Surg</source><year>1999</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>1009</fpage><lpage>1014</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10551746</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



