<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ann Clin Microbiol Antimicrob</journal-id><journal-title>Annals of Clinical Microbiology and Antimicrobials</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1476-0711</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15610563</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC544836</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1476-0711-3-27</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1476-0711-3-27</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>In vitro activity of antiamoebic drugs against clinical isolates of <italic>Entamoeba histolytica </italic>and <italic>Entamoeba dispar</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bansal</surname><given-names>Devendra</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>devbansalpgi@yahoo.co.in</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sehgal</surname><given-names>Rakesh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>rakesh.sehgal@rediffmail.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chawla</surname><given-names>Yogesh</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>ykchawla@hotmail.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mahajan</surname><given-names>Ramesh Chander</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>indurc@sify.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Malla</surname><given-names>Nancy</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>drnancymalla@yahoo.com</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Parasitology, Post Graduate Institute of Medical Education &#x00026; Research, Chandigarh, India</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Hepatology, Post Graduate Institute of Medical Education &#x00026; Research, Chandigarh, India</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>12</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ann-clinmicrob.com/content/3/1/27"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>9</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>12</month><year>2004</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2004 Bansal et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2004</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Bansal et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Bansal
               Devendra
               
               devbansalpgi@yahoo.co.in
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            In vitro activity of antiamoebic drugs against clinical isolates of Entamoeba histolytica and Entamoeba dispar
         </dc:title><dc:date>2004</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Annals of Clinical Microbiology and Antimicrobials 3(1): 27-. (2004)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1476-0711(2004)3:1&#x0003c;27&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1476-0711</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Amoebiasis is a major public health problem in tropical and subtropical countries. Although a number of antiamoebic agents are used for its treatment, yet the susceptibility data on clinical isolates of <italic>Entamoeba histolytica </italic>and <italic>Entamoeba dispar </italic>are not available. Therefore, the present study was aimed to assess the in vitro susceptibility of clinical isolates of <italic>E. histolytica </italic>and <italic>E. dispar </italic>to metronidazole, chloroquine, emetine and tinidazole.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>A total of 45 clinical isolates (15 <italic>E. histolytica </italic>and 30 <italic>E. dispar</italic>) were maintained in polyxenic cultures followed by monoxenic cultures. In vitro drug sensitivity (IC<sub>50</sub>) of clinical isolates and standard reference strain of <italic>E. histolytica </italic>(HM1: IMSS) was assessed by nitro blue tetrazolium (NBT) reduction assay after exposure to various concentrations of each drug.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The results showed that all clinical isolates had a higher IC<sub>50 </sub>compared to reference strain to all the four drugs. <italic>E. histolytica </italic>isolates appeared to be more susceptible [IC<sub>50 </sub>(&#x003bc;m) 13.2,26.3,31.2 and 12.4] compared to <italic>E. dispar </italic>isolates [IC<sub>50</sub>(&#x003bc;m) 15.6,28.9,32.8 and 13.2] and the reference strain of <italic>E. histolytica </italic>[IC<sub>50 </sub>(&#x003bc;m) 9.5, 15.5, 29.9 and 10.2] to the metronidazole, chloroquine, emetine and tinidazole respectively.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>The results indicate that till date, <italic>Entamoeba </italic>isolates in India do not seem to be resistant to the commonly used antiamoebic drugs.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p><italic>Entamoeba histolytica</italic>, is the etiological agent of amoebic dysentery and amoebic liver abscess (ALA). Worldwide, 40&#x02013;50 million symptomatic cases of amoebiasis occur annually and 70,000 to 100,000 deaths due to this infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. There are two distinct, but morphologically identical species of <italic>Entamoeba</italic>: <italic>Entamoeba histolytica</italic>, which is pathogenic and <italic>Entamoeba dispar</italic>, which is non-pathogenic. <italic>E. histolytica</italic>, has the capacity to invade intestinal mucosa resulting in intestinal amoebiasis and cause extra intestinal amoebiasis [amoebic liver abscess (ALA)] [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>].</p><p>Infection is primarily treated by instituting antiamoebic therapy. Drugs of choice for invasive amoebiasis are tissue active agents, like metronidazole, tinidazole and chloroquine or the more toxic emetine derivatives, including dehydroemetine. Metronidazole and tinidazole are derived from 5-nitroimdazole which kill the trophozoites by alterations in the protoplasmic organelles of the amoeba, but are ineffective in the treatment of cyst passers. Chloroquine is derived from 4-aminoquinolines, which acts on the vegetative forms of the parasite and kills it by inhibiting DNA synthesis. Emetine, a plant alkaloid, kills the trophozoites of <italic>E. histolytica </italic>mainly by inhibiting protein synthesis.</p><p>Indiscriminate use of drugs has led to an increase in the minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) of these therapeutic agents [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Although, drug resistance to <italic>E. histolytica </italic>does not appear to be a serious problem, there are occasional reports of failure with metronidazole suggesting that this could probably be heralding the development of drug resistance clinically [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Recurrence of ALA even after treatment with metronidazole has been reported and parasites may survive in spite of adequate treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. However, differences in drug sensitivity between strains of <italic>E. histolytica </italic>have been reported, indicating that there may be a small percentage of amoebae which are either resistant to the drug or may even eventually become resistant due to abuse of antiamoebic agents [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Although, earlier studies have been focused on in vitro sensitivity of the only axenic strains of <italic>E. histolytica </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>], yet to the best of our knowledge, studies on in vitro drug susceptibility studies on clinical isolates of <italic>E. histolytica </italic>and <italic>E. dispar </italic>have not been reported. Therefore, in the present study an attempt has been made to assess the in vitro activity of antiamoebic drugs (emetine, chloroquine, metronidazole and tinidazole) against clinical isolates of <italic>E. histolytica </italic>and <italic>E. dispar</italic>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Clinical isolates</title><p>Forty-five isolates from patients attending the Out Patient Departments of Nehru hospital, attached to the Post Graduate Institute of Medical Education &#x00026; Research, Chandigarh, India, identified earlier [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>] as either <italic>E. histolytica </italic>(15) or <italic>E. dispar </italic>(30) by hexokinase isoenzyme analysis and by Techlab ELISA were used in the present study. These have been cultured in modified Boeck and Drbohlav (NIH) medium [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>] followed by Robinson's medium [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Standard reference strain (HM1: IMSS)</title><p>Reference strain of <italic>E. histolytica </italic>(HM1: IMSS) maintained axenically in TYI-S-33 medium was included as control [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Preparation of antimicrobial agents</title><p>The drugs (metronidazole, chloroquine, emetine dihydrochloride and tinidazole) used in the study were procured as pure salt from Sigma-Aldrich Co., St. Louis, MO., 63178 USA. The stock solutions of drugs (each 0.1 M) were prepared in dimethyl sulphoxide (DMSO) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>] and stored at -20&#x000b0;C till use. The stock solutions were diluted in medium to the required concentration. A starting concentration used was 200 &#x003bc;M, which yielded a maximum concentration in the assay of 17.1 &#x003bc;g/ml metronidazole, 51.59 &#x003bc;g/ml chloroquine, 55.3 &#x003bc;g/ml emetine, and 24.7 &#x003bc;g/ml tinidazole.</p></sec><sec><title>In vitro drug sensitivity assay</title><p>Drug sensitivity to all the compounds was carried out by nitroblue tetrazolium (NBT) reduction method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. Each clinical isolate was tested in duplicate along with the reference <italic>E. histolytica </italic>strain (HM1: IMSS). Amoebae were harvested from 24 hour old cultures and suspended in medium. The parasite count was adjusted to 3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5 </sup>parasites/ml in medium by haemocytometer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>].</p><p>The assay was carried out in microtiter plates (Grenier bio-one, Germany). Briefly, in row A 200 &#x003bc;l of drug and in all other rows (B-H) medium was added and doubling dilutions of the drug were performed down the plate. Final drug concentration in rows A-H was as follows: 100, 50, 25, 12.5, 6.25, 3.12, 1.6 and 0.8 (&#x003bc;M). Further 100 &#x003bc;l of parasite suspension (3 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5</sup>/well) was added to all the rows (A-H). Each test included control (without drug) and blank wells (medium only). The plates were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 4 hrs. The contents of the plates were discarded and washed with pre warmed Hank's balanced salt solution (HBSS pH 7.2). Thereafter, 100 &#x003bc;l of NBT/well in HBSS was added and the plates were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 45 min. followed by aspiration of the contents. Plates were then washed with HBSS twice and 200 &#x003bc;l/well of DMSO (100% v/v) was added. Following incubation at 37&#x000b0;C for 10 min, the optical density (OD) was measured in an ELISA recorder at 540 nm.</p><p>The percentage of non-viable organisms, which failed to metabolize NBT and therefore did not produce the dark blue formazan product, was determined by applying the following formula:</p><p>Percentage of non-viable organisms at each drug conc. =</p><p><inline-graphic xlink:href="1476-0711-3-27-i1.gif"/></p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The mean IC<sub>50 </sub>values of all clinical isolates against the four drugs were compared with corresponding IC<sub>50 </sub>values of the reference <italic>E. histolytica </italic>strain (HM1: IMSS). Standard deviation (SD) was used to indicate the extent of variation around group mean values. The <italic>p </italic>value was calculated using the student's-t test.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The IC<sub>50 </sub>values of emetine, chloroquine, metronidazole and tinidazole for the 45 clinical isolates [15 <italic>E. histolytica </italic>and 30 <italic>E. dispar</italic>] and the reference strain HM1: IMSS were determined by the NBT reduction assay. The mean IC<sub>50 </sub>values were significantly higher (<italic>P </italic>&#x0003c; 0.001) in <italic>E. dispar </italic>isolates to all the four antiamoebic drugs as compared to the <italic>E. histolytica </italic>isolates and the reference <italic>E. histolytica </italic>strain (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref> &#x00026; Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1&#x02013;4</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Percentage inhibition of <italic>E. histolytica </italic>(HM1: IMSS) and clinical isolates of <italic>E. histolytica </italic>and <italic>E. dispar </italic>by metronidazole</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1476-0711-3-27-1"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Percentage inhibition of <italic>E. histolytica </italic>(HM1: IMSS) and clinical isolates of <italic>E. histolytica </italic>and <italic>E. dispar </italic>by chloroquine</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1476-0711-3-27-2"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Percentage inhibition of <italic>E. histolytica </italic>(HM1: IMSS) and clinical isolates of <italic>E. histolytica </italic>and <italic>E. dispar </italic>by emetine</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1476-0711-3-27-3"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Percentage inhibition of <italic>E. histolytica </italic>(HM1: IMSS) and clinical isolates of <italic>E. histolytica </italic>and <italic>E. dispar </italic>by tinidazole</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1476-0711-3-27-4"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Treatment failure among amoebiasis patients often raises the possibility of drug resistance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. In the present study the 15 <italic>E. histolytica </italic>and 30 <italic>E</italic>. <italic>dispar </italic>clinical isolates maintained by in vitro cultivation in monoxenic medium were subjected to drug susceptibility tests against four antiamoebic drugs: metronidazole, chloroquine, emetine and tinidazole by NBT reduction assay. <italic>E. histolytica </italic>reference strain (HM1: IMSS) was also included in each set of experiments.</p><p>Results showed a significant difference in drug sensitivity in clinical isolates as compared to the reference strain with all the four drugs. The mean IC<sub>50 </sub>values (&#x003bc;m) of the <italic>E. histolytica</italic>/<italic>E</italic>. <italic>dispar </italic>isolates against metronidazole, chloroquine, emetine and tinidazole were 13.2/15.6, 26.3/28.9, 31.2/32.8 and 12.4/13.2 respectively. The IC<sub>50 </sub>values (&#x003bc;m) of the reference strain against all the four respective drugs were 9.5, 15.5, 29.9 and 10.2. Recently Upcroft &#x00026; Upcroft [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>] have reported that the MIC values of metronidazole ranges from 12.5&#x02013;25 &#x003bc;m for laboratory-passaged <italic>E. histolytica </italic>strains. Adagu, et.al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>] have shown the mean metronidazole IC<sub>50 </sub>value as 18.47 &#x003bc;m for the most susceptible isolates of <italic>E. histolytica </italic>with a &#x0003e; 30 &#x003bc;m value as the cut off for resistance. Burchard &#x00026; Mirelman, studied in vitro sensitivity to metronidazole and emetine of non-pathogenic zymodemes and showed that all were similarly sensitive to both the drugs (1&#x02013;10 &#x003bc;g/ml) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. In the present study, clinical isolates maintained in monoxenic culture were used to detect the in vitro sensitivity as earlier it has been concluded that bacterial flora associated with the amebae did not significantly interfere with the test performance and sensitivity values [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>].</p><p>Although resistance to metronidazole has been reported against <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>], <italic>Giardia </italic>lamblia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>] and <italic>Leishmania donovani </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>], yet to the best of our knowledge there is no documented resistance among clinical isolates of <italic>E. histolytica </italic>and <italic>E</italic>. dispar.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The results of the present study are in agreement with previous findings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>], except that there was a significantly higher IC<sub>50 </sub>value of all four drugs to the clinical isolates as compared to the reference strain. <italic>E. dispar </italic>isolates showed higher IC<sub>50 </sub>values when compared to <italic>E. histolytica </italic>or reference strain. This is the first report of in vitro drug sensitivity pattern to clinical isolates of <italic>E. histolytica </italic>and <italic>E. dispar</italic>. There is definitely a need to monitor the random drug susceptibility among clinical isolates especially in context to widespread use of metronidazole and tinidazole, which are available over the counter in many countries. Increased awareness and continued surveillance for the possible emergence of resistance among clinical isolates is necessary for the ultimate prevention and control of amoebiasis.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p><bold>DB</bold>, carried the practical work mentioned in the manuscript.</p><p><bold>RS</bold>, was responsible for formulation of the project and provided guidance time to time.</p><p><bold>YC</bold>, he is clinician and carried clinical examination and proposed clinical diagnosis of the patient.</p><p><bold>RCM</bold>, he guided the proposed work related to differentiation of <italic>Entamoeba histolytica </italic>and <italic>Entamoeba dispar </italic>and in vitro drug sensitivity.</p><p><bold>NM</bold>, proposed the concept for this manuscript and guided the practical work and writing of the manuscript.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Comparison between 1C<sub>50 </sub>value of clinical isolates (<italic>E. histolytica </italic>and <italic>E. dispar</italic>) vs reference strain (HM1: IMSS)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left"><bold>COMPOUND</bold></td><td align="center" colspan="2"><bold>MEAN IC<sub>50 </sub>OF CLINICAL ISOLATES (&#x003bc;m &#x000b1; SD)</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>IC<sub>50 </sub>VALUE OF REFERENCE STRAIN (&#x003bc;m &#x000b1; SD)</bold></td></tr><tr><td></td><td colspan="2"><hr></hr></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center"><bold><italic>E. histolytica</italic></bold></td><td align="center"><bold><italic>E. dispar</italic></bold></td><td></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><bold>Metronidazole</bold></td><td align="center">6.5 &#x000b1; 0.81***<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center">15.6 &#x000b1; 2.12***<sup>c</sup></td><td align="center">9.5 &#x000b1; 1.53***<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Chloroquine</bold></td><td align="center">18.9 &#x000b1; 1.39***<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center">28.9 &#x000b1; 2.45***<sup>c</sup></td><td align="center">21.5 &#x000b1; 1.26***<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Emetine</bold></td><td align="center">26.8 &#x000b1; 1.27***<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center">32.8 &#x000b1; 1.68***<sup>c</sup></td><td align="center">28.0 &#x000b1; 2.62***<sup>b</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>Tinidazole</bold></td><td align="center">8.2 &#x000b1; 1.09***<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center">13.2 &#x000b1; 1.43***<sup>c</sup></td><td align="center">10.2 &#x000b1; 0.43***<sup>b</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><graphic xlink:href="1476-0711-3-27-i2.gif"/><bold>Results expressed as mean &#x000b1; SD from two experiments conducted in duplicate</bold></p><p><graphic xlink:href="1476-0711-3-27-i2.gif"/><bold>Student's t-test </bold>[*** P &#x0003c; 0.001]</p><p>a = Eh Vs Ed <bold>Eh &#x02013; <italic>E. histolytica</italic></bold></p><p>b = Eh Vs C <bold>Ed &#x02013; <italic>E. dispar</italic></bold></p><p>c = Ed Vs C <bold>C &#x02013; Reference strain (HM1: IMSS)</bold></p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Financial assistance from the Indian Council of Medical Research (ICMR), New Delhi, is gratefully acknowledged.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Problems in recognition and diagnosis of amoebiasis: estimation of the global magnitude of mortality and morbidity</article-title><source>Rev Infect Dis</source><year>1986</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>228</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2871619</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diamond</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A redescription of <italic>Entamoeba histolytica </italic>Schaudinn 1903 (emended walker, 1911) separating it from <italic>Entamoeba dispar </italic>Brumpt, 1925</article-title><source>J Eukaryot Microbiol</source><year>1993</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>340</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8508172</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez-Palomo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez-Baez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selective primary health care: strategies for control of disease in the developing world X amoebiasis</article-title><source>Rev Infect Dis</source><year>1983</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1093</fpage><lpage>1102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6140740</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayala</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Samuelson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Orozco</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physiology and molecular biology of multidrug resistance in <italic>Entamoeba histolytica</italic></article-title><source>Arch Med Res</source><year>1996</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>421</fpage><lpage>25</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8854404</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pittman</surname><given-names>FE</given-names></name><name><surname>Pittman</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Amoebic liver abscess following metronidazole therapy for amoebic colitis</article-title><source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source><year>1974</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>146</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4361705</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burchard</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirelman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Entamoeba histolytica </italic>virulence potential and sensitivity to metronidazole and emetine of four isolates possessing nonpathogenic zymodemes</article-title><source>Exp Parasitol</source><year>1988</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2899517</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0014-4894(88)90095-1</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Upcroft</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Upcroft</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drug targets and mechanisms of resistance in the anaerobic protozoa</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source><year>2001</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>150</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11148007</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.14.1.150-164.2001</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aguirre-Cruz</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Valadez-Salazar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Munoz</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro sensitivity of <italic>Entamoeba histolytica </italic>to metronidazole</article-title><source>Arch Invest Med (Mex)</source><year>1990</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2136490</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adagu</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><name><surname>Nolder</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Warhurst</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossignol</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In vitro activity of nitazoxanide and related compounds against isolates of <italic>Giardia intestinalis, Entamoeba histolytica, Trichomonas vaginalis</italic></article-title><source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source><year>2002</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>103</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11751773</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/49.1.103</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bansal</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sehgal</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Chawla</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahajan</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Malla</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative Evaluation of Hexokinase Isoenzyme Typing and Antigen Detection for Differentiation of <italic>Entamoeba histolytica </italic>and <italic>Entamoeba dispar</italic></article-title><source>Nepal Med Coll J</source><comment></comment></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="book"><source>Center disease Control Bulletin</source><year>1948</year><publisher-name>United States Public Health Service Publication (USPHS)</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The laboratory diagnosis of human parasite amoebae</article-title><source>Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg</source><year>1968</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>285</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4296113</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0035-9203(68)90170-3</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diamond</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Harlow</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunnick</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new medium for axenic cultivation of <italic>Entamoeba histolytica</italic></article-title><source>Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg</source><year>1978</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>431</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">212851</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0035-9203(78)90144-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Upcroft</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Upcroft</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Drug susceptibility testing of anaerobic protozoa</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2001</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>1810</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11353630</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.45.6.1810-1814.2001</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mukhopadhyay</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaudhuri</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rapid in vitro tests for determination of antiamebic activity</article-title><source>Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg</source><year>1996</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>91</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8761587</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0035-9203(96)90136-4</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ayala</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Samuelson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wirth</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Orozco</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Entamoeba histolytica </italic>: physiology of multidrug resistance</article-title><source>Exp Parasitol</source><year>1990</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>169</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2373187</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0014-4894(90)90019-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Voolmann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Boreham</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metronidazole resistant <italic>Trichomonas vaginalis </italic>in Brisbane</article-title><source>Med J Aust</source><year>1993</year><volume>159</volume><fpage>490</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8412928</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nash</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohl</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Subramanian</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Keiser</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Treatment of patients with refractory giardiasis</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2001</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11389490</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/320886</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sundar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>More</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>VP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Makharia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Failure of pentavalent antimony in visceral leishmaniasis in India: report from the center of the Indian epidemic</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2000</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>1104</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11049798</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/318121</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



