<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Genet</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Genetics</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2156</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15760477</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC555543</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2156-6-14</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2156-6-14</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Two new plumage mutations in the Japanese quail: "curly" feather and "rusty" plumage</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Minvielle</surname><given-names>Francis</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>minvielle@dga2.jouy.inra.fr</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gourichon</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>gouricho@tours.inra.fr</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moussu</surname><given-names>Chantal</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>Chantal.Moussu@tours.inra.fr</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>G&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;tique et Diversit&#x000e9; Animales, Institut National de la Recherche Agronomique, Centre de Jouy, 78352 Jouy-en-Josas, France</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Unit&#x000e9; Exp&#x000e9;rimentale de G&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;tique Factorielle Avicole, Institut National de la Recherche Agronomique, Centre de Tours, 37380 Nouzilly, France</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>3</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2156/6/14"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>12</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>3</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 Minvielle et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Minvielle et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Minvielle
               Francis
               
               minvielle@dga2.jouy.inra.fr
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Two new plumage mutations in the Japanese quail: "curly" feather and "rusty" plumage
         </dc:title><dc:date>2005</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>BMC Genetics 6(1): 14-. (2005)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1471-2156(2005)6:1&#x0003c;14&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1471-2156</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>The genetics of plumage of Japanese quail is of interest both from a biological standpoint, for comparative studies between avian species, and from a zootechnical standpoint, for identifying commercial selection lines or crosses. There are only few plumage mutations reported in quail, and the present work describes a new color variant "rusty" and a new feather structure "curly", and their heredity from an F1 and F2 segregation experiment.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Curly feathers result from abnormal early growth caused by transient joining of follicle walls of adjacent feathers around 10 days of age, but the expression of the trait is variable. Rusty plumage color results from the replacement of the wild-type plumage pattern on the tip of the feather by a reddish coloration, but the pigmentation of the bottom part of the feather is not affected. Two lines breeding true for the curly or the rusty phenotype were developed. Both characters are determined by autosomal recessive mutations which are independent. The curly mutation has also a positive effect on body weight at 5 weeks of age.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The curly line is a new model which may be used for further work on the growth of the feather, and the rusty mutation is a new addition to the panel of plumage mutations available for comparative studies in poultry, and more generally among avian species.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Japanese quail is both a model animal in biology and a bird used for meat and egg production under a large variety of settings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. In the recent past, a special attention was given to the study of its plumage, and several major genes have been described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Since the last compilation of plumage mutations of Japanese quail [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>], new loci were described [e.g. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]], linkage and epistasis relationships were explored [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>], and some genes were recently mapped [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. This knowledge has already been put to use for running comparisons between chicken and quail based on plumage genetics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>], and for tagging commercial quail lines with a visible plumage trait, like the "fawn" mutation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>], or with an auto-sexing mutation like the "roux" gene [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. Interestingly, some of the mutations described in quail, like the sex-linked "roux" and the lethal "yellow" mutations still have no known homologues in the chicken. Moreover, the fact that some plumage colors, like "lavender", are common to several avian species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>] is an added incentive to enrich the panel of characterised Japanese quail mutations as potential tools for comparative studies among bird species.</p><p>In the present work, a new feather structure phenotype (curly) and a new plumage color (rusty) were described, and their mode of inheritance and linkage were studied in two successive generations (F1 and F2) from an F0 made of eight quail with curly feathering and eight birds with rusty plumage. Growth of the F2 quail was also monitored and compared according to their phenotype for the two plumage mutations.</p></sec><sec><title>Results and discussion</title><sec><title>Phenotypic description</title><p>The quail line with the curly feathers was developed in 2001 from group mating 6 founding (G0) curly quail. Starting in G3, only quail for which the curly phenotype observed at 10 days of age was expressed most strongly were kept for breeding. No differential survival was observed in curly quail after hatching, but the hatching rate in the fixed line at G5 under pool mating was only 34%, mainly because some females did not get mated under this type of mating. In curly chicks, the calamus of the growing wing feathers are not independent from one another, but they are connected through the follicle walls which appear to be joined together. This phenomenon is best observed around 10 days of age and is associated with the curly growth (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). The expression of the trait is variable, however, and the penetrance of the curly mutation appears to be incomplete. The difference between normal and curly adults (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>) is not as marked as for other feather structure mutations, like porcupine [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>], for example. Following the gene nomenclature proposed for the chicken [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>], the locus for this new mutation was named CU, and the symbols of the allele responsible for the curly mutation and of the normal allele at this locus were CU*C and CU*N, respectively. In all instances, inheritance of the trait was similar for both sexes, and heterozygotes CU*C/CU*N had normal plumage structure, indicating that the locus CU was autosomal and the mutation was recessive.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Wing of a 10 day Japanese quail with the curly phenotype. </bold>In curly quail, the calamus of the adjacent growing wing feathers are not independent from one another, but they are connected through the follicle walls which appear to be joined together. This phenomenon which lasts one to two weeks is best observed around 10 days of age. It hinders the normal growth of the feathers, thereby inducing the permanent curly structure of the feathers.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2156-6-14-1"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Japanese quail with the curly and the normal feather structures. </bold>The adult curly quail is on the left. Its plumage has an overall fluffier look when compared to the normal quail on the right, but the intensity of the curliness varies between curly quail, as the penetrance of this autosomal recessive mutation is not complete.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2156-6-14-2"/></fig><p>The quail line with the rusty plumage color was started in 2000 from a founding base (G0) made of a single rusty female bred to a wild-type male from another origin. It was followed by sib mating of the all wild-type G1 quail to produce G2 and G3 pedigreed progeny and selection of the few rusty G4 birds. Survival rate to sexual maturity of the rusty descendance of the early generations was poor, and reproductive performance was low (hatched/incubated = 31%) in the fixed line under pool mating at G6, because of the mating system but also of inbreeding derived from having a single rusty ancestor. The plumage of the mutant chicks was rusty, but the down underneath retained the usual wild-type dark-slaty color. A similar color pattern was maintained in rusty adults: their contour and flight feathers had dark barbs on the bottom and rusty colored barbs on the top third of their length which produced the overall rusty look (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). The effect of this mutation appears to be different from the dilution of the pigmentation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>] associated with the roux mutation which affects the whole feather and produces a paler color (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). The locus for this new mutation was named RU, and the symbols of the allele responsible for the rusty mutation and of the wild-type allele at this locus were RU*R and RU*N, respectively. In all instances, inheritance of the trait was similar for both sexes, and heterozygotes RU*R/RU*N had wild-type plumage color, indicating that the locus RU was autosomal and the mutation was recessive.</p><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Japanese quail with the rusty plumage color. </bold>Quail with the rusty phenotype are homozygous for an autosomal recessive mutation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2156-6-14-3"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Comparison of colors of feathers from Japanese quail. </bold>On the left, the contour feather of a wild-type Japanese quail shows the usual brownish colored tip with a transversal lighter stripe and slaty colored barbs at the bottom. On the center, the feather of a quail with the rusty phenotype has a different, rusty colored, tip, but keeps the same slaty colored barbs than the wild-type bird at the bottom. On the right, the feather of a roux quail (caused by a sex-linked recessive mutation) shows a diluted color, paler than rusty, over its whole length.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2156-6-14-4"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Linkage analysis</title><p>All 68 F1 quail were wild-type birds, confirming that both mutations should be recessive, and not sex-linked. Four phenotypes were obtained in the 531 F2 progeny: 326"wild-type", 95 "rusty", 79 "curly" and 31 "rusty and curly" (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). The high hatching rate (81%) obtained in the F2 confirms that the much lower value obtained in the two lines fixed for the rusty or the curly mutation might have resulted from inbreeding due to the small number of founders and from the pool mating system used rather than from detrimental reproductive effects directly associated with the two mutations. Observed and expected distributions under two different null hypotheses (A: independent segregation given complete penetrance of the curly mutation, and B: independent segregation given incomplete penetrance of the curly mutation) are shown with the corresponding values of &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup><sub>s </sub>(7.5 and 1.9, respectively) in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>. None of the two hypotheses could be rejected because the probabilities for these values of &#x003c7;<sup>2</sup><sub>s </sub>were high enough (p &#x0003e; 0.05 and p &#x0003e; 0.1, respectively). The maximum likelihood estimation of the penetrance parameter (&#x000b1; SE) was 1-&#x003bb; = 0.83 (&#x000b1; 0.07) which indicates that 17% of F2 curly quail might have been misclassified as wild-type birds. This result is consistent with the observation that the expression of the curly trait was variable, and it would account for the relative deficit of curly birds in the F2. Overall, however, the segregation of the F2 results fits a simple two-locus Mendelian inheritance of two autosomal recessive and independent mutations.</p><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>Japanese quail with the rusty plumage color and the curly feather structure. </bold>This phenotype was the least frequent of the four quail types produced in the F2 between the curly and the rusty lines. These quail are homozygous for the two recessive mutations.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2156-6-14-5"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Segregation of plumage color and feather structure in the F2 from rusty plumage and curly feather quail lines</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center">Phenotype</td><td align="center">Observed (n = 531)</td><td align="center" colspan="2">Expected under independent segregation</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td colspan="2"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="center">And complete penetrance (&#x003bb; = 0)</td><td align="center">And incomplete penetrance (0 &#x0003c; &#x003bb; &#x0003c; 1)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">Wild-type</td><td align="center">a = 326</td><td align="center">9n/16 = 298.7</td><td align="center">9n/16+3&#x003bb;n/16 = 315.6<sup>&#x000a5;</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Rusty</td><td align="center">b = 95</td><td align="center">3n/16 = 99.6</td><td align="center">3n/16+&#x003bb;n/16 = 105.2</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Curly</td><td align="center">c = 79</td><td align="center">3n/16 = 99.6</td><td align="center">3n(1-&#x003bb;)/16 = 82.7</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Rusty and curly</td><td align="center">d = 31</td><td align="center">n/16 = 33.2</td><td align="center">n(1-&#x003bb;)/16 = 27.6</td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="2">Goodness of fit</td><td align="center">&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup><sub>s </sub>= 7.5<sup>&#x000a3;</sup></td><td align="center">&#x003c7;<sup>2</sup><sub>s </sub>= 1.9<sup>$</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>&#x000a5;</sup>: calculated using 1-&#x003bb; = 0.83</p><p><sup>&#x000a3;</sup>:0.10 &#x0003e; p &#x0003e; 0.05.</p><p><sup>$</sup>:0.5 &#x0003e; p &#x0003e; 0.1</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Growth</title><p>At hatching, none of the plumage mutations were associated with differences of body weight (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>), but after two weeks quail with curly feathers had become significantly heavier than wild-type ones, and the difference reached 3.4% (p &#x0003c; 0.001) of the average body weight at 35 days of age (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). On the opposite, quail with rusty plumage were 2.3 % lighter (p &#x0003c; 0.05) than wild-type ones. The mean body weight at 5 weeks of age was 176.8, 170.5, 181.0 and 182.0 g, respectively for the "wild-type", "rusty", "curly" and "rusty and curly" quail. The fact that both "curly" and "rusty and curly" birds had a similar high body weight, whereas "rusty" quail were the smallest ones is an indication that the effect on growth of the "curly" mutation might be epistatic over that of the "rusty" mutation. The association of plumage color mutations with lower growth have been previously reported in albino [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>] and roux [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>] quail, with respectively 9 and 3% lower body weight at a similar age, but no mutation with a favorable effect had been found so far. A large scale experiment focused on the associated effects of the curly mutation on growth is needed, however, to confirm and extend the present results.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Analyses of variance of body weight of the F2 from rusty plumage and curly feather quail lines</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center">Age</td><td align="center">At hatch</td><td align="center">1 week</td><td align="center">3 weeks</td><td align="center">5 weeks</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">Sample size<sup>1</sup></td><td align="center">348</td><td align="center">348</td><td align="center">346</td><td align="center">347</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Mean body weight (g) (SD)</td><td align="center">8.1 (0.8)</td><td align="center">27.6 (4.5)</td><td align="center">105.7 (12.5)</td><td align="center">176.7 (17.0)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">R<sup>2</sup></td><td align="center">0.82</td><td align="center">0.45</td><td align="center">0.47</td><td align="center">0.50</td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="5"><underline>Significance of main effects</underline></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Hatch</td><td align="center">**</td><td align="center">ns</td><td align="center">***</td><td align="center">***</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Family</td><td align="center">***</td><td align="center">***</td><td align="center">***</td><td align="center">***</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Sex</td><td align="center">**</td><td align="center">ns</td><td align="center">ns</td><td align="center">***</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Feather structure</td><td align="center">ns</td><td align="center">ns</td><td align="center">**</td><td align="center">***</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Plumage color</td><td align="center">ns</td><td align="center">***</td><td align="center">**</td><td align="center">*</td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="5"><underline>Contrast</underline> (g)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">"curly" &#x02013; "wild-type"</td><td align="center">-0.08<sup>ns</sup></td><td align="center">0.8<sup>ns</sup></td><td align="center">3.8**</td><td align="center">6.1***</td></tr><tr><td align="center">"rusty" &#x02013; "wild-type"</td><td align="center">0.04<sup>ns</sup></td><td align="center">-2.1***</td><td align="center">-3.6**</td><td align="center">-4.1*</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>1</sup>: The quail sample was made up of 215 wild-type, 59 curly, 58 rusty, and 16 curly and rusty quail from 17 full-sib families and born in two successive hatches. *: p &#x0003c; 0.05; **: p &#x0003c; 0.01; ***: p &#x0003c; 0.001; <sup>ns</sup>: not significant.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The two new "curly" and "rusty" mutations will enrich the small number of plumage mutations already available in Japanese quail for studying the genetics and the biology of feathers, a field of research with many perspectives [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. They may have also some interest from a zootechnical standpoint to tag commercial lines, and, if the positive effect of the "curly" mutation was confirmed, this gene might be worth introgressing in parental meat quail lines.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Birds</title><p>The two mutations originated in the experimental quail population maintained and selected on behavioral traits at the INRA Station de recherches avicoles in Nouzilly, France. After two quail lines were established by fixing separately the curly and the rusty phenotypes, eight reciprocal single pair matings (three "rusty &#x000d7; curly" and five "curly &#x000d7; rusty") were set up with G5 rusty and G4 curly quail from the two pure lines to produce the F1. Then, 531 F2 birds were produced in three consecutive hatches from 17 single pair matings of F1 birds. Sib-mating was avoided, and the hatching rate across all pair matings and hatches was 81%. All chicks were pedigreed, and they were phenotyped for plumage color at hatching and for feather structure at 10 days of age. F2 quail from the first two hatches were raised in two group pens (one per hatch) with free access to ad libitum commercial feed and drinking water, and they were weighed weekly until 5 weeks of age.</p></sec><sec><title>Genes</title><p>Gene nomenclature used in this paper followed recommendations published for chicken genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>], with a two-part symbol: "locus abbreviation"*"allele abbreviation/locus", and "locus abbreviation*N" as the symbol for the wild-type allele.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analyses</title><p>Analysis of the segregation in the F2 to test for linkage was carried out using maximum likelihood methodology and the &#x003c7;<sup>2 </sup>test [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. Penetrance and its standard error were estimated as: 1-&#x003bb; = (3c/(a+c)) + d(b+d) and SE = (9ac/(a+c)<sup>3</sup>) + bd/(b+d)<sup>3</sup>, derived for misclassification of phenotypes due to "partial manifestation" [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. In the formulae, a, b, c and d are the numbers of observations in the four phenotypic classes described in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>.</p><p>Five-way analyses of variance of individual body weights (BW) between hatching and 5 weeks of age were carried out by the GLM procedure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>] for the 348 quail hatched alive in the first two hatches, using the following linear model: BW=(overall mean) + hatch + family + sex + (feather structure phenotype) + (plumage color phenotype) + error. The number of classes for the five main effects were respectively, 2, 17, 2, 2 and 2. Contrasts between least-squared means for each mutant phenotype and for the wild-type quail were estimated from the analyses of variance, using data adjusted for systematic effects of hatch, family and sex.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>FM coordinated the study and wrote the paper, DG and CM participated in the design of the study and carried out the the data collection.</p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors wish to thank J.M. Faure (INRA SRA, Nouzilly, France) for kindly providing curly and rusty quail he had found in his experimental population.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Minvielle</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The future of Japanese quail for research and production</article-title><source>World Poult Sci J</source><year>2004</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>500</fpage><lpage>507</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1079/WPS200433</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Somes</surname><given-names>RG</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group><source>International Registry of Poultry Genetic Stocks</source><year>1988</year><publisher-name>Bulletin 476, Storrs Agricultural Experiment Station, University of Connecticut</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsudzuki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Orange: a plumage color mutation accompanied by semi-lethality in Japanese quail</article-title><source>J Hered</source><year>1994</year><volume>85</volume><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>56</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8120359</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Minvielle</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue-Murayama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizutani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wakasugi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic analyses of plumage color mutations on the Z chromosome of Japanese quail</article-title><source>J Hered</source><year>2000</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>499</fpage><lpage>501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11218091</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jhered/91.6.499</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Minvielle</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gourichon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Monvoisin</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of two-locus combinations, using the roux, lavender and beige mutation, on plumage color of Japanese quail</article-title><source>J Hered</source><year>2003</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>517</fpage><lpage>522</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14691319</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jhered/esg091</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miwa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue-Murayama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kayang</surname><given-names>BB</given-names></name><name><surname>Vignal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Minvielle</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Monvoisin</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mapping of plumage color and blood protein genes on the microsatellite linkage map of the Japanese quail</article-title><source>Proceedings of the 29th International Conference on Animal Genetics: September 11&#x02013;16 2004; Tokyo</source><year>2004</year><publisher-name>International Society for Animal Genetics, Japanese Society of Animal Breeding and Genetics</publisher-name><fpage>83</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silversides</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000e9;rat</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Homology of the s<sup>+ </sup>locus in the chicken with Al<sup>+ </sup>in the Japanese quail</article-title><source>J Hered</source><year>1991</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>247</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Minvielle</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gourichon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Monvoisin</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Testing homology of loci for two plumage colors, lavender and recessive white, with chicken and Japanese quail hybrids</article-title><source>J Hered</source><year>2002</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12011184</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jhered/93.1.73</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fawn- a plumage color mutation in Japanese quail</article-title><source>Poult Sci</source><year>1988</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>127</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Minvielle</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirigoyen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Boulay</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Associated effects of the roux plumage color mutation on growth, carcass traits, egg production, and reproduction of Japanese quail</article-title><source>Poult Sci</source><year>1999</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>1479</fpage><lpage>1484</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10560817</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fulton</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Associated porcupine</article-title><source>Poult Sci</source><year>1982</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>429</fpage><lpage>433</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7088798</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crittenden</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Bitgood</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Burt</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ponce de Leon</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tixier-Boichard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nomenclature for naming loci, alleles, linkage groups and chromosomes to be used in poultry genome publications and databases</article-title><source>Genet Sel Evol</source><year>1996</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>297</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>M&#x000e9;rat</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bordas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonon</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Perramon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effets quantitatifs associ&#x000e9;s au g&#x000e8;ne albinos li&#x000e9; au sexe chez la caille japonaise</article-title><source>Ann G&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;t S&#x000e9;l Anim</source><year>1981</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>91</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name><name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Medina</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Widelitz</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>TX</given-names></name><name><surname>Chuong</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The developmental biology of feather follicles</article-title><source>Int J Dev Biol</source><year>2004</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15272383</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name></person-group><source>Genetics and Probability in Animal Breeding Experiments</source><year>1981</year><publisher-name>London: MacMillan Publishers Ltd</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>NTJ</given-names></name></person-group><source>Introduction to the Mathematical Theory of Genetic Linkage</source><year>1961</year><publisher-name>London: Oxford University Press</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>SAS Institute</collab></person-group><source>SAS&#x000ae; User's Guide: Statistics</source><year>1988</year><publisher-name>Cary, SAS Institute Inc</publisher-name></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



