<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Neuroinflammation</journal-id><journal-title>Journal of Neuroinflammation</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1742-2094</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15500684</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC527877</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1742-2094-1-21</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1742-2094-1-21</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Brain inflammation and oxidative stress in a transgenic mouse model of Alzheimer-like brain amyloidosis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Yuemang</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>yuemang@yahoo.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chinnici</surname><given-names>Cinzia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>cinzia@hotmail.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Hanguan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>hanguan@yahoo.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Trojanowski</surname><given-names>John Q</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>trojanowsi@mail.med.upenn.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Virginia MY</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>lee@mail.med.upenn.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A6" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pratic&#x000f2;</surname><given-names>Domenico</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>domenico@spirit.gcrc.upenn.edu</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Center for Experimental Therapeutics and Department of Pharmacology; University of Pennsylvania, School of Medicine, Philadelphia, PA 19104 USA</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Center for Neurodegenerative Disease Research; University of Pennsylvania, School of Medicine, Philadelphia, PA 19104 USA</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Institute on Aging; University of Pennsylvania, School of Medicine, Philadelphia, PA 19104 USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>10</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>1</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jneuroinflammation.com/content/1/1/21"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>9</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>10</month><year>2004</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2004 Yao et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2004</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Yao et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Yao
               Yuemang
               
               yuemang@yahoo.com
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Brain inflammation and oxidative stress in a transgenic mouse model of Alzheimer-like brain amyloidosis
         </dc:title><dc:date>2004</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Journal of Neuroinflammation 1(1): 21-. (2004)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1742-2094(2004)1:1&#x0003c;21&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1742-2094</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>An increasing body of evidence implicates both brain inflammation and oxidative stress in the pathogenesis of Alzheimer's disease (AD). The relevance of their interaction in vivo, however, is unknown. Previously, we have shown that separate pharmacological targeting of these two components results in amelioration of the amyloidogenic phenotype of a transgenic mouse model of AD-like brain amyloidosis (Tg2576).</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>In the present study, we investigated the therapeutic effects of a combination of an anti-inflammatory agent, indomethacin, and a natural anti-oxidant, vitamin E, in the Tg2576 mice. For this reason, animals were treated continuously from 8 (prior to A&#x003b2; deposition) through 15 (when A&#x003b2; deposits are abundant) months of age.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>At the end of the study, these therapeutic interventions suppressed brain inflammatory and oxidative stress responses in the mice. This effect was accompanied by significant reductions of soluble and insoluble A&#x003b2;1-40 and A&#x003b2;1-42 in neocortex and hippocampus, wherein the burden of A&#x003b2; deposits also was significantly decreased.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>The results of the present study support the concept that brain oxidative stress and inflammation coexist in this animal model of AD-like brain amyloidosis, but they represent two distinct therapeutic targets in the disease pathogenesis. We propose that a combination of anti-inflammatory and anti-oxidant drugs may be a useful strategy for treating AD.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Alzheimer's disease (AD) is the most common, complex and challenging form of neurodegenerative disease associated with dementia in the elderly. Neuropathological examination of the AD brain shows extensive neuronal loss, accumulation of fibrillar proteins as extra-cellular amyloid &#x003b2; (A&#x003b2;) plaques, and as neurofibrillary tangles (NFTs) inside neurons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. However, besides these pathological hallmarks, AD brains exhibit clear evidence of chronic inflammation and oxidative damage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Currently, data from human studies as well as animal models strongly support the concept that oxidative imbalance and subsequent oxidative stress are among the earliest events in the pathogenesis of AD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Thus, an increase in lipid peroxidation, protein oxidation and DNA oxidation has been reported not only in AD patients, but also in subjects with mild cognitive impairment (MCI) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Similarly, immunohistochemical and biochemical evidence for these signatures of oxidative stress have been shown in animal models of AD-like brain amyloidosis, i.e. the Tg2576 transgenic mouse model thereof [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. Chronic neuroinflammation is another constant feature of AD, and this also is thought to play a significant role in the onset and progression of AD. Support for this hypothesis comes from epidemiological studies showing that prolonged use of nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) decreases the risk of developing AD as well as delaying the onset of this disorder [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>], while many mediators of inflammation have been detected in the AD brain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Further, recent studies in AD mouse models have shown that chronic treatment with a subset of NSAIDs (e.g. ibuprofen, flurbiprofen, indomethacin) reduced brain inflammation and A&#x003b2; levels in addition to the deposition of A&#x003b2; in brain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Despite this evidence, and the considerable theoretical and therapeutic interest, the relationship between brain inflammation responses and oxidative stress has not yet been clearly delineated in AD. For example, its is possible to consider these two events as elements of the same response mechanism, or they can be envisaged as two separate events. Alternatively, they also could work in concert to contribute synergistically to the pathogenesis of AD.</p><p>In the present study, we examined whether the simultaneous administration of an anti-oxidant, vitamin E, with an anti-inflammatory drug, indomethacin, would exert an additive anti-amyloidogenic effect in the Tg2576 mouse model of AD-like A&#x003b2; brain amyloidosis, one of the most extensively studied mouse models of AD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. Significantly, we found for the first time that coincidental suppression of brain oxidative stress further augments the anti-amylodogenic effect of indomethacin.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Animals</title><p>The genotype and phenotype features of the heterozygote Tg2576 mice that we studied here have been described in earlier reports on these mice from our group [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Mice were weaned at 4 weeks, kept on a chow diet, and males were always separated from females for the entire study. Eight-month-old Tg animals were divided in two groups (n = 10 each), and randomized to receive placebo, or simultaneously indomethacin (10 mg/liter) in their drinking water, and vitamin E (&#x003b1;-tocopherol) in their diet (2 I.U./mg diet) for seven months before being sacrificed. The detailed dosing of the animals receiving indomethacin or vitamin E alone (at the same concentration used in the present study) were described in two previously published studies which also included data on numerous non-transgenenic littermate controls of the Tg2576 mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Fresh drinking water and diet were always replaced every other day. Preliminary experiments demonstrated that the selected dose of indomethacin suppressed total cylcooxygenase-1 activity <italic>in vivo </italic>and significantly reduced brain inflammation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. The high dose of vitamin E was selected based on a previous study, which indicated that at this concentration it significantly reduced brain oxidative stress response [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. During the study, all mice gained weight regularly, and no significant difference was detected between the two groups.</p></sec><sec><title>Tissue preparation</title><p>Animals were anesthetized and euthanized following procedures recommended by the Panel on Euthanasia of the American Veterinary Medical Association. They were always perfused intra-cardially for 30 min with ice-cold 0.9% phosphate buffer saline (PBS), containing EDTA (2 mM/L) and BHT (2 mM/L), pH7.4. Brains were removed and one hemisphere was fixed by immersion in 4% paraformaldehyde in 0.1 M PBS (pH7.4) at 4&#x000b0;C overnight, blocked in the coronal plane, and embedded in paraffin as previously described for immunohistochemistry [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>], The other hemisphere was gently rinsed in cold 0.9% PBS, then immediately dissected in three anatomical regions (total cerebral cortex, hippocampus, and cerebellum) for biochemistry.</p></sec><sec><title>Biochemical analysis</title><p>Tissue samples were minced and homogenized, and total lipid extracted with ice-cold Folch solution (chloroform: methanol; 2:1, vol/vol). Lipids were subjected to base hydrolysis by adding aqueous 15% KOH and then incubated at 45&#x000b0;C for 1 hr for measurement of total iPF<sub>2&#x003b1;</sub>-VI by ion chemical ionization gas chromatography/mass spectrometry assay, as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. In brief, a known amount of the internal standard is added to each sample, after solid phase extraction samples are derivatized and purified by thin layer chromatography, and finally analyzed. An aliquot of these extracts was assayed for total levels of PGE<sub>2 </sub>and TxB<sub>2 </sub>by a standardized ELISA kit following the manufacturer's instructions (Cayman Chem. Com.). Briefly, extracts were diluted with acetate buffer and purified through an affinity column. The purified samples were evaporated, re-dissolved in the assay buffer and applied to 96-well plates pre-coated with goat anti-serum IgG and incubated with PGE<sub>2 </sub>or TxB<sub>2 </sub>monoclonal antibodies. The plates were rinsed with washing buffer and developed using Ellman's reagent for 60&#x02013;90 min at room temperature with gentle shaking. Specific concentrations were determined spectrophotometrically and expressed as pg/mg tissue.</p><p>IL-1&#x003b2; levels were measured by a standardized sandwich ELISA kit following the manufacturer's instructions (Endogen Pierce). Briefly, equal amounts of sample were loaded onto 96-well plate pre-coated with monoclonal antibody against mouse IL-1&#x003b2; overnight at 4&#x000b0;C. The plates were rinsed three times with washing buffer and developed with streptavidin-horseradish peroxidase (HRP) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Specific concentrations were determined spectrophotometrically and expressed as pg/mg protein.</p><p>Total protein carbonyls in tissue were determined by using the Zenith PC test kit according to the manufacturer's instructions (Zenith Tech.) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. Briefly, aliquots of the tissue homogenates were first reacted with dinitrophenylhydrazine (DNP), transferred to a multi-well plate, incubated with blocking reagent, washed and probed with anti-DNP-biotin solution. After washing, samples were incubated with streptavidin-HRP, washed again, and then developed. After 15 min, the reaction was stopped and absorbance immediately read at 450 nm. Oxidized protein standards, internal controls and blanks were always assayed at the same time and in the same way. All samples were always determined in triplicate and in a blind fashion.</p></sec><sec><title>Immunoblot analysis</title><p>An aliquot of brain homogenates was electrophoresed on a 10% acrylamide gel under reducing conditions. Protein were transferred to a polyvinylidene membrane before blocking in 10% nonfat dry milk for 2 hr. Blots were incubated with monoclonal antiboby against glial fibrillary acidic protein (GFAP) (2.2B10) (1:1,000), or an anti-beta actin (1:5,000) antibody overnight at 4&#x000b0;C. After three rinses, blots were incubated with HRP-conjugated goat anti-mouse for 45 min before development with chemiluminescent detection system using ECL (Amersham). Bands were quantified using densitometric software (Molecular Analyst). The anti-GFAP is a monoclonal antibody, and its characterization has previously been published [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] (Zymed Lab. Inc.). The anti-beta actin is from commercial sources (Novus Biological).</p></sec><sec><title>Brain A&#x003b2;1-40 and A&#x003b2;1-42 levels</title><p>Sequential extraction of brain samples was performed with high-salt buffer and formic acid, respectively to measure soluble and insoluble A&#x003b2;1-40 and A&#x003b2;1-42 levels, as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Briefly, cerebral cortex, hippocampus and cerebellum were serially extracted in high-salt Re-assembly buffer (0.1 M Tris, 1 mM EGTA, 0.5 nM Mgso4, 0.75 M NaCl, and 0.02 M NaF, pH 7.0) containing protease inhibitor mixture (pepstatin A, leupeptin, N-tosyl-L-phenylalanine chloromethyl ketone, soybean trypsin inhibitor, each at l &#x003bc;g/ml in 5 mM EDTA). Homogenates were centrifuged at 100,000 &#x000d7; g for 1 hr at 4&#x000b0;C. Supernatants were removed, pellets were re-suspended in 70% formic acid and sonicated and centrifuged at 100,000 &#x000d7; g for 1 hr at 4&#x000b0;C. Supernatants were diluted 1:20 with 1 M Tris base. Samples were mixed with buffer EC [0.02 M sodium Phosphate, 0.2 mM EDTA, 0.4 M NaCl, 0.2% BSA, 0.05% CHAPS, 0.4% Block-ace (Dainippon, Suita, Osaka, Japan), 0.05% sodium azide, pH7.0] and analyzed directly using Ban 50/BA27 for A&#x003b2;1-40 or Ban50/BC-05 for A&#x003b2;1-42/43 sandwich ELISA system as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Results were expressed as pmol/g tissue. The values were calculated by comparison with a standard curve of synthetic A&#x003b2;1-40 and A&#x003b2;1-42. Analyses were always performed in duplicates and in a coded fashion.</p></sec><sec><title>Burden of brain A&#x003b2; deposits</title><p>Serial 6-&#x003bc;m-thick paraffin sections were cut throughout each brain, and mounted on APES-coated slides. Sections were deparaffmized, hydrated, rinsed with PBS and pre-treated with formic acid (88%) for 10 min to antigen retrieval, and with 3% H<sub>2</sub>0<sub>2 </sub>in methanol for 30 min to eliminate endogenous peroxidase activity in the tissue and with the blocking solution (5% normal horse serum in Tris buffer, pH 7.6). Subsequently, sections were incubated with a biotinylated antibody against A&#x003b2; (4G8) (1:10,000 dilution), at 4&#x000b0;C overnight [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Sections were then incubated with secondary antibody for 1 hr (dilution 1:1,000), then reacted with horse-peroxidase-avidin-biotin complex (Vector Lab.), and immuncomplexes visualized by using 3,3'-diaminobenzidine as the chromogen. Finally, they were dehydrated with ethanol, cleared with xylene and coversliped with Cytoseal. As control, sections from the same group of animals were treated in the same manner, except for the primary antibody. Light microscopic images from the somatosensory cortex, perihippocampal cortex, and hippocampus were captured from eight series of sections using a Nikon Microphot-FXA microscope with 4 &#x000d7; objective lens. The area occupied by A&#x003b2;-immunoreactive products in the region of interest were identified, and the total area occupied by the outlined structures was measured to calculate: 1) the total area with selected immunoreactive products, 2) the percentage of the area occupied by immunoreactive products over the outlined anatomical area in the image, as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Analyses were always performed in a coded fashion.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Data are expressed as mean &#x000b1; standard error of mean (S.E.M.), analyzed by analysis of variance (ANOVA), and subsequently by student unpaired 2-tailed <italic>t </italic>test corrected for multiple comparisons. Significance was set at p &#x0003c; 0.05.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Starting at eight months of age, Tg2576 mice were randomized to receive placebo or vitamin E (2 I.U./mg diet) added to their diet, plus indomethacin (l0 mg/liter) in their water, and they were treated until they were 15 months old. Notably, at 8 months of age, the Tg2576 mice show elevated brain levels of soluble and insoluble A&#x003b2; as well as isoprostanes, relative to their non-transgenic littermates, but they show no evidence of any brain A&#x003b2; deposits, while following the initial onset of mature plaque-like brain deposits at about 11&#x02013;12 months of age, the Tg2576 mice show abundant A&#x003b2; deposits and higher levels of isoprostanes in neocortex and hippocampus a 15 months of age [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. Assuming that each mouse eats 4&#x02013;5 mg chow/day, the estimated average vitamin E intake for each animal was ~8&#x02013;10 I.U./day. Assuming that each mouse drinks 3 to 4 mL water/day, the estimated daily intake of indomethacin was calculated around 30&#x02013;40 ng. At the end of the study, body weight, total plasma cholesterol, triglycerides and peripheral blood cell count were not different between placebo and active treatment (not shown). Compared with placebo, Tg2576 mice receiving indomethacin plus vitamin E at the same time had a significant reduction in PGE<sub>2 </sub>and suppression of TxB<sub>2 </sub>levels in tissue homogenates from total cortex and hippocampus (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Further, the presence of vitamin E significantly reduced two independent markers of oxidative stress injury in both brain regions. Thus, neocortex and hippocampus levels of iPF<sub>2&#x003b1;</sub>-VI (a reliable biomarker of lipid peroxidation), as well as protein carbonyls (known biomarkers of protein oxidation) were both significantly decreased (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Compliance with the diet was evident from the rise in brain levels of vitamin E (+57%) in the mice receiving the supplemented chow.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Effects of indomethacin plus vitamin E on total brain cortex levels of PGE<sub>2</sub>, TxB<sub>2 </sub>and IL-1&#x003b2; in Tg2576 mice. Mice were treated starting at 8-months of age until they were 15-month-old (n = 10 animals per group).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="center"><bold>Placebo</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Indomethacin Vitamin E</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>P</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">PGE<sub>2 </sub>(pg/mg tissue)</td><td align="center">92 &#x000b1; 8</td><td align="center">39 &#x000b1; 5*</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="center">TxB<sub>2 </sub>(pg/mg tissue)</td><td align="center">148 &#x000b1; 10</td><td align="center">15 &#x000b1; 4*</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="center">IL-1&#x003b2; (pg/mg protein)</td><td align="center">75 &#x000b1; 12</td><td align="center">33 &#x000b1; 8*</td><td align="center">&#x0003c;0.01</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Values are expressed as means &#x000b1; S.E.M.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Effect of indomethacin plus vitamin E supplementation on markers of brain oxidative stress. Total cerebral cortex homogenates from Tg2576 receiving placebo (open bars) or the combination therapy (closed bars) were assayed for levels of iPF<sub>2&#x003b1;</sub>-VI (upper panel) and protein carbonyls (lower panel) (*p &#x0003c; 0.01, n = 10 per group).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1742-2094-1-21-1"/></fig><p>Western blot analysis was used to determine the effect of the drug treatment on GFAP levels, a marker of astrocytosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. These levels were significantly lower in the treated than in the placebo group (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). Another marker of brain inflammation was also assessed, i.e. IL-1&#x003b2;, which has been reported to be increased in these mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Compared with placebo, we found that IL-1&#x003b2; levels were significantly reduced by 55% in homogenates from neocortex (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>), and 61% in hippocampus (not shown) of the mice receiving the combination therapy.</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Effect of indomethacin plus vitamin E supplementation on GFAP levels. GFAP and actin levels were detected by immunoblots in homogenates from total cortex of Tg2576 administered with placebo (open bars) or indomethacin plus vitamin E (closed bars) (*p &#x0003c; 0.02, n = 8 per group).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1742-2094-1-21-2"/></fig><p>Next, we assessed the effect of indomethacin and vitamin E on brain levels of soluble and insoluble A&#x003b2;1-40 and A&#x003b2;1-42. As expected for their age, Tg2576 mice on placebo showed elevated levels of both forms of these peptides in their cortex and hippocampus (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>), whereas cerebellum had much lower levels (not shown). Soluble A&#x003b2;1-40 and A&#x003b2;1-42 were reduced by ~65% in both neocortex and hippocampus homogenates from treated mice (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Further, we found that the combination of vitamin E with indomethacin resulted in a significant reduction (55% and 59%) of the insoluble fraction of these peptides in both brain regions (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). The same treatment had no effect on both forms of A&#x003b2; in the cerebellum of Tg2576 compared with placebo (not shown). Amyloid deposits were widely present in the cerebral cortex and hippocampus of Tg2576 mice at 15 months of age, as previously reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. To determine the effect of this treatment on amyloid deposition, the areas occupied by 4G8-immunopositive reactions were analyzed in three different brain regions: the somatosensory cortex (SSC), perihippocampal cortex (PHC), and hippocampus (HIP) areas. Comparison of the burden of A&#x003b2; positive deposits between placebo and combination therapy groups revealed a significant reduction for the amyloid burden in all three regions considered (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Effect of indomethacin plus vitamin E supplementation on soluble A&#x003b2; levels. Levels of high salt soluble A&#x003b2;1-40 and A&#x003b2;1-42 in total cortex and hippocampus of Tg2576 on placebo (open bars), or indomethacin plus vitamin E (closed bars) (*p &#x0003c; 0.01, n = 8 per group).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1742-2094-1-21-3"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Effect of indomethacin plus vitamin E supplementation on insoluble A&#x003b2; levels. Levels of formic acid soluble A&#x003b2;1-40 and A&#x003b2;1-42 in total cortex and hippocampus homogenates from Tg2576 receiving placebo (open bars) or indomethacin plus vitamin E (closed bars) (*p &#x0003c; 0.001, n = 8 per group).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1742-2094-1-21-4"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Effect of indomethacin plus vitamin E supplementation on amyloid deposition. Percentage area of somatosensory cortex (SSC), hippocampus (HIP) and parahippocampal cortex (PHC) occupied by A&#x003b2; immunoreactive deposits in Tg2576 receiving placebo (open bars), or indomethacin plus vitamin E (closed bars) for seven months (*p &#x0003c; 0.001; n = 8 per group).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1742-2094-1-21-5"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Representative pictures of brain sections from mice on placebo or receiving indomethacin plus vitamin E.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1742-2094-1-21-6"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>There is substantial evidence implicating both oxidative stress and inflammatory mechanisms in AD pathogenesis. Evidence for oxidative stress derives from both human (post-mortem and living patients) studies, and transgenic mouse models of the disease. There is a long list of surrogate markers of reactive oxygen species-mediated injury that have been found increased in the brain and cerebrospinal fluid of AD patients. It includes, just to mention a few, malondialdehyde, 4-hydroxynonenal, F<sub>2</sub>-isoprostanes (lipid peroxidation); protein carbonyls, nitrotyrosine (protein oxdidation); 8-hydroxy-2'-deoxyguanosine (DNA oxidation) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Transgenic animals show the same type of oxidative damage that is found in AD, and it directly correlates with the presence of A&#x003b2; deposits [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. Oxidative stress also precedes amyloid deposition in human AD, the Tg2576 and a transgenic <italic>Caernorhabditis elegans </italic>model, which over-expresses A&#x003b2;1-42 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. Furthermore, dietary or genetic perturbation of the anti-oxidant defense system causes exacerbation of the amyloid pathology characteristic of Tg models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. Taken together, the data accumulated so far clearly indicate that oxidative imbalance and subsequent chronic oxidative stress are not only early events, but they also play a functional role in AD pathogenesis. Based on this evidence we started the treatment at an early stage before the amyloid deposition occurs.</p><p>Inflammatory mechanisms are also operative in the AD brain and significantly contribute to the pathophysiology of the disease. Although classical defined inflammation, including such features as edema and neutrophil invasion, is not seen in the AD brain, hallmark of innate immune response are constant elements of the neuropathology associated with brain degeneration in AD [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Further, evidence that inflammation contributes to the AD pathogenesis stems out from several retrospective epidemiological studies showing a significant reduction in the risk of AD associated with a prolonged usage of NSAIDs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. Tg2576 mice display age-related neocortical and hippocampal amyloid deposits, which correlate with microglia activation, reactive astrocytes with increased GFAP, IL-1&#x003b2; levels, and dystrophic neuritis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. Furthermore, plaque-associated reactive microglia in these animals show enhanced staining for TNF&#x003b1; and IL-1&#x003b2; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>].</p><p>Lim et al. first reported that chronic administration of the NSAID ibuprofen to Tg2576 reduces total A&#x003b2; levels, amyloid burden and brain inflammation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. More recently, we showed that a high dose of indomethacin, another NSAIDs member, which fully suppresses total cyclooxygenase (COX)-l activity, by modulating brain inflammation response reduces soluble A&#x003b2;1-40 and A&#x003b2;1-42, and insoluble A&#x003b2;1-42 but not A&#x003b2;1-40 levels in the same model. This effect was accompanied by a significant reduction of the amyloid burden in the hippocampus of these mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. However, recent studies indicate that a subset of NSAIDs, including indomethacin, also possesses a direct, COX-independent A&#x003b2;-lowering capacity in cell cultures as well as transgenic models [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. Further, we showed that vitamin E alone at the same high dose used in this study decreased soluble and insoluble A&#x003b2;1-40 and A&#x003b2;1-42 levels by ~28% and ~35%, respectively. This effect was associated with a significant reduction in amyloid deposition in the somatosensory cortex, but not in the hippocampus or parahippocampal areas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>].</p><p>In the present study, we extended these previous observations by examining whether administration of indomethacin in combination with vitamin E would result in a better anti-amyloidotic effect. Our findings show that soluble A&#x003b2;1-40 and A&#x003b2;1-42 levels were reduced by ~65%, while the insoluble fractions were decreased by ~55%. Consistently, we observed a better and more diffuse effect also on the amount of amyloid deposited in the brain at the end of the study. Finally, the two drugs together produced an additive affect on brain inflammation and oxidative stress [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>].</p><p>Our results confirm previous observation where low-dose curcumin, a drug with reported both anti-oxidant and anti-inflammatory activities, reduced total A&#x003b2; and plaque burden [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. However, several other mechanisms of action, unrelated to inflammation or oxidation, could underlie the effect of this compound in vivo, and the relative importance of each of them for the anti-amyloid effect observed is still unclear [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>].</p><p>In our study, we used two different drugs with a more restricted therapeutic target to provide further evidence that both oxidative stress and inflammation are indeed functionally relevant in the development of the phenotype of these animals. However, we also provide new information on the critical issue of the in vivo relationship between these two events. Thus, our results suggest that brain inflammation and oxidative stress are two separate events, which work in concert to modulate the development of this AD-like brain A&#x003b2; amyloidosis model. Previously, we have shown that a full dose of indomethacin alone despite a significant reduction in brain inflammation had only a marginal effect on brain oxidative stress in the Tg2576 mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. This finding suggests that lipid peroxidation products contribute minimally to brain inflammation in this model, and raise the possibility that vitamin E alone might have influenced amyloidosis by other mechanisms related to its anti-oxidant effect, such as inflammation. Thus, we observed that this antioxidant further suppressed both amyloidosis and brain inflammation when combined with indomethacin.</p><p>In summary, our findings support the hypothesis that oxidative stress and inflammation represent important but distinct therapeutic targets in AD-like amyloidosis. We conclude that a combination of therapeutic agents targeting these different disease-modulating mechanisms might be rationally evaluated in the prevention or therapy of AD in humans.</p></sec><sec><title>List of abbreviations</title><p>AD: Alzheimer's disease</p><p>A&#x003b2;: Amyloid &#x003b2; peptide</p><p>Tg: Transgenic mouse model</p><p>NSAIDs: Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs</p><p>PGE<sub>2</sub>: Prostaglandin E<sub>2</sub></p><p>TxB<sub>2</sub>: Thromboxane A<sub>2</sub></p><p>GFAP: Glial fibrillary acidic protein</p><p>IL-1&#x003b2;: Interleukin 1-&#x003b2;</p><p>IPF<sub>2&#x003b1;</sub>-VI: Isoprostane F<sub>2&#x003b1;</sub>-VI</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>Yuemang Yao and Cinzia Chinnici have made substantial contribution to the acquisition of data and biochemical analyses. Hanguan Tang contributed to the immunohistochemical analyses. John Q. Trojanowski and Virginia M-Y Lee have been involved in the interpretation of data, and the critical revision of the manuscript for intellectual content. Domenico Pratic&#x000f2; has been involved in the conception and design of the studies, interpretation of data, drafting and critical revision of the manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported by grants form the National Institute of Health (AG-11542, AG-22512), the Alzheimer's Association (IIRG-02-4010), and the CART Fund. We thank Dr. Karen Hsiao (now Dr. Karen Ashe) for the generous gift of the Tg2576 line of mice, and Ms. Susan Leight for assistance with the ELISAs.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Clark CM, Trojanowski JQ</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical manifestations and diagnostic evaluation of patients with Alzheimer's disease</article-title><source>Neurodegenerative dementias: clinical; features and pathological mechanisms</source><year>2000</year><publisher-name>New York: McGraw-Hill</publisher-name><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>114</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pratic&#x000f2;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Trojanowski</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inflammatory hypotheses: novel mechanisms of Alzheimer's neurodegeneration and new therapeutic targets?</article-title><source>Neurobiol Aging</source><year>2000</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>441</fpage><lpage>445</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10858591</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0197-4580(00)00141-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pratic&#x000f2;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Delanty</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oxidative injury in diseases of the Central Nervous System: focus on Alzheimer's disease</article-title><source>Am J Med</source><year>2000</year><volume>1009</volume><fpage>577</fpage><lpage>585</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0002-9343(00)00547-7</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pratic&#x000f2;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alzheimer's disease and oxygen radicals: new insights</article-title><source>Biochem Pharmacol</source><year>2002</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>563</fpage><lpage>567</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11992623</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-2952(01)00919-4</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rottkamp</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Nunomura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Raina</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oxidative stress in Alzheimer's disease</article-title><source>Biochem Biophys Acta</source><year>2000</year><volume>1502</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10899439</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pratic&#x000f2;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Liun</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>VM-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Trojanowski</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increase of brain oxidative stress in mild cognitive impairment: a possible predictor of Alzheimer's disease</article-title><source>Arch Neurol</source><year>2002</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>972</fpage><lpage>976</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12056933</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archneur.59.6.972</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mecocci</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oxidative stress in mild cognitive impairment and Alzheimer's disease: a continuum</article-title><source>J Alzhelmers Dis</source><year>2004</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>163</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pappolla</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chyan</surname><given-names>Y-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Omar</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsiao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bozner</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence of oxidative stress and in vivo neurotoxicity of &#x003b2;-amyloid in a transgenic mouse model of Alzheimer's disease</article-title><source>Am J Pathol</source><year>1998</year><volume>152</volume><fpage>871</fpage><lpage>877</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9546346</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pratic&#x000f2;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Uryu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Leight</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Trojanowski</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>VM-Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increased lipid peroxidation precedes amyloid plaque formation in an animal model of Alzheimer amyloidosis</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2001</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>4183</fpage><lpage>4187</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11404403</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsuoka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Picciano</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>La Francois</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Duff</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fibrillary &#x003b2;-amyloid evokes oxidative damage in a transgenic mouse model of Alzheimer's disease</article-title><source>Neuroscience</source><year>2001</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>609</fpage><lpage>613</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11440793</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0306-4522(01)00115-4</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawas</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Corrada</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Metter</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Risk of Alzheimer's disease and duration of NSAID use</article-title><source>Neurology</source><year>1997</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>626</fpage><lpage>632</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9065537</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Neuroinflammation Working Group</collab></person-group><article-title>Inflammation and Alzheimer's disease</article-title><source>Neurobiol Aging</source><year>2000</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>383</fpage><lpage>421</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10858586</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0197-4580(00)00124-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Beech</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Teter</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ubeda</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsiao Ashe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Frautschy</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ibuprofen suppresses plaque pathology and inflammation in a mouse model of Alzheimer's disease</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2000</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>5709</fpage><lpage>5714</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10908610</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jantzen</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Connor</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Dicarlo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wenk</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Rojiani</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Coppola</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microglia activation and &#x003b2;-amyloid deposit reduction caused by a nitric oxide-releasing nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drug in amyloid precursor protein plus presenilin-1 transgenic mice</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2002</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>2246</fpage><lpage>2254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11896164</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsiao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilsen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hargaya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Younkin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Correlative memory deficits, A&#x003b2; elevation, and amyloid plaque in transgenic mice</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1996</year><volume>274</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8810256</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.274.5284.99</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Uryu</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Shineman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Trojanowski</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>VM-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Pratic&#x000f2;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modulation of NF-&#x003ba; activity by indomethacin influences A&#x003b2; levels but not APP metabolism in a model of Alzheimer disease</article-title><source>Am J Pathol</source><year>2004</year><comment></comment></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Uryu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>VM-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Trojanowski</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pratic&#x000f2;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Early vitamin E supplementation in young but not aged mice reduces A&#x003b2; levels and deposition in a transgenic model of Alzheimer's disease</article-title><source>FASEB J</source><year>2004</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>323</fpage><lpage>325</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14656990</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stackman</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckenstein</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Frei</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kulhanek</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Nowlin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevention of age-related spatial memory deficits in a transgenic mouse model of Alzheimer's disease by chronic ginkgo biloba treatment</article-title><source>Exp Neurol</source><year>2003</year><volume>184</volume><fpage>510</fpage><lpage>520</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14637120</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0014-4886(03)00399-6</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kosik</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Orecchio</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Binder</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Trojanowski</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>VM-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Epitopes that span the tau molecule are shared with paired helical filaments</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>1988</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>817</fpage><lpage>825</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2483104</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0896-6273(88)90129-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawarabayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Younkin</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Saido</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>Shoji</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsiao Ashe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Younkin</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Age-dependent changes in brain, CSF, and plasma amyloid &#x003b2; protein in the Tg2576 transgenic mouse model of Alzheimer's disease</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2001</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>372</fpage><lpage>381</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11160418</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsiao</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Pappolla</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>PLR</given-names></name><name><surname>Siedlak</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabaton</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Amyloid &#x003b2; deposition in Alzheimer transgenic mice is associated with oxidative stress</article-title><source>J Neurochem</source><year>1998</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>2212</fpage><lpage>2215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9572310</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drake</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Link</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Butterfiled</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oxidative stress precedes fibrillar deposition of Alzheimer's disease amyloid beta-peptide (1&#x02013;42) in a transgenic Caernorhabditis elegans</article-title><source>Neurobiol Aging</source><year>2003</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>415</fpage><lpage>420</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12600717</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0197-4580(02)00225-7</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nunomura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Aliev</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Irai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Takeda</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Balraj</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghanbari</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wataya</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimohana</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiba</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Atwood</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Oxidative stress is the earliest event in Alzheimer's disease</article-title><source>J Neuropathol Exp Neurol</source><year>2001</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>759</fpage><lpage>767</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11487050</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pratic&#x000f2;</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Uryu</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sung</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Trojanowski</surname><given-names>JQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>VM-Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aluminum modulates brain amyloidosis through oxidative stress in APP transgenic mice</article-title><source>FASEB J</source><year>2002</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1138</fpage><lpage>1140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12039845</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Calingasan</surname><given-names>NY</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mauck</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name><name><surname>Toidze</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Beal</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Gouras</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increased plaque burden in brains of APP mutant MnSOD heterozygous knockout mice</article-title><source>J Neurochem</source><year>2004</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>1308</fpage><lpage>1312</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15147524</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1471-4159.2004.02455.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frautschy</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Irizarry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Saido</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microglia response to amyloid plaques in APPswe transgenic mice</article-title><source>Am J Pathol</source><year>1998</year><volume>152</volume><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>317</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9422548</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benzing</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wujek</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name><name><surname>Shaffer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashe</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Younkin</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunder</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence for glial-mediated inflammation in aged APPsw transgenic mice</article-title><source>Neurobiol Aging</source><year>2000</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>581</fpage><lpage>589</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10674423</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0197-4580(99)00065-2</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gasparini</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ongini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wenk</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) in Alzheimer's disease: old and new mechanisms of action</article-title><source>J Neurochem</source><year>2004</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>521</fpage><lpage>536</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15485484</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1471-4159.2004.02743.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>GP</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Beech</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Frautschy</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The curry spice curcumin reduces oxidative damage and amyloid pathology in an Alzheimer transgenic mouse</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>2001</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>8370</fpage><lpage>8377</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11606625</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kellof</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Criwell</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Steele</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lubert</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Malone</surname><given-names>WA</given-names></name><name><surname>Boone</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kopelovich</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawk</surname><given-names>ET</given-names></name><name><surname>Lieberman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Viner</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sigman</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Progress in cancer chemoprevention: development of diet-derived chemopreventive agents</article-title><source>J Nutr</source><year>2000</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>467</fpage><lpage>471</lpage></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



