<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ann Clin Microbiol Antimicrob</journal-id><journal-title>Annals of Clinical Microbiology and Antimicrobials</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1476-0711</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15287988</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC509281</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1476-0711-3-15</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1476-0711-3-15</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Activity of telithromycin and comparators against bacterial pathogens isolated from 1,336 patients with clinically diagnosed acute sinusitis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dohar</surname><given-names>Joseph</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>Joseph.Dohar@chp.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cant&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>Rafael</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>rafael.canton@smmc.es</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>robert.cohen@wanadoo.fr</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Farrell</surname><given-names>David John</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><email>d.farrell@grmicro.co.uk</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Felmingham</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><email>d.felmingham@grmicro.co.uk</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Pediatric Otolaryngology, Children's Hospital of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, USA</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Hospital Ramon y Cajal, Madrid, Spain</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Department of Microbiology, Intercommunal Hospital of Creteil, Creteil, France</aff><aff id="I4"><label>4</label>GR Micro Limited, London, United Kingdom</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>2</day><month>8</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ann-clinmicrob.com/content/3/1/15"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>4</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>8</month><year>2004</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2004 Dohar et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2004</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Dohar et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Dohar
               Joseph
               
               Joseph.Dohar@chp.edu
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Activity of telithromycin and comparators against bacterial pathogens isolated from 1,336 patients with clinically diagnosed acute sinusitis
         </dc:title><dc:date>2004</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Annals of Clinical Microbiology and Antimicrobials 3(1): 15-. (2004)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1476-0711(2004)3:1&#x0003c;15&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1476-0711</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Increasing antimicrobial resistance among the key pathogens responsible for community-acquired respiratory tract infections has the potential to limit the effectiveness of antibiotics available to treat these infections. Since there are regional differences in the susceptibility patterns observed and treatment is frequently empirical, the selection of antibiotic therapy may be challenging. PROTEKT, a global, longitudinal multicentre surveillance study, tracks the activity of telithromycin and comparator antibacterial agents against key respiratory tract pathogens.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>In this analysis, we examine the prevalence of antibacterial resistance in 1,336 bacterial pathogens, isolated from adult and paediatric patients clinically diagnosed with acute bacterial sinusitis (ABS).</p></sec><sec><title>Results and discussion</title><p>In total, 58.0%, 66.1%, and 55.8% of <italic>S. pneumoniae </italic>isolates were susceptible to penicillin, cefuroxime, and clarithromycin respectively. Combined macrolide resistance and reduced susceptibility to penicillin was present in 200/640 (31.3 %) of <italic>S. pneumoniae </italic>isolates (128 isolates were resistant to penicillin [MIC &#x0003e;= 2 mg/L], 72 intermediate [MIC 0.12&#x02013;1 mg/L]) while 99.5% and 95.5% of isolates were susceptible to telithromycin and amoxicillin-clavulanate, respectively. In total, 88.2%, 87.5%, 99.4%, 100%, and 100% of <italic>H. influenzae </italic>isolates were susceptible to ampicillin, clarithromycin, cefuroxime, telithromycin, and amoxicillin-clavulanate, respectively. In vitro, telithromycin demonstrated the highest activity against <italic>M. catarrhalis </italic>(MIC<sub>50 </sub>= 0.06 mg/L, MIC<sub>90 </sub>= 0.12 mg/L).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The high <italic>in vitro </italic>activity of against pathogens commonly isolated in ABS, together with a once daily dosing regimen and clinical efficacy with 5-day course of therapy, suggest that telithromycin may play a role in the empiric treatment of ABS.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>The incidences of both the acute and chronic forms of sinusitis have been increasing, and between 10 and 15% of the population of central Europe are affected annually [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. There are an estimated 30 million cases of ABS in the USA each year [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Acute sinusitis accounts for 0.5&#x02013;2.0% of all upper respiratory tract infections in adults and between 5&#x02013;10% in children and therefore is a common reason for visits to primary care physicians [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Although usually mild in severity, complications can be life threatening, including meningitis, brain abscess, orbital cellulitis and abscess, subempyema, osteomyelitis, and nasal polyposis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>].</p><p><italic>S. pneumoniae </italic>is the most common pathogenic bacterium responsible for ABS, isolated in 30&#x02013;50% of cases, followed by <italic>H. influenzae</italic>, isolated in 20&#x02013;40% of cases. <italic>Moraxella catarrhalis </italic>is isolated in 5&#x02013;10% of cases, beta haemolytic streptococci in less than 5%, and <italic>Staphylococcus aureus </italic>in less than 10% although it is often found co-infecting with other bacteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>].</p><p>Treatment options for ABS are controversial as up to 40% of patients recover spontaneously, however, studies have shown that treatment with an antibacterial reduces the time to recovery from sinusitis, improves symptoms, and helps to prevent complications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Guidelines on antibacterial use for ABS vary, possibly because of different regulations, antibacterial resistance patterns, and etiology in different countries, however, the choice of first-line antibacterial is similar across treatment guidelines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Nearly all recommend amoxicillin, as it is active against the major causative pathogens of AMS and is generally well tolerated. For patients with penicillin allergy, the recommended first-line agents vary in different countries. Trimethoprim or trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole is commonly recommended [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. In addition, the French guidelines have recently been reviewed and telithromycin has been included as an alternative first-line agent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. Macrolides are not included in the French guidelines due to the high macrolide resistance prevalence in France [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>].</p><p>Second line, or alternative antibacterial agents of choice, are clarithromycin or second-generation cephalosporins such as cefuroxime and cefpodoxime, third-generation cephalosporins such as cefdinir, and trimethoprim-sulphamethoxazole [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Telithromycin has been recommended as an alternative agent in Germany [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. High-dose amoxicillin-clavulanate should be used if the patient does not improve [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. In France, anti-pneumococcal fluoroquinolones are recommended after bacterial confirmation or if the patient is at high risk of complications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. A single dose of ceftriaxone can be used in a child who cannot be treated orally, i.e. vomiting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>].</p><p>However, due to increasing levels of resistance in bacterial respiratory tract pathogens to these commonly used antibacterials (particularly the rapid emergence of penicillin-and macrolide-resistant strains of pneumococci), new agents are required that have high <italic>in vitro </italic>activity and demonstrated clinical efficacy against bacterial pathogens causing community-acquired respiratory tract infections (RTI's) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. Telithromycin is the first ketolide approved for clinical use. The ketolides are semisynthetic derivatives of the 14-membered ring macrolide erythromycin and have high <italic>in vitro </italic>activity against the common community-acquired RTI pathogens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. Clinical trials have demonstrated the efficacy and tolerability of telithromycin therapy in ABS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>].</p><p>The PROTEKT (Prospective Resistant Organism Tracking and Epidemiology for the Ketolide Telithromycin) study is a longitudinal, global multicentre surveillance study designed in part to determine the activity of telithromycin against community-acquired RTI isolates, in relation to the frequency of prescribing, in the regions where the study is conducted [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. The aim of this paper is to focus on the data gathered in the PROTEKT surveillance study to determine the in vitro efficacy of the new ketolide telithromycin and comparator agents against bacterial pathogens isolated from the subset of patients with clinically diagnosed ABS collected in PROTEKT (2000&#x02013;2001, and 2001&#x02013;2002).</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Patients and bacterial isolates</title><p>Detailed study design, including patient selection and methodology for isolate identification and storage in the PROTEKT study has been described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. The isolates in this sub-study of PROTEKT were selected from those patients presenting with clinically diagnosed ABS in which the isolates were determined clinically to be the pathogenic organism and the specimen type was sinus aspirate or nasopharyngeal swab/aspirate only. Methodology for sinus aspiration was that used routinely by the investigator.</p></sec><sec><title>Antimicrobial testing</title><p>MIC susceptibility status was determined, using the National Committee of Clinical and Laboratory Standards (NCCLS) breakpoints, at a central laboratory (GR Micro Ltd, London, UK) from a panel of existing and new antibacterials, using the NCCLS broth microdilution method and lyophilised microtitre plates (Sensititre, Trek Diagnostics) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. NCCLS breakpoints were used for interpretation of MIC's [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. Tentative NCCLS breakpoints for telithromycin are: <italic>S. pneumoniae </italic>and <italic>S. aureus</italic>, &#x02264; 1 &#x003bc;g/ml is susceptible, 2 &#x003bc;g/ml is intermediate, and &#x02265; 4 &#x003bc;g/ml is resistant; for <italic>Haemophilus influenzae</italic>, &#x02264; 4 &#x003bc;g/ml is susceptible, 8 &#x003bc;g/ml is intermediate, and &#x02265; 16 &#x003bc;g/ml is resistant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Statistical analysis was performed using a &#x003c7;<sup>2 </sup>test.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>A total of 1,336 bacterial pathogens in all were collected from 25 countries within Western Europe (<italic>n </italic>= 652), North America (<italic>n </italic>= 14), Latin America (<italic>n </italic>= 207), Asia (<italic>n </italic>= 464), Eastern Europe (<italic>n </italic>= 68), Australia (<italic>n </italic>= 2), and South Africa (<italic>n </italic>= 126) in the PROTEKT study from years 2000&#x02013;2001 and 2001&#x02013;2002 for analysis of the susceptibility of bacterial pathogens isolated from patients with acute sinusitis. Gender distribution was 52.2% male (695 patients), 46.7% female (624 patients); gender was not provided for 1.3% of patients. Almost two thirds (66.3%) of patients were in the 0&#x02013;12 year age group, one third (29.7%) in the 13&#x02013;65 year age group, 2.7% in the over 65 year age group and age was not specified in 1.3% of patients. <italic>S. pneumoniae </italic>was the pathogen most frequently isolated (47.9% of isolates) followed by <italic>H. influenzae </italic>(24.6% of isolates) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Distribution of species by specimen type for the 1336 bacterial pathogens causing acute sinusitis [n (%)]</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left"><bold>Specimen</bold></td><td align="center"><bold><italic>S. pneumoniae</italic></bold></td><td align="center"><bold><italic>H. influenzae</italic></bold></td><td align="center"><bold><italic>M. catarrhalis</italic></bold></td><td align="center"><bold><italic>S. aureus</italic></bold></td><td align="center"><bold><italic>S. pyogenes</italic></bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Total</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Sinus</td><td align="center">272 (47.5)</td><td align="center">148 (25.9)</td><td align="center">67 (11.7)</td><td align="center">64 (11.2)</td><td align="center">21 (3.7)</td><td align="center">572 (42.8)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Nasopharynx<sup>1</sup></td><td align="center">368 (48.1)</td><td align="center">181 (23.7)</td><td align="center">145 (19.0)</td><td align="center">52 (6.8)</td><td align="center">18 (2.4)</td><td align="center">764 (57.2)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Total</td><td align="center">640 (47.9)</td><td align="center">329 (24.6)</td><td align="center">212 (15.9)</td><td align="center">116 (8.7)</td><td align="center">39 (2.9)</td><td align="center">1336 (100)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>1</sup>Aspirate or swab</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>MIC data for isolates from patients with ABS demonstrated that the <italic>in vitro </italic>activity of telithromycin against gram-positive cocci was similar to amoxicillin-clavulanate and was higher and more potent than clarithromycin and beta-lactams tested such as cefuroxime (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). In total, 99.5 % of streptococcal isolates were susceptible to telithromycin. With the exception of <italic>S. aureus </italic>isolates more than 90% of gram-positive cocci were inhibited at a telithromycin MIC of 0.25 mg/L (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><italic>In vitro </italic>activity of antibacterial agents and percent susceptible against 1336 bacterial pathogens isolated from patients with clinically diagnosed acute sinusitis</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td align="left"><bold>Organism</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>N (total, SA<sup>1</sup>, NP<sup>2</sup>)</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>Antibiotic</bold></td><td align="center" colspan="3"><bold>MIC (mg/L)</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>Percent susceptible </bold>(Total, <italic>SA, NP</italic>)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td colspan="3"><hr></hr></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="left"><bold>Range</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>50</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>90</bold></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold><italic>S. pneumoniae</italic></bold></td><td align="left">640, 272, 368</td><td align="left">Penicillin</td><td align="left">0.008 &#x02013; 8</td><td align="left">0.06</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">58.0, <italic>64.7, 53.0</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Amoxicillin-clavulanate</td><td align="left">0.015 &#x02013; 8</td><td align="left">0.03</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">95.5, <italic>95.2, 95.7</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Cefuroxime</td><td align="left">0.015 &#x02013; 16</td><td align="left">0.12</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">66.1, <italic>73.2, 60.9</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Cefpodoxime</td><td align="left">0.12 &#x02013; 32</td><td align="left">0.12</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">65.0, <italic>71.7, 60.1</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Trimethoprim-sulphamethoxazole</td><td align="left">0.12 &#x02013; 32</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">56.3, <italic>58.1, 54.9</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Erythromycin</td><td align="left">0.03 - &#x0003e;64</td><td align="left">0.06</td><td align="left">&#x0003e;64</td><td align="left">55.9, <italic>60.7, 52.5</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Clarithromycin</td><td align="left">0.015 - &#x0003e;32</td><td align="left">0.06</td><td align="left">&#x0003e;32</td><td align="left">55.8, <italic>60.7, 52.2</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Azithromycin</td><td align="left">0.03 - &#x0003e;64</td><td align="left">0.12</td><td align="left">&#x0003e;64</td><td align="left">55.8, <italic>60.7, 52.2</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Telithromycin</td><td align="left">0.008 &#x02013; 8</td><td align="left">0.015</td><td align="left">0.12</td><td align="left">99.5, <italic>98.9, 100</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold><italic>H. influenzae</italic></bold></td><td align="left">329, 148, 181</td><td align="left">Ampicillin</td><td align="left">0.12 &#x02013; 32</td><td align="left">0.25</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">88.2, <italic>91.2, 85.6</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Amoxicillin-clavulanate</td><td align="left">0.12 &#x02013; 4</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">100, 100,100</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Cefuroxime</td><td align="left">0.12 &#x02013; 16</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">99.4, <italic>99.3, 99.5</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Cefpodoxime</td><td align="left">0.015 &#x02013; 4</td><td align="left">0.06</td><td align="left">0.25</td><td align="left">99.4, <italic>100, 98.9</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Cefdinir</td><td align="left">0.06 &#x02013; 4</td><td align="left">0.25</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">97.3, 96.0, 98.3</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Trimethoprim-sulphamethoxazole</td><td align="left">0.03 &#x02013; 16</td><td align="left">0.06</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">84.5, <italic>82.4, 86.2</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Erythromycin</td><td align="left">0.25 &#x02013; 16</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">-<sup>3</sup></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Clarithromycin</td><td align="left">0.25 &#x02013; 32</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">16</td><td align="left">87.5, <italic>87.2, 87.9</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Azithromycin</td><td align="left">0.06 &#x02013; 4</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">100, 100,100</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Telithromycin</td><td align="left">0.06 &#x02013; 4</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">100, 100,100</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold><italic>M. catarrhalis</italic></bold></td><td align="left">212, 67, 145</td><td align="left">Ampicillin</td><td align="left">0.12 &#x02013; 32</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">16</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Amoxicillin-clavulanate</td><td align="left">0.12 &#x02013; 0.5</td><td align="left">0.12</td><td align="left">0.25</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Cefuroxime</td><td align="left">0.12 &#x02013; 16</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Cefpodoxime</td><td align="left">0.06 &#x02013; 4</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Cefdinir</td><td align="left">0.06 &#x02013; 1</td><td align="left">0.12</td><td align="left">0.25</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Trimethoprim-sulphamethoxazole</td><td align="left">0.03 &#x02013; 2</td><td align="left">0.12</td><td align="left">0.25</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Erythromycin</td><td align="left">0.25 &#x02013; 1</td><td align="left">0.25</td><td align="left">0.25</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Clarithromycin</td><td align="left">0.25 &#x02013; 0.5</td><td align="left">0.25</td><td align="left">0.25</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Azithromycin</td><td align="left">0.06 &#x02013; 0.25</td><td align="left">0.06</td><td align="left">0.06</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Telithromycin</td><td align="left">0.004 &#x02013; 0.5</td><td align="left">0.06</td><td align="left">0.12</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold><italic>S. aureus</italic></bold></td><td align="left">116, 64, 52</td><td align="left">Methicillin</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">-</td><td align="left">90.5, <italic>92.2, 88.5</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Amoxicillin-clavulanate</td><td align="left">0.06 &#x02013; 8</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">90.5, <italic>92.2, 88.5</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Cefuroxime</td><td align="left">0.5 &#x02013; 16</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">90.5, <italic>92.2, 88.5</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Cefpodoxime</td><td align="left">1 &#x02013; 32</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">88.8, <italic>92.2, 84.6</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Trimethoprim-sulphamethoxazole</td><td align="left">0.12 &#x02013; 32</td><td align="left">0.12</td><td align="left">0.12</td><td align="left">96.6, <italic>95.3, 98.1</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Erythromycin</td><td align="left">0.03 - &#x0003e;64</td><td align="left">0.25</td><td align="left">&#x0003e;64</td><td align="left">69.0, <italic>73.4, 63.5</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Clarithromycin</td><td align="left">0.015 - &#x0003e;32</td><td align="left">0.25</td><td align="left">&#x0003e;32</td><td align="left">69.8, <italic>75.0, 63.5</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Azithromycin</td><td align="left">0.03 - &#x0003e;64</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">&#x0003e;64</td><td align="left">69.0, <italic>75.0, 61.5</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Telithromycin</td><td align="left">0.015 - &#x0003e;32</td><td align="left">0.06</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">89.7, <italic>89.1, 90.4</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold><italic>S. pyogenes</italic></bold></td><td align="left">39, 21, 18</td><td align="left">Penicillin</td><td align="left">0.008 &#x02013; 0.008</td><td align="left">0.008</td><td align="left">0.008</td><td align="left">100, <italic>100,100</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Amoxicillin-clavulanate</td><td align="left">0.008 &#x02013; 0.03</td><td align="left">0.015</td><td align="left">0.015</td><td align="left">100, <italic>100,100</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Cefuroxime</td><td align="left">0.015 &#x02013; 0.015</td><td align="left">0.015</td><td align="left">0.015</td><td align="left">100, <italic>100,100</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Cefpodoxime</td><td align="left">0.12 &#x02013; 0.12</td><td align="left">0.12</td><td align="left">0.12</td><td align="left">100, <italic>100,100</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Trimethoprim-sulphamethoxazole</td><td align="left">0.12 &#x02013; 0.5</td><td align="left">0.12</td><td align="left">0.25</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Erythromycin</td><td align="left">0.03 &#x02013; 4</td><td align="left">0.06</td><td align="left">0.25</td><td align="left">92.3, <italic>100, 83.3</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Clarithromycin</td><td align="left">0.015 &#x02013; 2</td><td align="left">0.03</td><td align="left">0.25</td><td align="left">92.3, <italic>100, 83.3</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Azithromycin</td><td align="left">0.03 &#x02013; 16</td><td align="left">0.12</td><td align="left">0.25</td><td align="left">92.3, <italic>100, 83.3</italic></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="left">Telithromycin</td><td align="left">0.008 &#x02013; 0.12</td><td align="left">0.015</td><td align="left">0.015</td><td align="left">-</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>1</sup>Sinus aspirate <sup>2</sup>Nasopharyngeal aspirate or swab <sup>3</sup>No NCCLS interpretive guidelines available or pending</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Resistance to most antibiotics was slightly greater in nasopharyngeal specimens than sinus aspirates (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Considerable variation in <italic>in vitro </italic>antibiotic activity was apparent between geographical regions as observed in the key examples shown in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>. Insufficient data were available for analysis by country.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Key example of regional variation in <italic>in vitro </italic>antibiotic activity</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="left" colspan="3"><bold><italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae</italic></bold></td><td align="left" colspan="3"><bold><italic>Haemophilus influenzae</italic></bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">REGION<sup>1</sup></td><td align="center">N</td><td align="right">Penicillin susceptible</td><td align="right">Erythromycin susceptible</td><td align="center">N</td><td align="right">Beta-lactamase positive</td></tr><tr><td colspan="6"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Eastern Europe</td><td align="center">40</td><td align="right">70.0%</td><td align="right">82.5%</td><td align="center">13</td><td align="right">0.0%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Far East</td><td align="center">185</td><td align="right">24.9%</td><td align="right">15.7%</td><td align="center">96</td><td align="right">13.5%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Latin America</td><td align="center">108</td><td align="right">63.0%</td><td align="right">73.1%</td><td align="center">31</td><td align="right">6.5%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">South Africa</td><td align="center">61</td><td align="right">37.7%</td><td align="right">59.0%</td><td align="center">34</td><td align="right">2.9%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Western Europe</td><td align="center">246</td><td align="right">83.7%</td><td align="right">73.6%</td><td align="center">153</td><td align="right">11.8%</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Grand Total</td><td align="center">640</td><td align="right">58.0%</td><td align="right">55.9%</td><td align="center">329</td><td align="right">10.3%</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>1</sup>Australasia and North America not included due to insufficient data</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Combined macrolide resistance and reduced susceptibility to penicillin was present in 200/640 (31.3 %) of <italic>S. pneumoniae </italic>isolates (128 isolates were resistant to penicillin [MIC &#x0003e;= 2 mg/L], 72 intermediate [MIC 0.12&#x02013;1 mg/L]). Of note, 3 isolates of <italic>S. pneumoniae </italic>were non-susceptible to telithromycin (2 isolates intermediate with an MIC of 2 mg/L, 1 isolate resistant with an MIC of 8 mg/L). This represented 0.5% of isolates, a value that is significantly (p &#x0003c; 0.001) lower than those obtained by erythromycin (44.1%), clarithromycin (44.2%) and cefuroxime (33.9%).</p><p>Of the 329 <italic>H. influenzae </italic>isolates, 34 (10.3 %) were positive for &#x003b2;-lactamase production. All isolates of <italic>H. influenzae </italic>were susceptible to amoxycillin-clavulanate and telithromycin with an MIC<sub>90 </sub>of 1 and 2 mg/L, respectively. Amoxycillin-clavulanate and telithromycin were more potent and had greater activity than clarithromycin (MIC<sub>90 </sub>= 16 mg/L, 87.5% susceptible). This activity was comparable to azithromycin (MIC<sub>90 </sub>= 2 mg/l, 100% susceptible).</p><p>Although the number of <italic>S. aureus </italic>isolated from the total number of specimens was small (116/1366 isolates), telithromycin was as efficacious as comparators. Of the 116 isolates, 11 were resistant to methicillin (MRSA) and 105 were methicillin susceptible (MSSA). Ninety-nine (94.3%) of the MSSA isolates and 5 of the 11 MRSA isolates were susceptible to telithromycin. Of note, all of the <italic>S. pyogenes </italic>isolates were inhibited by &#x02264; 1 mg/L telithromycin, despite 17.7% resistance to erythromycin and clarithromycin.</p><p>Telithromycin was the most potent antimicrobial against <italic>M. catarrhalis </italic>with an MIC<sub>50 </sub>of 0.06 mg/L and MIC<sub>90 </sub>of 0.12 mg/L. &#x003b2;-lactamase production was detected in 97.6% of these isolates.</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>The data in this analysis demonstrates that telithromycin has high <italic>in vitro </italic>activity against bacterial pathogens isolated from a large, globally distributed population of patients diagnosed with ABS. Telithromycin was the most active and potent agent against all isolates of the pathogens isolated from patients with ABS with 99.4% of isolates susceptible. Not surprisingly, high levels of penicillin resistance, macrolide resistance, and combined penicillin and macrolides resistance were prevalent in <italic>S. pneumoniae </italic>although prevalence varied widely between geographical regions.</p><p>Amoxicillin has been the treatment of choice in ABS because of its general effectiveness, safety, tolerability, low cost and narrow spectrum [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. The high prevalence of beta-lactamase in <italic>H. influenzae </italic>and <italic>M. catarrhalis </italic>found in the present study demonstrate compromised <italic>in vitro </italic>efficacy of amoxicillin against these isolates. Although the cephalosporins (cefuroxime, cefpodoxime and cefdinir) showed high activity against <italic>H. influenzae </italic>(including beta-lactamase positive strains), resistance to these agents was high in <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic>: &#x0003e;30% for cefuroxime and cefpodoxime &#x02013; cefdinir was not tested against pneumococci in PROTEKT, however susceptibility is usually similar to the other cephalosporins reported here [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>].</p><p>Similarly, macrolides are prescribed in various countries for ABS and an overall resistance rate for <italic>S. pneumoniae </italic>of 44.1% to erythromycin, azithromycin, and clarithromycin was found. Trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole activity was low for <italic>S. pneumoniae </italic>(56.3% susceptible) and decreased for <italic>H. influenzae </italic>(84.5% susceptible).</p><p>Respiratory fluoroquinolones are recommended second-line treatment options in some countries (references needed to support this statement). However, recent evidence suggests that resistance to fluoroquinolones is rapidly developing in pneumococci and other pathogens (including gram-positive and gram-negative [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. To preserve the long-term utility of fluoroquinolones, including their use in the treatment of serious non-respiratory infections, it has been recommended that respiratory fluoroquinolones be reserved for treating severe (e.g. hospitalized) community-acquired RTIs only [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>].</p><p>The high prevalence of beta-lactam, macrolide, TMP-SMX resistance demonstrated in the large number of isolates from patients with clinically diagnosed sinusitis in our study demonstrates the need to be exploring new therapeutic options, especially in geographical regions of high prevalence such as the Far East.</p><p>The high <italic>in vitro </italic>activity of telithromycin against ABS pathogens reported in this study, regardeless of geographical region, also demonstrates its potential as an empiric therapeutic option for ABS. There are several other reasons to consider this option &#x02013; 1) High rates of clinical cure and bacteriological eradication have been demonstrated using telithromycin against sinus isolates of <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic>, <italic>H. influenzae</italic>, <italic>M. catarrhalis </italic>and <italic>S. aureus </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. 2) Telithromycin has been shown to have a targeted spectrum of activity against the major bacterial respiratory tract pathogens and has less effect on normal bacterial ecology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>]. 3) The pharmacokinetic profile of oral telithromycin allows it to be prescribed with a dosing regime of 800 mg once daily for 5 days [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>]. This contrasts favourably with its comparators, where a 10 &#x02013; 14 day course with administration either 2 or 3 times daily, depending on the chosen antibacterial, is generally prescribed. Studies have shown that the once daily dosing regime affords greater patient treatment compliance, thereby avoiding clinical failure and the ensuing development of antibacterial resistance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>]. 5) Telithromycin has been shown to have high penetration levels in paranasal sinuses, and it is preferentially absorbed by polymorphonuclear neutrophils (PMNs) within the azurophil granules allowing effective delivery to phagocytized intracellular bacteria [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>].</p><p>Although this study provides valuable information on the overall antimicrobial profile of bacteria causing ABS care should be taken when interpreting data related to specific demographics. A major limitation of this study, inherent to most surveillance studies, is the requirement for collecting centers to fulfill a specified quota of isolates over a defined time period (1 year). If, for instance, 1 center manages to fulfill their quota for <italic>S. pneumoniae </italic>isolates from patients with community-acquired pneumonia, they may then only send <italic>H. influenzae </italic>from patients with ABS to fulfill their quota for this organism. Thus, the potential exists to over or under estimate the prevalence of a species in a particular disease. A further limitation of this study is it is restricted to the major bacterial pathogens causing sinusitis and does not therefore assess anaerobic bacteria, which are also known to be involved in this disease. However, a recent study of sinus puncture specimens demonstrated that telithromycin had good <italic>in vitro </italic>activity against anaerobes involved in sinusitis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>].</p><p>The inclusion of nasopharyngeal specimens is a potential limitation of this study and the higher rate of resistance compared to sinus aspirates may indicate some isolates were nasopharyngeal flora rather than pathogens. However, the difference in resistance prevalence between nasopharyngeal specimens and sinus aspirates was not great for any species/antibiotic combination, and assuming the majority of isolates were the responsible pathogen, significant bias of resistance patterns is unlikely. The treatment of ABS is complicated by a difficulty in establishing the causative pathogen(s). Sampling of infected fluid using sinus puncture is a painful and rare procedure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>]. Nasopharyngeal culture is a painless and reliable method that can help identify patients that may benefit from antibacterial therapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>] and hence, could be useful in determining antibiotic resistance implicated in sinusitis &#x02013; particularly <italic>Streptococcus pneumoniae </italic>and <italic>Haemophilus influenzae</italic>. Additionally, there are regional differences in the susceptibility patterns observed and, as therapy is usually empirical, choosing an effective therapy can be challenging [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>].</p><p>In summary, the data presented here demonstrates that telithromycin has good <italic>in vitro </italic>activity against <italic>S. pneumoniae</italic>, <italic>H. influenzae, M. catarrhalis </italic>and <italic>S. aureus </italic>respiratory pathogens commonly isolated in ABS. It is as active as or more active than antibacterial agents that are currently used in this clinical setting. The development of resistance will always be a threat to the usefulness of antibacterial compounds, however surveillance studies such as PROTEKT allow the rapid detection and characterization of resistance mechanisms and highlight the need for and examine the <italic>in vitro </italic>efficacy of newer antibacterial agents. Providing careful surveillance for the development of resistance is maintained telithromycin currently offers a useful therapeutic option in the treatment of AS.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>JD, RCa and RCo reviewed the data and provided clinical and microbiological interpretation and discussion. DF and DJF participated in the design of the study, supervised the scientific testing, and provided data analysis, microbiological interpretation and discussion. All authors drafted the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We are grateful to our colleagues worldwide for the supply of bacterial isolates as part of the PROTEKT study and the GR Micro PROTEKT team who performed the testing. Aventis is acknowledged for their financial support of the PROTEKT study.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grevers</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Klemens</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>[Rhinosinusitis. Current diagnostic and therapeutic aspects]</article-title><source>MMW Fortschr Med</source><year>2002</year><volume>144</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12494595</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The diagnosis and management of sinusitis</article-title><source>Nurse Pract</source><year>1994</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>58</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7532290</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><article-title>Antimicrobial treatment guidelines for acute bacterial rhinosinusitis. Sinus and Allergy Health Partnership</article-title><source>Otolaryngol Head Neck Surg</source><year>2000</year><volume>123</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10887346</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1067/mhn.2000.107873</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>National health survey: prevalence of selected chronic conditions, United States 1983-1985.  U.S Department of Health and Human Services</article-title><source>US Department of Health and Human Services, Hyattsville, Md</source><year>1987</year></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fagnan</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute sinusitis: a cost-effective approach to diagnosis and treatment</article-title><source>Am Fam Physician</source><year>1998</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>1795</fpage><lpage>802, 805-6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9835855</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Hochman</surname><given-names>II,II</given-names></name><name><surname>DeRowe</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fliss</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complications of Acute Otitis Media and Sinusitis</article-title><source>Curr Infect Dis Rep</source><year>2000</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>130</fpage><lpage>140</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11095848</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Violaris</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chavda</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Pahor</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intracranial complications of sinusitis: the need for aggressive management</article-title><source>J Laryngol Otol</source><year>1995</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>1061</fpage><lpage>1062</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8551120</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clairmont</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Per-Lee</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Complications of acute frontal sinusitis</article-title><source>Am Fam Physician</source><year>1975</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>80</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">48329</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>TZ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extensive subgaleal abscess and epidural empyema in a patient with acute frontal sinusitis</article-title><source>J Formos Med Assoc</source><year>2003</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>338</fpage><lpage>341</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12874674</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>V Lund and J Corey</surname></name></person-group><article-title>The pathogenesis of infective rhinosinusitis</article-title><source>Rhinosinusitis : current issues in diagnosis and management</source><year>1999</year><publisher-name>London, The Royal Society of Medicine Press Ltd</publisher-name><fpage>11 </fpage><lpage>119</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corey</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>V Lund and J Corey</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Non-antibiotic treatment options</article-title><source>Rhinosinusitis: current issues in diagnosis and management</source><year>1999</year><publisher-name>London, The Royal Society of Medicine Press Ltd</publisher-name><fpage>33 </fpage><lpage>338</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Ferranti</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Ioannidis</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Anninger</surname><given-names>WV</given-names></name><name><surname>Barza</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Are amoxycillin and folate inhibitors as effective as other antibiotics for acute sinusitis? A meta-analysis</article-title><source>Bmj</source><year>1998</year><volume>317</volume><fpage>632</fpage><lpage>637</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9727991</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Scholz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>al-Nawas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Elies</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kresken</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lode</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Naber</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorgel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Stille</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Tauchnitz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Trautmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ullmann</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Wacha</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiedemann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>[Rational use of oral antibiotics. Findings of an expert commission of the Paul Ehrlich Society for Chemotherapy.]</article-title><source>Med Monatsschr Pharm</source><year>2002</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>193</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12109028</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>PRODIGY Guidance. Sinusitis (updated 2002). Accessed at http://www.prodigy.nhs.uk/guidance.asp?gt=sinusitis on 2nd February 2004</article-title></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>Agence Francaise de S&#x000e9;curit&#x000e9; Sanitaire des Produits de Sant&#x000e9;.  Mise au point sur l&#x02019;antibioth&#x000e9;rapie par voie g&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;rale en pratique courante (2002). Accessed at http://afssaps.sante.fr/htm/10/filltrpsc/antibio.pdf on 2 Feb 2004.</article-title></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Federspil</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Leitlinien zur antibiotika-therapie der bakterielleninfektionen an kopf und hals</article-title><source>Arzniemitteltherapie</source><year>2003</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>162</fpage><lpage>175</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Subcommittee on Management of Sinusitis and Committee on Quality Improvement</collab></person-group><article-title>Clinical Practice Guideline: Management of Sinusitis</article-title><source>Pediatrics</source><year>2001</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>798</fpage><lpage>808</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11533355</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Felmingham</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinert</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirakata</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodloff</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increasing prevalence of antimicrobial resistance among isolates of Streptococcus pneumoniae from the PROTEKT surveillance study, and comparative in vitro activity of the ketolide, telithromycin</article-title><source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source><year>2002</year><volume>50 Suppl S1</volume><fpage>25</fpage><lpage>37</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12239226</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Felmingham</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Washington</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trends in the antimicrobial susceptibility of bacterial respiratory tract pathogens--findings of the Alexander Project 1992-1996</article-title><source>J Chemother</source><year>1999</year><volume>11 Suppl 1</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>21</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10207769</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sahm</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Hickey</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Diakun</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mani</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Thornsberry</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resistance surveillance of Streptococcus pneumoniae, Haemophilus influenzae and Moraxella catarrhalis isolated in Asia and Europe, 1997-1998</article-title><source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source><year>2000</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>457</fpage><lpage>466</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10747822</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/45.4.457</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoban</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Felmingham</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The PROTEKT surveillance study: antimicrobial susceptibility of Haemophilus influenzae and Moraxella catarrhalis from community-acquired respiratory tract infections</article-title><source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source><year>2002</year><volume>50 Suppl S1</volume><fpage>49</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12239228</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mandell</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartlett</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Dowell</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>File</surname><given-names>T. M., Jr.</given-names></name><name><surname>Musher</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitney</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Update of practice guidelines for the management of community-acquired pneumonia in immunocompetent adults</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2003</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>1405</fpage><lpage>1433</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14614663</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/380488</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Felmingham</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microbiological profile of telithromycin, the first ketolide antimicrobial</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source><year>2001</year><volume>7 Suppl 3</volume><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11523558</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1469-0691.2001.00048.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luterman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tellier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Lasko</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Leroy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficacy and tolerability of telithromycin for 5 or 10 days vs amoxicillin/clavulanic acid for 10 days in acute maxillary sinusitis</article-title><source>Ear Nose Throat J</source><year>2003</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>576</fpage><lpage>80, 82-4, 586 passim</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14503094</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roos</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunswig-Pitschner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kostrica</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pietola</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Leroy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Rangaraju</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Boutalbi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficacy and tolerability of once-daily therapy with telithromycin for 5 or 10 days for the treatment of acute maxillary sinusitis</article-title><source>Chemotherapy</source><year>2002</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>100</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12011543</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000057670</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buchanan</surname><given-names>PP</given-names></name><name><surname>Stephens</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Leroy</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A comparison of the efficacy of telithromycin versus cefuroxime axetil in the treatment of acute bacterial maxillary sinusitis</article-title><source>American Journal of Rhinology</source><year>2003</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>369</fpage><lpage>377</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14750614</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Felmingham</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The need for antimicrobial resistance surveillance</article-title><source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source><year>2002</year><volume>50 Suppl S1</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12239224</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>NCCLS</collab></person-group><source>Methods for dilution antimicrobial susceptibility tests for bacteria that grow aerobically; Approved Standard - Sixth edition. NCCLS document M7-A6</source><year>2003</year><publisher-name>Wayne, Pennsylvania 19087-1898, USA, NCCLS</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>NCCLS</collab></person-group><source>Performance standards antimicrobial susceptibility testing; Twelfth information supplement.  
NCCLS document M100-S14</source><year>2004</year><publisher-name>Wayne, Pennsylvania 19807 - 1898, USA, NCCLS</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sader</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Fritsche</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mutnick</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contemporary evaluation of the in vitro activity and spectrum of cefdinir compared with other orally administered antimicrobials tested against common respiratory tract pathogens (2000-2002)</article-title><source>Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis</source><year>2003</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>515</fpage><lpage>525</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14596971</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0732-8893(03)00165-2</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quale</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Landman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ravishankar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Flores</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bratu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Streptococcus pneumoniae, Brooklyn, New York: fluoroquinolone resistance at our doorstep</article-title><source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><year>2002</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>594</fpage><lpage>597</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12023915</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morrissey</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Farrell</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckridge</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Felmingham</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular Characterization and Antimicrobial Susceptibility of Fluoroquinolone-Resistant or -Susceptible Streptococcus pneumoniae from Hong Kong</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2003</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>1433</fpage><lpage>1435</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12654686</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.47.4.1433-1435.2003</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>McGeer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>de Azavedo</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Low</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decreased susceptibility of Streptococcus pneumoniae to fluoroquinolones in Canada. Canadian Bacterial Surveillance Network</article-title><source>N Engl J Med</source><year>1999</year><volume>341</volume><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>239</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10413735</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM199907223410403</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mandell</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Wise</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Hooper</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Low</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaad</surname><given-names>UB</given-names></name><name><surname>Klugman</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name><surname>Courvalin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The battle against emerging antibiotic resistance: should fluoroquinolones be used to treat children?</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2002</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>721</fpage><lpage>727</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12203170</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/341900</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><citation citation-type="journal"><article-title>BTS Guidelines for the Management of Community Acquired Pneumonia in Adults</article-title><source>Thorax</source><year>2001</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>1iv</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11120894</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heffelfinger</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Dowell</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorgensen</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Klugman</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name><surname>Mabry</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name><name><surname>Musher</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Plouffe</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Rakowsky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuchat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitney</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Management of community-acquired pneumonia in the era of pneumococcal resistance: a report from the Drug-Resistant Streptococcus pneumoniae Therapeutic Working Group</article-title><source>Arch Intern Med</source><year>2000</year><volume>160</volume><fpage>1399</fpage><lpage>1408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10826451</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archinte.160.10.1399</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cremieux</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller-Serieys</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Panhard</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Delatour</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Tchimichkian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mentre</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Andremont</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emergence of Resistance in Normal Human Aerobic Commensal Flora during Telithromycin and Amoxicillin-Clavulanic Acid Treatments</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2003</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>2030</fpage><lpage>2035</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12760893</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.47.6.2030-2035.2003</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edlund</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Beyer</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiemer-Bau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ziege</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lode</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nord</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative effects of moxifloxacin and clarithromycin on the normal intestinal microflora</article-title><source>Scand J Infect Dis</source><year>2000</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>85</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10716083</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/00365540050164272</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Low</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Felmingham</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical and bacteriological efficacy of the ketolide telithromycin against isolates of key respiratory pathogens: a pooled analysis of phase III studies</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source><year>2004</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14706083</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-0691.2004.00752.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><citation citation-type="other"><article-title>Aventis Pharma 2001. KetekTM.  Telithromycin. Briefing document for the FDA Anti-infective DrugProducts Advisory Committee Meeting, April 2001</article-title><fpage>p62</fpage><lpage>63 [Section 5.6- Dose Determination]</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nicolau</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pharmacodynamic rationale for short-duration antibacterial therapy</article-title><source>J Infect</source><year>2002</year><volume>44 Suppl A</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12150491</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Claxton</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cramer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierce</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A systematic review of the associations between dose regimens and medication compliance</article-title><source>Clin Ther</source><year>2001</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1296</fpage><lpage>1310</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11558866</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0149-2918(01)80109-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sclar</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Tartaglione</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fine</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overview of issues related to medical compliance with implications for the outpatient management of infectious diseases</article-title><source>Infect Agents Dis</source><year>1994</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>266</fpage><lpage>273</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7866659</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miossec-Bartoli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pilatre</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Peyron</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>N'Diaye</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name><name><surname>Collart-Dutilleul</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Maridonneau-Parini</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Diu-Hercend</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The new ketolide HMR3647 accumulates in the azurophil granules of human polymorphonuclear cells</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>1999</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>2457</fpage><lpage>2462</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10508024</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B45"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miyamoto</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pharmocokinetic study of a new ketolide antimicrobial telithromycin (HMR3647) in otorhinolaryngology.</article-title><source>40th Interscience Conference on Antimicrobial Agents and Chemotherapy</source><year>2000</year><publisher-name>Toronto</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>Ellie J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Citron</surname><given-names>Diane M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Merriam</surname><given-names>C. Vreni</given-names></name><name><surname>Warren</surname><given-names>Yumi</given-names></name><name><surname>Tyrrel</surname><given-names>Kerin L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandez</surname><given-names>Helen</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In Vitro Activities of Telithromycin and 10 Oral Agents against Aerobic and Anaerobic Pathogens Isolated from Antral Puncture Specimens from Patients with Sinusitis</article-title><source>Antimicrob Agents Chemother</source><year>2003</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>1963</fpage><lpage>1967</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12760875</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AAC.47.6.1963-1967.2003</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brooks</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Gooch</surname><given-names>W. M., 3rd</given-names></name><name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><name><surname>Pichichero</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Reiner</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sher</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamauchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medical management of acute bacterial sinusitis. Recommendations of a clinical advisory committee on pediatric and adult sinusitis</article-title><source>Ann Otol Rhinol Laryngol Suppl</source><year>2000</year><volume>182</volume><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10823486</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Morabia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Stalder</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ricchetti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Auckenthaler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Terrier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirschel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Khaw</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Lacroix</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lew</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of nasopharyngeal culture in antibiotic prescription for patients with common cold or acute sinusitis</article-title><source>Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis</source><year>2001</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>445</fpage><lpage>451</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11561799</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s100960100544</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoban</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Doern</surname><given-names>GV</given-names></name><name><surname>Fluit</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Roussel-Delvallez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Worldwide prevalence of antimicrobial resistance in Streptococcus pneumoniae, Haemophilus influenzae, and Moraxella catarrhalis in the SENTRY Antimicrobial Surveillance Program, 1997-1999</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2001</year><volume>32 Suppl 2</volume><fpage>S81</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11320449</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/320181</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



