<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nucl Recept</journal-id><journal-title>Nuclear Receptor</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1478-1336</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15318942</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC516042</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1478-1336-2-5</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1478-1336-2-5</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Binding of estrogen receptor with estrogen conjugated to bovine serum albumin (BSA)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Taguchi</surname><given-names>Yasuto</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>taguchiyasuto@uams.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Koslowski</surname><given-names>Mirek</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>mirek.kozlowski@med.va.gov</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bodenner</surname><given-names>Donald L</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>bodennerdonald@uams.edu</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Obstetrics and Gynecology, University of Arkansas for Medical Sciences, 4301 West Markham Street, Little Rock, AR 72205, USA</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Endocrinology and Metabolism, Emory University School of Medicine and Veterans Affairs Medical Center, Atlanta, Georgia 30033, USA</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Geriatrics, University of Arkansas for Medical Sciences, 4301 West Markham Street, Little Rock, AR 72205, USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>8</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>5</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nuclear-receptor.com/content/2/1/5"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>7</month><year>2003</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>19</day><month>8</month><year>2004</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2004 Taguchi et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2004</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Taguchi et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Taguchi
               Yasuto
               
               taguchiyasuto@uams.edu
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Binding of estrogen receptor with estrogen conjugated to bovine serum albumin (BSA)
         </dc:title><dc:date>2004</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Nuclear Receptor 2(1): 5-. (2004)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1478-1336(2004)2:1&#x0003c;5&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1478-1336</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>The classic model of estrogen action requires that the estrogen receptor (ER) activates gene expression by binding directly or indirectly to DNA. Recent studies, however, strongly suggest that ER can act through nongenomic signal transduction pathways and may be mediated by a membrane bound form of the ER. Estradiol covalently linked to membrane impermeable BSA (E<sub>2</sub>-BSA) has been widely used as an agent to study these novel membrane-associated ER events. However, a recent report suggests that E<sub>2</sub>-BSA does not compete for E<sub>2 </sub>binding to purified ER <italic>in vitro</italic>. To resolve this apparent discrepancy, we performed competition studies examining the binding of E<sub>2 </sub>and E<sub>2</sub>-BSA to both purified ER preparations and ER within intact cells. To eliminate potential artifacts due to contamination of commercially available E<sub>2</sub>-BSA preparations with unconjugated E<sub>2 </sub>(usually between 3&#x02013;5%), the latter was carefully removed by ultrafiltration.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>As previously reported, a 10-to 1000-fold molar excess of E<sub>2</sub>-BSA was unable to compete with <sup>3</sup>H-E<sub>2 </sub>binding to ER when added simultaneously. However, when ER was pre-incubated with the same concentrations of E<sub>2</sub>-BSA, the binding of <sup>3</sup>H-E<sub>2 </sub>was significantly reduced. E<sub>2</sub>-BSA binding to a putative membrane-associated ER was directly visualized using fluorescein labeled E<sub>2</sub>-BSA (E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC). Staining was restricted to the cell membrane when E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC was incubated with stable transfectants of the murine ER&#x003b1; within ER-negative HeLa cells and with MC7 cells that endogenously produce ER&#x003b1;. This staining appeared highly specific since it was competed by pre-incubation with E<sub>2 </sub>in a dose dependent manner and with the competitor ICI-182,780.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>These results demonstrate that E<sub>2</sub>-BSA does bind to purified ER <italic>in vitro </italic>and to ER in intact cells. It seems likely that the size and structure of E<sub>2</sub>-BSA requires more energy for it to bind to the ER and consequently binds more slowly than E<sub>2</sub>. More importantly, these findings demonstrate that in intact cells that express ER, E<sub>2</sub>-BSA binding is localized to the cell membrane, strongly suggesting a membrane bound form of the ER.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>For many years, estrogen actions have been presumed to be mediated almost exclusively through the regulation of target gene transcription by a chromosomal bound estrogen receptor. These genomic estrogen effects are the well described interactions between the estrogen receptor and adapter transcription factors that result in activation or inhibition of the basal transcription protein machinery. However, there is a growing body of evidence that several rapid estrogen effects are non-transcriptional in nature. These rapid estrogen effects include changes of calcium flux in several cell types [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>], MAPK activation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>], cAMP levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>], and nitric oxide release [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. That many of these effects are mediated by a membrane-localized estrogen receptor has been postulated for some time [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>], but the majority of evidence supporting this hypothesis is indirect, relying on the induction of these non-genomic effects using estrogen covalently conjugated to BSA by a 6 atom hydrocarbon tether (E<sub>2</sub>-BSA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. However, the relative binding efficiency of these conjugates is low and concern has been raised regarding the use of these conjugates as direct surrogates for estrogen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. A recent report added to this controversy by showing that commercially available E<sub>2</sub>-BSA is contaminated by unconjugated free E<sub>2 </sub>and a series of binding experiments demonstrated that E<sub>2</sub>-BSA was unable to bind to ER after the contaminant E<sub>2 </sub>was removed. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. These findings contradict studies where fluorescein-labeled E<sub>2</sub>-BSA (E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC) specifically bound to a putative ER on the cell membrane [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>].</p><p>Elucidation of novel membrane-associated ER effects is crucial to our understanding of the non-genomic signaling pathways of ER and other hormone receptors. Hormone-conjugated BSA is an important tool in this pursuit. We believe the contradictory results are explained by differences in the rates of binding of the bulky E<sub>2</sub>-BSA and E<sub>2 </sub>with the ER. We show that pre-incubation of E<sub>2</sub>-BSA with ER&#x003b1; results in a highly significant decrease in the binding of <sup>3</sup>H-E<sub>2</sub>. The binding of <sup>3</sup>H-E<sub>2 </sub>with ER&#x003b1; is unaffected by the simultaneous addition of E<sub>2</sub>-BSA. We also demonstrate that fluorescein conjugated E<sub>2</sub>-BSA binds to the membrane of cells that endogenously produce ER&#x003b1; and to HeLa cell lines stably expressing mER&#x003b1;.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>E<sub>2</sub>-BSA binding to purified estrogen receptor</title><p>Although E<sub>2 </sub>is covalently attached to BSA using a relatively long six atom hydrocarbon tether, the bulky BSA moiety of E<sub>2</sub>-BSA still may be interfering with the binding between the estrogen molecule and the estrogen receptor. This would result in an increase in the energy of activation required for E<sub>2</sub>-BSA binding. If so, increasing the reaction time would allow for the establishment of an equilibrium between bound and free forms of E<sub>2</sub>-BSA, maximizing the amount of E<sub>2</sub>-BSA bound to the receptor. To test this hypothesis, E<sub>2</sub>-BSA free of contaminant E<sub>2 </sub>was prepared by ultrafiltration. Competition between the purified E<sub>2</sub>-BSA and labeled E<sub>2 </sub>for binding to purified ER&#x003b1; was determined after E<sub>2</sub>-BSA was pre-incubated with ER&#x003b1; and also when added at the same time as labeled E<sub>2</sub>. As shown in figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, concurrent addition of labeled E<sub>2 </sub>and E<sub>2</sub>-BSA had no effect on labeled E<sub>2 </sub>binding. However, a four-hour pre-incubation of E<sub>2</sub>-BSA with ER significantly decreased E<sub>2 </sub>binding. These results suggest that the large BSA molecule retards, but does not prevent binding of E<sub>2</sub>-BSA.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Pre-incubation of purified hER&#x003b1; with E<sub>2</sub>-BSA competes for estradiol binding. </bold>Purified ER&#x003b1; was incubated with E<sub>2 </sub>(solid line) or E<sub>2</sub>-BSA (dotted line) for four hours before (a) or concurrently with (b) the addition of labeled E<sub>2</sub>. Incubation was continued for another 2 h at room temperature, and at the end of this period, specific binding was determined by adsorption, removal, and counting of free labeled E<sub>2</sub>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1478-1336-2-5-1"/></fig></sec><sec><title>E<sub>2</sub>-BSA binding to ER in intact cells</title><p>Non-genomic actions of the estrogen receptor are now well established. Several investigators have demonstrated that fluorescein labeled E<sub>2</sub>-BSA (E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC) binds to the cell membrane, suggesting that a form of the estrogen receptor is present within the cell membrane and capable of binding to extracellular E<sub>2</sub>. Specific binding of E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC to this membrane-localized form of the ER would further establish that E<sub>2 </sub>conjugated to the BSA molecule is capable of binding to the ER. To examine this possibility, E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC binding studies were performed with MC7 cells that contain endogenous ER&#x003b1; and with ER-deficient HeLa cells stably transfected with the ER&#x003b1; (HeLa-ER&#x003b1;). Expression of ER&#x003b1; within the HeLa cells was established by demonstrating specific binding of labeled E<sub>2 </sub>to HeLa-ER&#x003b1;, but not native HeLa cells (figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). Scatchard analysis of the binding of E<sub>2 </sub>to HeLa-ER&#x003b1; cells showed that although weakly expressed, the Kd for the expressed ER&#x003b1; was 7.04 nM, similar to published values (figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). HeLa-ER&#x003b1; cells, but not native HeLa cells, exhibited fluorescent staining of the cell membrane after incubation with E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC (figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). The heterogeneous staining pattern reflected the low level of ER&#x003b1; expression. This fluorescence was not seen when HeLa-ER&#x003b1; cells were incubated with BSA conjugated to fluorescein alone (data not shown).</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Whole cell binding of estradiol to MC7 cells and HeLa cells stably transfected with ER&#x003b1;. </bold>2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6 </sup>cells were incubated with <sup>3</sup>H-17&#x003b2;-estradiol (10<sup>-8 </sup>M) in the absence (solid) and presence (white) of 100 fold excess of unlabeled estradiol for 15 minutes at room temperature, washed, and placed on ice for 30 minutes. Cells were then pelleted, lysed and counted. Results are expressed as the mean +/- the SEM of 3 experiments (* p &#x0003c; 0.01)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1478-1336-2-5-2"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Estradiol binding to HeLa cells stably transfected with ER&#x003b1;. </bold>Subconfluent HeLa-ER&#x003b1; cells were trypsinized and aliquots (2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6 </sup>cells) incubated with several concentrations of <sup>3</sup>H-17&#x003b2;-estradiol in the presence and absence of a 200-fold excess of cold 17&#x003b2;-estradiol for 30 min at 37&#x000b0;. Cells were then incubated on ice for 15 min, washed three times with 2 ml of ice cold 0.2% BSA-saline and pelleted by centrifugation at 1,5000 rpm for 10 min at 4&#x000b0;C. Cells were lysed by the addition of 100 ul of lysis buffer, vortexed and counted. a) Representative binding results of 3 independent experiments with total binding (solid box), non-specific binding (open box), and specific binding (triangle). b) Scatchard analysis of binding results.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1478-1336-2-5-3"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Membrane localization of ER&#x003b1;. </bold>HeLa cells stably transfected with ER&#x003b1;(a) and native HeLa cells (b) were incubated with fluorescein labeled membrane impermeable BSA conjugated to estradiol (E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC) and visualized under phase contrast bright field and with UV light with an excitation filter for FITC.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1478-1336-2-5-4"/></fig><p>To establish the specificity of E<sub>2</sub>-BSA binding, MC7 cells and HeLa-ER&#x003b1; cells were incubated with E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC after pre-incubation with various concentrations of E<sub>2 </sub>and the anti-estrogen ICI-182,780. As shown in figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>, fluorescence was lost in both cell types in a dose dependent manner with increasing concentrations of E<sub>2</sub>. Fluorescence was almost completely eliminated by pre-incubation with the specific competitor ICI-182,780. BSA conjugated to FITC alone did not bind. These results suggest that estrogen covalently bound to BSA can bind to ER in a biologically significant manner.</p><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>E<sub>2 </sub>competition with E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC binding. </bold>MC7 cells (black bars) or HeLa-ER&#x003b1; (white bars) were incubated with vehicle, various concentrations of E<sub>2</sub>, or ICI 182,780 (10<sup>-8 </sup>M) for 30 minutes and then incubated an additional 30 minutes with E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC or BSA-FITC alone (grey bar). Cells were fixed, and visualized by confocal microscopy. Digitized images were inverted to black on white and pixel density for each cell was determined by averaging the density across the cell membrane at four orthogonal points. Each bar represents &#x0003e;20 cells counted +/- SEM. (* p &#x0003c; 0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1478-1336-2-5-5"/></fig><p>The possibility that E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC could be degraded during incubation with intact cells was examined using HPLC. E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC was incubated in empty wells or wells containing MC7 cells under the same conditions employed for the binding studies described above. Media was removed from the cells and HPLC performed with a reverse phase column. Peaks were visualized using a scanning fluorescence detector. Aqueous solutions of E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC produced a single peak with a retention time of 5.5 minutes using a methanol-water gradient from 80% to 50% over 30 minutes at 1 ml/minute. E<sub>2 </sub>and E<sub>2</sub>-BSA did not fluoresce at the excitation and emission wavelengths used (data not shown). Spectra obtained from media containing E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC alone and media containing E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC incubated with MC7 cells are shown in figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>. The average area under the curve for E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC was the same (p &#x0003c; 0.05) for solutions incubated in the presence (44,556 +/- 432) and absence (43,436 +/- 289) of MC7 cells (p, 0.05). These results demonstrate that E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC is stable under the culture conditions employed for the binding experiments.</p><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>Stability of E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC. </bold>E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC (10<sup>-8 </sup>M in estrogen) was placed in empty wells or wells containing MC7 cells and incubated for 30 minutes at 4&#x000b0;C. E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC was detected by reverse phase HPLC using a methanol-water gradient from 80% methanol to 50% methanol over 30 minutes at 1.0 ml/min. The assay was run in triplicate. Representative spectra are shown for E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC alone (A) and E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC incubated with MC7 cells (B).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1478-1336-2-5-6"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>The cellular effects elicited by estrogen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>] testosterone [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>] and progesterone [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>] covalently conjugated to membrane impermeable BSA have been attributed to non-genomic actions mediated by membrane associated hormone receptors. The use of these reagents for this purpose remains controversial for several reasons. A recent report demonstrated that E<sub>2</sub>-BSA does not bind to purified ER in competition assays with labeled E<sub>2 </sub>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. The studies were performed when E<sub>2</sub>-BSA or cold E<sub>2 </sub>were added concurrently with labeled E<sub>2</sub>. We obtained similar results under these conditions. However, pre-incubation of E<sub>2</sub>-BSA with purified ER results in significant competition with labeled E<sub>2</sub>. These conflicting results may be explained by differences in the rate of binding between E<sub>2 </sub>and E<sub>2</sub>-BSA. E<sub>2</sub>-BSA is a large, bulky molecule similar in size to the ER and is probably spherical in general structure as is the parent BSA molecule. The BSA protein conformation immediately adjacent to the covalently bound estrogen undoubtedly provides substantial steric hindrance to the proper presentation of conjugated E<sub>2 </sub>to the binding pocket of ER. The increased size of the E<sub>2</sub>-BSA molecule would also reduce the rate of its diffusion compared with the smaller E<sub>2</sub>. Correct orientation of E2 in the ER binding pocket is also impeded by the restraint on three-dimensional movement imposed by the six atom spacer used to connect BSA and E<sub>2</sub>. Lastly, the use of E<sub>2</sub>-BSA solutions that are formulated in terms of the molarity of total bound-E<sub>2 </sub>probably overestimates the amount of E<sub>2 </sub>available for binding. The rate of binding between E<sub>2 </sub>and ER can be expressed using the second order rate equation: rate = k [E<sub>2</sub>] [ER], where [E<sub>2</sub>] is the concentration of estradiol, [ER] is the concentration of the ER, and k the rate constant.</p><p>Commercially available E<sub>2</sub>-BSA is commonly composed of approximately 10 molecules of E2 attached to every BSA molecule. An E<sub>2</sub>-BSA solution equimolar in estradiol to a solution of estradiol alone would contain one-tenth the molarity of E<sub>2</sub>-BSA with respect to the concentration of estradiol alone. However the rate of E<sub>2</sub>-BSA binding is dependent upon the concentration of E<sub>2</sub>-BSA (rate = k [E<sub>2</sub>-BSA] [ER]). Even if every collision between E<sub>2</sub>-BSA and ER produced binding as successful as collisions between E2 alone and the ER, an E2-BSA solution equimolar in E2 would have approximately one-tenth the rate.</p><p>Taken together, these factors reduce the binding efficiency of E<sub>2</sub>-BSA to ER compared with free E<sub>2</sub>. However, once binding has occurred, the stability of the E<sub>2 </sub>molecule in the ER binding pocket may be only modestly impaired. This may explain how pre-incubation with E<sub>2</sub>-BSA results in successful binding, whereas immediate addition of E<sub>2</sub>-BSA does not have sufficient time to establish successfully bound forms. A similar rationale may explain our results and those of other investigators [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>] that demonstrate specific cell surface binding of E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC only to cells that express ER&#x003b1;. These studies typically employ at least a 30-minute incubation time with E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC, which may be sufficient to result in significant binding. These factors strongly suggest that the rate of binding is an important consideration in experiments assessing potential interactions between E<sub>2</sub>-BSA and ER.</p><p>Although an estrogen receptor has not been directly isolated and characterized from the cell membrane, evidence other than E<sub>2</sub>-BSA activation of non-genomic effects has recently been reported that strongly supports the existence of a membrane ER. Immunocytochemistry using antibodies specific to several domains of the ER&#x003b1; stained only on the membrane of GH3 cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. Membrane specific staining was prevented by treatment with antisense ER&#x003b1; mRNA or peptides that interfere with antibody binding. E<sub>2 </sub>conjugated to peroxidase also bound only to the membrane of pancreatic islet cells and this binding was competed by E<sub>2 </sub>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. The membrane impermeable E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC was shown to stain only the membrane of ER deficient CHO cells transiently transfected with ER&#x003b1; and ER&#x003b2; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. Moreover, ER&#x003b1; and ER&#x003b2; interact directly with the membrane associated Src complex to trigger prostate cancer cell proliferation through the RAF-1/Erk-2 signal transduction pathway [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Lastly, we demonstrate that E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC membrane staining is absent with ER deficient HeLa cells and present only on the membrane of cells that endogenously produce ER or HeLa cells that stably express mER&#x003b1;. Taken together these data strongly suggest that non-genomic effects of E<sub>2 </sub>are at least partially mediated by a membrane associated ER. However, whether the receptor is the classical nuclear ER translocated to the membrane or an ER unique to the membrane remains unanswered.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>The results presented here suggest that E<sub>2</sub>-BSA can bind to the estrogen receptor but the rate of binding is impeded due to steric and other considerations. Commercially available forms of the reagent are contaminated with dissociable E<sub>2 </sub>and should be purified prior to studies designed to demonstrate effects mediated through a membrane ER. Although we demonstrate that classical nuclear ERs can be translocated to the membrane, the conclusive identity of the endogenous membrane receptor awaits purification and sequencing of the putative membrane ER protein.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Establishment of ER stable transfectants</title><p>Full-length cDNA encoding the mouse ER&#x003b1; was cloned into a vector containing the CMV promoter driving the neomycin resistance gene (pcER&#x003b1;). HeLa cells maintained in MEM containing 10% fetal bovine serum under 5% CO2 were transfected with pcER&#x003b1; and successful transfectants (HeLa-ER&#x003b1;) were selected by survival in media containing the neomycin analog, G418 (400 ug/ml).</p></sec><sec><title>Preparation of E<sub>2</sub>-BSA free of E<sub>2</sub></title><p>400 ul of E<sub>2</sub>-BSA (10<sup>-5 </sup>M in estrogen dissolved in 50 mM tris, pH 8.5, Sigma) was added to a centrifugal filter unit with a MW cut-off of 3,000 (Millipore) and centrifuged at 14,000 &#x000d7; g until 50 ul of retentate remained. The retentate was washed 3 times with 350 ul of buffer, recovered and volume adjusted to 400 ul.</p></sec><sec><title>Binding of estradiol to purified estrogen receptor</title><p><sup>3</sup>H-labeled E<sub>2 </sub>(NEN, specific activity 48 Ci/mmol, 10<sup>-8 </sup>M) was incubated with recombinant ER&#x003b1; (.035 pM, Alexis Corp) for four hours at room temperature in binding buffer (10 mM tris, 10% glycerol, 2 mM DTT, and 1 mg/ml BSA). The binding of labeled E<sub>2 </sub>to ER&#x003b1; was competed by various concentrations of ultrafiltered E<sub>2</sub>-BSA or E<sub>2 </sub>(10<sup>-9 </sup>to 3.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>-6 </sup>M in E<sub>2</sub>) added four hours prior to or concurrently with the addition of labeled E<sub>2</sub>. ER&#x003b1; was precipitated by the addition of a hydroxyapatite slurry (50% v/v in TE) and centrifugation at 10,000 &#x000d7; g. The pellet was washed three times with wash buffer (40 mM tris, 100 mM KCl, 1 mM EDTA, and 1 mM EGTA) and <sup>3</sup>H-E<sub>2 </sub>binding determined by liquid scintillation counting.</p></sec><sec><title>E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC binding to cell membranes of ER producing cells</title><p>HeLa-ER&#x003b1; cells or mammary tumor cells (MC7, ATTC) were plated on glass cover slips and incubated with 500 ul of 10<sup>-8 </sup>M (in estrogen) E<sub>2</sub>-BSA conjugated to FITC (E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC, Sigma, 10 moles E2 and 3.5 moles FITC per mole BSA) or BSA-FITC (Sigma, equimolar to E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC with respect to BSA) for 30 minutes at 4&#x000b0;C. Binding of E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC to MC7 cells was competed by a 30 minute pre-incubation with E<sub>2</sub>, ICI-182,780, or E<sub>2</sub>-BSA (Sigma, 10<sup>-7 </sup>to 10<sup>-9 </sup>M). Cells were fixed and FITC staining visualized by confocal microscopy. Images were digitized, inverted to black on white, and pixel density for each cell determined by averaging the density across the cell membrane at four orthogonal points (Scion Image, Scion Corp).</p><p>The stability of E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC during the incubation with MC7 cells was assessed by HPLC. E<sub>2</sub>-BSA-FITC (500 ul, 10<sup>-8 </sup>M in estrogen) was added to empty wells and to wells containing MC7 cells prepared as above for 30 minutes at 4&#x000b0;C. 10 ul of supernatant was resolved using a C-18 reverse phase column (Xterra C-18 RP, 5 um, 4.6 mm &#x000d7; 250 mm, Waters). A multiple solvent deliver system (BIO CM 4000, Milton Roy) provided a methanol-water gradient from 80% methanol to 50% methanol over 30 minutes at a flow rate of one ml/minute. Peaks were detected by a scanning fluorescence detector (model 747, Waters) at an excitation wavelength of 495 nm and emission wavelength of 519 nm. Area under the curve was calculated using standard algorithms (Millenium Software). Assays were performed in triplicate.</p></sec><sec><title>Estradiol binding studies</title><p>Subconfluent HeLa-ER&#x003b1; or native HeLa cells were trypsinized and aliquots (2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6 </sup>cells) incubated with several concentrations of <sup>3</sup>H 17&#x003b2;-estradiol in the presence and absence of a 200-fold excess of cold 17&#x003b2;-estradiol for 30 min at 37&#x000b0;. Cells were then incubated on ice for 15 min, washed three times with 2 ml of ice cold 0.2% BSA-saline and pelleted by centrifugation at 1,5000 rpm for 10 min at 4&#x000b0;C. Cells were lysed by the addition of 100 ul of lysis buffer, vortexed and counted. Data was analyzed by Scatchard analysis.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>None declared.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>DB wrote the manuscript and performed binding assays. MK generated the stable cell lines. YT performed binding assays.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mermelstein</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Surmeier</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estradiol reduces calcium currents in rat neostriatal neurons via a membrane receptor</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>1996</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>595</fpage><lpage>604</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8551343</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Dudley</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fawcett</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The specificity of the response of preoptic-septal area neurons to estrogen: 17 alpha-estradiol versus 17 beta-estradiol and the response of extrahypothalamic neurons</article-title><source>Exp Brain Res</source><year>1977</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">563340</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Armen</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gay</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Simultaneous detection and functional response of testosterone and estradiol receptors in osteoblast plasma membranes</article-title><source>J Cell Biochem</source><year>2000</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>620</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10996853</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1097-4644(20001215)79:4&#x0003c;620::AID-JCB110&#x0003e;3.3.CO;2-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Migliaccio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Domenico</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Castoria</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>de Falco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bontempo</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nola</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Auricchio</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tyrosine kinase/p21ras/MAP-kinase pathway activation by estradiol-receptor complex in MCF-7 cells</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>1996</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1292</fpage><lpage>300</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8635462</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Migliaccio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Castoria</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Domenico</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>de Falco</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bilancio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lombardi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Barone</surname><given-names>MV</given-names></name><name><surname>Ametrano</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Zannini</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Abbondanza</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Steroid-induced androgen receptor-oestradiol receptor beta-Src complex triggers prostate cancer cell proliferation</article-title><source>Embo J</source><year>2000</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>5406</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11032808</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/19.20.5406</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vargas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Delaney</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Farhat</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rego</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramwell</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of estradiol 17 beta on pressor responses of rat mesenteric bed to norepinephrine, K+, and U-46619</article-title><source>J Cardiovasc Pharmacol</source><year>1995</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>200</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7752645</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Farhat</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name><name><surname>Abi-Younes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dingaan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Vargas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramwell</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estradiol increases cyclic adenosine monophosphate in rat pulmonary vascular smooth muscle cells by a nongenomic mechanism</article-title><source>J Pharmacol Exp Ther</source><year>1996</year><volume>276</volume><fpage>652</fpage><lpage>7</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8632333</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caulin-Glaser</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Cardena</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarrel</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sessa</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bender</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>17 beta-estradiol regulation of human endothelial cell basal nitric oxide release, independent of cytosolic Ca2+ mobilization</article-title><source>Circ Res</source><year>1997</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>885</fpage><lpage>92</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9351464</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakhla</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosner</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stimulation of prostate cancer growth by androgens and estrogens through the intermediacy of sex hormone-binding globulin</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><year>1996</year><volume>137</volume><fpage>4126</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8828467</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/en.137.10.4126</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pietras</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Szego</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Specific binding sites for oestrogen at the outer surfaces of isolated endometrial cells</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1977</year><volume>265</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">834244</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Prevot</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Croix</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rialas</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Poulain</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Fricchione</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Stefano</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Beauvillain</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estradiol coupling to endothelial nitric oxide stimulates gonadotropin-releasing hormone release from rat median eminence via a membrane receptor</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><year>1999</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>652</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9927290</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/en.140.2.652</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benten</surname><given-names>WP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lieberherr</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Giese</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wunderlich</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estradiol binding to cell surface raises cytosolic free calcium in T cells</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><year>1998</year><volume>422</volume><fpage>349</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9498814</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0014-5793(98)00039-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Goeij</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>van Zeeland</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Beek</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bosman</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Steroid-bovine serum albumin conjugates: molecular characterization and their interaction with androgen and estrogen receptors</article-title><source>J Steroid Biochem</source><year>1986</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1017</fpage><lpage>31</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3724140</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0022-4731(86)90355-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stevis</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Deecher</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Suhadolnik</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mallis</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Frail</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential effects of estradiol and estradiol-BSA conjugates</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><year>1999</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>5455</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10537181</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/en.140.11.5455</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Razandi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedram</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Greene</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cell membrane and nuclear estrogen receptors (ERs) originate from a single transcript: studies of ERalpha and ERbeta expressed in Chinese hamster ovary cells</article-title><source>Mol Endocrinol</source><year>1999</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>307</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9973260</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/me.13.2.307</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tassignon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Haeseleer</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Borkowski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural antiestrogen receptor autoantibodies in man with estrogenic activity in mammary carcinoma cell culture: study of their mechanism of action; evidence for involvement of estrogen-like epitopes</article-title><source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>1997</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>3464</fpage><lpage>70</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9329387</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/jc.82.10.3464</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berthois</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Pourreau-Schneider</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gandilhon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mittre</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tubiana</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estradiol membrane binding sites on human breast cancer cell lines. Use of a fluorescent estradiol conjugate to demonstrate plasma membrane binding systems</article-title><source>J Steroid Biochem</source><year>1986</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>963</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3025520</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0022-4731(86)90330-4</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Leclercq</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of potential implication of membrane estrogen binding sites on ERE-dependent transcriptional activity and intracellular estrogen receptor-alpha regulation in MCF-7 breast cancer cells</article-title><source>J Steroid Biochem Mol Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>109</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11867270</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0960-0760(01)00175-3</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loomis</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of estrogens and xenoestrogens on androgen production by Atlantic croaker testes in vitro: evidence for a nongenomic action mediated by an estrogen membrane receptor</article-title><source>Biol Reprod</source><year>2000</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>995</fpage><lpage>1004</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10727269</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berthois</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Pourreau-Schneider</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gandilhon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mittre</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tubiana</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estradiol membrane binding sites on human breast cancer cell lines. Use of a fluorescent estradiol conjugate to demonstrate plasma membrane binding systems</article-title><source>J Steroid Biochem</source><year>1986</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>963</fpage><lpage>72</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3025520</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0022-4731(86)90330-4</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Swenson</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Sladek</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gonadal steroid modulation of vasopressin secretion in response to osmotic stimulation</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><year>1997</year><volume>138</volume><fpage>2089</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9112409</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/en.138.5.2089</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christian</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Rolls</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nongenomic actions of testosterone on a subset of lactotrophs in the male rat pituitary</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><year>2000</year><volume>141</volume><fpage>3111</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10965881</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/en.141.9.3111</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiebe</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute, nongenomic actions of the neuroactive gonadal steroid, 3 alpha-hydroxy-4-pregnen-20-one (3 alpha HP), on FSH release in perifused rat anterior pituitary cells</article-title><source>Endocrine</source><year>1997</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9368676</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Contreras</surname><given-names>HR</given-names></name><name><surname>Llanos</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of progesterone receptors in human spermatozoa and their correlation with morphological and functional properties</article-title><source>Int J Androl</source><year>2001</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>246</fpage><lpage>52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11454077</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2605.2001.00294.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Somanath</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gandhi</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of membrane associated non-genomic progesterone receptor(s) in caprine spermatozoa</article-title><source>Anim Reprod Sci</source><year>2002</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>205</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12417121</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0378-4320(02)00168-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Norfleet</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Gametchu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estrogen receptor-alpha detected on the plasma membrane of aldehyde-fixed GH3/B6/F10 rat pituitary tumor cells by enzyme-linked immunocytochemistry</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><year>1999</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>3805</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10433242</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/en.140.8.3805</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nadal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ropero</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Laribi</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Maillet</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuentes</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Soria</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nongenomic actions of estrogens and xenoestrogens by binding at a plasma membrane receptor unrelated to estrogen receptor alpha and estrogen receptor beta</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>11603</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11027358</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.97.21.11603</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



