<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Retrovirology</journal-id><journal-title>Retrovirology</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1742-4690</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15601474</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC544868</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1742-4690-1-44</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1742-4690-1-44</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>HIV-1 nef suppression by virally encoded microRNA</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Omoto</surname><given-names>Shinya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>shinyaomoto@hotmail.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>Masafumi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>shin@snow.odn.ne.jp</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tsutsumi</surname><given-names>Yutaka</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><email>tsutsumi@fugita-hu.ac.jp</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ichikawa</surname><given-names>Yuko</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>ichikawa@phar.nagoya-cu.ac.jp</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Okuyama</surname><given-names>Harumi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>okuyamh@phar.nagoya-cu.ac.jp</email></contrib><contrib id="A6" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Brisibe</surname><given-names>Ebiamadon Andi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I5">5</xref><email>brisbie2002@yahoo.co.uk</email></contrib><contrib id="A7" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Saksena</surname><given-names>Nitin K</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I6">6</xref><email>nitin_saksena@wmi.usyd.edu.au</email></contrib><contrib id="A8" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>Yoichi R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>yofuji@phar.nagoya-cu.ac.jp</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Molecular Biology and Retroviral Genetics Group, Graduate School of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Nagoya City University, Nagoya 467-8603, Japan</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Division of Nutritional Sciences, Graduate School of Pharmaceutical Sciences, Nagoya City University, Nagoya 467-8603, Japan</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Department of Molecular Diagnostics, Fields of Pathology, Nagoya University Graduate School of Medicine, Nagoya 464-8550, Japan</aff><aff id="I4"><label>4</label>Department of Pathology, Fujita Health University School of Medicine, Toyoake, Aichi 470-1192, Japan</aff><aff id="I5"><label>5</label>Research and Scientific Developments Division, Molecular Bio/Sciences Limited, 124 MCC Road, Calabar, Cross River State, Nigeria</aff><aff id="I6"><label>6</label>Retroviral Genetics Division, Center for Virus Research, Westmead Millennium Institute, Westmead Hospital, Westmead NSW 2145, Sydney, Australia</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>12</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>1</volume><fpage>44</fpage><lpage>44</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.retrovirology.com/content/1/1/44"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>8</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>12</month><year>2004</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2004 Omoto et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2004</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Omoto et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Omoto
               Shinya
               
               shinyaomoto@hotmail.com
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            HIV-1 nef suppression by virally encoded microRNA
         </dc:title><dc:date>2004</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Retrovirology 1(1): 44-. (2004)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1742-4690(2004)1:1&#x0003c;44&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1742-4690</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>MicroRNAs (miRNAs) are 21~25-nucleotides (nt) long and interact with mRNAs to trigger either translational repression or RNA cleavage through RNA interference (RNAi), depending on the degree of complementarity with the target mRNAs. Our recent study has shown that HIV-1 <italic>nef </italic>dsRNA from AIDS patients who are long-term non-progressors (LTNPs) inhibited the transcription of HIV-1.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Here, we show the possibility that <italic>nef</italic>-derived miRNAs are produced in HIV-1 persistently infected cells. Furthermore, <italic>nef </italic>short hairpin RNA (shRNA) that corresponded to a predicted <italic>nef </italic>miRNA (~25 nt, miR-N367) can block HIV-1 Nef expression <italic>in vitro </italic>and the suppression by shRNA/miR-N367 would be related with low viremia in an LTNP (15-2-2). In the 15-2-2 model mice, the weight loss, which may be rendered by <italic>nef </italic>was also inhibited by shRNA/miR-N367 corresponding to suppression of <italic>nef </italic>expression <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>These data suggest that <italic>nef</italic>/U3 miRNAs produced in HIV-1-infected cells may suppress both Nef function and HIV-1 virulence through the RNAi pathway.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>The human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), which infect humans cause acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS), which has reached pandemic levels in some societies, especially those in Southern Africa and Southeast Asia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Given the immensity of HIV pandemic, the development of a rather safe and cheap, effective therapeutics, has become the main focus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Several strategies attempted to control the spread of AIDS have not shown major breakthrough and the vaccines have shown little promise as far as their efficacy is concerned. However, one approach used extensively in other diploid organisms, which now has tremendous potential to encourage antiviral defense against HIV appears to be double stranded RNA-dependent post-transcriptional gene silencing or RNA interference (RNAi).</p><p>RNAi is a defense mechanism against aberrant transcripts that may be produced during viral infection and mobilization of transposons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. The RNAi pathway has been implicated in silencing transposons in the <italic>C. elegans </italic>germline [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>], silencing stellate repeats in the <italic>Drosophila </italic>germline, and the response against invading viruses in plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Post-transcriptional regulation by RNAi is mediated by small non-coding RNAs (~25-nucleotides; nt). Small interfering RNAs (siRNAs) are short RNA duplexes that direct the degradation of homologous transcripts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. In contrast, the single stranded microRNAs (miRNAs) bind to 3' untranslated regions of mRNA with complementarity of 50 to 85% to give translational repression without target degradation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. The mature miRNA (~25-nt) is produced by processing of ~70-nt precursor stem-loop hairpin RNAs (Pre-miRNA) by Dicer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. At the moment several human diseases, including spinal muscular atrophy (Paushkin <italic>et al</italic>., 2002), fragile X mental retardation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>] and chronic lymphocytic leukemia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>] have been identified as illnesses in which miRNAs or their machinery might be implicated. However, up until now there has been no clear-cut scientific proof that establishes the exact correlation between miRNAs and human infectious diseases such as AIDS.</p><p>One of the human immunodeficiency virus type 1 (HIV-1) coding accessory genes, <italic>nef</italic>, is located at the 3' end of the viral genome and partially overlaps the 3'-long terminal repeat (LTR). The <italic>nef </italic>gene is uniquely conserved in HIV-1, HIV-2 and simian immunodeficiency virus (SIV) and is not essential but important for viral replication <italic>in vivo </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. The <italic>nef </italic>gene is expressed during HIV infection and often accounts for up to 80% of HIV-1 specific RNA transcripts during the early stages of viral replication [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Our own investigations have shown that defective variants of <italic>nef </italic>dsRNA containing the 3'-LTR regions, obtained from long-term non-progressor (LTNP) AIDS patients, actually inhibited the transcription of HIV-1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Furthermore, <italic>cis</italic>-expression of mutated F12-HIV-1 <italic>nef </italic>inhibits replication of highly productive NL43-HIV-1 strain, which is not related to down-regulation of CD4 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. It has been demonstrated that F12 <italic>nef </italic>gene cloned from the provirus of naturally occurring HUT-78 T cells infected with the supernatant of the peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) of an HIV-seropositive non-producer patient, induces a block of viral replication [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. Thus, it has been suggested that <italic>nef </italic>RNAs may be a <italic>cis</italic>-regulatory factor for HIV-1 replication [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>].</p><p>In the current study, we have established the link between miRNAs and HIV infections by demonstrating that <italic>nef</italic>-derived miRNAs are produced in HIV-1-infected cells. The results presented here show that <italic>nef </italic>short hairpin RNAs (shRNAs) corresponding to the <italic>nef </italic>miRNAs efficiently block RNA stability or mRNA translation, perhaps an indication that HIV-1 regulates its own replication by using <italic>nef </italic>miRNAs.</p></sec><sec><title>Results and Discussion</title><sec><title>Identification of a candidate of miRNAs in HIV-1-infected cells</title><p>Very recently, the Epstein-Barr virus (EBV)-encoded miRNAs were identified. Thus, during the preliminary stages of this study, our curiosity was fixed on the need to find out if indeed there was any relationship between <italic>nef </italic>miRNAs and HIV-1-infected cells. To achieve this purpose, we extracted total RNA from HIV-1 IIIB strain persistently infected MT-4 T cells and northern blot analysis was performed using eight probes against the <italic>nef </italic>coding region, as shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>. Analyses using several anti-sense probes, small RNA molecules approximately ~25-nt in size were detected as well as HIV-1 major transcripts, 9.1, 4.3 and 1.8 kb bands (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>). Similar results were obtained with total RNA from HIV-1 SF2 strain infected MT-4 T cells (data not shown). RNA samples treated with a mixture of the single stranded specific RNases A and T1 also generated ~25-nt RNAs that hybridized in northern blots with the sense probes against the same <italic>nef </italic>region. However HIV-1 major transcripts were not detected (data not shown), indicating that the structure of the small RNA molecules could be double-stranded RNAs (miRNAs). Some variability was observed when the quantity of the miRNAs was compared with the total of the major transcripts. A maximum of 3.2% of miRNAs was detected by using #367 probe when compared with total HIV-1 transcripts, and the minimum of 0.3% was detected by using probe# 90 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Detection of HIV-1 <italic>nef </italic>miRNAs and inhibition of Nef expression by <italic>nef </italic>RNAs. (<bold>A</bold>) Schematic representation of HIV-1 <italic>nef </italic>in its genome and synthetic DNA probes (#) used in this study. (<bold>B</bold>) Total RNAs were extracted from MT-4 T cells persistently infected with HIV-1 IIIB, separated on a 15% polyacrylamide-7 M urea gel, and subjected to northern blot analysis. The approximate sizes of the three classes of HIV-1 transcripts and small RNAs are indicated on the right. The loading control was rRNA stained with ethidium bromide. Relative expression (%) of <italic>nef </italic>small RNAs to the three classes of HIV-1 transcripts is at the bottom of figure. (<bold>C</bold>) Schematic representation of effector plasmids (<bold>E</bold>) H1 promoter-driven shRNA expression plasmids. Reporter (R) Nef-EGFP expression plasmid (pYM2.2) is also shown. <bold>(D) </bold>Inhibition by sinefs in pH1 plamids of Nef-EGFP expression. Either sinef, siluc or siegfp in each plasmid was transfected into Jurkat T cells in the presence of either pYM2.2 or control pEGFP-N1. At 36 h after transfection EGFP-positive cells were counted by flow cytometry. Data represent the relative activity of EGFP-positive cells where the percentage of positive cells in the sample transfected with pYM2.2 or pEGFP-N1 plus pcDNA3.1 or si(-) in pH1 plasmid was scored as 100%. Data are averages of three independent experiments + SD. Bars, SD. (<bold>E</bold>) Immunoblot analysis showing inhibition of YM2.2 expression by different <italic>nef </italic>shRNAs. Jurakat T cells were transfected with pYM2.2 and pH1/sinefs or siluc plasmid, cellular lysates were prepared 48 h after transfection, and immunoblotted with rabbit serum against Nef (upper panel) and anti-&#x003b2;-actin antibody (<bold>lower panel</bold>). The &#x003b2;-actin expression shows equal loading of all samples.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1742-4690-1-44-1"/></fig><p>To randomly clone the <italic>nef </italic>miRNA, ~25-nt RNAs were gel purified, cloned and sequenced. The sequences from the <italic>nef </italic>miRNA clones were 5'-acugaccuuuggauggugcuucaa-3' or similar ones, corresponded to the nucleotides approximately 420 to 443 conserved region of <italic>nef </italic>(miR-N367). The most notable feature of this analysis is that it has proven beyond reasonable doubts that <italic>nef</italic>-derived miRNAs are produced in HIV-1 infected cells.</p></sec><sec><title>Inhibition of Nef by plasmids-encoding siRNA/miRNA</title><p>To examine inhibition of <italic>nef </italic>expression by the <italic>nef </italic>miRNA, we constructed eight shRNAs homologous to the native miRNA or probes used in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. Although it has been reported that three to four mutations in the sense strand derived from miRNA could have the potential to control unmutated 21-nt stem loop [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>], we investigated whether the native shRNA-expressing plasmid can effectively reduce <italic>nef </italic>gene expression or not (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1D</xref>). We used <italic>egfp </italic>or <italic>luc </italic>gene (pH1/siegfp or luc) as a positive or negative control. All the shRNA-expressing plasmids including the controls were co-transfected into Jurkat T cells with pYM2.2 and cell fluorescence resulting from the expression of EGFP reporter gene was quantified by flow cytometry. The sinef176, 190, 367/miR-N367 and control siegfp all showed efficient reduction, but the sinef 007, 084, 299, 468 and 580 constructs gave only modest reductions, and no suppression was observed with si(-) and luc (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1D</xref> and Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). Immunoblot analysis using anti-Nef rabbit serum also confirmed the inhibition of Nef-EGFP expression by sinef 176, 190 and 367/miR-N367 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1E</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Relation between AIDS clinical courses and <italic>nef </italic>dsRNA or siRNA/miRNA in suppression of <italic>nef </italic>gene expression</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center">Nef inhibitor</td><td align="center" colspan="3">Nef expressed by:</td><td align="center">Target region</td><td align="center">Clinical courses</td></tr><tr><td></td><td colspan="3"><hr></hr></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Nef-EGFP</td><td align="center">HIV-1 IIIB</td><td align="center">PFV/nef</td><td></td><td></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><bold><italic>dsRNA</italic>*</bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center"><bold><italic>Human</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="center">SF2</td><td align="center">++ <sup>&#x02020;</sup></td><td align="center">++</td><td align="center">ND<sup>&#x02021;</sup></td><td align="left">Full-length (including miR-N367)</td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1-3-3</td><td align="center">++</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="left">U3 deleted</td><td align="center">Rapid progressor, Died within 3 years</td></tr><tr><td align="center">4-2-1</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="left">U3 region (including miR-N367)</td><td align="center">Rapid progressor, Died within 3 years</td></tr><tr><td align="center">15-2-2</td><td align="center">++</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="left">U3 region (including miR-N367)</td><td align="center">Non progressor with low plasma viremia</td></tr><tr><td align="center">16-1-1</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="left">U3 deleted</td><td align="center">Non progressor with low plasma viremia</td></tr><tr><td align="center">jw95-1</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="left">U3 region (including miR-N367)</td><td align="center">Non progressor with undetectable viremia</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold><italic>siRNA</italic></bold></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td align="center"><bold><italic>15-2-2 model mouse</italic></bold></td></tr><tr><td align="center">dsnef</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="left">Full-length</td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="center">sinef007</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="left">Upstream of U3 region</td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="center">sinef084</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="left">Upstream of U3 region</td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="center">sinef176</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="center">++</td><td align="left">Upstream of U3 region<sup>&#x000a7;</sup></td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="center">sinef190</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="left">Upstream of U3 region</td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="center">sinef299</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="left">U3 region (aa 83&#x02013;135)</td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="left">sinef367/miR-N367</td><td align="center">++</td><td align="center">+++</td><td align="center">++</td><td align="left">U3 region</td><td align="center">No weight loss</td></tr><tr><td align="center">sinef468</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="left">U3 region</td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="center">sinef580</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="left">U3 region</td><td align="center">ND</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*dsRNA to LTNPs' <italic>nef </italic>has been described (Yamamoto <italic>et al</italic>., 2002).</p><p><sup>&#x02020; </sup>-, negative; +, 0 to 50 % inhibition; ++, 50 to 75% inhibition; +++, 75 to 100 % inhibition.</p><p><sup>&#x02021; </sup>ND, not done.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Inhibition of Nef expression by STYLE vector-encoding nef siRNA/miR-N367</title><p>To assess the effects of <italic>nef </italic>miR-N367 <italic>in vivo</italic>, we constructed a prototype foamy virus (PFV)-based live vector. The PFV vector expressed HIV-1 SF2 <italic>nef </italic>gene as a reporter and the STYLE vector expressed shRNA as effectors. The full-length <italic>nef </italic>gene was inserted into the <italic>bel-2 </italic>portion of a PFV clone (22) in frame to obtain pPFV/nef (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>). The pPFV/nef was transfected into BHK cells and treated with the histone deacetylase inhibitor, trichostatin A (TA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. The viral supernatant, which contained approximately 5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6 </sup>infectious units (IFU), was collected at 72 h after transfection. For preparation of the STYLE vectors to deliver the shRNAs, the <italic>env </italic>gene portion of pSKY3.0 was replaced with the shRNA expression cassette under the control of the H1 promoter. The pSTYLE was produced (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref>), and transfected into the FFV envelope-expressing packaging cells, CRFK sugi clone # 6, in the presence of TA. The transfected CRFKsugi clone #6 had 99% FFV Env positive cells when analyzed by flow cytometry. The viral supernatant with a titer of ca. 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5 </sup>IFU was collected at 72 h post-transfection.</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Inhibition of <italic>nef </italic>expression in human T cells by <italic>nef </italic>siRNAs. (<bold>A</bold>) Schematic representation of shRNA-expressing STYLE vector (<bold>E</bold>) and HIV-1 SF2 <italic>nef </italic>gene expressing pPFV/nef vector (R). The helper plasmid, pFFenv expresses FFV envelope protein under the control of CMV promoter. (<bold>B</bold>) Detection of expression of <italic>nef </italic>mRNA and integration of vectors. STYLE, SKY3.0, PFV/nef, PFV or mock was used to infect Jurkat T cells and the infected cells were cultured for 2 weeks. After 2 weeks, <italic>gag </italic>and <italic>nef </italic>mRNA expression was measured by RT-PCR. Genomic DNA of LTR, <italic>gag </italic>and <italic>nef </italic>of STYLE or PFV/nef were also detected by PCR. &#x003b2;-<italic>actin </italic>was used as a control. (<bold>C</bold>) Inhibition of Nef-EGFP expression by <italic>nef </italic>siRNA-expressing STYLE in Jurkat T cells. The pYM2.2 was transfected into each of the STYLE or mock-infected Jurkat T cells and EGFP-expressing cells were counted by flow cytometry at 48 h after transfection. Data represent the relative activity of EGFP-positive cells, where the percentage of positive cells in the sample transfected with pYM2.2 upon the STYLE-si(-) infected cells was scored as 100%. (<bold>D</bold>) Inhibition of HIV-1 transcription and replication by <italic>nef </italic>STYLE-367. HIV-1 IIIB persistently infected MT-4 T cells were transfected with the pLTR<sub>SF2 </sub>reporter and &#x003b2;-gal expressing control pCMV&#x003b2; plasmids at 72 h after infection with STYLE. At 48 h post-transfection, Luc activity was measured and normalized as Luc values (Luc/&#x003b2;-gal). Absolute levels of Luc activity in the samples of pLTR<sub>SF2 </sub>plus SRYLE-si(-) were 16,311 + 1,253 or 783 + 87 light units for STYLE-367/miR-N367 transfectants. Data represent the relative Luc activities where the percentage of positive cells in the samples infected with the STYLE-si(-) was scored as 100%. After 48 h, p24 antigen was also measured in the cell culture supernatant of STYLE-infected Jurkat T cells. Data are averages of three independent experiments + SD. Bars, SD. (<bold>E</bold>) Inhibition of <italic>nef </italic>expression by <italic>nef </italic>siRNA in Jurkat T cells. Cells were infected with PFV/nef 48 h after infection with the STYLE and then subjected to semi-quantitative RT-PCR analysis. Data represent the relative expression of mRNA, where the percentage of positive cells in the sample of mock-infected cells (E: Mock) relative to the PFV/nef (R: PFV/nef) infected cells was scored as 100%. Data averages were derived from three independent experiments + SD. Bars, SD.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1742-4690-1-44-2"/></fig><p>The expression of viral mRNAs and integrated DNAs from either the PFV/nef or STYLE vectors was confirmed by infection of Jurkat T cells. The mRNAs and genomic DNA were extracted from the infected cells at 2 weeks post-infection. The PFV/nef-expressed <italic>gag </italic>and <italic>nef </italic>mRNAs and the STYLE-expressed <italic>gag </italic>mRNA were detected after amplification of these regions using reverse transcription (RT)-PCR. The integration of the DNAs into the genome of Jurkat T cells was also confirmed by PCR of the LTR, <italic>gag </italic>and/or <italic>nef </italic>regions (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>). The control SKY3.0 and PFV-infected cells were both negative for <italic>nef </italic>mRNA and integrated DNA (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref>). The integrated DNA was also detected by southern blot analysis with genomic DNA of either PFV/nef or STYLE-infected cells (data not shown). Expression of shRNAs (~22-nt) was also confirmed in STYLE-infected cells by northern blot analysis (data not shown). Expression of Nef protein in PFV/nef-infected cells was also detected with specific rabbit anti-Nef serum in immunoblots (data not shown).</p><p>To evaluate whether the STYLE encoding siRNA could inhibit the expression of the <italic>nef </italic>gene in cultured human T cells, pYM2.2 was transfected into each of the STYLE-infected Jurkat T cells (m.o.i. = ca. 0.1). The most efficient sinef176, 190 and 367/miR-N367 vectors for reduction in <italic>nef </italic>expression (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1D</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1E</xref>) were selected for this experiment. The EGFP-positive cells were counted by flow cytometry at 48 h after transfection. Expression of Nef-EGFP fusion protein was reduced drastically following treatment with either the STYLE-176 (74 + 3.2) or 190 (51 + 4.2) and also reduced with 367/miR-N367 (32 + 2.3%). Reduction was insignificant with either the STYLE-si(-) (0 + 0.7) or STYLE-luc (7 + 0.9%) controls (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C</xref>).</p><p>The <italic>in vitro </italic>inhibitory effects of STYLE encoding <italic>nef </italic>siRNA on HIV-1-infected cells were evaluated in Luc assays and using MT-4 T cells persistently infected with HIV-1 IIIB. Cultivation of the STYLE infected cells for 72 h followed by transfection with the pLTR<sub>SF2 </sub>and culture for another 48 h showed that STYLE-176, 190 and 367/miR-N367 all significantly (p &#x0003c; 0.005) suppressed Luc activity when compared to controls (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2D</xref>). HIV-1 p24 Gag was also significantly inhibited in the culture supernatant by infection with STYLE-176, 190 and 367/miR-N367 when compared to controls (p &#x0003c; 0.001) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2D</xref>). These data suggested that shRNA/miR-N367 could inhibit HIV-1 transcription and replication in intact HIV-1-infected human T cells.</p><p>Jurkat T cells that had been transduced with <italic>nef </italic>shRNA for 48 h were infected with the PFV/nef. Semi-quantitative RT-PCR analysis revealed that while treatment with STYLE-190 dramatically reduced the expression of both <italic>nef </italic>and <italic>gag </italic>mRNAs of the PFV/nef, the expression of <italic>nef </italic>mRNA was also drastically suppressed by STYLE-176 and 367/miR-N367 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2E</xref>). However the STYLE-si(-) and luc controls showed ~10% suppression of <italic>nef </italic>and ~20% suppression of <italic>gag </italic>mRNAs (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2E</xref>), which was probably a result of interference following super-infection. Nonetheless, both <italic>nef </italic>transcription and PFV/nef replication were substantially inhibited by STYLE-176, 190 and 367/miR-N367.</p></sec><sec><title>Inhibition of Nef expression by siRNA/miR-N367 in mice</title><p>Since different host gene products are required for siRNA-mediated RNAi and miRNA-mediated translational repression with <italic>let-7 </italic>and <italic>lin-4 </italic>in <italic>C. elegans</italic>, the two RNAs may not have the same functions <italic>in vivo </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. To test this point, we investigated the efficacy of miR-N367 using STYLE-367 in mammalian tissues. The study mice were group 1 = PFV/nef-infected (n = 6); group 2 = PFV/nef and control STYLE-luc infected (n = 6); group 3 = PFV/nef and STYLE-367-infected (n = 8); and group 4 = STYLE-367-infected (n = 6). Identical study groups were used for both Balb/c and C3H/Hej mouse strains. Nef protein expressing lymphocytes were quantified by histochemical analysis using F3 Nef monoclonal antibody (mAb) or anti-Nef rabbit serum 2 days after PFV/nef infection. Nef protein was detected by immunofluoresence assay in the subcapsular area of the spleens of groups 1 or 2 Balb/c mice, but not groups 3 or 4 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref> and Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). No positive cell staining was observed using normal rabbit serum as a primary antibody (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>). To test the expression of <italic>nef</italic>, nested RT-PCR was also done on day 2 to evaluate the degree of <italic>nef </italic>mRNA expression in the spleen, liver, adipose tissues and hematopoietic cells in groups 1&#x02013;4. The <italic>nef </italic>mRNA was significantly expressed in liver and hematopoietic cells of Balb/c mice in groups 1 and 2, but not in the group 3 animals that were STYLE-367 infected (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Tissues from group 4 did not show any <italic>nef </italic>bands after RT-PCR (data not shown).</p><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><italic>In vivo </italic>effects of miR-N367. (<bold>A</bold>) Distribution of Nef positive staining cells in the subcapsular area of groups 2 or 3 mouse spleens at 2 days after infection with PFV/nef. Anti-Nef rabbit serum or normal rabbit serum was used as a primary antibody. (<bold>B</bold>) Immunofluorescence for 305 mAb positive staining cells in the subcapsular area of groups 2 or 3 mouse spleens at 2 days after infection with PFV/nef and immunoperoxidase staining by 305 mAb in cells of interfollicular area of HIV-1 uninfected human spleen and tonsillar follicle. (<bold>C</bold>) Short term body weights of PFV/nef-infected Balb/c mice. The body weights of the PFV/nef-infected mice (group 1, n = 6, solid circle), the PFV/nef-infected followed by the STYLE-luc-infected mice (group 2, n = 6, solid triangle), the PFV/nef-infected followed by the STYLE-367-infected mice (group 3, n = 8, open triangle) and the STYLE-367-infected mice (group 4, n = 6, open circles) were measured from days 0 to 5. (<bold>D</bold>) Long term body weights of PFV/nef-infected C3H/Hej mice. Treatment of each group and numbers of mice were same as (<bold>C</bold>). Bars, SD. *; p &#x0003c; 0.05, **; p &#x0003c; 0.01 (relative to group 3). (<bold>E</bold>) Immunoperoxidase staining by 305 mAb and anti-Nef rabbit serum in cells of mouse or human adipose tissue. Arrows show positively stained areas. Magnification, X 20 (A and B); X 20 and X 200 (<bold>E</bold>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1742-4690-1-44-3"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Histochemical detection and RT-PCR amplification of Nef from human and mouse tissues</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center">Tissues</td><td align="center" colspan="3">Histochemistry*</td><td align="center" colspan="3">RT-PCR<sup>&#x02020;</sup></td></tr><tr><td></td><td colspan="6"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">F3</td><td align="center">Anti-Nef rabbit serum</td><td align="center">305</td><td align="center"><italic>nef</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>gag</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>PPAR&#x003b3;</italic></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center"><italic>Human (HIV-1 uninfected)</italic></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Spleen</td><td align="center">-<sup>&#x000a7;</sup></td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-<sup>&#x02021;</sup></td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Tonsillar follicle</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Liver</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Adipose tissue (Salivary gland)</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Bone marrow</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Bronchi</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Thyroid gland</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Heart muscle</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Prostate gland</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Testis</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Colon mucosa</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Lung</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Adrenal gland</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Brain (Cerebrum cortex)</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>Mouse Group 1 and 2</italic></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Spleen</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Liver</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Hematopoietic cells</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Adipose tissue (Intestine)</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>Mouse Group 3</italic></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td align="center">Spleen</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">&#x000b1;</td><td align="center">&#x000b1;</td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Liver</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Hematopoietic cells</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="center">ND</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">ND</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Adipose tissue (Intestine)</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">+</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*Histological analysis was performed with human or each group of mouse tissues by using F3 anti-Nef mAb, anti-Nef rabbit serum or 305 mAb as a primary antibody. For secondary antibody, FITC or peroxidase-conjugated antibody was used.</p><p><sup>&#x02020;</sup>HIV-1 <italic>nef</italic>, PFV <italic>gag </italic>(<sup>&#x02021;</sup>HIV-1 <italic>gag </italic>for human tissues), and <italic>PPAR&#x003b3; </italic>mRNA expression were detected by RT-PCR with mRNA from human or each group of mouse tissues.</p><p><sup>&#x000a7;</sup>+, positive; -, negative; ND, not done.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Because extracellular Nef is internalized into human and mouse lymphocytes and macrophages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>], we examined putative Nef receptor molecule (Ner) expression with 305 mAb [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>] in both mouse and human tissues by histochemical analysis. In mice, 305 mAb positive lymphocytes were detected in the subcapsular area of the spleens by immunofluoresence assay (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>) and liver and hematopoietic cells (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>) in groups 1, 2 and 3, indicating that detection of antigen by 305 mAb was not altered by Nef expression. In HIV-1 uninfected humans, the 305 mAb positive cells were detected by immunoperoxidase staining in spleen (red pulp), tonsillar follicle (germinal center), liver (Kupffer cells), salivary gland (germinal center and adipose cells), bronchi (smooth muscle cells), lung (stroma cells), thyroid gland (colloid), heart muscle (smooth muscle cells), prostate gland (smooth muscle cells), colon mucosa (intestinal absorptive and muscle cells), testis (basement membrane of tubuli seminiferi), adrenal gland (adipose cells), and brain (cerebrum cortex and cortical cells) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref> and Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>).</p><p>Since Nef suppressed PPAR&#x003b3; expression and reduced fatty acid levels <italic>in vitro </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>], we monitored the expression of <italic>PPAR&#x003b3; </italic>mRNA and body weights of mice. Significant PPAR&#x003b3; mRNA expression in intestinal adipose tissue of group 3, but not group 1 and 2, was detected on day 2 (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). All Balb/c mice in group 1 showed sedation and a drastic loss of weight from days 1 to 3 (day 1, p = 0.003; day 2, p = 0.021; day 3, p = 0.032 relative to mice in group 3) (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref>). Similar results were obtained in group 2 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref>). However, group 3 mice infected with STYLE-367 did not appear to be sedated and had no drastic loss of weight (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref>). The group 4 animals, which were not infected with the PFV/nef but treated with STYLE-367, had no changes in either behavior or weight (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref>). In longitudinal examinations done during the post-infection period, the animals in groups 1 and 2 had recovered the lost weight (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D</xref>). Similar results were obtained in group 2 from day 1 to 5 (day 1, p = 0.037; day 3, p = 0.044; day 5, p = 0.048 relative to mice in group 3) in the C3H/Hej mouse groups (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3D</xref>). To assess the above <italic>in vivo </italic>results, expression of <italic>nef </italic>mRNA was examined in adipose tissues (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). As shown in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>, although mRNAs of <italic>nef </italic>and <italic>gag </italic>were not detected in mouse adipose tissues, 305 mAb and anti-Nef rabbit serum positive staining cells were detected in mouse group 1 and 2 adipose tissues (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3E</xref> and Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Considering that the 305 mAb positive staining adipocytes appeared in mouse as well as human tissues (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3E</xref> and Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>), these data suggest that the interaction between 305 and soluble Nef detected in adipose tissues may be responsible for the weight loss observed in mice.</p><p>In this study, whereas siRNA has been reported to inhibit hepatitis B virus replication <italic>in vivo </italic>(33&#x02013;34), our results show that <italic>nef</italic>-derived miRNAs are produced in HIV-1 infected cells, and support the possibility that miRNA and siRNA may be functionally identical, at least in a retrotransposon such as HIV. Recent studies have revealed that miRNAs and siRNAs could block mRNA expression by similar mechanisms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>] and that siRNAs could function as miRNAs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>] and EBV-encoded miRNAs were found [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]. Our results reported here are consistent with these previous observations and are suggestive of the fact that <italic>nef </italic>miR-N367 could regulate <italic>nef </italic>expression even <italic>in vivo</italic>. In our unpublished data, HIV-1 LTR promoter activity was inhibited by miR-N367 (nt number 379 to 449 of SF2 <italic>nef</italic>, 71-nt) expression, of which activity was dependent on negative responsive element (NRE) of U3 region (our unpublished data). Although no mismatch shRNA against region #367 was active, the miR-N367 from HIV-1 genome may have some mismatches and effectively inhibit HIV-1 transcription. Further the effects of siRNAs of Tc<italic>1</italic>, in particular those to the terminal inverted repeats derived from read-through transcription of entire transposable elements, were presented for silencing transposase gene expression by RNAi machinery in germ lines of <italic>C. elegans</italic>, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>]. Taken together, it could be implied from these and our other results that miRNAs produced in HIV-1-infected cells can efficiently block not only Nef function but also HIV-1 replication through RNAi, which renders persistently low pathogenic infection latent as observed in an LTNP of 15-2-2 (see Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). It is equally important that although the weight loss reported here occurred only temporarily <italic>in vivo</italic>, however the inserted <italic>nef </italic>gene in the foamy retrotransposon may represent miRNAs which could inhibit <italic>nef </italic>mRNA expression by presumably an identical mechanism to that observed of siRNAs. Thus, RNAi might serve as a new sequence-specific therapeutic arsenal in AIDS prevention and possibly treatment.</p><p>Overall, our results indicate that nef shRNA transduced into T cell line inhibited HIV-1 transcription. Further, nef miRNAs could be produced from infected T cells and can block the trans-activity of Nef as well as HIV-1 replication on its own via the cis-action of nef. These functions of nef via RNAi pathways may allow persistently low pathogenic or latent infection as observed in HIV-infected non-progressors. Cumulatively, these data suggest that Nef may be involved in both viral replication and the disease progression, the findings, which may facilitate new strategies for HIV control <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Patient details</title><p>Patient selection is showed in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>. These SF2 (HIV-1 subtype B prototype) was included as a control <italic>nef </italic>sequence, because of the inclusion of viruses, which were also subtype B. The SF2 contained full-length <italic>nef </italic>reading frame as indicated in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>. Patients 1-3-3, 4-2-1 (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>) are rapid progressors infected with HIV-1. These patients were infected in 1984&#x02013;1985 and died within 3 years of primary infection with &#x0003e;1 &#x000d7; 106 viral copies and CD4+ T cell count of 75 and 110/ml blood. Patients 15-2-2 and 16-1-1 (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>) are slow progressors, who were infected in 1984 and have survived HIV-1 infection with high and stable CD4+ T cell counts (690 and 760/ml blood) with low (&#x0003c;5000 copies) plasma viremia. All these patients acquired virus through homosexual sex. JW95-1 (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>) is a boy who was infected from his mother via breast feeding. The child was infected in 1983 and has survived disease free with high CD4+ T cell count (890/ml blood) with undetectable viremia. Human samples were obtained from a donor after informed consent.</p></sec><sec><title>Cells and viruses</title><p>HeLa and BHK cells were grown in Dulbecco's modified Eagle Medium (DMEM) (GIBCO, Grand Island, NY) supplemented with 10% heat-inactivated fetal bovine serum (FBS) and antibiotics. CRFK cells were grown in Iscove's Modified Dulbecco's Medium (IMDM) (GIBCO) with 10% FBS and antibiotics. Jurkat T cells and MT-4 T cells persistently infected with HIV-1 IIIB strain were cultured in RPMI-1640 medium (GIBCO) supplemented with 10% FBS and antibiotics. The packaging cells (CRFKsugi) were made by transfecting CRFK cells with 10 &#x003bc;g of the pFFenv with Lipofectin Reagent (Invitrogen) and selecting transformants after culture for 14 days with 25 &#x003bc;g/ml of hygromycine B (Invitrogen). After 14 days, FFV Env protein expression was measured by flow cytometry and immunoblot analyses with FFV-infected cat B serum [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. The pPFV/nef (10 &#x003bc;g) was transfected into BHK cells and pSTYLE/si (10 &#x003bc;g) was transfected into CRFKsugi cells with Lipofectin Reagent. The transfected cells were cultured for 72 hr, and the viral supernatant was collected and filtered through a 0.45 &#x003bc;m pore size Millex-GP filter (Millipore, Bedford, MA). Vector stocks were stored at -70&#x000b0;C prior to use. Viral titers were determined as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. Cells were infected with PFV/nef and/or SKY/si at an m.o.i. of ca. 0.1 in the presence of 4 &#x003bc;g/ml of polybrene and infected cells were cultured at a density of 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6 </sup>cells per ml for 3 days.</p><p>The details of plasmid constructs and the primer sequences used in cloning strategies are shown in supplementary file (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Additional file: 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Flow cytometric analysis</title><p>Flow cytometry was performed with a FACS Calibur (Becton Dickson, San Jose, CA) as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Luc assay and Immunoblotting</title><p>Firefly Luc assay was performed using the Luciferase Assay System (Promega) as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. Immunoblotting was performed essentially as described previously by Otake et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>P24 ELISA</title><p>The concentration of p24 supernatant was determined by an antigen capture assay (Beckman Coulter, Fullerton, CA) according to the manufacturer's instructions.</p></sec><sec><title>Confocal laser microscopy analysis</title><p>Confocal laser microscopy analysis was performed as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Northern blot analysis</title><p>Total RNAs were extracted from HIV-1 IIIB or SF2 persistently infected or uninfected MT-4 T cells using TRIzol reagent (Invitrogen). Approximately 40 &#x003bc;g of total RNA was treated with RNase A and T1 (Sigma, St. Louis, MO) as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>], subjected to electrophoresis on a 15% polyacrylamide-7 M urea gel and electroblotted to HybondN+ (Pharmacia, Uppsala, Sweden) for 4 hr at 400 mA. RNAs were immobilized by UV crosslinking and baking for 1 hr at 80&#x000b0;C. Hybridization was done with an ECL direct Kit (Pharmacia). Synthetic DNA probes were labeled with horseradish peroxidase. The sequence for synthetic sense DNA probes for northern blot analysis are as follows: #007 (5'-gcgtcgacggcaagtggtcaaaacgta-3'); #084 (5'-gcgtcgacgccagcagcagatggggtg-3'); #176 (5'-gcgtcgacgtgcctggctagaagcaca-3'); #190 (5'-gcgtcgacgcacaagaggaggaga-3'); #299 (5'-gcgtcgacgactggaagggctaatttg-3'); #367 (5'-gctcgacggctacttccctgattggc-3'); #468 (5'-gcgtcgacggtagaagaggccaatgaa-3'); #580 (5'-gcgtcgacgcatttcatcacatggccc-3'). RNAs were cloned by 5'RACE System (Invitrogen, CA., USA) with a slight modification in that primers were used that were the same as the synthetic DNA probes as described above that are abbreviated as #primer. In brief, gel purified small RNAs were annealed with #primer and first strand cDNA was synthesized with SuperScript II RT (Invitrogen, CA., USA). Afrer RNase H and T1 treatment, a homopolymeric tail was added to the 3'-end of the cDNA using terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase and dCTP. After ethanol precipitation, PCR amplification was done with abridged anchor primer and #primer. Then the PCR products were obtained using abridged universal amplification primer and #primer. The PCR fragments were digested with <italic>Sal</italic>I and cloned into <italic>Sal</italic>I site of pBluescript SK(-), followed by sequence analysis. The secondary structures of RNAs were predicted by GENETYX-MAC program (Software Development Co. Ltd, Tokyo, Japan).</p></sec><sec><title>Semi-quantitative RT-PCR analysis</title><p>Semi-quantitative RT-PCR analysis was performed using the ThermoScript RT-PCR System (Invitrogen, CA., USA) according to the manufacturer's protocol with the following primers: III (5'-atcatgggccaaagagaattc-3') and IV (5'-aaatttcactcaatcgagcc-3') for FFV LTR, VI (5'-aggacctgaaaggcatg-3') and VII (5'-ttgttgagatcgtcccg-3') for FFV <italic>gag</italic>, VIII (5'-tgtggtggaatgccactag-3') and IX (5'-attgtcatggaattttgta-3') for PFV LTR, XI (5'-tcttacagaccagtaacaa-3') and XII (5'-gtcaatcattacatctgca-3') for PFV <italic>gag</italic>, XIII (5'-aactactagtacccttcagg-3') and XIV (5'-aaaactcttgctttatggcc-3') for HIV-1 <italic>gag</italic>, XV (5'-atgggtggcaagtcaaaacg-3') and XVI (5'-tcagcagtctttgtagtactccg-3') for HIV-1 <italic>nef</italic>, XVII (5'-gttatgggtgaaactctgggagat-3') and XVIII (5'-atgttcctgaacataatcgtc-3') for <italic>PPAR&#x003b3;</italic>, XIX (5'-gacaacggctccggcatgtgcaaag-3') and XX (5'-ttcacggttggccttagggttcag-3') for &#x003b2;-<italic>actin</italic>, respectively. The nested PCR followed RT reaction was performed as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. PCR products were quantified with the NIH image program. Relative mRNA expression was calculated as percentage expression using the following formula: integrating number of <italic>nef </italic>or <italic>gag </italic>bands/integrating number of &#x003b2;-<italic>actin </italic>X 100.</p></sec><sec><title>In vivo studies and tissue analyses</title><p>Balb/c and C3H/Hej mice were raised under specific pathogen-free (SPF) conditions. Mice were infected with 1 ml of 10<sup>5 </sup>IFU of PFV/nef and STYLE-367 by intravenous (i.v.) injection. RT-PCR analyses were performed 2 days after infection. For histological analysis, cryostat sections were prepared from both human and mouse tissues. The fixed sections were rinsed with PBS and incubated with 5% BSA for at least 1 hr to inhibit nonspecific binding of antibodies. Sections were incubated overnight at 4&#x000b0;C with anti-Nef rabbit serum, F3 or 305 mAb, and incubated with peroxidase or FITC conjugated secondary antibodies. The washed sections were incubated in 0.03% 3,3'diaminobenzidine (Sigma) solution in 0.05 M Tris buffer with 0.01% H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>2 </sub>for development of peroxidase activity. After counterstaining with hematoxylin or methylgreen, the sections were dehydrated and mounted.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical methods</title><p>Data were analysed using a one-way ANOVA analysis with a post-hoc Fisher's test. P values of 0.05 or more were determined for that of cut off.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>List of abbreviations used</title><p>HIV-1 human immunodeficiency virus type 1</p><p>miRNA microRNA</p><p>nt, nucleotides</p><p>LTNP long-term non-progressors</p><p>shRNA short hairpin RNA</p><p>AIDS acquired immunodeficiency syndrome</p><p>RNAi RNA interference</p><p>siRNA small interfering RNA</p><p>LTR long terminal repeat</p><p>SIV simian immunodeficiency virus</p><p>PBMCs peripheral blood mononuclear cells;</p><p>EBV Epstein-Barr virus;</p><p>EGFP enhanced green fluorescence protein</p><p>PFV prototype foamy virus</p><p>TA trichostatin</p><p>A IFU infectious units</p><p>FFV feline foamy virus</p><p>RT reverse transcription</p><p>m.o.i., multiplicity of infectionm</p><p>Ab monoclonal antibody;</p><p>Ner Nef receptor molecule;</p><p>NRE negative responsive element.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>S.O. carried out northern analyses, immunoblot analyses, RNAi assays and was involved in the construction of plasmids. M.I. and Y.T. participated in <italic>in vivo </italic>studies and tissue analyses. Y.I. and H.O. participated in data validation and overall experimental design. E.A.B. and N.K.S. carried out the clinical, sequencing, and virological studies and the writing of the manuscript. Y.R.F. participated in the design of the study and coordinated it. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1"><caption><title>Additional file 1</title></caption><media xlink:href="1742-4690-1-44-S1.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank S. Hatama, T. Yamamoto, R. Shimizu, M. Sugiyama, Y. Mitsuki and Y. Yasui for excellent technical assistance; T. Kawamura, N. Okada and H. Okada for financial supports; K. Otake for technical support of flow cytometric analysis; Y. Murase and N. Takeo, for primary experiments; M. Kameoka for gift of Gal4 plasmid; and K. Imakawa for supplement of technical advices of Luc assay.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weidle</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mastro</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Nkengasong</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Macharia</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>HIV/AIDS treatment and HIV vaccines for Africa</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2002</year><volume>359</volume><fpage>2261</fpage><lpage>2267</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12103304</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(02)09297-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brisibe</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizukami</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Okuyama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>YR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNA interference: potentials for the prevention of HIV infections and the challenges ahead</article-title><source>Trends Biotechnol</source><year>2003</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>306</fpage><lpage>311</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12837615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0167-7799(03)00118-5</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fire</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Montgomery</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kostas</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Driver</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Mello</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potent and specific genetic interference by double-stranded RNA in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1998</year><volume>391</volume><fpage>806</fpage><lpage>811</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9486653</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35888</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tuschl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamore</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehmann</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartel</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Targeted mRNA degradation by double-stranded RNA <italic>in vitro</italic></article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>1999</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>3191</fpage><lpage>3197</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10617568</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.13.24.3191</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ketting</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Haverkamp</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>van Luenen</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Plasterk</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>mut-7 </italic>of <italic>C. elegans</italic>, required for transposon silencing and RNA interference, is a homolog of Werner syndrome helicase and RNaseD</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1999</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10535732</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(00)81645-1</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tabara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarkissian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleenor</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Grishok</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Timmons</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Fire</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mello</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>rde-1 </italic>gene, RNA interference, and transposon silencing in <italic>C. elegans</italic></article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1999</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>132</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10535731</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(00)81644-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aravin</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Naumova</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tulin</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Vagin</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name><surname>Rozovsky</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gvozdev</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Double-stranded RNA-mediated silencing of genomic tandem repeats and transposable elements in the D. melanogaster germline</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1017</fpage><lpage>1027</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11470406</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0960-9822(01)00299-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elbashir</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lendeckel</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuschl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNA interference is mediated by 21- and 22-nucleotide RNAs</article-title><source>Gene Dev</source><year>2001</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>188</fpage><lpage>200</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11157775</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.862301</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cullen</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNAs and small interfering RNAs can inhibit mRNA expression by similar mechanisms</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>9779</fpage><lpage>9784</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12902540</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1630797100</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahn</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Provost</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Radmark</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The nuclear RNase III Drosha initiates microRNA processing</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2003</year><volume>425</volume><fpage>415</fpage><lpage>419</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14508493</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature01957</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeon</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>VN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MicroRNA maturation: stepwise processing and subcellular localization</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><year>2002</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>4663</fpage><lpage>4670</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12198168</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/cdf476</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paushkin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gubitz</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Massenet</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dreyfuss</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The SMN complex, an assemblyosome of ribonucleoproteins</article-title><source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>305</fpage><lpage>312</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12067652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0955-0674(02)00332-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caudy</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannon</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fragile X-related protein and VIG associate with the RNA interference machinery</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2002</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>2491</fpage><lpage>2496</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12368260</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.1025202</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishizuka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Siomi</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Siomi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A Drosophila fragile X protein interacts with components of RNAi and ribosomal proteins</article-title><source>Genes Dev</source><year>2002</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>2497</fpage><lpage>2508</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12368261</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.1022002</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Calin</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Dumitru</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Shimizu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bichi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Zupo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Noch</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Aldler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rattan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Keating</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Rassenti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kipps</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Negrini</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bullrich</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Croce</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Frequent deletions and down-regulation of micro-RNA genes miR15 and miR16 at 13q14 in chronic lymphocytic leukemia</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2002</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>15524</fpage><lpage>15529</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12434020</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.242606799</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kestler</surname><given-names>HW</given-names></name><name><surname>Ringler</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Panicali</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Schgal</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name><name><surname>Daniel</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Desrosiers</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Importance of the nef gene for maintenance of high virus loads and for development of AIDS</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1991</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>651</fpage><lpage>662</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2032289</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(91)90097-I</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Omoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizuguchi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizukami</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Okuyama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Saksena</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name><surname>Brisibe</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Otake</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>YR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Double-stranded <italic>nef </italic>RNA interferes with human immunodeficiency virus type 1 replication</article-title><source>Microbiol Immunol</source><year>2002</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>809</fpage><lpage>817</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12516779</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>D'Aloja</surname><given-names>PE</given-names></name><name><surname>Olivetta</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bona</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Nappi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pedacchia</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Pugliese</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrari</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Verani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Federico</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>gag</italic>, <italic>vif</italic>, and <italic>nef </italic>genes contribute to the homologous viral interference induced by a nonproducer human immunodeficiency virus type 1 (HIV-1) variant: identification of novel HIV-1-inhibiting viral protein mutants</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>1998</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>4308</fpage><lpage>4319</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9557721</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olivetta</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Pugliese</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bona</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>D'Aloja</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferrantelli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Santarcangelo</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Verani</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Federico</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>cis </italic>expression of the F12 human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) Nef allele transforms the highly productive NL4-3 HIV type 1 to a replication-defective strain: involvement of both Env gp41 and CD4 intracytoplasmic tails</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>2000</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>483</fpage><lpage>492</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10590138</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacque</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Triques</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modulation of HIV-1 replication by RNA interference</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2002</year><volume>418</volume><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>438</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12087358</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature00896</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Brummelkamp</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Westerhout</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Vink</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Madiredjo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernards</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Berkhout</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human immunodeficiency virus type 1 escapes from RNA interference-mediated inhibition</article-title><source>J Virol</source><year>2004</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>2601</fpage><lpage>2605</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14963165</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.78.5.2601-2605.2004</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miyagishi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumimoto</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyoshi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawakami</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Taira</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optimization of an siRNA-expression system with an improved hairpin and its significant suppressive effects in mammalian cells</article-title><source>J Gene Med</source><year>2004</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>715</fpage><lpage>723</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15241778</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jgm.556</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Murase</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Otake</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokota</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Omoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Okuyama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Imakawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A potential live vector, foamy virus, directed intra-cellular expression of ovine interferon-&#x003c4; exhibited the resistance to HIV infection</article-title><source>J Vet Med Sci</source><year>2004</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15031537</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1292/jvms.66.115</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hatama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Otake</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Imakawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikemoto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Okuyama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mochizuki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyazawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tohya</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reactivation of feline foamy virus from a chronically infected feline renal cell line by trichostatin A</article-title><source>Virology</source><year>2001</year><volume>283</volume><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>323</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11336556</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/viro.2000.0861</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grishok</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasquinelli</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Conte</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Parrish</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ha</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Baillie</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Fire</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruvkun</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mello</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genes and mechanisms related to RNA interference regulate expression of the small temporal RNAs that control <italic>C. elegans </italic>developmental timing</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2001</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11461699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(01)00431-7</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Takei</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tashiro</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nef protein of HIV-1 induces apoptotic cytolysis of murine lymphoid cells independently of CD95 (Fas) and its suppression by serine/threonine protein kinase inhibitors</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><year>1997</year><volume>417</volume><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>64</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9395075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0014-5793(97)01255-6</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quaranta</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Camponeschi</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Straface</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Malorini</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Viora</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction of interleukin-15 production by HIV-1 Nef protein: a role in the proliferation of uninfected cells</article-title><source>Exp Cell Res</source><year>1999</year><volume>250</volume><fpage>112</fpage><lpage>121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10388525</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/excr.1999.4494</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Otake</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Ohta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Minowada</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Takahashi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ikemoto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Okuyama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extracellular Nef of HIV-1 can target CD4 memory T population</article-title><source>AIDS</source><year>2000</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1662</fpage><lpage>1664</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10983657</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00002030-200007280-00026</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olivetta</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Percario</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiorucci</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Schiavoni</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jager</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Romeo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Affabris</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Federico</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>HIV-1 Nef induces the release of inflammatory factors from human monocyte/macrophages: Involvement of Nef endocytotic signals and NF-&#x003ba;B activation</article-title><source>J Immunol</source><year>2003</year><volume>170</volume><fpage>1716</fpage><lpage>1727</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12574335</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hanna</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Rebai</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Guimond</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jothy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jolicoeur</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nef harbors a major determinant of pathogenicity for an AIDS-like disease induced by HIV-1 in transgenic mice</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1998</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>175</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9790524</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(00)81748-1</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brisibe</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizukami</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Okuyama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>YR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>RNA interference: potentials for the prevention of HIV infections and the challenges ahead</article-title><source>Trends Biotechnol</source><year>2003</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>306</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12837615</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0167-7799(03)00118-5</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Otake</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Omoto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Okuyama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Okada</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Saksena</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>YR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>HIV-1 Nef in the nucleus influences adipogenesis as well as viral transcription through the peroxisome proliferator-activated receptors</article-title><source>AIDS</source><year>2004</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15075535</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00002030-200401230-00007</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bock</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Wedemeyer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>W&#x000fc;stefeld</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Locarnini</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dienes</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubicka</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Manns</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Trautwein</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of hepatitis B virus replication in vivo by nucleoside analogues and siRNA</article-title><source>Gastroenterology</source><year>2003</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12851866</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0016-5085(03)00720-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giladi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ketzinel-Gilad</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivkin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Felig</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Nussbaum</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Galun</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Small interfering RNA inhibits hepatitis B virus replication in mice</article-title><source>Mol Ther</source><year>2003</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>769</fpage><lpage>776</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14599810</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1525-0016(03)00244-2</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doench</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharp</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>siRNAs can function as miRNAs</article-title><source>Gene Dev</source><year>2003</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>438</fpage><lpage>442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12600936</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gad.1064703</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pfeffer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zavolan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Grasser</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chien</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ju</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>John</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Enright</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Marks</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sander</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuschl</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of virus-encoded microRNAs</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2004</year><volume>304</volume><fpage>734</fpage><lpage>736</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15118162</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1096781</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sijen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Plasterk</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transposon silencing in the <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans </italic>germ line by natural RNAi</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2003</year><volume>426</volume><fpage>310</fpage><lpage>314</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14628056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature02107</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



