<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Reprod Biol Endocrinol</journal-id><journal-title>Reproductive biology and endocrinology : RB&#x00026;E</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1477-7827</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15588330</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC544582</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1477-7827-2-81</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1477-7827-2-81</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Potential action of androstenedione on the proliferation and apoptosis of stromal endometrial cells</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Maliqueo</surname><given-names>Manuel A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>mmaliqueo@med.uchile.cl</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Quezada</surname><given-names>Susana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>squezada@med.uchile.cl</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Clementi</surname><given-names>Marisa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>marisa_clementi@yahoo.com.ar</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bacallao</surname><given-names>Ketty</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>kbacallao@yahoo.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Anido</surname><given-names>Mabel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>manido@med.uchile.cl</email></contrib><contrib id="A6" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>Cecilia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>cjohnson@med.uchile.cl</email></contrib><contrib id="A7" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vega</surname><given-names>Margarita</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>mvega@med.uchile.cl</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Institute of Maternal and Child Research, School of Medicine, University of Chile, Santiago, Chile</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Laboratory of Endocrinology and Metabolism, Department of Internal Medicine, School of Medicine, University of Chile, Santiago, Chile</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>12</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><fpage>81</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rbej.com/content/2/1/81"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>10</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>12</month><year>2004</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2004 Maliqueo et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2004</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Maliqueo et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Maliqueo
               A
               Manuel
               
               
               mmaliqueo@med.uchile.cl
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Potential action of androstenedione on the proliferation and apoptosis of stromal endometrial cells
         </dc:title><dc:date>2004</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Reproductive Biology and Endocrinology 2(1): 81-. (2004)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1477-7827(2004)2:1&#x0003c;81&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1477-7827</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Hyperandrogenic conditions have been associated with a high prevalence of endometrial pathologies related to cell survival. However, the action of androgens on proliferation and apoptosis in endometrial cells is poorly understood. Therefore, the aim of the present study was to evaluate the effect of androstenedione on cell proliferation, cell death and expression of estrogen receptor (ER) isoforms and proteins related to apoptosis in endometrial cells using two in vitro experimental approaches.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>The endometrial tissue was obtained from 20 eumenorrheic women [28.7 (25 &#x02013; 35) years] during the early secretory phase. We analyzed cell proliferation (immunohistochemistry of Ki-67 and spectrophotometric assay); apoptosis (DNA fragmentation (TUNEL) and Annexin V-FITC binding); ER-alpha, ER-beta bcl-2 and bax mRNA abundance (RT-PCR) in explants and isolated endometrial epithelial (EEC) and stromal cells (ESC) incubated with androstenedione 1 micro mol/l (A4) or A4 plus hydroxyflutamide 10 micro mol/l (F) for 24 h.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>In explants, A4 induced an increase of cell proliferation and a decrease on apoptosis in the stromal compartment (p &#x0003c; 0.05). In isolated ESC, proliferation augmented with A4 (p &#x0003c; 0.05), whereas, no significant modifications in the expression of ER-alpha, ER-beta bcl-2 and bax nor in the apoptotic index were observed. In EEC, A4 increase the ER-beta mRNA abundance (p &#x0003c; 0.05) and a decrease of the bcl-2/bax ratio (p &#x0003c; 0.05), without an increase in the apoptotic index. Hydroxyflutamide reverted the effect of androstenedione on the parameters described.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>These results indicate that androstenedione may modulate cell survival, expression of ER-beta and proteins related to apoptosis, suggesting a potential mechanism that associates the effect of hyperandrogenemia on the endometrial tissue.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Polycystic ovary syndrome (PCOS) is a complex endocrine-metabolic disorder, associated to hyperandrogenism, menstrual disturbances and in many cases to insulin resistance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. It has been observed that in some of PCOS women, the endometrium is thicker than that of normal cycling women [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>] and a higher prevalence of endometrial hyperplasia and adenocarcinoma have also been described in these women [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. The latter may indicate that the mechanisms that regulate the process of cell survival may be disrupted in the endometrium of PCOS women. Recently, we have shown that the expression of proteins involved in the regulation of apoptosis in PCOS endometria were altered [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Besides, we and other investigators demonstrated an elevated expression of the estrogen receptor (ER) and its co-activators in endometria of women bearing this syndrome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Nevertheless, in those studies it was difficult to establish the exact contribution of androgens as a regulatory steroid of endometria of PCOS women, since multiple factors could be affecting their endometrial function, including hyperinsulinemia and the possible contribution of the unopposed effect of estrogens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. Therefore, in vitro experimental models such as tissue and cell culture may constitute interesting approaches to determine the potential role of androgens in the regulation of endometrial cell survival.</p><p>Early reports in isolated endometrial stromal cells (ESC) have shown that androgens can induce decidualization and inhibition of the expression of ER and progesterone receptors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Moreover, in endometrial epithelial cells (EEC), androgens altered the expression of proteins related to uterine receptivity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>] and induced a decrease in the proliferation capacity of those cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>].</p><p>Cell proliferation and apoptosis of the endometrium are importantly regulated by the expression of ER [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>], which exists in two major subtypes, estrogen receptors alpha (ER&#x003b1;) and estrogen receptor beta (ER&#x003b2;). The two isoforms of ER derive from separate genes, with different ligand binding affinities and the response of the tissue to estrogens will depend upon their relative concentrations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>].</p><p>On the other hand, in some tissues including the human endometrium, the control of apoptosis has been associated to proteins related to the Bcl-2 family, like Bcl-2 that promotes cell survival and Bax which is an inducer of apoptosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. Evenmore, other proteins are involved in the machinery of cell death like caspases which are associated with the cleavage and thus, breakdown of cell structure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. In regard to this issue, we have demonstrated that the expression of bcl-2 and bax is increased in the stromal compartment of the endometrium of PCOS women, but we could not observe an increase in the apoptotic index in the endometria of these women [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>].</p><p>Previous reports have shown that androstenedione is an important androgen detected in the endometrial tissue [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. Therefore, based on the amount of androgens normally found in endometria and their potential importance in alterations of the endometrial cell survival in PCOS women, the objective of the present study was to evaluate the effect of androstenedione on cell proliferation, apoptosis and the expression of ER isoforms and proteins related to apoptosis using two in vitro experimental approaches.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Subjects</title><p>Endometrial tissue was obtained with pipelle suction curette from the corpus of the uteri of 20 women with regular menstrual cycles, aged 28.7 (25 &#x02013; 35) years, at the time of bilateral tubal ligation at the San Borja-Arriar&#x000e1;n Clinical Hospital, National Health Service, Santiago, Chile. The tissue was obtained during the early secretory phase since the cells obtained from this phase maintain a high degree of proliferation capacity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. None of these women had taken oral contraceptives or other medications for at least 6 months before starting the study. Women who had evidences of PCOS, endometriosis and/or endometrial hyperplasia were excluded. This investigation was approved by the Institutional Ethics Committee of the San Borja-Arriar&#x000e1;n Clinical Hospital and an informed written consent was obtained from all subjects.</p></sec><sec><title>Culture System</title><sec><title>Explants</title><p>Human endometrium was cut into slices (20 to 50 mg wet weight) and incubated in 1 mL of Hank's media supplemented with 2 mmol/L glutamax-I (BRL, Life Technology, Bethesda, MD, USA), insulin-transferrin-selenium (ITS) solution (BRL), 0.1% w/v bovine serum albumin (BSA; Sigma Chemical Co., St Louis, MO, USA), 26 mmol/L of NaHCO<sub>3</sub>, 25 mmol/L of HEPES aminoacids solution, 100 IU/ml of penicillin, and 5 mg/mL of streptomycin (Sigma). Incubation was performed during 6 h at 37&#x000b0;C in 5% CO<sub>2</sub>/air in humidified atmosphere in the absence or presence of androstenedione 10<sup>-7 </sup>to 10<sup>-5 </sup>M (Sigma) or androstenedione 10<sup>-6 </sup>M plus hydroxyflutamide 10<sup>-5 </sup>M (Sigma), the latter added 30 min before androstenedione. After incubation, one piece from both basal and treated tissue explants were frozen in liquid N<sub>2 </sub>and maintained at -70&#x000b0;C for RT-PCR protocols. Another piece was fixed in 4% buffered formaldehyde for 24 h, embedded in paraffin, and cut into 5 &#x003bc;m thick sections before in situ analysis of apoptosis and immunohistochemistry.</p></sec><sec><title>Cells</title><p>The cells were separated and purified according to previously described methods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. Briefly, the tissue was cut into small pieces and suspended in Dulbecco's modified Eagle medium (DMEM) (GibcoBRL), collagenase (370 IU/100 mg tissue) (Worthington, Biochemical Corp. Freehold, NJ, USA) and DNAse (14 KU/100 mg tissue) (Sigma) during 1 h at 37&#x000b0;C. Epithelial cells, predominantly from glands, were separated from ESC by decantation and the supernatant containing the ESC was filtered, centrifuged and the cell pellet washed in DMEM. Stromal cells were incubated in appropriate cell culture media (ESC media) (DMEM/MCDB-105 (3:1 v/v), 2% charcoal stripped fetal bovine serum (FBS) (GibcoBRL), insulin-transferrin-selenium (ITS) solution, 2 mmol/L glutamax-I (GibcoBRL), 0.25 &#x003bc;g/mL ascorbic acid (GibcoBRL), 0.25 &#x003bc;g/mL fungizone (GibcoBRL), 100 IU/mL penicillin and 5 mg/mL streptomycin at 37&#x000b0;C in 5% CO<sub>2</sub>/air in humidified atmosphere until confluence.</p><p>The glands cells were washed in DMEM and incubated for 1 h (30 min in each side of the culture flask), and then cultured in EEC culture media (DMEM/MCDB-105 (3:1, v/v), 10% charcoal stripped FBS, 2 mmol/L glutamax-I, 0.25 &#x003bc;g/mL ascorbic acid, 0.5 mg% insulin (Sigma), 1 &#x003bc;g% transferrin (Sigma), antibiotic and fungizone), similarly to ESC. In both cell cultures, the media were changed every 3 days. Upon reaching confluence, ESC and EEC were passaged by treatment with 0.5 g/L tripsin-0.2 g/L EDTA solution (GibcoBRL).</p><p>The purity of cell cultures was greater than 90% for ESC and EEC, evaluated by immunocytochemistry of vimentin and cytokeratin, respectively.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Epithelial and stromal cell culture</title><p>Cells, EEC and ESC, were grown in appropriate medium in 6-well or 96-well plates at 2.5 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5 </sup>cells/well or 0.1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5 </sup>cells/well, respectively. When cells were subconfluent (48 &#x02013; 72 h of culture), the media were changed to Hank's media and incubated for 24 h. Then, the cells were incubated in fresh Hank's media at 37&#x000b0;C in 5% CO<sub>2</sub>/air in humidified atmosphere in the absence or presence of androstenedione 10<sup>-6 </sup>M or androstenedione 10<sup>-6 </sup>M plus hydroxyflutamide 10<sup>-5 </sup>M. The latter was added 15 min before androstenedione. The culture was carried out for 24 h to evaluate the early effect of androstenedione on cell survival. The concentration of androstenedione used in the present investigation was established in dose-response experiments and are in agreement with those previously reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Immunohistochemical detection</title><p>Sections (4 to 6 &#x003bc;m) of human endometrial tissue obtained from cultured explants were deparaffinized in xylene and hydrated gradually through graded alcohols. Endogenous peroxidase activity was prevented by incubating the samples in 3% hydrogen peroxide for 5 min. The sections were incubated in 10 mM sodium citrate buffer (pH 6.0) at 95&#x000b0;C for 20 min. Nonspecific antibody binding was prevented with 2% PBS-BSA for 1 h. Primary antibody of Ki-67 (1:200; Novocastra Laboratories, Newcastle, UK) was applied to the samples and incubated overnight at 4&#x000b0;C; the antibody for caspase-3 (1: 100; R&#x00026;D System, Inc., Minneapolis, MN) was incubated for 1 h at 37&#x000b0;C and the antibody for androgen receptor (AR) was incubated overnight at 4&#x000b0;C (1: 75; Santa Cruz, CA, USA). The second antibody used in both cases was a biotinylated rabbit antimouse immunoglobulin. The reaction was developed by the streptavidin-peroxidase system and 3,3'diaminobenzidine was used as the chromogen; counterstaining was carried out with hematoxylin. The slides were evaluated in a Nikon optical microscope (Nikon Inc., Melville, NY, USA). The immunohistochemical evaluation was determined as the percentage of positive stained cells. In all cases, at least 500 cells were evaluated by three independent observers.</p></sec><sec><title>In Situ 3'-End Labeling of DNA in Apoptotic cells (TUNEL)</title><p>Programmed cell death was detected using TdT-mediated dUTP nick end labeling as previously described (Promega, Madison, WI, USA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. Briefly, paraffin sections were dewaxed with xylene and rehydrated for 3'-end labeling. Tissue sections were incubated with proteinase K (20 &#x003bc;g/ml) at room temperature for 10 min and washed with PBS for 5 min. Then, incubated for 1 h at 37&#x000b0;C with the nucleotide mix labelled with fluorescein and terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase enzyme and counterstained with propidium iodide. The number of apoptotic cells was quantified by at least counting 1000 cells in a fluorescence microscope by three independent observers. The number of apoptotic cells was expressed as the percentage of positive cells.</p></sec><sec><title>Cell proliferation</title><p>CellTiter 96 AQueous Cell Proliferation Assay (Promega) was used to perform cell proliferation, following manufacturer's instructions. Briefly, EEC or ESC were plated in 96-well until sub-confluence; then, the cells were cultured with androstendione 10<sup>-6 </sup>M alone or androstenedione 10<sup>-6 </sup>M with hydroxyflutamide 10<sup>-5 </sup>M, as described above. Twenty &#x003bc;L of a mix of tetrazolium compound (3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-5-(3-carboxymethoxyphenyl)-2-(4-sulfophenyl) 2H-tetrazolium; MTS) and an electron coupling reagent (phenazine methosulfate; PMS) were added to each well and incubated for 2 h at 37&#x000b0;C. The quantity of the soluble formazan product was measured at 450-nm absorbance in an ELISA reader (Sigma) and expressed as optical density units (OD).</p></sec><sec><title>Detection of apoptosis by Annexin V</title><p>Apoptosis was performed using Annexin V-FITC Apoptosis Detection Kit (Oncogene Reasearch Products, Boston, MA, USA). Briefly, after EEC and ESC achieved sub-confluence in 6-well plates, the cells were incubated with androstenedione 10<sup>-6 </sup>M alone or androstenedione 10<sup>-6 </sup>M with hydroxyflutamide 10<sup>-5 </sup>M, as described above. The cells were dissociated by 0.25 g/L trypsin-0.1 g/L EDTA treatment, gently re-suspended in cold binding buffer to approximately 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6 </sup>cells, and incubated with Annexin V-FITC, as indicated by the manufacturer. The cells were counter-stained with propidium iodide, analyzed and counted by two independent observers in at least 1000 cells in each experimental condition using a fluorescent and optical microscope (Nikon, UFX-NX model. Nikon Inc., Melville, NY, USA). The results are expressed as percentage of apoptotic Annexin V-FITC positive cells respect to total cells counted.</p></sec><sec><title>RNA isolation and semiquantitative Reverse Transcription-Polymerase Chain Reaction</title><p>Total RNA was isolated using TRIzol Reagent (GibcoBRL) from endometrial tissue and ESC culture according to the manufacturer's instructions. Total RNA was then reverse transcribed, and cDNA was subjected to polymerase chain reaction (PCR) using specific primers for ER&#x003b1; and ER&#x003b2;[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>], bcl-2 and bax cDNA (NIDig 4558699) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. &#x003b2;-actin was used as an internal control.</p><p>Semiquantitative RT-PCRs were achieved in the exponential linear zone amplification for each gene studied. Two &#x003bc;g of total RNA were used for reverse transcription in a total volume of 20 &#x003bc;l using the Revertaid H Minus M-Mulv Reverse (Fermentas Hannover, MD, USA). The PCR condition for ER&#x003b1; and ER&#x003b2; was 2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.15 mM of dNTP, 0.63 U of Taq DNA polymerase (Fermentas Hannover, MD, USA), and 0.4 &#x003bc;M of each primer; for bcl-2 and bax was 3 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 0.25 mM of dNTP, 0.63 U of Taq DNA polymerase, and 0.4 &#x003bc;M of each primer. The PCR amplification was carried out in the Thermocycler, model PTC-100 (MJ Research Inc, Watertown, MA), as previously reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>].</p><p>The PCR products were electrophoretically resolved on 1% agarose gel and stained with ethidium bromide. The bands were evaluated using an image analyser (Kodak Electrophoresis Documentation and Analysis System [EDAS 290] and Kodak 1D Image Analysis software, Rochester, NY, USA), and normalized relative to &#x003b2;-actin PCR product and expressed as arbitrary units (AU).</p><p>To confirm the specificity of RT-PCR products, the fragments were purified with CONCERT Rapid PCR Purification System (GibcoBRL) and sequenced using an ABI PRISM310 automated Sequencer (Perkin Elmer; Norwalk, CT, USA).</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical evaluation</title><p>The results are expressed as the percentage of changes obtained in the treated respect to the basal condition. Comparisons between groups were performed by ANOVA following Dunnett test. The significance level was set at 5%. Results are expressed as mean &#x000b1; standard error of the mean (SEM).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Explants culture</title><p>In all samples, the expression of the AR was present in the nucleus of EEC and ESC cells (data not shown). Moreover, in EEC showed a positive staining in the cytoplasm. The nucleolar antigen Ki-67 was detected in the nucleus of EEC and ESC. After six hours of incubation with androstenedione at different concentrations (10<sup>-7 </sup>M &#x02013; 10<sup>-5 </sup>M), the percentage of positive cells increased significantly only in the presence of androstenedione 10<sup>-6 </sup>M and on the stromal compartment (basal: 9,9 &#x000b1; 2.5%; treated: 21.2 &#x000b1; 6.4%; p &#x0003c; 0.05) (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1D</xref>). Therefore, the following experiments were performed at a concentration of androstenedione 10<sup>-6 </sup>M.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Effect of androstendione on endometrial cell proliferation and apoptosis of human endometria. Basal condition (left panel) and androstenedione-treated explants (right panel). The nucleolar antigen Ki-67, evaluated by immunohistochemistry, was detected in the nucleus of both cell compartments (A, D), indicative of cell proliferation. The nucleus of positive cells for TUNEL, determined by TdT-mediated dUTP nick end labeling, were stained in yellow and counterstained with propidium iodide (B, E), showing DNA fragmentation. The positive staining for caspase-3, determined by immunohistochemistry in paraffin wax sections of endometria, was found in the cell cytoplasm of both compartments (C, G). Negative controls (inserts) for inmunohistochemistry was performed with non-immune rabbit serum in the place of the respective primary antibody and for TUNEL, by the replacement of TdT enzyme. Arrowheads indicate positive staining of the respective proteins. Magnification in all panels, &#x000d7;400.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1477-7827-2-81-1"/></fig><p>On the other hand, TUNEL positive cells were lower in ESC after androstenedione treatment (basal: 21.2 &#x000b1; 5.0%; treated:10.3 &#x000b1; 3.7%; p &#x0003c; 0.05), (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1E</xref>). The expression of caspase-3 did not change with the androstenedione treatment in both compartments (Figures <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1F</xref>). The addition of hydroxyflutamide plus androstenedione did not modify the degree of proliferation or cell death in tissue explants.</p></sec><sec><title>Isolated endometrial cells</title><p>Basal values of cell proliferation were 0.39 &#x000b1; 0.09 OD and 0.64 &#x000b1; 0.16 OD for EEC and ESC, respectively, whereas, the percentage of annexin V positive cells was 16.3 &#x000b1; 4.6% for EEC and 12.7 &#x000b1; 4.3% for ESC. The addition of androstenedione significantly increased cell proliferation in ESC cultures (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>; p &#x0003c; 0.05), and this effect was reverted by the addition of hydroxyflutamide (0.63 &#x000b1; 0.16 OD vs 0.70 &#x000b1; 0.19 OD); no changes were observed in the EEC subpopulation (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Effect of androstenedione in cell proliferation and apoptotic index in endometrial epithelial cells (EEC) and endometrial stromal cells (ESC) in vitro.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="center" colspan="2">Cell Proliferation (%)</td><td align="center" colspan="2">Apoptotic index (%)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td></td><td align="center">EEC</td><td align="center">ESC</td><td align="center">EEC</td><td align="center">ESC</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Basal</td><td align="center">100</td><td align="center">100</td><td align="center">100</td><td align="center">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Androstenedione (10<sup>-6 </sup>M)</td><td align="center">91.6 &#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0; 6.9</td><td align="center">135.4&#x000a0; &#x000b1; &#x000a0;1.2*</td><td align="center">165.0 &#x000a0;&#x000b1; &#x000a0;59.0</td><td align="center">120.0&#x000a0; &#x000b1; &#x000a0;11.0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Androstenedione (10<sup>-6 </sup>M) plus hydroxyflutamide (10<sup>-5 </sup>M)</td><td align="center">99.1 &#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0; 10.0</td><td align="center">109.2&#x000a0; &#x000b1;&#x000a0; 4.2</td><td align="center">111.2&#x000a0; &#x000b1;&#x000a0; 6.3</td><td align="center">106.7&#x000a0; &#x000b1;&#x000a0; 7.4</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*p &#x0003c; 0.05. Values are calculated as percentage of basal and are expressed as mean &#x000b1; SEM.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The percentage of cells with positive signs of apoptosis was similar between the basal and the treated conditions, independently of the cell type analyzed. The addition of hydroxyflutamide plus androstenedione to both cell cultures did not modify the degree of cell death (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Effect of androstenedione on the abundance of messenger RNA for bcl-2 and bax</title><p>A similar mRNA abundance for bcl-2 and bax was obtained in tissue explants without treatment (bcl-2; 0.96 &#x000b1; 0.12 AU; bax: 0.99 &#x000b1; 0.17 AU). Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref> shows the effect of androstenedione on the mRNA abundance of bcl-2 and bax in endometrial explants. For bcl-2, the level of its mRNA decreased with androstenedione treatment (p &#x0003c; 0.05) and hydroxyflutamide inhibited this effect, whereas, the mRNA abundance of bax did not change with the treatment. Despite these results, a similar bcl-2/bax ratio was obtained (basal: 1.06 &#x000b1; 0.21; treated: 0.99 &#x000b1; 0.12).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Effect of androstenedione in the mRNA abundance for bcl-2 and bax in endometrial tissue explants.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="center">bcl-2 (%)</td><td align="center">bax (%)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Basal</td><td align="center">100</td><td align="center">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Androstenedione (10<sup>-6 </sup>M)</td><td align="center">73.6 &#x000b1; 3.9*</td><td align="center">90.0 &#x000b1; 20.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Androstenedione (10<sup>-6 </sup>M) plus hydroxyflutamide (10<sup>-5 </sup>M)</td><td align="center">86.7 &#x000b1; 14.5</td><td align="center">113.3 &#x000b1; 37.1</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*p &#x0003c; 0.05. Values are calculated as percentage of basal and are expressed as mean &#x000b1; SEM.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>In isolated cells, the basal mRNA abundance for bcl-2 in EEC was 0.47 &#x000b1; 0.07 AU and for bax 0.39 &#x000b1; 0.25 AU and in ESC, basal expression of bcl-2 mRNA was 0.87 &#x000b1; 0.16 AU and 1.09 &#x000b1; 0.10 AU for bax. Androstenedione induced a decrease of 58% of bcl-2 mRNA expression (p &#x0003c; 0.05) and a 30% increase of bax mRNA (p &#x0003c; 0.05) in EEC (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>); therefore, the ratio bcl-2/bax was significantly lower compared to the basal condition (p &#x0003c; 0.05). In ESC, no significant differences on mRNA expression for bcl-2 and bax were found between the basal and androgen-treated conditions. No important changes in mRNAs expression were observed when hydroxyflutamide was added to both cell culture systems.</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) amplification from reverse-transcribed cDNA from endometrial epithelial cells (EEC) under the stimulation with androstenedione 10<sup>-6 </sup>M, using primers for bcl-2, bax and &#x003b2;-actin. Results represent six experiments performed in duplicate. Normalized yield for bcl-2 and bax PCR fragments relative to &#x003b2;-actin. PCR products from different experiments are shown as percentage respect to basal. The values are expressed as mean &#x000b1; SEM. <sup>a</sup>p &#x0003c; 0.05 between basal vs androstenedione.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1477-7827-2-81-2"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Effect of androstenedione on messenger RNA abundance of steroid receptors</title><p>In the endometrial explant cultures, the abundance of mRNA for ER&#x003b1; was similar between the basal condition and the tissue treated with androstenedione (0.44 &#x000b1; 0.12 AU; 0.41 &#x000b1; 0.07 AU, respectively). In contrast, androstenedione treatment induced a decrease in ER&#x003b2; mRNA abundance (basal: 0.91 &#x000b1; 0.11 AU ; treated: 0.75 &#x000b1; 0.08 AU; p &#x0003c; 0.05). However, the ratio between the level of ER isoforms did not change. No significant modifications were observed when hydroxyflutamide was added to the cultures.</p><p>On the other hand, basal expression of ER&#x003b1; mRNA was 0.31 &#x000b1; 0.05 AU and 0.39 &#x000b1; 0.08 AU for ER&#x003b2; in EEC; in ESC was 0.82 &#x000b1; 0.23 AU for ER&#x003b1; and 0.86 &#x000b1; 0.28 AU for ER&#x003b2;.</p><p>Androstenedione tended to modify mRNA abundance of ER&#x003b1; in EEC and ESC, a 30% and 25% diminution was obtained, respectively (p = 0.07). In EEC, gene expression of ER&#x003b2; increased 48% with androstenedione (0.39 &#x000b1; 0.08 AU vs 0.56 &#x000b1; 0.18, p &#x0003c; 0.05) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>), with no modification in ESC. Therefore, the ratio between the expression of ER isoforms decreased 70% in EEC. Hydroxyflutamide reverted the effect of androstenedione on gene expression of ER&#x003b2; and on the ratio ER&#x003b1;/ER&#x003b2;.</p><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Polymerase chain reaction (PCR) amplification from reverse-transcribed cDNA from endometrial epithelial cells (EEC) under the stimulation with androstenedione 10<sup>-6 </sup>M, using primers for ER&#x003b1;, ER&#x003b2; and &#x003b2;-actin. Results represent six experiments performed in duplicate. Normalized yield for ER&#x003b1; and ER&#x003b2; PCR fragments relative to &#x003b2;-actin. PCR products from different experiments are shown as percentage respect to basal. The values are expressed as mean &#x000b1; SEM. <sup>a </sup>P &#x0003c; 0.05 between basal vs androstenedione.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1477-7827-2-81-3"/></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>The present investigation represents an interesting approach that associates the potential effect of androgens on endometrial cell survival. By means of two <italic>in vitro </italic>models, we could observe that androstenedione can modulate the proliferation and apoptosis of the stromal compartment and modify the mRNA abundance of proteins related to apoptosis and &#x003b2;-isoform of ER in EEC.</p><p>Thereby, in explant cultures, androstenedione stimulated cell proliferation in stroma. One possible explanation to this finding may be related to the fact that androgens can induce the expression of the receptor of epidermal growth factor in the stromal compartment, as reported previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. In turn, the increase in the proliferation rate may occur through an indirect effect of the growth factor on stromal cells.</p><p>Also, in the tissue explants model we observed that androstenedione induced a diminution in the apoptosis degree; although, the abundance of bcl-2 gene decreased. This observation may be in contrast to the mechanism that regulates apoptosis in cells; however, the ratio bcl-2/bax did not change and, concomitantly, we did not observe important differences in the expression of caspase-3. This is a relevant point because according to previous reports the control of cell death is principally associated with an unbalance in the expression of proteins related to the bcl-2 family, mainly bcl-2 and bax [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. These findings may suggest that alternative apoptotic pathways can be also operating in the endometrial cells.</p><p>On the other hand, it is well known that in endometrial tissue, estrogen actions mediated through their own receptors have been related to cell survival and progression of proliferation. Furthermore, during the menstrual cycle, it has been demonstrated the presence of the isoforms &#x003b1; and &#x003b2; of ER in endometrial tissue [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. Moreover, it has been postulated that the expression of ER&#x003b1; may be associated to bcl-2 gene expression [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. Studies in other reproductive tissues have also suggested that ER&#x003b2; could be involved in the inhibition of cell proliferation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. Therefore, it acquires great relevance the relationship between &#x003b1; and &#x003b2; isoforms of ER, considering that both isoforms could have an antagonistic action ligand-dependent, in accordance to the relative expression of each isoform in different tissues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. In the tissue explant model used in the present study, in contrast to a previous report [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>], we were unable to demonstrate an increase of ER&#x003b1;. Nevertheless, we observed a decrease of the &#x003b2;-isoform of ER under the effect of androstenedione, which could be associated to the increase of stromal cell proliferation detected in the explants. Numerous clinical and <italic>in vitro </italic>studies have suggested that the imbalanced of ER&#x003b1;/ER&#x003b2; is a common feature and could be critical in the progression of estrogen-dependent tumors. It seems that ER&#x003b2; is an important modulator of the mitogenic action estrogen and it confers protection against the ER&#x003b1; hyperproliferation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. Moreover, in prostate carcinoma cells the expression of ER&#x003b2; has been associated with triggers of apoptotic pathway, similar to observed in models of ovarian cancer cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. Therefore, the observations in our models open an important field in a possible relationship between androgens effects with control of ER&#x003b2;-mediated cell proliferation</p><p>When isolated cells were evaluated, some differences were obtained in the parameters studied compared to the explant cultures, which highlight the importance of the relationship between the different cell compartments in the regulation of the cell survival [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>].</p><p>In ESC, androstenedione stimulated cell proliferation with no changes in the apoptosis degree nor on the expression of the genes bcl-2 and bax. This observation suggests that ESC exhibit an independent capacity to respond to androstenedione, whose action may be mediated by the androgen receptor. The latter is based mainly on the effect of the competitive inhibitor of the androgen receptor, hydroxyflutamide, which reverts the effect of androstenedione in the two models.</p><p>In EEC, androstenedione induced a diminution in the ratio between the mRNA abundance of bcl-2 and bax without an evident increase in the apoptosis degree. Previous studies in other models, such as breast cancer cell lines, have demonstrated that androgens can induce a decrease on the expression of bcl-2 and also an atrophy of the mammary ephitelium [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]. The present observations suggest that the mechanisms of control of cell death in EEC are different from those of ESC, indicating that ESC may be responsible in providing molecular and physical interactions that can inhibit the early changes in the balance of apoptosis control genes in EEC.</p><p>In contrast to our results, a previous study showed that in EEC cultures, androstenedione produces a fall in cell proliferation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. In fact, we did not observe this phenomenon, most likely due to technical differences in which the treatment was performed for 24 h in the present study with the aim to evaluate the early expression of genes related to apoptosis.</p><p>Moreover, in EEC we observed that androstenedione up-regulated the ER&#x003b2; expression and hence, a decrease in ER<inline-graphic xlink:href="1477-7827-2-81-i2.gif"/>/ER&#x003b2; ratio was obtained. The meaning of this effect on cell survival is difficult to evaluate in our experimental model, since no estradiol was added to the culture system. Furthermore, it is unlikely that androstenedione may produce estrogen by P<sub>450 </sub>aromatase activity, because normal endometrial cells present a very low expression of this enzyme, as previously demonstrated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>]. However, in EEC the decrease in ER&#x003b1;/ER&#x003b2; may be related to an unbalance of the bcl-2/bax ratio although this hypothesis needs further studies.</p><p>Taking together our results, we can speculate that in the presence of androgens the regulatory mechanisms of cell survival in endometrial cells would be associated to the interaction capacity elicited by the different cellular components of the tissue. In fact, we postulate that androgens induce an increase of proliferation in stroma, probably related to growth factors and that these signals interact with epithelial cells, promoting an inhibition on the expression of genes related to cell death. In isolated cells, the mechanisms that allow these interactions between cell compartments are lost and the cells act according to their proper feature.</p><p>Our findings on the effect of androstendione on cell proliferation and apoptosis of ESC allows us to suggest a potential regulatory action of androgen in the physiology of the endometrium and its implications in the genesis of endometrial pathologies frequently found in women with hyperandrogenism. Even more, we have observed that endometrial androstenedione concentration in women with PCOS are three times higher than in normal women during the proliferative phase [unpublished data). Therefore, these in vitro models are important approaches to understand the potential role of androstenedione in the PCOS endometria. It is well established that women with PCOS exhibit a high prevalence of hyperplasia and endometrial cancer, which is associated with disturbances in the regulation of cell survival [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. According to our results, androgens may be involved in these endometrial alterations. However, we cannot ruled out the possible action of hyperinsulinaemia, common feature observed in PCOS women, which has been associated to increase the potential for neoplastic change through theirs effects on sex hormone binding-globulin (SHBG), insulin-like growth factor-1 and estrogen concentrations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>In summary, our results indicate that androstenedione may modulate cell survival, the expression of &#x003b2;-ER isoforms and proteins related to apoptosis. These observations are closely related to the control of endometrial cell function and may help to understand the possible effect of the hyperandrogemia on endometrial tissue.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>MM conceived and designed the study, carried out the experimental protocols, and drafted the manuscript. SQ, MC and KB performed the RT-PCR and scored of immunohistochemistry, MA carried out the score of immunohistochemistry studies. CJ reviewed and supported in the drafting the manuscript and MV conceived the study as principal investigator and participated in drafting the manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors are grateful to Fondo Nacional de Ciencia y Tecnolog&#x000ed;a (FONDECYT) # 1010821 for financial support, to Dr. Fernando Gabler (Pathology Department, San Borja-Arriar&#x000e1;n Clinical Hospital) for his role in histological procedures of endometria biopsies, Dr. Alberto Palomino for his contribution in recruitment and surgical procedures of subjects, and to the women who donated tissue.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zawadzky</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunaif</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hershmann JM</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Diagnosis criteria: Towards a rational approach</article-title><source>In Current Issues in Endocrinology and Metabolism</source><year>1992</year><publisher-name>Boston: Blackwell Scientific Publications</publisher-name><fpage>377</fpage><lpage>384</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nestler</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polycystic ovary syndrome: a disorder for a generalist</article-title><source>Fertil Steril</source><year>1998</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>811</fpage><lpage>812</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9806557</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0015-0282(98)00318-5</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Polson</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Franks</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prevalence of polycystic ovaries in women with anovulation and idiopathic hirsutism</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>1986</year><volume>293</volume><fpage>355</fpage><lpage>359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3089520</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coulam</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Annegers</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kranz</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chronic anovulation syndrome and associated neoplasia</article-title><source>Obstet Gynecol</source><year>1983</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>407</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6828267</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Segreti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Azziz R, Nestler J, Dewailly D</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Endometrial hyperplasia and carcinoma in women with androgen excess disorders</article-title><source>In Androgen excess disorders women</source><year>1997</year><publisher-name>Lippincott-Raven</publisher-name><fpage>667</fpage><lpage>672</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polycystic ovary syndrome and cancer</article-title><source>Hum Reprod Update</source><year>2001</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>522</fpage><lpage>525</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11727859</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/humupd/7.6.522</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maliqueo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Clementi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabler</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sir-Petermann</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Palomino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vega</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Steroid receptors and proteins related to apoptosis in endometria of women with polycystic ovary syndrome</article-title><source>Fertil Steril</source><year>2003</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>812</fpage><lpage>819</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14505758</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0015-0282(03)00987-7</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Apparao</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lovely</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gui</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Lininger</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lessey</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Elevated endometrial androgen receptor expression in women with polycystic ovarian syndrome</article-title><source>Biol Reprod</source><year>2002</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>297</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11804942</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gregory</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Apparao</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lininger</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kowalik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fritz</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lessey</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Steroid receptor coactivator expression throughout the menstrual cycle in normal and abnormal endometrium</article-title><source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2002</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>2960</fpage><lpage>2966</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12050280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/jc.87.6.2960</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Legro</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polycystic ovary syndrome: the new millenium</article-title><source>Mol Cell Endocrinol</source><year>2002</year><volume>186</volume><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>225</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0303-7207(02)00033-3</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carmina</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lobo</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Polycystic ovary syndrome (PCOS): arguably the most common endocrinopathy is associated with significant morbidity in women</article-title><source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>1999</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>1897</fpage><lpage>1899</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10372683</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/jc.84.6.1897</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Narukawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanzaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Imai</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Higuchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatayama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kariya</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Androgens induce prolactin production by human endometrial stromal cells in vitro</article-title><source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>1994</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8288699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/jc.78.1.165</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iwai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanzaki</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujimoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatayama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Inoue</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Higuchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakayama</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of sex steroid receptor gene expression by progesterone and testosterone in cultured human endometrial stromal cells</article-title><source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>1995</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>450</fpage><lpage>454</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7852503</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/jc.80.2.450</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tuckerman</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Okon</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Laird</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Do androgens have a direct effect on endometrial function? An in vitro study</article-title><source>Fertil Steril</source><year>2000</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>771</fpage><lpage>779</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11020522</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0015-0282(00)00711-1</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dahmoun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Boman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Cajander</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Westin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Backstrom</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Apoptosis, proliferation, and sex hormone receptors in superficial parts of human endometrium at the end of the secretory phase</article-title><source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>1999</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>1737</fpage><lpage>1743</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10323409</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/jc.84.5.1737</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gustafsson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An update on estrogen receptors</article-title><source>Semin Perinatol</source><year>2000</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10709863</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hengartner</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The biochemistry of apoptosis</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2000</year><volume>407</volume><fpage>770</fpage><lpage>776</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11048727</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35037710</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Anido</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cortinez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gabler</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Vega</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of nitric oxide and bcl-2 family genes in the regulation of human endometrial apoptosis</article-title><source>Fertil Steril</source><year>2002</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>587</fpage><lpage>595</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12215338</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0015-0282(02)03304-6</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Apoptosis pathways: paper wraps stone blunts scissors</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2000</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10929706</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0092-8674(00)00003-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bonney</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Scanlon</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>VH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adrenal androgen concentrations in endometrium and plasma during the menstrual cycle</article-title><source>J Endocrinol</source><year>1984</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6232333</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suri</surname><given-names>NK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Steroid content in endometrial tissue</article-title><source>East Afr Med J</source><year>1997</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>242</fpage><lpage>248</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9299827</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name><name><surname>Dowsett</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mudge</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>JO</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeffcoate</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The inhibitory effects of danazol, danazol metabolites, gestrinone, and testosterone on the growth of human endometrial cells in vitro</article-title><source>Fertil Steril</source><year>1988</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>224</fpage><lpage>228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3338580</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Maliqueo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Boric</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Villavicencio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vantman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Vega</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential in vitro actions of nitric oxide on human endometrial cell survival</article-title><source>Fertil Steril</source><year>2004</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>176</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14711563</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fertnstert.2003.05.018</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brandenberger</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Tee</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name><name><surname>Chao</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaffe</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Tissue distribution of estrogen receptors alpha (ER-alpha) and beta (ER-beta) mRNA in the midgestational human fetus</article-title><source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>1997</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>3509</fpage><lpage>3512</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9329394</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/jc.82.10.3509</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Franks</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonney</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of epidermal growth factor receptor by androgens in human endometrial cells in culture</article-title><source>Hum Reprod</source><year>1998</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>2585</fpage><lpage>2591</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9806289</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/humrep/13.9.2585</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Critchley</surname><given-names>HO</given-names></name><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nayak</surname><given-names>NR</given-names></name><name><surname>Slayden</surname><given-names>OD</given-names></name><name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estrogen receptor beta, but not estrogen receptor alpha, is present in the vascular endothelium of the human and nonhuman primate endometrium</article-title><source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2001</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>1370</fpage><lpage>1378</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11238534</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/jc.86.3.1370</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lecce</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Meduri</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Ancelin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergeron</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Perrot-Applanat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Presence of estrogen receptor beta in the human endometrium through the cycle: expression in glandular, stromal, and vascular cells</article-title><source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>2001</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>1379</fpage><lpage>1386</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11238535</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/jc.86.3.1379</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Critchley</surname><given-names>HO</given-names></name><name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Drudy</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Baird</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of bcl-2 gene family members in human endometrium by antiprogestin administration in vivo</article-title><source>J Reprod Fertil</source><year>1999</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>395</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10434946</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahla</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Makela</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gustafsson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Rochefort</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Decreased expression of estrogen receptor beta protein in proliferative preinvasive mammary tumors</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>2537</fpage><lpage>2541</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11289127</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weihua</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Makela</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Salmi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Saji</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Warner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gustafsson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A role for estrogen receptor beta in the regulation of growth of the ventral prostate</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2001</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>6330</fpage><lpage>6335</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11371645</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.111150898</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petterson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Gustafsson</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of estrogen receptor beta in estrogen action</article-title><source>Annu Rev Physiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>192</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11181953</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.physiol.63.1.165</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bardin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Boulle</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazennec</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Vignon</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Pujol</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Loss of ERbeta expression as a common step in estrogen-dependent tumor progression</article-title><source>Endocr Relat Cancer</source><year>2004</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>537</fpage><lpage>551</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15369453</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1677/erc.1.00800</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Madison</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazennec</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of estrogen receptor beta in prostate carcinoma cells inhibits invasion and proliferation and triggers apoptosis</article-title><source>FEBS Lett</source><year>2004</year><volume>566</volume><fpage>169</fpage><lpage>172</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15147889</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.febslet.2004.04.025</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bardin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Boulle</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Katsaros</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Vignon</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Pujol</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lazennec</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Involvement of estrogen receptor beta in ovarian carcinogenesis</article-title><source>Cancer Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>5861</fpage><lpage>5869</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15313930</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lessey</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Endometrial integrins and the establishment of uterine receptivity</article-title><source>Hum Reprod</source><year>1998</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>247</fpage><lpage>259</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9755427</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lapointe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fournier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Richard</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Labrie</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Androgens down-regulate bcl-2 protooncogene expression in ZR-75-1 human breast cancer cells</article-title><source>Endocrinology</source><year>1999</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>416</fpage><lpage>421</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9886853</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1210/en.140.1.416</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kitawaki</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Noguchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Amatsu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Maeda</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsukamoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fushiki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Osawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Honjo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of aromatase cytochrome P450 protein and messenger ribonucleic acid in human endometriotic and adenomyotic tissues but not in normal endometrium</article-title><source>Biol Reprod</source><year>1997</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>514</fpage><lpage>519</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9282984</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reproductive health and polycystic ovary syndrome</article-title><source>Am J Med</source><year>1995</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>67S</fpage><lpage>75S</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7825642</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0002-9343(99)80061-8</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



