<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Clin Mol Allergy</journal-id><journal-title>Clinical and molecular allergy : CMA</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1476-7961</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15644142</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC546202</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1476-7961-3-1</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1476-7961-3-1</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Allergens of the entomopathogenic fungus <italic>Beauveria bassiana</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Westwood</surname><given-names>Greg S</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>gregwest@ufl.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>Shih-Wen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>huangsw@peds.ufl.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Keyhani</surname><given-names>Nemat O</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>keyhani@ufl.edu</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Microbiology and Cell Science, University of Florida, Gainesville, FL 32611, USA</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Pediatrics, University of Florida, College of Medicine, 32610, USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>11</day><month>1</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>3</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>1</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.clinicalmolecularallergy.com/content/3/1/1"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>11</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>11</day><month>1</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 Westwood et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Westwood et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Westwood
               S
               Greg
               
               gregwest@ufl.edu
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Allergens of the entomopathogenic fungus Beauveria bassiana
         </dc:title><dc:date>2005</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Clinical and Molecular Allergy 3(1): 1-. (2005)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1476-7961(2005)3:1&#x0003c;1&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1476-7961</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p><italic>Beauveria bassiana </italic>is an important entomopathogenic fungus currently under development as a bio-control agent for a variety of insect pests. Although reported to be non-toxic to vertebrates, the potential allergenicity of <italic>Beauveria </italic>species has not been widely studied.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>IgE-reactivity studies were performed using sera from patients displaying mould hypersensitivity by immunoblot and immunoblot inhibition. Skin reactivity to <italic>B. bassiana </italic>extracts was measured using intradermal skin testing.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Immunoblots of fungal extracts with pooled as well as individual sera showed a distribution of IgE reactive proteins present in <italic>B. bassiana </italic>crude extracts. Proteinase K digestion of extracts resulted in loss of IgE reactive epitopes, whereas EndoH and PNGaseF (glycosidase) treatments resulted in minor changes in IgE reactive banding patterns as determined by Western blots. Immunoblot inhibitions experiments showed complete loss of IgE-binding using self protein, and partial inhibition using extracts from common allergenic fungi including; <italic>Alternaria alternata</italic>, <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic>, <italic>Cladosporium herbarum</italic>, <italic>Candida albicans</italic>, <italic>Epicoccum purpurascens</italic>, and <italic>Penicillium notatum</italic>. Several proteins including a strongly reactive band with an approximate molecular mass of 35 kDa was uninhibited by any of the tested extracts, and may represent <italic>B. bassiana </italic>specific allergens. Intradermal skin testing confirmed the <italic>in vitro </italic>results, demonstrating allergenic reactions in a number of individuals, including those who have had occupational exposure to <italic>B. bassiana</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p><italic>Beauveria bassiana </italic>possesses numerous IgE reactive proteins, some of which are cross-reactive among allergens from other fungi. A strongly reactive potential <italic>B. bassiana </italic>specific allergen (35 kDa) was identified. Intradermal skin testing confirmed the allergenic potential of <italic>B. bassiana</italic>.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Microorganisms are currently under intensive study for use as biopesticides [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Several fungal species including <italic>Metarhizium anisopliae</italic>, <italic>Verticillium lecanii</italic>, and <italic>Beauveria bassiana </italic>are being used as biocontrol agents for a number of crop, livestock, and human nuisance pests [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Strains of <italic>B. bassiana </italic>have been licensed for commercial use against whiteflies, aphids, thrips, and numerous other insect and arthropod pests. <italic>B. bassiana </italic>fungal formulations are being spread onto a range of vegetables, melons, tree fruits and nuts, as well as organic crops. As alternatives to chemical pesticides these agents are natural occurring and are considered to be non-pathogenic to humans, although a few cases of <italic>B. bassiana </italic>mediated tissue infections have been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>].</p><p>Airborne mold spores are widespread, and many have been identified as inhalant allergens eliciting type I hypersensitive reactions in atopic individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Common allergenic moulds include the anamorphs of ascomycetes and constitute many species within the <italic>Alternaria</italic>, <italic>Aspergillus</italic>, and <italic>Cladosporium </italic>genera [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. The genes encoding for numerous fungal allergens have been isolated, and their protein products expressed and characterized. Purified fungal allergens have been shown to be bound by human IgEs and to elicit allergic reactions in atopic individuals using skin prick tests. Patients with mould allergies often display IgE-mediated responses to multiple fungi, a phenomenon typically thought to result from the presence of common cross-reactive allergen(s) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>], although parallel independent sensitization to multiple fungal allergens can also occur. In this regards, identification of genus and/or species specific allergens would provide useful tools in differentiating allergic reactions due to primary sensitization and those mediated by cross-reactive epitopes.</p><p>In the present study, we demonstrate <italic>Beauveria bassiana </italic>crude extracts contain numerous allergens capable of being recognized by human serum IgEs. The allergens were proteinaceous in nature, and immunoblot inhibition experiments revealed the presence of shared epitopes between <italic>Beauveria </italic>and several other common fungal moulds. Potential <italic>Beauveria-specific </italic>allergens were also identified, including a strongly reactive ~35-kDa protein band. Intradermal skin testing using <italic>B. bassiana </italic>extracts resulted in allergenic reactions in several individuals, including some who have had occupational exposure to the fungus.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Strains and cultures</title><p><italic>Beauveria bassiana </italic>(ATCC 90517) was grown on Sabouraud dextrose + 0.5&#x02013;1% yeast extract or Potato dextrose (PD) media on either agar plates or in liquid broth. Plates were incubated at 26&#x000b0;C for 10&#x02013;12 days and conidia were harvested by flooding the plate with sterile dH<sub>2</sub>O containing 0.01% Tween-20. Liquid cultures were inoculated with conidia harvested from plates at 0.5&#x02013;1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>5 </sup>conidia/ml.</p></sec><sec><title>Extract preparation</title><p><italic>Alternaria alternata</italic>, <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic>, <italic>Candida albicans</italic>, <italic>Cladosporium herbarum</italic>, <italic>Epicoccum purpurascens</italic>, and <italic>Penicillium notatum </italic>were acquired from Greer Laboratories inc., (Lenoir, NC). Extracts were resuspended in TE (40 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.0, 1 mM EDTA) to a final concentration of 2 mg/ml. <italic>Beauveria bassiana </italic>was grown in Sabouraud's broth containing 1% yeast extract with aeration at 25&#x000b0;C for 3&#x02013;5 d. Cellular mass was harvested by centrifugation (10,000 &#x000d7; g, 10 min) and freeze-dried. Cells were resuspended in TE containing 0.1% phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride (PMSF) and homogenized using a bead-beater apparatus.</p></sec><sec><title>Precipitations</title><p>Crude extracts of <italic>B. bassiana </italic>were subjected to three successive precipitations before use in Western blots.</p><sec><title>Acetone precipitation</title><p>Homogenized <italic>B. bassiana </italic>extracts (50 ml) were mixed with 8 &#x000d7; volume (400 ml) of acetone (kept at -20&#x000b0;C), with rapid stirring, and incubated overnight at -20&#x000b0;C. The precipitate was collected by centrifugation (30 min, 4000 &#x000d7; g), and the pellet was air dried (10 min) before being resuspended in TE containing 0.1% PMSF.</p></sec><sec><title>Streptomycin precipitation (removal of DNA)</title><p>Streptomycin sulfate (5 ml of 10% solution) was added dropwise to resuspended acetone precipitated extracts (40 ml) at 4&#x000b0;C with rapid stirring. Samples were incubated for an additional 30 min on ice before being centrifuged (15 min, 10,000 &#x000d7; g) in order to remove the precipitate. Proteins in the resultant supernatant were precipitated using ammonium sulfate.</p></sec><sec><title>Ammonium sulfate</title><p>The proteins present in the streptomycin sulfate treated supernatant were precipitated using ammonium sulfate (75%, final concentration). Saturated ammonium sulfate (120 ml) was added dropwise to the <italic>Beauveria </italic>extract (40 ml) at 4&#x000b0;C with rapid stirring. The solution was allowed to stir overnight at 4&#x000b0;C and precipitated proteins were harvested by centrifugation (30 min, 100,000 &#x000d7; g). The protein pellet was resuspended in TE containing 0.1% PMSF (40 ml) and extensively dialyzed against the same buffer before use.</p></sec><sec><title>SDS-Polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (PAGE)</title><p>Protein samples (30&#x02013;40 &#x003bc;g) were analyzed by sodium-dodecyl-sulphate-polyacrylaminde gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE, 10% Bis-tris gel, Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA) using standard protocols. Gels were stained with Gelcode blue stain reagent (Pierce, Rockford, IL) and subsequently de-stained with dH20.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Western blotting</title><p>Protein samples were separated under reducing conditions using 10% Bis-tris polyacrylamide gels (Invitrogen Mops system) and transferred to polyvinylidene-fluoride (PVDF) membranes (Invitrogen) as described. Immunoblot experiments were performed using individual and pooled human sera as the primary antibody solution as indicated. Typically, sera were diluted 1:5 with Tris-HCl buffered saline (TBS) containing 5% dry milk + 0.1% Tween-20. IgE-specific reactivity was visualized using a horseradish peroxidase (HRP) conjugated goat anti-human IgE (polyclonal) secondary antibody (BioSource International, Los Angeles, CA). Membranes were washed with TBS containing 0.1% Tween-20 and bands were visualized using the Immuno-Star HRP detection system (Biorad, Hercules, CA).</p></sec><sec><title>Enzyme Treatments</title><p>The ammonium sulfate fraction of <italic>B. bassiana </italic>crude extracts was treated with Proteinase K (ICN-Biomed, Aurora, Oh) following standard protocols. Typically, samples (36 &#x003bc;l) were incubated with 4 &#x003bc;l Proteinase K solution (10 mg/ml in 50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5) for 2 hr at 37&#x000b0;C before analysis. Samples were also treated with endoglycosidase-H (EndoH, New England Biolabs, Beverly, MA) and peptide: N-Glycosidase F (PNGaseF, New England Biolabs) according to the manufacturer's recommendations. For EndoH and PNGaseF treatments, samples (36 &#x003bc;l) were denatured in 4 &#x003bc;l 10 &#x000d7; denaturing buffer (0.5% SDS, 1% &#x003b2;-mercaptoethanol) at 100&#x000b0;C for 10 min prior to the addition of the EndoH (5 &#x003bc;l of 10 &#x000d7; G5 Reaction Buffer, 50 mM sodium citrate, pH 5.5) and PNGaseF reaction buffers (50 mM sodium phosphate pH 7.5) and enzymes (5 &#x003bc;l), respectively. Reactions were incubated at 37&#x000b0;C for 2 h before being analyzed by SDS-PAGE and Western blotting.</p></sec><sec><title>Immunoblot inhibition</title><p>IgE binding to <italic>B. bassiana </italic>proteins were competed with proteins of other fungal extracts. SDS-PAGE resolved <italic>B. bassiana </italic>proteins were electroblotted to PVDF membranes as described above. Membranes were blocked with TBS containing 5% dry milk + 0.1% Tween-20 and strips were incubated with pooled human sera (1:5 v/v in same buffer) containing 100&#x02013;500 &#x003bc;g of the indicated fungal crude protein extract.</p></sec><sec><title>Skin sensitivity profiles to fungal extracts</title><p>Patients were tested with 9 common fungal extracts for allergy diagnosis using a skin prick assay. The following extracts were obtained from ALA-Abello (Round Rock, TX); <italic>Alternaria tenius</italic>, <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic>, <italic>Cephalosporium </italic>(<italic>Acremonium strictum</italic>), <italic>Curvularia </italic>spp. <italic>Bipolaris</italic>, <italic>Epicoccum nigram</italic>, <italic>Fusarium </italic>spp., <italic>Helminthosporium sativum</italic>, <italic>Hormodendrum horde</italic>, <italic>Penicillium </italic>(mixed, <italic>P. chrysogenum </italic>and <italic>P. notatum</italic>). Extracts were tested using a 1:10 dilution of the 20,000 PNU/ml stock solution, and skin sensitivity was recorded on a relative scale from 0&#x02013;4 reflecting the size of induration or weal (4 representing the highest reactivity) and using histamine (0.1 mg/ml) reaction scored as a 3 if no interference was present.</p></sec><sec><title>Intradermal skin testing</title><p><italic>B. bassiana </italic>crude extracts were prepared as described above but were extensively dialyzed against 0.15 N NaCl and filtered through a 0.22 &#x003bc;m filter before use. Subjects were given intradermal injections of 0.1 ml crude extract ranging in concentration from 0.01&#x02013;1 mg/ml. Control injections included saline and histamine (0.1 mg/ml). Allergenic reactions were allowed to develop for 15&#x02013;30 min before the height and width of the reactions were recorded.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Identification of IgE reactive bands</title><p>An ammonium sulfate fraction of <italic>B. bassiana </italic>proteins was resolved on SDS-PAGE (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, lane B) and transferred to PVDF membranes as described in the Materials and Methods. Membranes were probed with sera from individual patients who were reactive to various moulds (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>), which was pooled and used to demonstrate IgE reactivity against antigens present in <italic>B. bassiana </italic>extracts (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). Serum mix-I represents pooled sera derived from patients E, J, K, L, and M, as well as three additional patients that were only tested (skin prick) against <italic>Aspergillus </italic>and <italic>Penicillium</italic>, displaying test scores of 3&#x02013;4 for each. These data demonstrate human IgE binding of allergens present in <italic>B. bassiana </italic>extracts. Initial blots showed 12&#x02013;15 distinct reactive protein bands, ranging in molecular mass from 12 kDa to &#x0003e;95 kDa (under denaturing conditions); with the most prominent bands located around 64, 45, and 35 kDa. Control experiments omitting either the primary or secondary antibody incubation steps resulted in complete loss of signal. Proteinase K digestion of samples also resulted in loss of all signal (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, lane 4), indicating the proteinaceous nature of the IgE reactive bands. Since the carbohydrate moieties of several protein allergens are known to play a role in their allergenicity and even cross-reactivity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>], samples were treated with the deglyocosylating enzymes EndoH and PNGaseF. Control experiments incubating samples in the EndoH denaturing buffer without any enzyme altered the IgE-reactive signals (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, lane 5), however, samples treated with EndoH did not appear any different than control reactions (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, lane 6). Similar results were obtained in PNGaseF digests (data not shown). These data appear to indicate that the <italic>B. bassiana </italic>IgE-antigen profiles observed on Western blots are proteins with minimal contributions due to glycosylation.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>SDS-PAGE and immunoblot analysis of <italic>Beauveria bassiana </italic>crude extracts. SDS-PAGE, Gelcode blue stained, lanes A) 5 &#x003bc;g protein standards, and B) 40 &#x003bc;g <italic>B. bassiana </italic>crude extract. Immunoblots probed with pooled serum mix-I (patients displaying mould allergies), lanes 1), 5 &#x003bc;g protein standards, 2) 20 &#x003bc;g <italic>B. bassiana </italic>crude extract, 3) 40 &#x003bc;g crude extract, 4) 40 &#x003bc;g crude extract, Proteinase K treated, 5) 40 &#x003bc;g crude extract, denaturing buffer control (no EndoH), 6) 40 &#x003bc;g crude extract, EndoH treated</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1476-7961-3-1-1"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Allergic profile of patients A&#x02013;G, obtained by skin prick testing.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center">Patient ID</td><td align="center" colspan="9">Individual Skin Reactivity to Fungal Extracts*</td></tr><tr><td></td><td colspan="9"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center"><italic>Alt</italic><sup>&#x02020;</sup></td><td align="center"><italic>Asp</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>Cep</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>Cur</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>Epi</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>Fusa</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>Helmin</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>Hormo</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>Pen</italic></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">A</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">B</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">C</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">D</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">E</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">F</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">G</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">3</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*Skin test scores were registered using a relative scale from 0&#x02013;4 with 4 representing the highest reactivity as described in the Materials and Methods. <sup>&#x02020;</sup>Abbreviations used; <italic>Alt</italic>, <italic>Alternaria tenius</italic>; <italic>Asp</italic>, <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic>; <italic>Cep</italic>, <italic>Cephalosporium </italic>(<italic>Acremonium strictum</italic>); <italic>Cur</italic>, <italic>Curvularia </italic>spp. <italic>Bipolaris</italic>; <italic>Epi</italic>, <italic>Epicoccum nigram</italic>; <italic>Fusa</italic>, <italic>Fusarium </italic>spp.; <italic>Helmin</italic>, <italic>Helminthosporium sativum</italic>; <italic>Hormo</italic>, <italic>Hormodendrum horde</italic>; <italic>Pen</italic>, <italic>Penicillium </italic>(mixed, <italic>P. chrysogenum </italic>and <italic>P. notatum</italic>).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Immunoprint Analysis of <italic>B. bassiana</italic>: Reactivity with Individual Sera</title><p>In order to determine the variation and distribution of serum IgEs reactive to <italic>B. bassiana </italic>extracts, individual sera from patients displaying mould allergies (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>, lanes A&#x02013;G) as well as random sera from the general population (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>, lanes H&#x02013;M) were used as probes for Western blots (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). The reactivity of pooled sera from patients A&#x02013;G (termed serum mix-II) is also shown (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>, lane 2). Skin prick test results for patients A&#x02013;G are shown for comparative purposes (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>) and represent the clinically determined reactivity of each patient to extracts of the tested fungal species. Patients (A&#x02013;G) were selected based skin prick reactivity to at least 4 different fungi with scores of 2 or greater. Identical concentrations of <italic>B. bassiana </italic>extract (40 &#x003bc;g) were resolved by SDS-PAGE, blotted to PVDF membranes, and the lanes were cut into separate strips. Each strip was treated with a 1:5 dilution of each respective serum as described in the Materials and Methods (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>, lane 2 is the sera pool). A total of 16 individual sera were tested, with the sera from three patients displaying no IgEs reactive to proteins present in the <italic>B. bassiana </italic>extracts. The results for the remaining 13 sera are shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>. The data show a large individual variation in serum IgEs capable of binding epitopes present in <italic>B. bassiana </italic>extracts, both in terms of banding distribution and the intensity of the reaction. No correlation was observed between measurements of total IgE and the observed binding to <italic>B. bassiana </italic>allergens. Some patients displayed strong reactions to multiple bands, whereas others to a more limited set of epitopes. Distinct strongly reactive bands ranging from 40 kDa to approximately 200 kDa could be seen in sera A, E, and to a lesser extent L. A strongly reactive 35 kDa band was visible in sera C, G, E, and L. Several sera displayed IgEs that bound to only a limited set of 2&#x02013;3 allergens (C, F, G, weak bands in B, I, J, K, and M). Blots probed with one serum (H) resulted in a large smear ranging from ~30 kDa to 55 kDa. The reason for the observed smear is unknown and efforts to distinguish separate bands by manipulating the concentrations of either sera or extract were unsuccessful. A number of bands (based upon molecular mass) appeared to be common to several sera including proteins of approximately 35, 42&#x02013;48, and 60 kDa. A number of allergens of high molecular weight (~100&#x02013;200 kDa) were also visible; however the resolution in this range on the Western blots is poor.</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Immunoprint analysis of <italic>B. bassiana </italic>extracts (40 &#x003bc;g crude extract/strip) probed with individual sera. Lane 1) 5 &#x003bc;g protein standards, 2) pooled serum mix-II (patients displaying mould allergies). Lanes A)&#x02013;G) membrane strips treated with individual sera, Lanes H)&#x02013;M) membrane strips probed with individuals having had occupational exposure to <italic>B. bassiana </italic>and other fungi (see intra-dermal skin test results for individuals J&#x02013;M, Table 2).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1476-7961-3-1-2"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>IgE immunoblot inhibition with fungi. <italic>B. bassiana </italic>protein strips (40 &#x003bc;g crude extract) were blocked and incubated with mix containing (500 &#x003bc;l) pooled sera (mix-II) and 2) no additions, 3) 40 &#x003bc;g <italic>Alternaria alternata </italic>crude extract, 4) 400 &#x003bc;g <italic>Alternaria alternata</italic>, 5) 40 &#x003bc;g <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic>, 6) 400 &#x003bc;g <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic>, 7) 400 &#x003bc;g <italic>Cladosporium herbarum</italic>, 8) 400 &#x003bc;g <italic>Candida albicans</italic>, 9) 400 &#x003bc;g <italic>Epicoccum purpurascens</italic>, and 10) 400 &#x003bc;g <italic>Penicillium notatum </italic>protein.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1476-7961-3-1-3"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Intradermal Skin Testing</title><p>A total of ten individuals were tested for allergenic reactivity to <italic>B. bassiana </italic>crude extracts using an intradermal delivery procedure. Data using 1 mg/ml <italic>B. bassiana </italic>crude extract and histamine controls are presented in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>. Seven out of the ten individuals (ID #s, J&#x02013;O, and Q) displayed skin reactivity reactions to the <italic>B. bassiana </italic>extracts (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>, also see corresponding Western blot results for individuals J, K, L, and M; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). It is interesting to note that 4 (J&#x02013;M) of 5 individuals (plus S) that have had occupational exposure to <italic>B. bassiana </italic>displayed skin reactivity as well as bands on Western blots. A preliminary correlation was observed between the <italic>B. bassiana</italic>/histamine ration and the <italic>in vitro </italic>reactivity of individual sera in Western blots. Individuals J, K, and M, displayed <italic>B. bassiana</italic>/histamine control ratios &#x0003c;1, also showed weak bands in Western blots (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>), whereas individual L who had a <italic>B. bassiana</italic>/histamine ratio = 1.65, reacted against numerous epitopes in the extract and with a higher intensity.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Intradermal skin test results using <italic>B. bassiana </italic>extract</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center">Patient ID</td><td align="center" colspan="2">Histamine control<sup>1 </sup>(0.1 mg/ml)</td><td align="center" colspan="2"><italic>B. bassiana </italic>Extract (1 mg/ml)</td><td align="center"><italic>B. bassiana</italic>/Histamine</td></tr><tr><td></td><td colspan="5"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Induration<sup>2</sup></td><td align="center">Erythema<sup>2</sup></td><td align="center">Induration<sup>2</sup></td><td align="center">Erythema<sup>2</sup></td><td align="center">Induration ratio<sup>3</sup></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">J<sup>4,5</sup></td><td align="center">7 &#x000d7; 6</td><td align="center">12 &#x000d7; 16</td><td align="center">8 &#x000d7; 8</td><td align="center">12 &#x000d7; 13</td><td align="center">0.65</td></tr><tr><td align="left">K<sup>4,5</sup></td><td align="center">20 &#x000d7; 15</td><td align="center">55 &#x000d7; 50</td><td align="center">13 &#x000d7; 12</td><td align="center">14 &#x000d7; 13</td><td align="center">0.52</td></tr><tr><td align="left">L<sup>4,5</sup></td><td align="center">11 &#x000d7; 10</td><td align="center">16 &#x000d7; 33</td><td align="center">13 &#x000d7; 14</td><td align="center">26 &#x000d7; 28</td><td align="center">1.65</td></tr><tr><td align="left">M<sup>4,5</sup></td><td align="center">15 &#x000d7; 16</td><td align="center">36 &#x000d7; 44</td><td align="center">10 &#x000d7; 12</td><td align="center">10 &#x000d7; 12</td><td align="center">0.30</td></tr><tr><td align="left">N</td><td align="center">16 &#x000d7; 14</td><td align="center">38 &#x000d7; 58</td><td align="center">10 &#x000d7; 11</td><td align="center">21 &#x000d7; 17</td><td align="center">0.49</td></tr><tr><td align="left">O</td><td align="center">21 &#x000d7; 16</td><td align="center">39 &#x000d7; 59</td><td align="center">9 &#x000d7; 8</td><td align="center">18 &#x000d7; 21</td><td align="center">0.21</td></tr><tr><td align="left">P</td><td align="center">15 &#x000d7; 17</td><td align="center">44 &#x000d7; 45</td><td align="center">5 &#x000d7; 4</td><td align="center">5 &#x000d7; 4</td><td align="center">0.08</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Q</td><td align="center">15 &#x000d7; 14</td><td align="center">36 &#x000d7; 38</td><td align="center">9 &#x000d7; 12</td><td align="center">10 &#x000d7; 13</td><td align="center">0.51</td></tr><tr><td align="left">R</td><td align="center">15 &#x000d7; 15</td><td align="center">55 &#x000d7; 38</td><td align="center">4 &#x000d7; 4</td><td align="center">11 &#x000d7; 13</td><td align="center">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left">S<sup>4</sup></td><td align="center">20 &#x000d7; 19</td><td align="center">38 &#x000d7; 43</td><td align="center">4 &#x000d7; 4</td><td align="center">4 &#x000d7; 4</td><td align="center">0.04</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>1</sup>In all instances saline control injections produced indurations of 3&#x02013;4 mm &#x000d7; 3&#x02013;4 mm.</p><p><sup>2</sup>Values recorded in mm &#x000d7; mm.</p><p><sup>3</sup>Induration ratio expressed as <italic>B. bassiana </italic>reaction area (mm<sup>2</sup>)/histamine reaction area (mm<sup>2</sup>).</p><p><sup>4</sup>Individual with occupational exposure to <italic>Beauveria bassiana</italic>.</p><p><sup>5</sup>See Western Blot results for individual, Fig. 2.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Cross-reactivity among different fungi</title><p>In order to determine the extent of cross-reactivity of <italic>B. bassiana </italic>allergens with other fungi, immunoblot inhibition experiments were performed. Identical concentrations of <italic>B. bassiana </italic>crude extract (40 &#x003bc;g) were resolved by SDS-PAGE, blotted to PVDF membranes, and lanes were cut into separate strips. Each strip was treated with a 1:5 dilution pooled sera (serum mix-II) as the primary antibody supplemented with concentrations of fungal crude extracts as described in the Materials and Methods. Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> shows Western blots in which the binding of human IgEs to allergens present in <italic>B. bassiana </italic>extracts were competed with: excess crude extracts from <italic>Alternaria alternata </italic>(Fig <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>, lanes 3, 4), <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus </italic>(lanes 5, 6), <italic>Cladosporium herbarum </italic>(lanes 7)<italic>, Epicoccum purpurascens </italic>(Lane 8)<italic>, Penicillium notatum </italic>(lane 9)<italic>, </italic>and <italic>Candida albicans </italic>(lane 10). There was complete loss of all signals using 2-fold excess <italic>B. bassiana </italic>extract as the competitor (data not shown). These data indicate that while <italic>Beauveria </italic>possess many epitopes in common with several other fungi, notably <italic>Alternaria </italic>and <italic>Penicillium</italic>, a 35-kDa major reactive band was not inhibited by any extract tested.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>Although it is well known that fungi are important triggers of respiratory allergies, the potential allergenicity of entomopathogenic fungi used in biocontrol has largely been untested. Aerobiological surveys of conidial fungi and skin sensitivity tests to fungal extracts performed in the 1980s in the Netherlands revealed that although <italic>Beauveria </italic>could barely be detected in airborne samples, and represented less than 0.1% of the airborne fungal "flora", the incidence of allergic skin test reaction to <italic>Beauveria </italic>was the highest of all fungal species tested [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. In rural areas, the use of fungi in agricultural pest management practices can greatly increase the potential for human exposure to these agents. Likewise, in urban settings, the commercialization of fungal products for household use may potentiate a much wider problem since indoor air concentrations of the moulds can greatly increase. For these reasons, an examination of the allergenic potential of <italic>Beauveria bassiana </italic>is imperative.</p><p>The present study demonstrated the allergenic potential of <italic>B. bassiana </italic>directly by intradermal skin testing of individuals and <italic>in vitro </italic>by revealing the presence of serum IgEs capable of binding allergens present in fungal crude extracts. Over 20 different IgE binding proteins were observed using Western blots probed with sera from patients displaying mould allergies. Results using individual sera revealed a wide variation in IgE-binding proteins between sera, although several common bands, including a protein with an apparent molecular mass of 35 kDa were visible among the sera of several patients.</p><p>Our <italic>in vitro </italic>observations were confirmed by intradermal skin testing on individuals using <italic>B. bassiana </italic>extracts. While the testing sample population was small, these results indicated that our extracts were able to elicit allergic reactions in individuals, including some that have had occupational exposure to the fungus. Concentrations of ~1 mg/ml of <italic>B. bassiana </italic>extracts were required to elicit indurations equivalent to 0.1 mg/ml histamine in most individuals, indicating the possibility of potent allergens in the <italic>Beauveria </italic>extract. Interestingly, not all individuals specifically exposed to <italic>B. bassiana </italic>displayed allergic reactions and individuals J, K, and M (who did display mild allergic reactions, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>) did not react to the 35 KDa protein based upon Western blotting results (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). We do not, however, have any quantifiable index of exposure for the individuals in our sample and any interpretations should be made with some caution.</p><p>Numerous studies have revealed the presence of cross-reactive proteins among fungal species between genera [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. In our experiments, (excess) crude extract from a test organism was added during the primary antibody (human sera) incubation. Common or shared epitopes between <italic>B. bassiana </italic>and the test fungus would result in a loss of signal due to competition for reactive IgEs. However, IgEs reactive to <italic>Beauveria-specific </italic>allergens would not be affected, resulting in no change in the corresponding reactive bands on a Western blot. Loss of a signal would indicate that a homolog or shared epitope (IgE-reactive) exists between the two fungal species, implying that primary sensitization by one organism can result in an allergic reaction when exposed to the homologous allergen of another organism. Competitive immunoblot inhibition experiments revealed significant epitope homology between <italic>B. bassiana </italic>and several clinically important fungi responsible for IgE-mediated allergic reactions in atopic individuals. Thus, an allergic reaction to <italic>Beauveria </italic>exposure may arise in patients sensitized to other fungi. Extracts from <italic>A. alternata </italic>and <italic>E. purpurascens </italic>almost completely competed with allergens present in the <italic>B. bassiana </italic>extract with the notable exception of the ~35 kDa allergen. Competition experiments using <italic>A. fumigatus</italic>, <italic>C. herbarum</italic>, <italic>C. albicans</italic>, and <italic>P. notatum </italic>extracts also indicated the presence of many shared epitopes, although distinct (non-competed) IgE-binding <italic>B. bassiana </italic>proteins of 35 kDa, 64 kDa, and &#x0003e;200 kDa molecular mass were detectable. These proteins, particularly the 35 kDa allergens may represent <italic>B. bassiana </italic>specific allergens. Experiments are underway to characterize the 35 kDa allergen, which may lead to a diagnostic assay for <italic>B. bassiana </italic>sensitization. Finally, our analysis of potential <italic>B. bassiana </italic>allergens was limited to cell extracts grown under specific conditions and did not include the culture filtrate. Extracellular proteases, an important class of fungal proteins that can elicit allergenic reactions, have been characterized from a number of fungal species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>], and are likely to be present in <italic>B. bassiana</italic>. A careful examination of culture growth conditions is also warranted in order to provide a standardized reagent for testing purposes.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Although <italic>Beauveria </italic>holds promise as an arthropod biological control agent, there have been few reports on the allergenic potential of these organisms. Identification of <italic>B. bassiana </italic>specific allergens can lead diagnostic methods for determining sensitization to this organism and may provide a rational basis for allergen attenuation in order to yield safer biocontrol products. The observed cross-reactivity among proteins of <italic>B. bassiana </italic>and the fungi tested, highlight the importance of considering the possibility that multiple fungal sensitivity can occur due to exposure to a single fungus. Further testing should be performed to determine the scope, severity, and range of allergenic reactions to <italic>B. bassiana</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing Interests</title><p>The author(s) declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>GSW carried out the immunoassays and other <italic>in vitro </italic>experiments. SWH performed the clinical experiments and participated in the design of the study. NOK conceived of the study, and participated in its design and coordination, and drafted the manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We would like to thank Ruby Teng and Moya Chin for technical assistance. This paper is Florida Agricultural Experimental Station Journal series number R-10187.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCoy</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Baker RR and Dunn PE</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Entomogenous fungi as microbial pestidides</article-title><source>New Directions in Biological Control</source><year>1990</year><publisher-name>New York, NY, A.R. Liss</publisher-name><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>159</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leathers</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mycopesticides: status, challenges, and potential</article-title><source>Journal of Industrial Microbiology</source><year>1993</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>75</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Pell</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Entomopathogenic fungi as biological control agents</article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2003</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>413</fpage><lpage>423</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12764556</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Skinner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Brownbridge</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Parker</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of <italic>Beauveria bassiana</italic> and <italic>Metarhizium anisopliae</italic> isolates for management of tarnished plant bug, <italic>Lygus lineolaris</italic> (Hemiptera: Miridae)</article-title><source>J Invertebr Pathol</source><year>2003</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>147</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12676549</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-2011(03)00018-1</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kirkland</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Westwood</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Keyhani</surname><given-names>NO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pathogenicity of entomopathogenic fungi <italic>Beauveria bassiana</italic> and <italic>Metarhizium anisopliae</italic> to Ixodidae tick species <italic>Dermacentor variabilis, Rhipicephalus sanguineus,</italic> and <italic>Ixodes scapularis</italic></article-title><source>J Med Entomol</source><year>2004</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>705</fpage><lpage>711</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15311464</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lecuona</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Edelstein</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Berretta</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>La Rossa</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Arcas</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of <italic>Beauveria bassiana</italic> (hyphomycetes) strains as potential agents for control of <italic>Triatoma infestans</italic> (Hemiptera: Reduviidae)</article-title><source>J Med Entomol</source><year>2001</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>172</fpage><lpage>179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11296819</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reithinger</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cadena</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Alexander</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of the fungus <italic>Beauveria bassiana</italic> as a potential biological control agent against phlebotomine sand flies in Colombian coffee plantations</article-title><source>J Invertebr Pathol</source><year>1997</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>135</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9281401</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/jipa.1997.4671</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henke</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>De Hoog</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmermann</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kraemer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Weig</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Human deep tissue infection with an entomopathogenic <italic>Beauveria</italic> species</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>2698</fpage><lpage>2702</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12089314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.40.7.2698-2702.2002</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kisla</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cu-Unjieng</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sigler</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Medical management of <italic>Beauveria bassiana</italic> keratitis</article-title><source>Cornea</source><year>2000</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>406</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10832710</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00003226-200005000-00031</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beaumont</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kauffman</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Sluiter</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>De Vries</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sequential sampling of fungal air spores inside and outside the homes of mould-sensitive, asthmatic patients: a search for a relationship to obstructive reactions</article-title><source>Ann Allergy</source><year>1985</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>740</fpage><lpage>746</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4061983</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kurup</surname><given-names>VP</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Respiratory fungal allergy</article-title><source>Microbes Infect</source><year>2000</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>1101</fpage><lpage>1110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10967290</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1286-4579(00)01264-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aukrust</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mold allergy. Introduction</article-title><source>Clin Rev Allergy</source><year>1992</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>147</fpage><lpage>151</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1477810</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kurup</surname><given-names>VP</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name><surname>Vijay</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunobiology of fungal allergens</article-title><source>Int Arch Allergy Immunol</source><year>2002</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12444314</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000066780</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fungal allergy and pathogenicity. Introduction</article-title><source>Chem Immunol</source><year>2002</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>4</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12101997</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horner</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Helbling</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Salvaggio</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehrer</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fungal allergens</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source><year>1995</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7621398</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberger</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>JN</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurup</surname><given-names>VP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunological characterization of Asp f 2, a major allergen from <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic> associated with allergic bronchopulmonary aspergillosis</article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>1998</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>5175</fpage><lpage>5182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9784519</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kurup</surname><given-names>VP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular biology of <italic>Aspergillus</italic> allergens</article-title><source>Front Biosci</source><year>2003</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>S128</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12456370</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kurup</surname><given-names>VP</given-names></name><name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hemmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenberger</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Blaser</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Crameri</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selected recombinant <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic> allergens bind specifically to IgE in ABPA</article-title><source>Clin Exp Allergy</source><year>2000</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>988</fpage><lpage>993</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10848921</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2222.2000.00837.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kurup</surname><given-names>VP</given-names></name><name><surname>Banerjee</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fungal allergens and peptide epitopes</article-title><source>Peptides</source><year>2000</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>589</fpage><lpage>599</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10822116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0196-9781(00)00181-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aukrust</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Borch</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cross reactivity of moulds</article-title><source>Allergy</source><year>1985</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4083424</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aalberse</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Akkerdaas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>van Ree</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cross-reactivity of IgE antibodies to allergens</article-title><source>Allergy</source><year>2001</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>478</fpage><lpage>490</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11421891</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1034/j.1398-9995.2001.056006478.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Sridhara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaur</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaudhary</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name><name><surname>Arora</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Allergenic cross-reactivity of <italic>Curvularia lunata</italic> with other airborne fungal species</article-title><source>Allergy</source><year>2002</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>636</fpage><lpage>640</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12100306</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1034/j.1398-9995.2002.03331.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beaumont</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kauffman</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>de Monchy</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Sluiter</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>de Vries</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Volumetric aerobiological survey of conidial fungi in the North-East Netherlands. II. Comparison of aerobiological data and skin tests with mould extracts in an asthmatic population</article-title><source>Allergy</source><year>1985</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>181</fpage><lpage>186</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4039540</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beaumont</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Kauffman</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Mark</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sluiter</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>de Vries</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Volumetric aerobiological survey of conidial fungi in the North-East Netherlands. I. Seasonal patterns and the influence of metereological variables</article-title><source>Allergy</source><year>1985</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3887975</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vieths</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheurer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballmer-Weber</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Current understanding of cross-reactivity of food allergens and pollen</article-title><source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source><year>2002</year><volume>964</volume><fpage>47</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12023194</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weichel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmid-Grendelmeier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Fluckiger</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Breitenbach</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Blaser</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Crameri</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nuclear transport factor 2 represents a novel cross-reactive fungal allergen</article-title><source>Allergy</source><year>2003</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>198</fpage><lpage>206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12653793</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1034/j.1398-9995.2003.23822.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simon-Nobbe</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Probst</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kajava</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Oberkofler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Susani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Crameri</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ebner</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Breitenbach</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>IgE-binding epitopes of enolases, a class of highly conserved fungal allergens</article-title><source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source><year>2000</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>887</fpage><lpage>895</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11080711</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1067/mai.2000.110799</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>CY</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsai</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The prevalence of IgE antibody reactivity against the alkaline serine protease major allergen of <italic>Penicillium chrysogenum</italic> increases with the age of asthmatic patients</article-title><source>Ann Allergy Asthma Immunol</source><year>2003</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>248</fpage><lpage>253</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12602675</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gupta</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Sridhara</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name><name><surname>Arora</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of serine protease as a major allergen of <italic>Curvularia lunata</italic></article-title><source>Allergy</source><year>2004</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>421</fpage><lpage>427</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15005766</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1398-9995.2003.00378.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nigam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghosh</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarma</surname><given-names>PU</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new glycoprotein allergen/antigen with the protease activity from <italic>Aspergillus fumigatus</italic></article-title><source>Int Arch Allergy Immunol</source><year>2003</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>124</fpage><lpage>131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14600424</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000073713</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name><surname>Tam</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The importance of serine proteinases as aeroallergens associated with asthma</article-title><source>Int Arch Allergy Immunol</source><year>1999</year><volume>119</volume><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10474030</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000024202</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



