<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Neuroinflammation</journal-id><journal-title>Journal of Neuroinflammation</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1742-2094</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15312232</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC516045</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1742-2094-1-15</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1742-2094-1-15</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Similar promotion of A&#x003b2;<sub>1-42 </sub>fibrillogenesis by native apolipoprotein E &#x003b5;3 and &#x003b5;4 isoforms</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sweeney</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>sweeney@aecom.yu.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>Ralph</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>rmartins@cyllene.uwa.edu.au</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>LeVine</surname><given-names>Harry</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>hlevine@email.uky.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>Jonathan D</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><email>smithj@lerner.ccf.org</email></contrib><contrib id="A5" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gandy</surname><given-names>Sam</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I5">5</xref><email>samgandy3d@aol.com</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Cornell University Medical College, 1300 York Ave, Room A569, New York, NY 10021 USA</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Sir James McCusker Alzheimer's Unit, The University of Western Australia, Perth WA, Australia 6009</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Sanders-Brown Institute on Aging, University of Kentucky, Lexington, KY 40508 USA</aff><aff id="I4"><label>4</label>Cleveland Clinic, Cleveland, OH 44195 USA</aff><aff id="I5"><label>5</label>Farber Institute for Neurosciences Thomas Jefferson University 900 Walnut Street, JHN 467 Philadelphia, PA 19107-5587 USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>8</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>1</volume><fpage>15</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jneuroinflammation.com/content/1/1/15"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>7</day><month>8</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>8</month><year>2004</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2004 Sweeney et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2004</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Sweeney et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Sweeney
               David
               
               sweeney@aecom.yu.edu
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Similar promotion of A&#x003b2;1-42 fibrillogenesis by native apolipoprotein E &#x003b5;3 and &#x003b5;4 isoforms
         </dc:title><dc:date>2004</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>Journal of Neuroinflammation 1(1): 15-. (2004)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1742-2094(2004)1:1&#x0003c;15&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1742-2094</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><p>The apolipoprotein E &#x003b5;4 allele contributes to the genetic susceptibility underlying a large proportion (~40&#x02013;60%) of typical, sporadic Alzheimer disease. Apolipoprotein E deficient mice made transgenic for human apolipoprotein E &#x003b5;4 accumulate excess cerebral amyloid when compared to similarly prepared mice expressing human apolipoprotein E &#x003b5;3. Therefore, it is important to search for relevant interactions(s) between apolipoprotein E &#x003b5;4 and A&#x003b2; in order to clarify the biological role for apolipoprotein E &#x003b5;4 in Alzheimer disease. Using a thioflavine T (ThT)-based assay, we have investigated the effects of native human apolipoprotein E isoforms on the kinetics of A&#x003b2; fibrillogenesis. No obvious profibrillogenic activity was detected in A&#x003b2;<sub>1-40</sub>-based assays of any native apolipoprotein E isoform. However, when ThT assays were repeated using A&#x003b2;<sub>1-42</sub>, modest, but statistically significant, profibrillogenic activity was detected in both apolipoprotein E &#x003b5;3- and apolipoprotein E &#x003b5;4-containing media and was similar in magnitude for the two isoforms. These data demonstrate that native apolipoprotein E possesses "pathological chaperone"-type activity for A&#x003b2;: in other words, the data indicate that a chaperone-like misfolding reaction can occur between native apolipoprotein E and A&#x003b2;. However, the equipotent activities of the apolipoprotein E &#x003b5;3 and &#x003b5;4 isoforms suggests the possibility that either extended co-incubation of apolipoprotein E and A&#x003b2;, or, perhaps, the inclusion in the reaction of other fibrillogenesis-modulation co-factors (such as metal ions, or inflammatory mediators such as reactive oxygen species, &#x003b1;<sub>2</sub>-macroglobulin, apolipoprotein J, etc.) may be required for modeling <italic>in vitro </italic>the apolipoprotein E-isoform-specific-regulation of extracellular A&#x003b2; accumulation that occurs <italic>in vivo</italic>. Alternatively, other events, such as differential apolipoprotein E-isoform-mediated clearance of A&#x003b2; or of apolipoprotein E/A&#x003b2; complexes may underlie apolipoprotein E-isoform-dependent A&#x003b2; accumulation.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Genetic-neuropathological correlation indicates that the apolipoprotein E type &#x003b5;4 isoform specifies increased cerebral [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>] and cerebrovascular [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>] accumulation of amyloid &#x003b2;-protein (A&#x003b2;). In addition, the apolipoprotein E &#x003b5;2 isoform can apparently prevent the expression of clinical Alzheimer-type dementia which is otherwise typically associated with amyloidogenic mutations in the amyloid-&#x003b2; protein precursor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Since the apolipoprotein E &#x003b5;4 allele contributes to the genetic susceptibility underlying a large proportion (~40&#x02013;60%) of typical, sporadic Alzheimer disease, it is important to search for relevant interactions(s) between apolipoprotein E &#x003b5;4 and A&#x003b2; in order to clarify the biological role for apolipoprotein E &#x003b5;4 in Alzheimer disease. Currently proposed mechanisms include differential activities of apolipoprotein E isoforms in modulating A&#x003b2; fibrillogenesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>] and/or A&#x003b2; clearance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Many studies of apolipoprotein E modulation of A&#x003b2; fibrillogenesis have utilized denatured apolipoprotein E, purified from the serum of human apolipoprotein E homozgotes following extraction in organic solvents [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. While providing a convenient source of pure apolipoprotein E protein, this preparation does not represent native apolipoprotein E as it exists <italic>in vivo</italic>. Using a thioflavine T (ThT)-based assay [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>] we have investigated the effects of native human apolipoprotein E isoforms on the kinetics of A&#x003b2; fibrillogenesis.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>Synthetic A&#x003b2;<sub>1-40 </sub>or A&#x003b2;<sub>1-42 </sub>(Keck Foundation Protein Facility, Yale University, New Haven CT) was freshly prepared for each assay at a concentration of 16 mg/ml in distilled, deionized water and diluted with phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) to generate a 5 mg/ml working solution. The "aggregation step" consisted of a reaction mixture containing 8 &#x003bc;l A&#x003b2; peptide (1 mg/ml final conc) and 32 &#x003bc;l of either apolipoprotein E &#x003b5;3- or &#x003b5;4-containing conditioned medium or control conditioned medium from SV40 empty vector-transfected cells.</p><p>For the investigation of native apolipoprotein E preparations, apolipoprotein E isoforms were generated in the conditioned medium of stably-transfected SV40-apolipoprotein E &#x003b5;3-, or SV40-apolipoprotein E &#x003b5;4-, expressing Chinese hamster ovary (CHO) cells (CHO cells lack detectable endogenous apolipoprotein E; data not shown). All conditioned media were prepared using Dulbecco's minimal essential medium supplemented with 0.2% (wt/vol) bovine serum albumin only (no fetal bovine serum). Apolipoprotein E isoform levels were determined by quantitative immunoblotting of conditioned medium and apolipoprotein E-containing serum standards, the latter having been kindly provided by Dr. Petar Alaupovic of the Oklahoma Medical Research Foundation (Oklahoma City OK). Conditioned medium apolipoprotein E concentrations were then standardized using control medium conditioned by SV40 empty vector-transfected cells as diluent, yielding a final concentration of apolipoprotein E of 14 &#x003bc;g/ml, within the range of that reported in human cerebrospinal fluid. Since the final concentration of A&#x003b2; peptide was 1 mg/ml, the A&#x003b2;/apolipoprotein E stoichiometry (molar ratio) was ~500:1, suggesting models for the A&#x003b2;/apolipoprotein E interaction based either on a "catalytic" "pathological chaperoning" model of apolipoprotein E action on A&#x003b2;, or with a "seeding" model of A&#x003b2; folding. Detailed biochemical characterization of this native apolipoprotein E preparation has been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>].</p><p>The "aggregation step" fibrillogenesis reaction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>] was incubated at 37&#x000b0;C until the time of the ThT fluorescence measurement, which was performed from 1 to 7 days later. For the "measurement step" [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>], 960 &#x003bc;1 of 10 &#x003bc;M ThT (Nakarai Chemicals, Kyoto, Japan) in 50 mM phosphate buffer (pH 6.0) was added to the "aggregation step" reaction mixture. Within 30 minutes after addition of ThT, fluorescence was measured with a Millipore Cytofluor (Bedford MA) in each of five successive 200 &#x003bc;l aliquots of the reaction mixture, using an excitation filter of 450 nm and an emission filter of 482 nm, and a temperature of 25&#x000b0;C.</p><p>In order to standardize the ThT assay in our Laboratory, we performed studies of A&#x003b2; fibrillogenesis following 1&#x02013;7 day incubations of A&#x003b2;<sub>1-40</sub>, either in physiological phosphate buffer alone or in the presence of metal ions (Zn<sup>2+</sup>, Fe<sup>2+</sup>, or A1<sup>3+</sup>; 1 mM final conc [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. ThT fluorescence and ultrastructural features were measured daily (not shown). Profibrillogenic activities of the metal ions tested were in agreement with a published report [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>] (e.g., Al<sup>3+</sup>stimulated ThT fluorescence of A&#x003b2;<sub>1-40 </sub>by 3.6 &#x000b1; 1.1- to 5.7 &#x000b1; 1.4-fold; p &#x0003c; 0.01), indicating that our A&#x003b2; preparations were capable of metal ion-induced fibrillogenesis. Metals were not present during assessment of profibrillogenic effects of apolipoprotein E isoforms.</p></sec><sec><title>Results and discussion</title><p>No obvious profibrillogenic activity was detected in A&#x003b2;<sub>1-40</sub>-based assays of any native apolipoprotein E isoform (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). However, when ThT assays were repeated using A&#x003b2;<sub>1-42</sub>, modest, but statistically significant, profibrillogenic activity was detected in both apolipoprotein E &#x003b5;3- and apolipoprotein E &#x003b5;4-containing media and was similar in magnitude for the two isoforms (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). The observation of a profibrillogenic effect of apolipoprotein E specifically for A&#x003b2;<sub>1-42 </sub>has been noted [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>] and is of particular interest in light of biophysical and molecular neuropathological evidence suggesting that "long" A&#x003b2; peptides ending at positions N-42 or N-43 are apparently crucial for the initiation ("seeding") of A&#x003b2; deposition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>].</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Effects of native apolipoprotein E isoforms on fibrillogenesis of A&#x003b2;<sub>1-40 </sub>and A&#x003b2;<sub>1-42</sub>. Fold-effects represent means &#x000b1; SEM of the quotients of ThT fluorescence values obtained for each A&#x003b2; peptide in the presence of apolipoprotein E-isoform-containing conditioned medium divided by ThT values obtained in the presence of conditioned medium lacking apolipoprotein E, derived from empty vector-transfected cells (n = 5&#x02013;6).</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td align="center" colspan="4">A&#x003b2;<sub>1-40</sub></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><underline>1 day co-incubation</underline></td><td align="left">CHO apolipoprotein E &#x003b5;3</td><td align="left">1.0 &#x000b1; 0.l-fold</td><td align="left">N.S.</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">CHO apolipoprotein E &#x003b5;4</td><td align="left">1.0 &#x000b1; 0.l-fold</td><td align="left">N.S.</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><underline>7 day co-incubation</underline></td><td align="left">CHO apolipoprotein E &#x003b5;3</td><td align="left">1.0 &#x000b1; 0.l-fold</td><td align="left">N.S.</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">CHO apolipoprotein E &#x003b5;4</td><td align="left">1.2 &#x000b1; 0.l-fold</td><td align="left">N.S.</td></tr><tr><td align="center" colspan="4">A&#x003b2;<sub>1-42</sub></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><underline>4 day co-incubation</underline></td><td align="left">CHO apolipoprotein E &#x003b5;3</td><td align="left">1.7 &#x000b1; 0.27-fold</td><td align="left">p &#x0003c; 0.01</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">CHO apolipoprotein E &#x003b5;4</td><td align="left">1.6 &#x000b1; 0.18-fold</td><td align="left">p &#x0003c; 0.005</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><underline>7 day co-incubation</underline></td><td align="left">CHO apolipoprotein E &#x003b5;3</td><td align="left">1.7 &#x000b1; 0.22-fold</td><td align="left">p &#x0003c; 0.005</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">CHO apolipoprotein E &#x003b5;4</td><td align="left">1.8 &#x000b1; 0.19-fold</td><td align="left">p &#x0003c; 0.0005</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>These data demonstrate that native apolipoprotein E possesses "pathological chaperone"-type activity for A&#x003b2;: in other words, the data indicate that a chaperone-like misfolding reaction can occur between native apolipoprotein E and A&#x003b2;, at least at the concentrations and proportions evaluated herein. However, the equipotent activities of the apolipoprotein E &#x003b5;3 and &#x003b5;4 isoforms suggests the possibility that either extended co-incubation of apolipoprotein E and A&#x003b2;, or, perhaps, the inclusion in the reaction of other fibrillogenesis-modulation co-factors (such as metal ions, or inflammatory mediators such as reactive oxygen species, &#x003b1;<sub>1</sub>-antichymotrypsin, heparin sulfate-protcoglycan, non-A&#x003b2; component, apolipoprotein J, complement, etc.) may be required for modeling <italic>in vitro </italic>the apolipoprotein E-isoform-specific-regulation of extracellular A&#x003b2; accumulation that occurs <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p><p>Alternatively, other events, such as differential apolipoprotein E-isoform-mediated clearance of A&#x003b2; or of apolipoprotein E/A&#x003b2; complexes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>] may contribute to apolipoprotein E-isoform-dependent A&#x003b2; accumulation. Differential anti-inflammatory activity might also play a role. Further investigation will be required in order to elucidate the precise mechanism(s) which specify how apolipoprotein E &#x003b5;4 promotes A&#x003b2; accumulation in human brain and cerebral vessels <italic>in vivo</italic>.</p></sec><sec><title>List of abbreviations</title><p>ThT, thioflavine T; A&#x003b2;, amyloid-&#x003b2; peptide; PBS, phosphate-buffered saline; CHO, Chinese hamster ovary cells.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>None declared.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>DS performed all assays, including the ThT assay, which was originated by HL. HL also oversaw the transfer of the assay from his lab to ours. RM prepared standard conditioned media from transfected cells provided by JDS. SG oversaw the project, supported the project as noted below, and wrote the manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This research was supported by USPHS PPG grant AG10491 to S.G. We thank Jan Naslund and Christer Nordstedt (Karolinska Institute, Stockholm, Sweden) for critical comments and helpful discussion.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmechel</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Saunders</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Strittmatter</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Crain</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hulette</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Joo</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelicak-Vance</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldgaber</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Roses</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increased amyloid &#x003b2;-peptide deposition in cerebral cortex as a consequence of apolipoprotein E genotype in late-onset Alzheimer disease</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1993</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>9649</fpage><lpage>9653</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8415756</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holtzman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bales</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Tenkova</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fagan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsadanian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sartorius</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackey</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Olney</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>McKeel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wozniak</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Paul</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Apolipoprotein E isoform-dependent amyloid deposition and neuritic degeneration in a mouse model of Alzheimer's disease</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>2892</fpage><lpage>2897</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10694577</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.050004797</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rebeck</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Vonsattel</surname><given-names>JPG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomez-Isla</surname><given-names/></name><name><surname>Hyman</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Apolipoprotein E &#x003b5;4 and cerebral hemorrhage associated with amyloid angiopathy</article-title><source>Ann Neurol</source><year>1995</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>254</fpage><lpage>259</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7654074</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>St George-Hyslop</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Crapper McLachlan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tuda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogaev</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Karlinsky</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lippa</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Pollen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alzheimer's disease and possible gene interaction</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1994</year><volume>263</volume><fpage>537</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8290965</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Brewer</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Amyloid-associated proteins &#x003b1; <sub>1</sub>-antichymotrypsin and apolipoprotein E promote assembly of Alzheimer &#x003b2;-protein into filaments</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1994</year><volume>372</volume><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7969426</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/372092a0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wisniewski</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Castano</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Golabek</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Frangione</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acceleration of Alzheimer's fibril formation by apolipoprotein E <italic>in vitro</italic></article-title><source>Am J Pathol</source><year>1994</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>1030</fpage><lpage>1035</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7977635</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name><name><surname>Cho</surname><given-names>C-G</given-names></name><name><surname>Weisgraber</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lansbury</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Apolipoprotein E is a kinetic but not a thermodynamic inhibitor of amyloid formation: Implications for the pathogenesis and treatment of Alzheimer's disease</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1995</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>763</fpage><lpage>767</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7846048</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>LaDu</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Falduto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Manelli</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Reardon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Getz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Frail</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isoform-specific binding of apolipoprotein E to &#x003b2; amyloid</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1994</year><volume>269</volume><fpage>23403</fpage><lpage>23406</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8089103</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Greengard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gandy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Alzheimer amyloid-&#x003b2; peptide forms denaturant-resistant complex with type &#x003b5;3 but not type &#x003b5;4 isoform of native apolipoprotein E</article-title><source>Molecular Medicine</source><year>1996</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8726460</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s0089460020175</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rail</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Weisgraber</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahley</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Isolation and characterization of apolipoprotein E</article-title><source>Meth Enzymol</source><year>1986</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>287</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3724506</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>LeVine</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thioflavine T interaction with synthetic Alzheimer's disease &#x003b2;-amyloid peptides: Detection of amyloid aggregation in solution</article-title><source>Protein Science</source><year>1993</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>404</fpage><lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8453378</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mantyh</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghilardi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>DeMaster</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Stimson</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Maggio</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Aluminum, iron and zinc ions promote aggregation of physiological concentration of &#x003b2;-amyloid peptide</article-title><source>J Neurochem</source><year>1993</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>1171</fpage><lpage>1174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8360682</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iwatsubo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Odaka</surname><given-names/></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mizusawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Nukina</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ihara</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Visualization of A&#x003b2; 42(43) and A&#x003b2;40 in senile plaques with end-specific Af3 monoclonals: Evidence that an initially deposited species is A&#x003b2;42(43)</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>1994</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>45</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8043280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0896-6273(94)90458-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naslund</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Thyberg</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tjemberg</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wemstedt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Karlstrom</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bogdanovic</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gandy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lannfelt</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Terenius</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Nordstedt</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of stable complexes involving apolipoprotein E and the amyloid &#x003b2;-peptide in Alzheimer disease brain</article-title><source>Neuron</source><year>1995</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>219</fpage><lpage>228</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7619525</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0896-6273(95)90079-9</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



