<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Neurosci</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Neuroscience</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2202</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15733324</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC554110</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2202-6-14</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2202-6-14</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effects of prostaglandin E<sub>2 </sub>on the electrical properties of thermally classified neurons in the ventromedial preoptic area of the rat hypothalamus</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ranels</surname><given-names>Heather J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>hjrane@hotmail.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>John D</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>jdgri2@wm.edu</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Biology, College of William and Mary. Williamsburg, Virginia 23187, USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>2</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2202/6/14"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>26</day><month>6</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>2</month><year>2005</year></date></history><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 Ranels and Griffin; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p></license><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Physiological and morphological evidence suggests that activation of the ventromedial preoptic area of the hypothalamus (VMPO) is an essential component of an intravenous LPS-dependent fever. In response to the endogenous pyrogen prostaglandin E<sub>2 </sub>(PGE<sub>2</sub>), the majority of temperature insensitive neurons in the VMPO show an increase in firing rate, while warm sensitive neurons are inhibited. We have hypothesized that these PGE<sub>2 </sub>dependent effects on firing rate are due to changes in the inherent electrical properties of VMPO neurons, which are regulated by the activity of specific ionic currents.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>To characterize the electrical properties of VMPO neurons, whole-cell recordings were made in tissue slices from male Sprague-Dawley rats. Our results indicate that PGE<sub>2 </sub>dependent firing rate responses were not the result of changes in resting membrane potential, action potential amplitude and duration, or local synaptic input. However, PGE<sub>2 </sub>reduced the input resistance of all VMPO neurons, while increasing the excitability of temperature insensitive neurons and decreasing the excitability of warm sensitive neurons. In addition, the majority of temperature insensitive neurons responded to PGE<sub>2 </sub>with an increase in the rate of rise of the depolarizing prepotential that precedes each action potential. This response to PGE<sub>2 </sub>was reversed for warm sensitive neurons, in which the prepotential rate of rise decreased.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>We would therefore suggest that PGE<sub>2 </sub>is having an effect on the ionic currents that regulate firing rate by controlling how fast membrane potential rises to threshold during the prepotential phase of the action potential.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Fever, an elevation in body temperature, is thought to play an adaptive role in the immune system's ability to fight infection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. A suggested mechanism for its production and maintenance is a shifting of the thermostatic set-point into the hyperthermic range [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Through the integration of both central and afferent thermal information, this set-point is established by the activity of neurons in the preoptic and anterior regions of the hypothalamus (PO/AH) that can be thermally classified on the basis of their inherent ability to respond to changes in temperature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. The majority of PO/AH neurons are considered temperature insensitive, showing little or no temperature dependent changes in firing rate. Approximately 30% of PO/AH neurons can be classified as warm sensitive, responding to local warming with an increase in firing rate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. While there has been considerable debate as to the criteria that should be used to classify a neuron as warm sensitive, we have used a regression coefficient of at least 0.8 impulses&#x000b7;s<sup>-1</sup>&#x000b7;&#x000b0;C<sup>-1</sup>. This criterion is based on previous studies that indicate a functional difference for neurons which show this degree of inherent thermosensitivity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. In addition to responding to local changes in temperature, some of these warm sensitive neurons are also responsive to changes in skin or spinal temperature, while others show thermally dependent changes in their firing rates that may directly correlate with the activation of specific thermoregulatory responses. Although this integrative ability seems to be restricted to warm sensitive neurons in the PO/AH, temperature insensitive neurons may also play an important role in determining the set-point temperature through their synaptic interactions with thermoregulatory effector neurons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Regardless of thermosensitivity, many PO/AH neurons may respond to adjustments in other homeostatic conditions or the presence of endogenous pyrogens such as prostaglandin E<sub>2 </sub>(PGE<sub>2</sub>), which could shift the thermostatic set-point and alter the activation of thermoregulatory mechanisms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>].</p><p>In response to stimulation of the immune system, changes in the activity of neurons in specific regions of the PO/AH may be responsible for the adjustment of the thermostatic set-point that results in an elevation in body temperature. Physiologic evidence suggests that in response to endotoxins such as lipopolysaccharide (LPS), this shift in set-point is mediated by the activation of afferent neural pathways or the production of systemic pyrogens, which ultimately leads to the local production of PGE<sub>2 </sub>within the hypothalamus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Early microinjection studies clearly established a role for prostaglandins in the production of a fever and later identified the importance of the region surrounding the OVLT in this response [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. More recently, it has been shown that fever in response to intravenous LPS is dependent on the presence of the PGE<sub>2 </sub>producing enzyme cyclooxygenase-2 in the ventromedial preoptic area of the hypothalamus (VMPO) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. In addition, it has now been demonstrated that unlike other regions of the PO/AH, PGE<sub>2 </sub>has a selective effect on the firing rates of VMPO neurons, based on thermosensitivity, with PGE<sub>2 </sub>increasing the firing rates of temperature insensitive neurons and inhibiting the firing rates of warm sensitive neurons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Anatomical studies also support the importance of the VMPO in the production of a fever, demonstrating that either the intravenous injection of LPS or microinjection of PGE<sub>2 </sub>directly into the VMPO will produce a fever that can be correlated with an increase in the cellular activation of neurons within the VMPO [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>].</p><p>Using a functional criterion for determining the thermosensitivity of hypothalamic neurons, a clear difference in the effects of PGE<sub>2 </sub>on the firing rates of VMPO neurons has been demonstrated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Based on current models of set-point temperature regulation, this PGE<sub>2 </sub>dependent increase in the firing rates of temperature insensitive neurons or decrease in the firing rates of warm sensitive neurons could lead to a hyperthermic shift in the thermostatic set-point and production of a fever [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Yet, little is known about the electrical responses by which PGE<sub>2 </sub>regulates the firing rates of VMPO neurons. We have hypothesized that these PGE<sub>2 </sub>dependent changes in firing rate are not the result of a change in the frequency of synaptic input to these neurons, but a selective effect on specific electrical properties of VMPO neurons. To characterize these responses, whole-cell recordings were made from VMPO neurons in tissue slices from male Sprague-Dawley rats, in response to changes in temperature and PGE<sub>2</sub>.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>For forty two VMPO neurons, temperature sensitivity and PGE<sub>2 </sub>dependent changes in firing rate, electrical activity, and the frequency of synaptic input were determined. The majority of these neurons were classified as temperature insensitive (n = 32). The remaining ten neurons were classified as warm sensitive. With respect to thermosensitivity or responses to PGE<sub>2</sub>, there was no specific pattern to the distribution of these neurons throughout the VMPO (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>).</p><p>Using the cellularly invasive procedure of whole cell recording, the PGE<sub>2 </sub>dependent changes in firing rate that were recorded from VMPO neurons were similar to those reported in an earlier extracellular single-unit recording study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. In response to PGE<sub>2</sub>, fourteen temperature insensitive neurons showed significant increases in firing rate. Thirteen of these neurons had thermosensitivities &#x02264; 0.4 impulses&#x000b7;s&#x000b7;&#x000b0;C<sup>-1</sup>. The firing rates of temperature insensitive neurons, having thermosensitivities &#x02264; 0.4 impulses&#x000b7;s<sup>-1.</sup>&#x000b0;C<sup>-1</sup>, significantly increased in response to PGE<sub>2</sub>, from 5.75 &#x000b1; 1.31 impulses&#x000b7;s<sup>-1 </sup>to 6.5 &#x000b1; 1.31 impulses&#x000b7;s<sup>-1 </sup>(paired T test, P = 0.04; firing rates at least 10 minutes into the following washout period = 6.37 &#x000b1; 1.32 impulses&#x000b7;s<sup>-1</sup>). Of the thirteen temperature insensitive neurons with thermosensitivities of 0.41 &#x02013; 0.79 impulses&#x000b7;s<sup>-1.</sup>&#x000b0;C<sup>-1</sup>, the majority (n = 10) showed little or no change in firing rate in response to PGE<sub>2</sub>. The firing rates of these neurons did not significantly change from a baseline of 8.4 &#x000b1;1.21 impulses&#x000b7;s<sup>-1 </sup>(PGE<sub>2 </sub>= 8.55 &#x000b1; 1.24 impulses&#x000b7;s<sup>-1 </sup>(paired T test, P = 0.38); washout = 8.34 &#x000b1; 1.24 impulses&#x000b7;s<sup>-1</sup>). In contrast to the responses of temperature insensitive neurons, the majority (n = 8) of VMPO warm sensitive neurons showed a significant decrease in firing rate during perfusion with PGE<sub>2</sub>. The firing rates of warm sensitive neurons significantly decreased from 15.28 &#x000b1; 4.93 impulses&#x000b7;s<sup>-1 </sup>to 12.35 &#x000b1; 4.85 impulses&#x000b7;s<sup>-1 </sup>in response to PGE<sub>2 </sub>(paired T test, P = 0.003; firing rates at least 10 minutes into the following washout period = 12.87 &#x000b1; 4.12 impulses&#x000b7;s<sup>-1</sup>).</p><sec><title>Electrical properties</title><p>All VMPO neurons recorded in this study had resting membrane potentials of -45.0 &#x000b1; 1.1 mV (n = 42). There was no significant difference between the resting membrane potentials of temperature insensitive neurons (-45.6 &#x000b1; 1.2 mV; n = 32) and warm sensitive neurons (-43.1 &#x000b1; 2.4 mV; n = 10). In addition, resting membrane potential did not change in response to PGE<sub>2 </sub>and was not responsible for PGE<sub>2 </sub>dependent changes in firing rate.</p><p>The top panels of Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> show the action potential activity of a temperature insensitive neuron during baseline conditions, perfusion with PGE<sub>2</sub>, and the washout period. While the resting membrane potential did not change from a baseline mean of -43.94 mV, firing rate increased 43.4% in response to PGE<sub>2</sub>, from a mean of 5.11 impulses&#x000b7;s<sup>-1 </sup>to 7.33 impulses&#x000b7;s<sup>-1</sup>. The onset of this response occurred several minutes after perfusion with PGE<sub>2 </sub>had begun and lasted approximately 15 minutes beyond the point when perfusion with PGE<sub>2 </sub>ended. This was typical of all temperature insensitive neurons which had a significant change in firing rate in response to PGE<sub>2</sub>. These neurons showed response latencies of 3.5 &#x000b1; 0.69 minutes and durations that ranged from 7 to 40 minutes before firing rate returned towards the baseline level.</p><p>The lower panels of Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> show the action potential activity of a warm sensitive neuron during baseline conditions, perfusion with PGE<sub>2</sub>, and the washout period. While the resting membrane potential did not change from a baseline mean of -51.62 mV, the firing rate of this neuron decreased in response to PGE<sub>2</sub>, from a mean of 10.07 impulses&#x000b7;s<sup>-1 </sup>to 8.40 impulses&#x000b7;s<sup>-1</sup>. The onset of this response occurred several minutes after perfusion with PGE<sub>2 </sub>had begun and lasted approximately 25 minutes beyond the point when perfusion with PGE<sub>2 </sub>was stopped. Similar changes were recorded for the other warm sensitive neurons that were inhibited by PGE<sub>2</sub>, which showed response latencies of 3.90 &#x000b1; 0.95 minutes and durations that ranged from 10 to 25 minutes.</p><p>Throughout the entire length of a recording (46.7 &#x000b1; 1.8 minutes), the amplitude and duration of action potentials recorded from VMPO neurons slowly decreased by an average of 4.6 mV and 0.16 milliseconds, respectively (n = 42). It is presumed that this was due to minor changes in ionic gradients, resulting from the technique of whole-cell recording. Based on the PGE<sub>2 </sub>dependent changes in firing rate reported in this study and previous extracellular recordings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>], these small changes in action potential amplitude and duration did not affect the ability of VMPO neurons to respond to PGE<sub>2</sub>. There were also no significant changes in the amplitudes or durations of action potentials recorded from temperature insensitive and warm sensitive neurons in response to PGE<sub>2</sub>.</p><p>The input resistance of VMPO neurons recorded in this study significantly decreased in response to PGE<sub>2 </sub>from 367.1 &#x000b1; 24.5 M&#x003a9;. to 339.7 &#x000b1; 23.7 M&#x003a9; (n = 42; paired T test, P = 0.0001). This PGE<sub>2 </sub>dependent decrease in resistance was independent of thermosensitivity. Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> shows current-voltage plots from a temperature insensitive neuron (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>) and a warm sensitive neuron (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>). For both of these neurons, input resistance decreased similarly in response to PGE<sub>2</sub>, with a reversal potential at or near the resting membrane potential.</p><p>During the application of a depolarizing current, VMPO neurons did not show PGE<sub>2 </sub>dependent changes in the frequency of action potentials (frequency response). However, the majority of VMPO neurons did show PGE<sub>2 </sub>dependent changes in another characteristic of neuronal excitability, the first spike latency. Temperature insensitive neurons with thermosensitivities &#x02264; 0.4 impulses&#x000b7;s<sup>-1.</sup>&#x000b0;C<sup>-1</sup>showed a significant PGE<sub>2 </sub>dependent decrease in the first spike latency, from 7.4 &#x000b1; 1.2 ms during baseline conditions to 5.2 &#x000b1; 0.6 ms in response to PGE<sub>2 </sub>(n = 18; paired T test, P = 0.008; Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). The first spike latency for these temperature insensitive neurons returned to baseline levels during the washout period (7.6 &#x000b1; 1.4 ms). In contrast, warm sensitive neurons showed a significant increase in this latency response during perfusion with PGE<sub>2</sub>(n = 7), similar to the response of the warm sensitive neuron in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>. (baseline = 4.9 &#x000b1; 0.5 ms; PGE<sub>2 </sub>= 7.9 &#x000b1; 1.1 ms (paired T test, P = 0.046); washout = 4.2 &#x000b1; 0.5 ms). Temperature insensitive neurons with thermal coefficients of 0.41 to 0.79 impulses&#x000b7;s<sup>-1.</sup>&#x000b0;C<sup>-1 </sup>showed little change in this measurement of neuronal excitability (n = 8), in response to PGE<sub>2 </sub>(baseline = 7.0 &#x000b1; 1.3 ms; PGE<sub>2 </sub>= 6.8 &#x000b1; 1.1 ms (paired T test, P = 0.69); washout = 6.8 &#x000b1; 1.1 ms).</p><p>In Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>, the averaged pre- and post-spike activity of a temperature insensitive neuron (A) and a warm sensitive neuron (B) are shown during baseline conditions and in response to PGE<sub>2</sub>. In a similar manner to the neuron shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref>, the majority of temperature insensitive neurons with thermal coefficients &#x02264; 0.4 impulses&#x000b7;s<sup>-1.</sup>&#x000b0;C<sup>-1 </sup>showed a significant increase in the rate of rise of the depolarizing prepotential in response to PGE<sub>2 </sub>(n = 12; baseline = 0.46 &#x000b1; 0.04 mV&#x000b7;ms<sup>-1</sup>, PGE<sub>2 </sub>= 0.55 &#x000b1; 0.05 mV&#x000b7;ms<sup>-1</sup>; paired T test, P = 0.01). In contrast, the majority of warm sensitive neurons showed a significant decrease in the rate of rise of the depolarizing prepotential in response to PGE<sub>2</sub>, similar to the response of the neuron in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref> (n = 8; baseline= 0.61 &#x000b1; 0.08 mV&#x000b7;ms<sup>-1</sup>, PGE<sub>2 </sub>= 0.50 &#x000b1; 0.08 mV&#x000b7;ms<sup>-1</sup>; paired T test, P = 0.012). Although small changes in the voltage deflections that occurred at the end of an action potential showed some degree of change in response to PGE<sub>2</sub>, these changes were inconsistent in both temperature insensitive or warm sensitive neurons. Temperature insensitive neurons with thermosensitivities of 0.41 &#x02013; 0.79 impulses&#x000b7;s<sup>-1.</sup>&#x000b0;C<sup>-1 </sup>did not show a significant change in the rate of rise of the depolarizing prepotential in response to PGE<sub>2</sub>.</p></sec><sec><title>Synaptic input</title><p>The frequency of post synaptic potentials (PSPs) recorded from VMPO neurons in the localized environment of coronal tissue slices was predominately inhibitory and insensitive to changes in temperature (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). In 92% of the recordings, temperature had little or no effect on the frequencies of either inhibitory post synaptic potentials (IPSPs; m = 0.25 &#x000b1; 0.06 PSPs&#x000b7;s<sup>-1.</sup>&#x000b0;C<sup>-1</sup>) or excitatory post synaptic potentials (EPSPs; m = 0.23 &#x000b1; 0.06 PSPs&#x000b7;s<sup>-1.</sup>&#x000b0;C<sup>-1</sup>). In response to PGE<sub>2</sub>, the frequency of synaptic input recorded from VMPO neurons did not change (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>PGE<sub>2 </sub>dependent changes in the firing rates of VMPO neurons</title><p>As current models for temperature regulation suggest, the integrated responses of hypothalamic warm sensitive neurons and temperature insensitive neurons play an important role achieving and maintaining a discrete set-point for temperature control [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. While their importance in thermoregulatory pathways has yet to be determined, <italic>in vitro </italic>recordings from tissue slices have also identified neurons in the PO/AH that lack spontaneously generated activity (silent neurons), are predominantly driven to produce action potentials by synaptic input (EPSP-driven neurons), or produce action potentials in a bursting pattern [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. However, only prepotential driven warm sensitive and temperature insensitive neurons were identified in the VMPO.</p><p>In the generation of a fever, current thermoregulatory models of neural networking suggest that either an increase in the activity of temperature insensitive neurons or the inhibition of warm sensitive neurons would shift the set-point to a more hyperthermic temperature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Through competing synaptic inputs, either of these responses would alter the temperature at which thermoeffector neurons begin to activate thermoregulatory responses. However, previous studies have not been able to show a correlation between the thermosensitivity of hypothalamic neurons and firing rate responses to PGE<sub>2 </sub>or other endogenous pyrogens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. This may be the result of the various criteria that were used to define thermosensitivity in many of these studies, as well as recordings from more general areas of the PO/AH. In a recent study of the extracellular single-unit activity of neurons in the VMPO, a clear thermal distinction in firing rate responses to PGE<sub>2 </sub>was reported, with temperature insensitive neurons excited by PGE<sub>2 </sub>and warm sensitive neurons inhibited [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. In this previous study, a functionally significant criterion was used to define warm sensitivity (m &#x02265; 0.8 impulses&#x000b7;s<sup>-1.</sup>&#x000b0;C<sup>-1</sup>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. As this criterion provides a method for identifying integrative warm sensitive neurons in the tissue slice preparation, it allows the experimental findings to have a functional significance in modeling thermoregulation <italic>in vivo</italic>. In the present study, which uses whole-cell recording techniques to record the intracellular properties of VMPO neurons and the same functional criterion for defining warm sensitivity, similar firing rate responses were recorded. As suggested above, either an increase in the firing rates of temperature insensitive neurons or a decrease in the firing rates of warm sensitive neurons could lead to a hyperthermic shift in the thermostatic set-point and a fever.</p><p>It is also important to note that while the majority of PGE<sub>2 </sub>responsive neurons showed a significant recovery in firing rate during the washout period, some did not. This lack of complete recovery may have resulted from responses to PGE<sub>2 </sub>that were considerably long in duration, lasting up to 40 minutes, and minor changes in ionic gradients that can occur over time during whole-cell recordings. As mentioned in the methods, all recordings were closely monitored for any changes that would make them unacceptable.</p></sec><sec><title>Cellular properties of VMPO neurons and responses to PGE<sub>2</sub></title><p>In addition to the direct effects of PGE<sub>2 </sub>on the electrical properties of VMPO neurons, the frequency of localized synaptic input was characterized. In the present study, we were specifically interested in monitoring firing rate responses to PGE<sub>2 </sub>and characterizing the resulting voltage potential changes (i.e., action potentials and membrane potentials). In order to ensure that we did not interrupt the firing rate responses, we did not perform any voltage clamp measurements and did all recordings in current clamp, with current = 0 pA. This prevented any detailed characterization of synaptic potentials, other than frequency. As has been shown in other regions of the PO/AH [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>], the majority of this synaptic input to VMPO neurons was inhibitory and predominantly insensitive to temperature. In response to PGE<sub>2</sub>, the frequency of PSPs recorded from most VMPO neurons either did not change or showed an increase. However, PGE<sub>2 </sub>dependent increases in the frequency of PSPs were not recorded from neurons that showed PGE<sub>2 </sub>dependent changes in firing rate. This may have resulted from a smaller degree of synaptic influence on firing rate, due to a change in the input resistance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. Additionally, the lack of local synaptic input from warm sensitive neurons would suggest that the axonal projections of these neurons may not terminate within the VMPO, but form efferent projections to other hypothalamic nuclei such as the paraventricular nucleus.</p><p>As shown in Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>, the input resistance recorded from most of the VMPO neurons decreased in response to PGE<sub>2</sub>, regardless of temperature sensitivity or PGE<sub>2 </sub>dependent changes in firing rate. Since this response had little or no influence on firing rate, we would suggest that decreases in resistance resulted from changes in the activity of multiple currents, which continued to maintain equilibrium at or near the resting membrane potential. While we have also suggested that PGE<sub>2 </sub>may cause cAMP concentrations to either increase or decrease within these neurons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>], the net effect on hyperpolarizing K<sup>+ </sup>currents and depolarizing Na<sup>+ </sup>or Ca<sup>++ </sup>currents may still lead to an increase in conductance that does not result in a change in resting membrane potential. Therefore, although these changes in the input resistance may be an important response to PGE<sub>2</sub>, they are not directly responsible for PGE<sub>2 </sub>dependent changes in firing rate.</p><p>In response to a depolarizing current pulse, PGE<sub>2 </sub>dependent changes in the excitability of VMPO neurons were recorded. Using two primary measurements of excitability, the frequency response and first spike latency (see: Results &#x00026; Methods), our recordings indicate that PGE<sub>2 </sub>selectively increased the excitability of temperature insensitive neurons, while decreasing the excitability of warm sensitive neurons. Although there was no significant PGE<sub>2 </sub>dependent changes in the frequency responses of VMPO neurons, temperature insensitive neurons showed a significant decrease in first spike latency in response to PGE<sub>2 </sub>(Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>), while warm sensitive neurons showed a significant increase (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). This would suggest that PGE<sub>2 </sub>is having a direct effect of the activity of transient voltage dependent currents, which are responsible for regulating the excitability and rhythmic firing rates of these neurons. While these current pulses were not matched so that they would result in the same level of depolarization, making it difficult to discern which voltage-gated conductances may be responding to PGE<sub>2</sub>, this data does provide support for our finding of PGE<sub>2 </sub>dependent changes in the prepotential [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>].</p><p>Several transient voltage dependent currents have been identified in hypothalamic neurons which regulate excitability and rhythmic firing rate activity. These include a slow component sodium current and a calcium dependent potassium current (I<sub>K, Ca</sub>) in suprachiasmatic neurons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>], a low voltage activated calcium current and a I<sub>K, Ca </sub>current in posterior hypothalamic neurons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>], a non-inactivating potassium current in neurhypophyseal nerve terminals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>], and a I<sub>A </sub>current in PO/AH neurons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. Although any or all of these currents may be present in VMPO neurons, only the I<sub>A </sub>has been implicated in temperature dependent changes in firing rate, through a mechanism in which the thermally dependent inactivation rate of this current influences the rate of rise of the prepotential that precedes each action potential [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. In a similar manner, our data suggests that PGE<sub>2 </sub>has a direct effect on the firing rates of VMPO neurons through changes in the prepotential, increasing the rate of rise in temperature insensitive neurons, while decreasing the rate of rise of the prepotential in warm sensitive neurons (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). Therefore, PGE<sub>2 </sub>dependent changes in the firing rates of VMPO neurons may also depend on an ability to influence the inactivation rate of the I<sub>A </sub>type current.</p><p>Within the VMPO, overlapping expression of EP<sub>3 </sub>and EP<sub>4 </sub>receptors may provide PGE<sub>2 </sub>with the ability to selectively affect the activity of neurons in this region [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. Activation of either receptor subtype is known to influence cellular activity through the regulation of intracellular cAMP concentrations, with EP<sub>4 </sub>activation leading to an increase in cAMP and EP<sub>3 </sub>activation leading to a decrease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. Support for this mechanism is provided by evidence showing that cAMP plays a role in thermoregulation and more specifically, in the generation of a fever [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. With respect to excitability and rhythmic firing rate activity, several studies have demonstrated that cAMP modulates PGE<sub>2 </sub>dependent changes the activity of certain potassium currents, including the I<sub>A </sub>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. Therefore, selective activation of either EP<sub>3 </sub>or EP<sub>4 </sub>receptors may be responsible for the changes in firing rate and electrical activity we have recorded from VMPO neurons.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>In response to intravenous LPS, the local production of PGE<sub>2 </sub>within the PO/AH region results in a thermally dependent change in the firing rates of VMPO neurons. Through a direct effect on the rate of rise of the depolarizing prepotential, which is also a determinant of thermosensitivity, PGE<sub>2 </sub>increases the firing rates of temperature insensitive neurons, while decreasing the firing rates of warm sensitive neurons in the VMPO. While the results of this study provide a clear focus for future studies into the conductance mechanisms of these responses, it also supports a functional and important role for the VMPO region and both groups of thermally classified neurons in the production of this type of fever.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>Anterior hypothalamic tissue slices containing the VMPO were prepared from male Sprague-Dawley rats (100 &#x02013; 150 grams), which were housed under standard conditions and given food and water <italic>ad lib</italic>. Prior to each recording session, an animal was anesthetized (isoflurane) and sacrificed by quick decapitation, according to procedures approved by the National Science Foundation and the Animal Care and Use Committee of the College of William and Mary. Following removal of the brain, a tissue block of the hypothalamus was cut using a vibratome into 400 &#x003bc;m thick coronal slices. Two or three slices containing the VMPO were then placed in a recording chamber and allowed to equilibrate for 1&#x02013;2 hours. Tissue slices were continually perfused with pyrogen free artificial cerebral spinal fluid (aCSF), which consisted of (in mM), 124 NaCl, 26 NaHCO<sub>3</sub>, 10 glucose, 5 KCl, 2.4 CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 1.3 MgSO<sub>4</sub>, and 1.24 KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>. This nutrient medium was oxygenated (95% O<sub>2 </sub>&#x02013; 5% CO<sub>2</sub>), warmed to a stable temperature of ~36&#x000b0;C by a thermoelectric assembly, and allowed to gravity flow into the chamber at 1 &#x02013; 1.5 ml&#x000b7; min<sup>-1 </sup>(chamber volume = 1.2 ml) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. A small thermocouple, positioned in the recording chamber just below the tissue slices, was used to continuously monitor tissue temperature.</p><p>Tight-seal whole-cell recordings were made using glass microelectrodes with tip inner diameters of ~2 &#x003bc;m (3&#x02013;5 M&#x003a9;), filled with a solution that consisted of (in mM) 130 K-gluconate, 10 EGTA, 2 ATP, 1 MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 CaCl, having a pH of 7.2 and an osmolarity of approximately 295 mOsmols/liter. As described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>], a liquid junction potential of 12.0 mV was subtracted from all recorded potentials. All recordings were made using an integrated patch-clamp amplifier (Axopatch 200B, Axon Instruments) and along with temperature, were stored on digital tape for later analysis. Firing rate was continuously recorded as a voltage measurement from a rate/interval monitor and was determined by action potential triggered input from a window discriminator (FHC Inc.). Specific stimulation protocols to measure input resistance and excitability were generated by a computer that was interfaced with the amplifier (pClamp software, Axon Instruments). Acceptable recordings consisted of action potential amplitudes through 0 mV and stable recordings of at least 20 minutes.</p><p>Using a stereomicroscope, the recording electrode was positioned in the VMPO, which encompasses 700 &#x003bc;m of the hypothalamus just rostral to the suprachiasmatic nucleus. It extends laterally 900 &#x003bc;m from the third ventricle and dorsally 500 &#x003bc;m from the ventral brain surface [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. Once a tight seal (&#x0003e; 2 G&#x003a9;) was achieved between the electrode and the surface of a neuron, the cell membrane was ruptured by suction, establishing an intracellular recording. When the activity of a neuron was stable for several minutes, temperature in the recording chamber was varied 2&#x02013;3&#x000b0;C above and below 36&#x000b0;C, by changing the input voltage to the thermoelectric assembly. Neuronal thermosensitivity (impulses&#x000b7; s<sup>-1</sup>&#x000b7;&#x000b0;C<sup>-1</sup>) was characterized by plotting firing rate as a function of temperature to determine the regression coefficient (m) of this plot. As in previous studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>], warm sensitivity was defined as a regression coefficient of at least 0.8 impulses&#x000b7; s<sup>-1</sup>&#x000b7;&#x000b0;C<sup>-1</sup>. All other neurons in this study were defined as temperature insensitive.</p><p>After thermosensitivity had been characterized, each neuron was tested for its response to PGE<sub>2</sub>. At a stable temperature (~36&#x000b0;C), the perfusion medium was switched to one containing PGE<sub>2 </sub>(200 nM or 1 &#x003bc;M, Sigma Chemical Co.). The duration of exposure to PGE<sub>2 </sub>ranged from 5 &#x02013; 15 minutes, with durations of less than 10 minutes occurring only when there was a clear indication of a response. Exposure to PGE<sub>2 </sub>was followed by perfusion with aCSF for a washout period of at least 10 minutes.</p><p>To determine if PGE<sub>2 </sub>had a significant effect on firing rate, one-minute segments of stable activity were digitized for comparison (60 Hz; pClamp Software, Axon Instruments). These segments were collected during baseline conditions (just prior to perfusion with PGE<sub>2</sub>) at the end of perfusion with PGE<sub>2</sub>, and at the end of a 10-minute washout period (or when firing rate returned to baseline levels). For each segment, a mean and standard error were calculated (Sigmaplot software, SPSS Inc.). A significant response to PGE<sub>2 </sub>was determined by comparison to the baseline level using a standard T-test (P &#x02264; 0.05).</p><p>Changes in resting membrane potential and the action potential waveform in response to PGE<sub>2 </sub>were also characterized. As in a previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>], the resting membrane potential was continuously recorded. After rapid changes in membrane potential (including action potentials) were filtered out (half amplitude response setting at 0.5 Hz), one minute segments of voltage activity were digitized (60 Hz) during baseline conditions, perfusion with PGE<sub>2</sub>, and the washout period. To characterize changes in the action potential, an averaged action potential from ten inherently activated action potentials was produced for each of the experimental conditions (sampling rate = 66.7 kHz). Measurements were made of action potential amplitude (resting membrane potential to peak) and duration (at one half peak). Measurements were also made of the rate of rise of the depolarizing prepotential that precedes each action potential [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. For resting membrane potential and action potential measurements, significant responses to PGE<sub>2 </sub>were determined by comparison to baseline using a standard T-test (P &#x02264; 0.05).</p><p>Throughout each recording, input resistance and excitability were measured every 5 &#x02013; 10 minutes to determine changes in response to PGE<sub>2 </sub>and to insure that recordings remained stable. Large changes that did not return towards baseline levels were a characteristic of a deteriorating recording and marked the end of legitimate data. Input resistance was determined by the slope of a current-voltage plot obtained from a computer generated protocol in which a series of ten current pulses (-10 to -100 pA) were administered [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. In addition, two primary characteristics of neuronal excitability were measured in response to a depolarizing current [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]. The frequency response was determined by the number of action potentials produced during the depolarizing current. The first spike latency was also measured and was defined as the duration from the start of the depolarizing current to the peak of the first action potential. All significant responses to PGE<sub>2 </sub>were again determined by comparison to baseline using a standard T-test (P &#x02264; 0.05).</p><p>The frequencies of synaptic potentials (EPSPs and IPSPs) recorded from each VMPO neuron were determined during baseline conditions, perfusion with PGE<sub>2</sub>, and the washout period. As in previous whole-cell recordings, individual potentials were identified as rapid changes in membrane potential of at least 1 mV greater than background noise [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. For each experimental condition, blind counts of PSPs were made over a 20 second duration to produce frequency averages (PSPs&#x000b7;s<sup>-1</sup>). As with the other measurements, all significant responses to PGE<sub>2 </sub>were determined by comparison to baseline using a standard T-test (P &#x02264; 0.05). In addition, the thermosensitivities of EPSPs and IPSPs were characterized by calculating frequency averages (using the same methods as detailed above) at different temperatures (&#x02265; 3&#x000b0;C range) and plotting the results as a function of temperature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>].</p><p>Once a recording had been completed, a stereomicroscope was used to visually confirm the location of the recording electrode. The ventral edge of the third ventricle was used as a reference to determine the lateral-medial and dorsal-ventral coordinates. The coronal position was also specified by the depth of the electrode from the surface of the tissue slice. In addition, the side of the brain from which the recording was made was identified by preparing the tissue slices with more lateral tissue on the left. Tissue slices were then removed from the recording chamber, fixed in a 10% formalin solution, and sectioned again to a thickness of 50 &#x003bc;m. Sections were then stained with giemsa to identify specific hypothalamic areas so that the location of each recording within VMPO could be reconfirmed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>] [38].</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>HJR, carried out the majority of cellular recordings and data analysis. JDG conceived of the study and participated in its design, coordination and completion. Both authors contributed equally to the drafting of this manuscript.</p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We want to thank Erin Waller, Sarah Norcross and Elizabeth Wallis for their assistance in the histological processing of neural tissue. This work was supported by NSF grant IBN-9983624, and in part by a Howard Hughes Medical Institute grant through the Undergraduate Biological Sciences Program to the College of William and Mary.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saper</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Breder</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The neurological basis of fever</article-title><source>N Eng J Med</source><year>1994</year><volume>330</volume><fpage>1880</fpage><lpage>1886</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM199406303302609</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boulant</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hypothalamic neurons: Mechanism of sensitivity to temperature</article-title><source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source><year>1998</year><volume>856</volume><fpage>108</fpage><lpage>115</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9917871</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boulant</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><source>Thermoregulation In Fever: Basic Mechanisms and Management</source><year>1991</year><publisher-name>New York: Raven Press</publisher-name><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>22</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boulant</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardy</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effect of spinal and skin temperatures on the firing rate activity and thermosensitivity of preoptic neurons</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>1974</year><volume>240</volume><fpage>639</fpage><lpage>660</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4416218</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blatties</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sehic</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pyrogen sensing and signaling: Old views and new concepts</article-title><source>Clinical Infectious Disease</source><year>2000</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>168</fpage><lpage>177</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/317522</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elmquist</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Scammell</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Saper</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms of CNS response to systemic immune challenge; the febrile response</article-title><source>Trends in Neuroscience</source><year>1997</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>565</fpage><lpage>570</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0166-2236(97)01138-7</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blatteis</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bealer</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Llanos-Q</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mashburn</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Suppression of fever after lesions of the anteroventral third ventricle in guinea pigs</article-title><source>Brain Res Bull</source><year>1983</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>519</fpage><lpage>526</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6365250</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0361-9230(83)90124-7</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feldberg</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Saxena</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Further studies on prostaglandin E<sub>1 </sub>fever in cats</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>1971</year><volume>219</volume><fpage>739</fpage><lpage>745</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5157600</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stitt</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prostaglandin E<sub>1 </sub>fever in rabbits</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>1973</year><volume>232</volume><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>179</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4733481</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stitt</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential sensitivity in the sites of fever production by prostaglandin E<sub>1 </sub>within the hypothalamus of the rat</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>1991</year><volume>432</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1886074</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scammell</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Elmquist</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Saper</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Microinjection of a cyclooxygenase inhibitor into the anteroventral preoptic region attenuates LPS fever</article-title><source>Am J Physiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>274</volume><fpage>R783</fpage><lpage>789</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9530246</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ranels</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of prostaglandin E<sub>2 </sub>on the firing rate activity of thermosensitive and temperature insensitive neurons in the ventromedial preoptic area of the rat hypothalamus</article-title><source>Brain Res</source><year>2003</year><volume>964</volume><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12573511</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-8993(02)04063-5</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elmquist</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Scammell</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Saper</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution of Fos-like immunoreactivity in the rat brain following intravenous lippopolysaccharide administration</article-title><source>J Comp Neurology</source><year>1996</year><volume>371</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>19</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cne.903710102</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scammell</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Elmquist</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Saper</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ventromedial preoptic prostaglandin E<sub>2 </sub>activates fever-producing autonomic pathways</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>1996</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>6246</fpage><lpage>6254</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8815905</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Saper</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Boulant</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synaptic and morphological characteristics of temperature sensitive and insensitive rat hypothalamic neurons</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>537</volume><fpage>521</fpage><lpage>535</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11731583</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-7793.2001.00521.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Shibata</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakashima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yakashima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Asami</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Asami</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Koga</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of interleukin-1 and arachiodonate on the preoptic and anterior hypothalamic neurons</article-title><source>Brain Res Bull</source><year>1988</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>75</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3124931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0361-9230(88)90010-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakashima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thermal and PGE<sub>2 </sub>sensitivity of the organum vasculosum lamina terminalis region and preoptic area in rat brain slices</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>1992</year><volume>454</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1474492</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morimoto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Murakami</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of prostaglandin E<sub>2 </sub>on thermoresponsive neurons in the preoptic and ventromedial hypothalamic regions of rats</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>1988</year><volume>405</volume><fpage>713</fpage><lpage>725</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3255803</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakashima</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuriyama</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Matsuda</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of interferon-&#x003b1; on the activity of preoptic thermosensitive neurons in tissue slices</article-title><source>Brain Res</source><year>1988</year><volume>454</volume><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>367</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2841998</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0006-8993(88)90838-4</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burgoon</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Boulant</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Temperature sensitive properties of rat suprachiasmatic nucleus neurons</article-title><source>Am J Physiol Regul Integr Comp Physiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>281</volume><fpage>R706</fpage><lpage>715</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11506983</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The effects of cAMP dependent protein kinase activation on the firing rates of thermosensitive and temperature insensitive neurons in the ventromedial preoptic area of the rat hypothalamus [Abstract]</article-title><source>FASEB J</source><year>2003</year><fpage>A28</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaple</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Chow</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Boulant</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cellular mechanisms for neuronal thermosensitivity in the rat hypothalamus</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>1996</year><volume>492</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>242</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8730598</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pennartz</surname><given-names>CMA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bos</surname><given-names>NPA</given-names></name><name><surname>De Jeu</surname><given-names>MTG</given-names></name><name><surname>Geurtsen</surname><given-names>AMS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirmiran</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sluiter</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Buijs</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Membrane properties and morphology of vasopressin neurons in slices of rat suprachiasmatic nucleus</article-title><source>J Neurophysiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>2710</fpage><lpage>2717</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9819275</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Y-P</given-names></name><name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Waldrop</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biophysical characterization of rat caudal hypothalamic neurons; calcium channel contribution to excitability</article-title><source>J Neurophysiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>2896</fpage><lpage>2903</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11110819</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Karpinski</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Benishin</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prostaglandin E<sub>2 </sub>modulates a non-inactivation potassium current in rat neurohypophyseal nerve terminals</article-title><source>Neurochem Intern</source><year>1999</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>355</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0197-0186(99)00073-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Oka</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Scammell</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Nantel</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Elmquist</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Saper</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationship of EP<sub>1&#x02013;4 </sub>prostaglandin receptors with rat hypothalamic cell groups involved in lippolysaccharide fever response fever response</article-title><source>J Comp Neurology</source><year>2000</year><volume>428</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1096-9861(20001204)428:1&#x0003c;20::AID-CNE3&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-X</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Arias</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sawchenko</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ericsson-Dahlstrand</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution of the EP<sub>3 </sub>prostaglandin E<sub>2 </sub>receptor subtypes in the rat brain: Relationship to sites of Interleukin-1 induced cellular responsiveness</article-title><source>J Comp Neurology</source><year>2000</year><volume>428</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>20</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1096-9861(20001204)428:1&#x0003c;5::AID-CNE2&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-M</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oka</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Aou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hori</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intracerebroventricular injection of prostaglandin E<sub>2 </sub>induces thermal hyperalgesia in rats: the possible involvement of EP<sub>3 </sub>receptors</article-title><source>Brain Res</source><year>1994</year><volume>663</volume><fpage>287</fpage><lpage>292</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7874513</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0006-8993(94)91275-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steiner</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Branco</surname><given-names>LGS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fever and anapyrexia in systemic inflammation: intracellular signaling by cyclic nucleotides</article-title><source>Frontiers in Bioscience</source><year>2003</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>s1398</fpage><lpage>1408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12957844</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasko</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicol</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The cAMP transduction cascade mediates the PGE<sub>2 </sub>induced inhibition of potassium currents in rat sensory neurons</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>1999</year><volume>516</volume><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10066931</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-7793.1999.163aa.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lopshire</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicol</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The cAMP transduction cascade mediates the PGE<sub>2 </sub>enhancement of the capsaicin-elicited current in rat sensory neurons: whole cell and single unit studies</article-title><source>J Neurosci</source><year>1998</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>6081</fpage><lpage>6092</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9698303</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelso</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>DO</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Boulant</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A slice chamber for intracellular and extracellular recording during continuous perfusion</article-title><source>Brain Res Bull</source><year>1983</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>853</fpage><lpage>857</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6311362</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0361-9230(83)90219-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Boulant</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Temperature effects on membrane potential and input resistance in rat hypothalamic neurones</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>1995</year><volume>488</volume><fpage>407</fpage><lpage>418</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8568679</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paxinos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><source>The Rat Brain In Stereotaxic Coordinates</source><year>1998</year><publisher-name>New York: Academic Press</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelso</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Perlmutter</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name><name><surname>Boulant</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Thermosensitive single-unit activity in vitro hypothalamic neurons</article-title><source>Am J Physiol</source><year>1982</year><volume>242</volume><fpage>R77</fpage><lpage>84</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7058933</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Russier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Carlier</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ankri</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Fronzaroli</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Debanne</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A-, T-, and H-type currents shape intrinsic firing of developing rat abducens motoneurons</article-title><source>J Physiol</source><year>2003</year><volume>549</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><comment>DOI: 10.1113/jphysiol.2002.037069</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12651919</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.2002.037069</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="display-objects"><title>Figures and Tables</title><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Intracellular whole-cell recordings from VMPO Neurons. </bold>The positions of all recorded neurons in this study are indicated on the above coronal diagrams (temperature insensitive = &#x025cf;, warm sensitive = &#x025b2; modified from Figures 18&#x02013;20, Paxinos &#x00026; Watson, 1998). <bold>A </bold>corresponds to the anterior regions of VMPO, approximately 400 &#x003bc;m rostral to the areas shown in <bold>B</bold>, which correspond to the midpoint of the VMPO. <bold>C </bold>corresponds to the posterior regions of VMPO, approximately 400 &#x003bc;m caudal to the areas shown in <bold>B</bold>. 3 V, third ventricle; AVPe, anteroventral periventricular nucleus; MPA, medial preoptic area; Pe, periventricular hypothalamic nucleus; ox, optic chiasm; VMPO, ventromedial preoptic nucleus.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2202-6-14-1"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>The effects of temperature and PGE<sub>2 </sub>on the activity of a VMPO temperature insensitive neuron and a VMPO warm sensitive neuron. </bold>The top panels show one second records of the action potential activity of a VMPO temperature insensitive neuron during all three experimental conditions (resting membrane potential = -43.94 mV). The firing rate significantly increased from a baseline of 5.11 &#x000b1; 0.12 impulses&#x000b7;s<sup>-1 </sup>to 7.33 &#x000b1; 0.13 impulses&#x000b7;s<sup>-1 </sup>during perfusion with 1 &#x003bc;M PGE<sub>2 </sub>(washout = 4.90 &#x000b1; 0.14 impulses&#x000b7;s<sup>-1</sup>). The lower panels show one second records of the action potential activity of a VMPO warm sensitive neuron during all three experimental conditions (resting membrane potential = -51.62 mV). The firing rate significantly decreased from a baseline of 10.07 &#x000b1; 0.13 impulses&#x000b7;s<sup>-1 </sup>to 8.40 &#x000b1; 0.12 impulses&#x000b7;s<sup>-1 </sup>during perfusion with 1 &#x003bc;M PGE<sub>2 </sub>(washout = 10.20 &#x000b1; 0.16 impulses&#x000b7;s<sup>-1</sup>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2202-6-14-2"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>The effects of PGE<sub>2 </sub>on the input resistance of a VMPO temperature insensitive neuron (A) and a VMPO warm sensitive neuron (B). </bold>For each, changes in membrane potential are plotted in response to a series of hyperpolarizing current pulses (-10 to -100 pA, 200 ms), during baseline conditions (&#x025cf;), perfusion with PGE<sub>2 </sub>(&#x025b2;), and after PGE<sub>2 </sub>has been washed out of the chamber (&#x025a0;). For the temperature insensitive neuron in <bold>A </bold>(m = 0.05), input resistance decreased from a baseline of 406.33 M&#x003a9;, to 332.40 M&#x003a9; during perfusion with PGE<sub>2</sub>. After PGE<sub>2 </sub>had been washed out of the chamber, input resistance increased to 372.32 M&#x003a9;. For the warm sensitive neuron in B (m = 1.30), input resistance decreased from a baseline of 388.00 M&#x003a9;, to 244.86 M&#x003a9; during perfusion with PGE<sub>2</sub>. After PGE<sub>2 </sub>had been washed out of the chamber, input resistance increased to 327.63 M&#x003a9;.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2202-6-14-3"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>The effect of depolarizing current and PGE<sub>2 </sub>on the activity of a VMPO temperature insensitive neuron. A </bold>shows the initial action potential that was produced during baseline conditions, in response to a depolarizing current injection (50 pA, 500 msec). The onset of the current is indicated on the line at the bottom of the figure and only the initial 34 mSec are shown. The first spike latency was 8.0 mSec. In <bold>B</bold>, the initial action potential that was produced in response to a depolarizing current injection is shown during perfusion with PGE<sub>2 </sub>(1 &#x003bc;M). The first spike latency was 3.0 mSec.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2202-6-14-4"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>The effect of depolarizing current and PGE<sub>2 </sub>on the activity of a VMPO warm sensitive neuron. A </bold>shows the initial action potential that was produced during baseline conditions, in response to a depolarizing current injection (50 pA, 500 msec). The onset of the current is indicated on the line at the bottom of the figure and only the initial 22.0 mSec are shown. The first spike latency was 4.0 mSec. In <bold>B</bold>, the initial action potential that was produced in response to a depolarizing current injection is shown during perfusion with PGE<sub>2 </sub>(200 nM). The first spike latency was 6.6 mSec.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2202-6-14-5"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>Averaged pre- and post-spike activity of a temperature insensitive VMPO neuron (A) and warm sensitive VMPO neuron (B)</bold>. For each, averages of 10 action potentials (truncated) during baseline conditions and during perfusion with PGE<sub>2 </sub>(1 &#x003bc;M), are superimposed on the spike threshold (post-pike activity during PGE<sub>2 </sub>is indicated by an asterisk). These averages do not include pre-spike activity that contained putative postsynaptic potentials. For the temperature insensitive neuron in <bold>A</bold>, the rate of rise of the depolarizing prepotential increased from 0.17 mV&#x000b7;mSec<sup>-1 </sup>to 0.27 mV&#x000b7;mSec<sup>-1</sup>. For the warm sensitive neurons in <bold>B</bold>, the rate of rise of the depolarizing prepotential decreased from 0.38 mV&#x000b7;mSec<sup>-1 </sup>to 0.18 mV&#x000b7;mSec<sup>-1</sup>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2202-6-14-6"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Effect of PGE<sub>2</sub>on the Frequency of IPSPs and EPSPs recorded from VMPO Neurons.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="center" colspan="3">IPSPs&#x000b7;s<sup>-1</sup></td><td align="center" colspan="3">EPSPs&#x000b7;s<sup>-1</sup></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td colspan="3"><hr></hr></td><td colspan="3"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="center"><bold>Thermosensitivity (impulses&#x000b7;s<sup>-1.</sup>&#x000b0;C<sup>-1</sup>)</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>N</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Baseline</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>PGE<sub>2</sub></bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Washout</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Baseline</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>PGE<sub>2</sub></bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Washout</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">&#x02264;0.4</td><td align="center">19</td><td align="center">5.1 &#x000b1; 1.2</td><td align="center">5.6 &#x000b1; 1.0</td><td align="center">5.3 &#x000b1; 1.0</td><td align="center">3.0 &#x000b1; 0.0</td><td align="center">3.1 &#x000b1; 0.7</td><td align="center">3.2 &#x000b1; 0.1</td></tr><tr><td align="center">0.41 &#x02013; 0.79</td><td align="center">13</td><td align="center">6.4 &#x000b1; 1.1</td><td align="center">7.3 &#x000b1; 1.3</td><td align="center">6.2 &#x000b1; 1.1</td><td align="center">3.3 &#x000b1; 0.7</td><td align="center">4.2 &#x000b1; 3.3</td><td align="center">3.7 &#x000b1; 0.8</td></tr><tr><td align="center">&#x02265; 0.8</td><td align="center">10</td><td align="center">4.2 &#x000b1; 1.1</td><td align="center">3.8 &#x000b1; 0.9</td><td align="center">3.8 &#x000b1; 0.9</td><td align="center">2.4 &#x000b1; 0.7</td><td align="center">3.2 &#x000b1; 0.4</td><td align="center">1.4 &#x000b1; 0.3</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec></back></article>



