<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Ecol</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Ecology</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1472-6785</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15723710</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC554990</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1472-6785-5-3</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1472-6785-5-3</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Sarcocystosis of chital-dhole: conditions for evolutionary stability of a predator parasite mutualism</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jog</surname><given-names>Maithili M</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>captjog@smjet.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Watve</surname><given-names>Milind G</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>watve@vsnl.com</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Microbiology, Abasaheb Garware College, Karve Road, Pune 411 004, India</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Life Research Foundation 10, Pranav, 1000/6-c Navi Peth, Pune 411 030, India</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>2</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>3</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1472-6785/5/3"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>11</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>22</day><month>2</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 Jog and Watve; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Jog and Watve; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Jog
               M
               Maithili
               
               captjog@smjet.com
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Sarcocystosis of chital-dhole: conditions for evolutionary stability of a predator parasite mutualism
         </dc:title><dc:date>2005</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>BMC Ecology 5(1): 3-. (2005)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1472-6785(2005)5:1&#x0003c;3&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1472-6785</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>For parasites with a predator-prey life cycle, the completion of the life cycle often depends on consumption of parasitized prey by the predator. In the case of such parasite species the predator and the parasite have common interests and therefore a mutualistic relationship is possible. Some evidence of a predator-parasite mutualism was reported from spotted deer or chital (<italic>Axix axis</italic>) as a prey species, dhole or Indian wild-dog (<italic>Cuon alpinus</italic>) as the predator and a protozoan (<italic>Sarcocystis axicuonis</italic>) as the parasite. We examine here, with the help of a model, the ecological conditions necessary for the evolution and stability of such a mutualistic relationship. A two &#x02013; level game theory model was designed in which the payoff of a parasite is decided not only by alternative parasite strategies but also by alternative host strategies and vice versa. Conditions for ESS were examined.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>A tolerant predator strategy and a low or moderately virulent parasite strategy which together constitute mutualism are stable only at a high frequency of recycling of parasite and a substantial prey &#x02013; capture benefit to the predator. Unlike the preliminary expectation, parasite will not evolve towards reduced virulence, but reach an optimum moderate level of virulence.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The available data on the behavioral ecology of dhole and chital suggest that they are likely to meet the stability criteria and therefore a predator-parasite mutualism can be stable in this system. The model also points out the gaps in the current data and could help directing further empirical work.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Preferential killing of sick and disabled prey individuals by the predator has been the focus of many ecologists working with different predator &#x02013; prey systems. In a variety of prey predator systems, diseased or weaker animals are shown to be consumed in greater proportion by predators [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>]. Increased susceptibility of parasitized prey to predation, or predator preference for parasitized prey is possible under a set of conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. Where the prey species is an intermediate host and the predator is the definitive host for a parasite species, the capture of prey is often an essential part of the life cycle. Therefore any mechanism that makes the prey susceptible to predation would enhance the parasite fitness. In such relationships the susceptibility induced by the parasite can be very specific towards the predator host [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. A mutualistic relationship can be said to exist between a predator and a parasite [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>] if the cost of harboring the parasite is less than the benefit of greater success in catching the prey [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. Some evidence suggestive of predator-parasite mutualism comes from dhole or Indian wild dog (<italic>Cuon alpinus</italic>) and a protozoan parasite (<italic>Sarcosystis axicuonis</italic>) with chital or spotted deer (<italic>Axis axis</italic>) as the prey-host [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>].</p><p>There can be a potential problem in such a mutualistic relationship. Low virulence of the parasite towards the predator host and parasite tolerance by the predator host are essential factors for the maintenance of a mutualistic relationship. However, it is possible that a virulent parasite can grow faster and invade a mild parasite population. On the other hand a parasite resistant predator can avoid the cost of parasitism but share the benefit of prey capture and therefore invade a tolerant population. Either of the events can destabilize the mutualistic relationship. It is essential therefore to examine the evolutionary stability of the mutualism. In a completely randomized distribution, a mild parasite population can be easily invaded by a virulent one and a tolerant predator can be invaded by a resistant one. Population viscosity, group selection and kin selection can alter the evolution of virulence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. The dhole &#x02013; <italic>Sarcocystis </italic>system makes group selection and viscosity very likely factors in shaping the relationship [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. The life cycle of the parasite is very short as compared to dhole life span. Dhole groups are stable and retain their territories over a long time. Dhole territories are large and encompass home ranges of several chital packs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Therefore the protozoan harboured by a dhole pack is very likely to be recycled to the same pack. The benefit of the parasite is more likely to be gained by the same pack. The distribution of a parasite within a pack is shown to follow a consistent pattern in which only a few individuals carry most of the parasite load. On the other hand, one or two individuals in each pack are found to be parasite free. This suggests that within a pack there can be distribution of labor. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. A distribution of labor, in which some individuals do active hunting and some disseminate the parasite, can reduce the effective cost of carrying the parasite. Evolution can take a different route under such conditions.</p><p>We examine here the effect of parasite recycling on the evolution of a predator-parasite mutualism, using a theoretical model.</p><sec><title>The model</title><p>We consider two alternative strategies, namely mild and virulent, for the parasite (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). The virulent parasite multiplies rapidly in the predator host and therefore enjoys greater success (v) and exerts a higher cost (x) on the predator host. The mild parasite exerts relatively low cost (y) on the predator host and gains a limited success (m). The predator has two alternative strategies, namely tolerant and resistant. A tolerant predator always harbors the parasite population whereas the resistant one attempts to resist or eliminate the parasite. However, since the parasite virulence mechanisms also evolve, there is a probability (p) that the parasite can infect a resistant predator. The predator gets an additional net benefit (z) from capturing a prey infected with the parasite as compared to capturing an uninfected prey. The prey can have only one viable strategy, that of becoming resistant to the parasite. The prey will not get any benefit by tolerating the parasite since it would make it more susceptible for predation. Therefore, we do not consider alternative prey strategies in the model.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Pay &#x02013; off matrix for predator and parasite strategies.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="center">parasite</td><td></td><td align="center">predator</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td colspan="5"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td align="center">Mild</td><td align="center">Virulent</td><td align="center">Tolerant</td><td align="center">Resistant</td></tr><tr><td></td><td colspan="5"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td align="left">parasite</td><td align="left">Mild</td><td align="center">1-y</td><td align="center">fr(1-y)+(1-fr)(1-x)</td><td align="center">m</td><td align="center">p* m</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Virulent</td><td align="center">fr(1-x)+(1-fr)(1-y)</td><td align="center">(1-x)</td><td align="center">v</td><td align="center">p* v</td></tr><tr><td align="left">predator</td><td align="left">Tolerant</td><td align="center">-y</td><td align="center">-x</td><td align="center">z</td><td align="center">(1-fr) p *z + fr *z</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="left">Resistant</td><td align="center">- p * y</td><td align="center">- p* x</td><td align="center">(1-fr)*z + fr (p* z)</td><td align="center">p* z</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The table differs from pay-off matrix tables for classical game theory models. The table accounts for two alternative strategies each for two different types of players namely parasite and predator. The pay-off of the parasite is not only decided by other parasites but also by the predator strategy and vice-versa. Therefore the complete pay-off of a mild parasite invading a virulent population in a tolerant host population is m * [fr(1-y)+(1-fr)(1-x)]. Others to be calculated similarly.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>If the parasite population consists of the mild type, they enjoy a fitness of 'm' from the tolerant host and 'p*m' from a resistant one. Since they exert a cost y on the host, there is erosion of the host resource. The host resource available to them is therefore (1-y). Similarly for a population of virulent parasites the mean fitness gain is v and the host resource available (1-x). A virulent host invading a mild population will gain a fitness of 'v' such that v &#x0003e; m. In the absence of recycling the host resource available to it would be (1-y). However with a frequency of recycling 'fr', the host resource would be,</p><p>fr (1-x) + (1-fr)(1-y)</p><p>Similarly, that for a mild parasite invading a virulent population would be,</p><p>fr (1-y) + (1-fr)(1-x)</p><p>If the predator population is tolerant the parasite will be harbored in large numbers and disseminated to the prey population. Since the parasitized prey is more susceptible to predation the predator gets a benefit 'z' of easy catching. A resistant population, on the other hand has a small probability 'p' of harboring the parasite. Therefore the benefit the predator gets would be 'p*z'. If a resistant predator invades a tolerant population, with the recycling factor 'fr', the benefit of prey capture would be,</p><p>fr * p *z + z(1-fr).</p><p>The benefit for a tolerant one invading a resistant population would be,</p><p>fr * z + (1-fr)* p*z.</p><p>We assume that 'v', the benefit for a virulent parasite by infecting single host is directly proportional to 'x' i.e the loss to the host from infection by virulent parasite.</p><p>V = &#x003b1; *x similarly, m = &#x003b1; *y</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results and discussion</title><p>A mild parasite will be able to invade a virulent population if the pay-off to the mild invader is greater than that for the virulent population. When the predator population is tolerant, this condition is satisfied when,</p><p>y * [fr (1-y)+(1-fr) (1-x)] &#x0003e; x (1-x)</p><p>The condition under which a virulent invader is unable to invade a mild population is</p><p>(1-y)* y &#x0003e; [fr *(1-x) + (1-fr)*(1-y)]*x</p><p>Since x &#x0003e; y, for satisfying both these conditions, fr should be large, y should be moderate and x should be large. Thus selection would favour a moderate virulence in the parasite towards the predator host. Unlike our expectation, low virulence is unlikely to be stable. However, a mutualistic relation can remain if the prey capture benefit is sufficiently large. It can be easily seen that the above conditions remain unaffected even if the predator population is resistant.</p><p>Considering predator strategies, a tolerant predator will be able to invade a resistant population in the presence of a mild predator if,</p><p>p *z - p*y &#x0003c; (1-fr) p *z + fr*z - y</p><p>i. e. p*fr * z - p* y &#x0003c; fr *z - y</p><p>This condition will be satisfied if fr *z &#x0003e; y since p &#x0003c; 1. A resistant predator will be unable to invade a tolerant population since the necessary condition is</p><p>z-y &#x0003c; (1-fr)*z + fr*(p*z) - (p * y)</p><p>fr*z - y &#x0003c; p*fr*z - p*y</p><p>This invasion is impossible if fr*z &#x0003e; y. If the parasite is virulent, the necessary condition would be fr*z &#x0003e; x. Since x is assumed to be large, a resistant predator would be stable if the prevalent parasite strategy is virulent.</p><p>Thus when fr and z are large and y is small mutualism would be stable. When this condition is not satisfied the predator will evolve resistance to the parasite and the parasite will evolve greater virulence.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>A large recycling frequency (fr) appears to be the only critical factor in the evolution of parasite virulence. However, the parasite is unlikely to evolve towards low virulence. There will be a moderate virulence optimum. For a net benefit to the host the cost associated with this level of virulence should be less than the benefit in terms of ease of prey capture.</p><p>For the evolution and stability of the tolerant strategy in the predator a large fr as well as large z and small y are necessary. A predator-parasite mutualism therefore critically depends upon these factors, whereas it is independent of p and &#x003b1;.</p><p>In the case of Dhole-chital &#x02013; <italic>Sarcocystis </italic>system, these condition are very likely to be satisfied. Field data show that the frequency of sarcocystosis of the heart in dhole kills was approximately double that of chital dyeing of other causes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. This suggests a substantially large z. Dhole have large, stable and defended territories upto 80 Km<sup>2 </sup>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. There is only marginal overlap between neighboring packs unlike the overlap in tigers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>]. The territory of a dhole pack encompasses the home ranges of several chital groups. The home ranges of chital groups are small and stable [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. This can ensure a large 'fr'. Unlike wolves, which tend to defecate more on the boundaries of the territory [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>], the frequently used defecation sites of dhole tend to be towards the center of their home range and close to the major hunting areas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>], further ensuring a large 'fr'. The intensity of intestinal infection is reflected in the density of sporocyst in Dhole scat. Dhole shading large numbers of sporocysts of <italic>S. axicuonis </italic>show no apparent symptoms of disease or abnormality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. This indicates that the virulence of <italic>S. axicuonis </italic>towards dhole is low. Further, the division of labor can substantially reduce the effective cost of carrying the parasite. Currently we are unable to quantify these parameters empirically and have no estimate of the actual cost of harboring the parasite. Therefore we are unable to state quantitatively that all the necessary conditions for mutualism are met by the system. The importance of the model is that it helps us identify the gaps in the data and thus orient future empirical work.</p><p>Although we are far from having an empirical estimate of y, fr and z, the known ecology of chital and dhole suggest that fr and z could be sufficiently large. This makes the system a likely candidate for the evolution of predator parasite mutualism. Any other predator-prey system that satisfies these conditions is also likely to co-evolve with some parasite species towards a predator-parasite mutualism. Parasites of diverse taxa have evolved predator-prey life cycles and any of them could be possible candidates for a mutualism. Predator-prey-parasite systems that satisfy the following three criteria are the most likely candidates for a stable mutualistic relationship:</p><p>i) parasitized prey individuals are killed with substantially greater frequency by the predator</p><p>ii) pathogenicity of the parasite towards the predator host is low or moderate</p><p>iii) there is a high rate of parasite recycling to the predator host.</p><p>We need to look at a number of systems that could satisfy these criteria. The chital-dhole-<italic>Sarcocystis </italic>system may not be unique and many possible examples of predator-parasite mutualism may be present in nature.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>Both authors have contributed approximately equally to the model development.</p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We are grateful to the Department of Science &#x00026; Technology, Govt. of India for financially assisting this work. We thank the forest departments of Tamilnadu and Maharashtra State for their permission for field work. We thank Dr. R. Sukumar, CES, field station in Mudumalai for providing necessary facilities, and Arun Venkatraman and R. Arumugum for their active interaction during field work. Discussions with Dr. S. A. Paranjape, Dr. N. V. Joshi and Arun Venkatraman were useful. We are grateful to Prof. Arun Bhagwat for his help in language and presentation during revision of the manuscript. We also thank Sachin, Krushnamegh, Rahul, Shantanu and Dilip for field support.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jog</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Marathe</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Goel</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranade</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunte</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Watve</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sarcocystosis of chital (<underline>Axis</underline><underline>axis</underline>) and dhole (<underline>Cuon</underline><underline>alpinus</underline>): ecology of a mammalian prey-predator-parasite system in Peninsular India</article-title><source>J Tropical Ecol</source><comment></comment></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rau</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Caron</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parasite-induced susceptibility of moose to hunting</article-title><source>Can J Zool</source><year>1979</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>2466</fpage><lpage>2468</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vorisek</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Votyppka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zvara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Svobodova</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Heteroxenous coccidia increase the predation risk of parasitized rodents</article-title><source>Parasitology</source><year>1998</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>521</fpage><lpage>524</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9881375</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0031182098003242</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kruuk</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><source>The spotted hyena. A study of predation and social behavior</source><year>1972</year><publisher-name>University of Chicago press, Chicago, London</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hudson</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dobson</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Newborn</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Rollison D, Anderson RM</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Cyclic and non-cyclic populations of red grouse: a role for parasitism?</article-title><source>Ecology and genetics of host parasite interactions</source><year>1985</year><publisher-name>Academic Press, London</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bethel</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Canning EV, Wright C</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Modification of intermediate host by parasites</article-title><source>Behavioral aspects of parasite transmission</source><year>1972</year><publisher-name>Linnean Soc. London, A P London</publisher-name><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>150</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Temple</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Do predators always capture substandard individuals disproportionately from prey populations?</article-title><source>Ecology</source><year>1987</year><volume>68</volume><fpage>669</fpage><lpage>674</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>FitzGibbon</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Fanshawe</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The condition and age of Thompson's Gazelles killed by cheetahs and wild dogs</article-title><source>J Zool London</source><year>1989</year><volume>218</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>107</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Levri</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The influence of non-host predators on parasite induced behavioural changes in a freshwater snail</article-title><source>Oikos</source><year>1998</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>531</fpage><lpage>537</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freedman</surname><given-names>HI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A model of predator prey dynamics as modified by the action of a parasite</article-title><source>Mathematical Biosciences</source><year>1990</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2134516</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0025-5564(90)90001-F</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jog</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Marathe</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Goel</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranade</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunte</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name><name><surname>Watve</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Sarcocystis </italic>infection in chital (<italic>Axis Axis</italic>) and dhole (<italic>Cuon alpinus</italic>) in two Indian protected areas</article-title><source>Zoos' Print Journal</source><year>2003</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1220</fpage><lpage>1222</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A kin selection model for the evolution of virulence</article-title><source>Proc R Soc Lond Biol Sci</source><year>1992</year><volume>250</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>197</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Venkatrama</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Armugam</surname><given-names/></name><name><surname>Sukumar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The foraging ecology of dhole (<italic>Coun alpinus</italic>) in Mudumalai Sanctuary, southern India</article-title><source>J Zool London</source><year>1995</year><volume>237</volume><fpage>543</fpage><lpage>561</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnsingh</surname><given-names>AJT</given-names></name><name><surname>Acharya</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Venkatraman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Johnsingh AJT, Manjrekar N</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Dhole</article-title><source>The Mammals of South Asia</source><publisher-name>Permanent Black, New Delhi</publisher-name><comment></comment></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karanth</surname><given-names>UK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sunquist</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Behavioural correlates of predation by tiger (<italic>Panthera tigris</italic>), leopard (<italic>Panthera pardus</italic>) and dhole (<italic>Cuon alpinus</italic>) in Nagarhole, India</article-title><source>J Zool London</source><year>2000</year><volume>250</volume><fpage>255</fpage><lpage>265</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barette</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The size of Axis deer fluid groups in Wilpattu National Park, Sri Lanka</article-title><source>Mammalia</source><year>1991</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>220</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><name><surname>Mech</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Scent marking in wolves</article-title><source>American Scientist</source><year>1975</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>628</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1200478</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Venkatraman</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Narendrababu</surname><given-names/></name></person-group><article-title>personal communication</article-title></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watve</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecology of host parasite interactions in a wild mammalian host community in Mudumalai, southern India</article-title><source>Ph D thesis Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore</source><year>1992</year></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jog</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Study of quantitative ecological patterns in abundance and distribution of parasites of wild mammals in India</article-title><source>Ph D Thesis University of Pune, Pune</source><year>2004</year></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



