<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Evol Biol</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Evolutionary Biology</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2148</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15453916</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC543456</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2148-4-35</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2148-4-35</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Long branch attraction, taxon sampling, and the earliest angiosperms: <italic>Amborella </italic>or monocots?</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" equal-contrib="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stefanovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>Sa&#x00161;a</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>sstefano@bio.indiana.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" equal-contrib="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>Danny W</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>dwrice@indiana.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>Jeffrey D</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>jpalmer@bio.indiana.edu</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Department of Biology, Indiana University, Bloomington, IN 47405, USA</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Biology, University of Toronto at Mississauga, Mississauga ON, L5L 1C6, Canada</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>9</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><fpage>35</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2148/4/35"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>6</day><month>8</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>9</month><year>2004</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2004 Stefanovi&#x00107; et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2004</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Stefanovi&#x00107; et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Stefanovi&#x00107;
               Sa&#x00161;a
               
               
               sstefano@bio.indiana.edu
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Long branch attraction, taxon sampling, and the earliest angiosperms: Amborella or monocots?
         </dc:title><dc:date>2004</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>BMC Evolutionary Biology 4(1): 35-. (2004)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1471-2148(2004)4:1&#x0003c;35&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1471-2148</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Numerous studies, using in aggregate some 28 genes, have achieved a consensus in recognizing three groups of plants, including <italic>Amborella</italic>, as comprising the basal-most grade of all other angiosperms. A major exception is the recent study by Goremykin et al. (2003; <italic>Mol. Biol. Evol</italic>. 20:1499&#x02013;1505), whose analyses of 61 genes from 13 sequenced chloroplast genomes of land plants nearly always found 100% support for monocots as the deepest angiosperms relative to <italic>Amborella</italic>, <italic>Calycanthus</italic>, and eudicots. We hypothesized that this conflict reflects a misrooting of angiosperms resulting from inadequate taxon sampling, inappropriate phylogenetic methodology, and rapid evolution in the grass lineage used to represent monocots.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>We used two main approaches to test this hypothesis. First, we sequenced a large number of chloroplast genes from the monocot <italic>Acorus </italic>and added these plus previously sequenced <italic>Acorus </italic>genes to the Goremykin et al. (2003) dataset in order to explore the effects of altered monocot sampling under the same analytical conditions used in their study. With <italic>Acorus </italic>alone representing monocots, strongly supported <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister trees were obtained in all maximum likelihood and parsimony analyses, and in some distance-based analyses. Trees with both <italic>Acorus </italic>and grasses gave either a well-supported <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister topology or else a highly unlikely topology with 100% support for grasses-sister and paraphyly of monocots (i.e., <italic>Acorus </italic>sister to "dicots" rather than to grasses). Second, we reanalyzed the Goremykin et al. (2003) dataset focusing on methods designed to account for rate heterogeneity. These analyses supported an <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister hypothesis, with bootstrap support values often conflicting strongly with cognate analyses performed without allowing for rate heterogeneity. In addition, we carried out a limited set of analyses that included the chloroplast genome of <italic>Nymphaea</italic>, whose position as a basal angiosperm was also, and very recently, challenged.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>These analyses show that <italic>Amborella </italic>(or <italic>Amborella </italic>plus <italic>Nymphaea</italic>), but not monocots, is the sister group of all other angiosperms among this limited set of taxa and that the grasses-sister topology is a long-branch-attraction artifact leading to incorrect rooting of angiosperms. These results highlight the danger of having lots of characters but too few and, especially, molecularly divergent taxa, a situation long recognized as potentially producing strongly misleading molecular trees. They also emphasize the importance in phylogenetic analysis of using appropriate evolutionary models.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>A correct understanding of relationships among the "earliest" lineages of angiosperms is important if we wish to elucidate the causes and consequences of their origin, to understand patterns and tempos of character evolution in the earliest lineages, and to decipher subsequent patterns of diversification. [We sometimes use "earliest", "deepest", "basal", etc. as a convenient shorthand to refer to plants hypothesized to belong to lineages that result from the first or one of the first evolutionary branchings within angiosperm evolution. We do not mean to imply that any extant plants (e.g., <italic>Amborella</italic>) are themselves the "earliest" angiosperms, but rather that they belong to the lineage of angiosperms that resulted from the first evolutionary split in angiosperm evolution. When the term "sister" is used to refer to a phylogenetic placement it refers to the sister group to the rest of the angiosperms unless otherwise specified.] A breakthrough in the seemingly intractable problem of identifying the earliest lineages of angiosperms occurred in 1999 and 2000, when each of many multigene studies identified the same three groups as the earliest branching angiosperms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Most of these studies, as well as most subsequent analyses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>] have converged on the placement of the monotypic genus <italic>Amborella</italic>, a vessel-less shrub with unisexual flowers endemic to New Caledonia, as the sister-group to all living angiosperms (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>), with the next two divergences within angiosperms corresponding to the water lilies (Nymphaeaceae) and then the Austrobaileyales. This grade leads toward the well-supported remainder of the flowering plants, also known as core angiosperms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>] (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). The monophyly of each of the five lineages of core angiosperms is well established, but relationships among them are unclear (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Current consensus hypothesis of angiosperm relationships. </bold>Tree topology is based on [42, 91] and references in Table 1. Small asterisks indicate the general phylogenetic position of the ten angiosperms (generic names shown for all but the three grasses) examined by Goremykin et al. [19]. The large asterisk indicates the addition in this study of the early-arising monocot <italic>Acorus </italic>to the Goremykin et al. [19] dataset. The height of the triangles reflects the relative number of species in eudicots (~175,000 species), monocots (~70,000), and magnoliids (~9,000) as estimated by Judd et al. [18] and Walter Judd (personal communication). The other five angiosperm groups shown contain only between 1 and ~100 species.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2148-4-35-1"></graphic></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Comparison of recent studies<sup>a </sup>that identify the sister lineages of angiosperms.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center">Study reference</td><td align="center">No. of genes (genomes<sup>b</sup>)</td><td align="center">No. of angiosperms</td><td align="center">No. of nucleotides</td><td align="center" colspan="2"><italic>Amborella </italic>sister to the rest of angiosperms<sup>c</sup></td><td align="center" colspan="2">Basal vs. core angiosperms<sup>c</sup></td><td align="center" colspan="2">Monophyly of monocots<sup>c</sup></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">[4]</td><td align="center">5 (c, m, n)</td><td align="center">97</td><td align="center">8,733</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">90</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">97</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">99/98</td></tr><tr><td align="left">[3]</td><td align="center">5 (c, m, n)</td><td align="center">45</td><td align="center">6,564</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">94<sup>d</sup></td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">99<sup>d</sup></td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">98<sup>d</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">[6]</td><td align="center">3 (c, n)</td><td align="center">553</td><td align="center">4,733</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">65<sup>e</sup></td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">71<sup>e</sup></td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">95<sup>e</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="left">[1]</td><td align="center">2 (n)</td><td align="center">26</td><td align="center">2,208</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">92/83<sup>f</sup></td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">86</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left">[2]</td><td align="center">2 (n)</td><td align="center">52</td><td align="center">2,606</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">88/57<sup>f</sup></td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">68</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">87</td></tr><tr><td align="left">[8]</td><td align="center">6 (c, m, n)</td><td align="center">33</td><td align="center">8,911</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">n/a<sup>g</sup></td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">99</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left">[9]</td><td align="center">17 (c)</td><td align="center">18</td><td align="center">14,244</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">69</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">94</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">53</td></tr><tr><td align="left">[11]</td><td align="center">1 (c)</td><td align="center">38</td><td align="center">4,707</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">99</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">100</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">100</td></tr><tr><td align="left">[14]</td><td align="center">1 (c)</td><td align="center">361</td><td align="center">1,749</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">86</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">89</td><td align="center">+</td><td align="center">99</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Not included are several other studies also supportive of <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister, but which are largely duplicative of the above [5, 7, 31], or whose structure does not match sufficiently with the structure of this table [10, 12, 13], or which have extremely limited sampling (6 taxa) within angiosperms [15].</p><p><sup>b</sup>c = chloroplast; m = mitochondrial; n = nuclear</p><p><sup>c</sup>Indicated relationship recovered (+) or not recovered (-); parsimony BS values shown unless otherwise specified. See Fig. 1 for definition of indicated relationships.</p><p><sup>d</sup>Only BS values derived from ML analysis are shown.</p><p><sup>e</sup>Jackknife support values.</p><p><sup>f</sup>Bootstrap values were inferred from separate <italic>phyA </italic>and <italic>phyC </italic>treatments; other BS values in this study were derived from concatenated <italic>phyA </italic>and <italic>phyC </italic>sequences.</p><p><sup><italic>g</italic></sup>n/a &#x02013; not applicable. This study found <italic>Amborella</italic>+<italic>Nymphaea </italic>as sister to all other angiosperms (see Discussion).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>In sharp contrast stands the study of Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>], in which the <italic>Amborella </italic>chloroplast genome was sequenced and in which 61 protein genes shared among 13 land plants (including 10 angiosperms) were analyzed. In 31 of 33 phylogenetic analyses this study found that "<italic>Amborella </italic>is not the basal angiosperm and not even the deepest branching among dicots" ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] Abstract). Instead, these results indicate, with 100% BS in most analyses, that the first split within angiosperm evolution occurred between monocots and dicots. Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] imply that the earlier studies are in error with respect to the placement of <italic>Amborella </italic>because these "studies were based on a limited number of characters derived from only a few genes" and used "unmasked sequences of chloroplast genes [i.e., with all three codon positions included] with high substitution rates at their synonymous sites" (p. 1503).</p><p>Thus, we are faced with a major paradox. On the one hand, many different studies, employing in aggregate 28 different genes (19 chloroplast, five mitochondrial, and four nuclear; Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>), consistently and strongly place the branch leading to <italic>Amborella </italic>deeper in angiosperm evolution than the branch leading to the monocots, whereas a study that employed twice as many genes found the opposite result, also with strong support. It is critical to resolve this paradox, for the groups and issues involved are such important ones in angiosperm phylogeny.</p><p>One notable difference between the two sets of studies concerns taxon sampling, which can be critical in phylogenetic analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. Even though sampling strategies in the <italic>Amborella</italic>-deep studies listed in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref> varied substantially, ranging from 18 to 553 species of angiosperms and from 2,208 to 14,244 nucleotides (NT) of aligned data, a commonality was their relatively broad taxon sampling. Most of these studies attempted to represent the diversity of living angiosperms by including critical species identified by prior morphological [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>] and single-gene molecular analyses [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">31</xref>]. Even the listed study with the fewest taxa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>] was based on exemplar species, compiled by the Green Plant Phylogeny Research Coordination Group and chosen to represent most of the major putatively basal lineages suggested by a large body of previously accumulated results. In contrast, the Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] study included only 10 angiosperms. Five of these belong to a single derived group (eudicots) and three are grasses (the only monocots sampled), leaving <italic>Amborella </italic>and <italic>Calycanthus </italic>(the only sampled member of the other three lineages of core angiosperms) as the other two angiosperms sampled (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). It is known that grasses have accelerated substitution rates in all three genomes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>], especially the chloroplast genome, making them a poor representative for such a large and diverse group as monocots.</p><p>Relevant here is that the grasses-sister topology obtained by Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] (see their Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>, which also corresponds to our Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>) shows one long branch, leading to grasses, connecting to another long branch, separating angiosperms from the outgroups. When the outgroups are removed and the Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] tree is taken as an unrooted network, it becomes apparent that there is no difference between their ingroup topology and those of studies that obtained the <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister rooting. In other words, given the taxonomic sampling of Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>], their grasses-sister topology differs from the canonical <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister topology only with respect to where the outgroup branch attaches [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>], either to grasses or to <italic>Amborella </italic>(see Discussion and Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref> for an elaboration of this point).</p><p>These observations led us to suspect that the grasses-sister topology is an artifact stemming from long branch attraction (LBA), a phenomenon known [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>] to give strongly supported, but spurious results under precisely the set of conditions operative in the Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] study. These are 1) inadequate taxon sampling, 2) large amounts of data per taxon, 3) two known long branches (the grass branch and the outgroup branch) separated by short internodes, and 4) phylogenetic analyses that do not account for rate heterogeneity.</p><p>The current study was undertaken to test whether the grasses-sister topology is indeed an LBA artifact. We hypothesize that, by analyzing the Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] dataset with a focus on rate heterogeneity and taxon sampling of monocots, the <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister topology will be recovered instead. In addition, we carried out a similar, but much more limited set of analyses in response to a follow-up paper by Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>] that appeared while this manuscript was in the final stages of preparation and which similarly challenged the position of <italic>Nymphaea </italic>as a basal angiosperm.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><sec><title>Addition of <italic>Acorus</italic></title><p>We gathered new sequence data for an additional monocot representative, <italic>Acorus</italic>, and added it to the 13 taxa, 61 gene first- and second-position alignment matrix of Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] to give a 14 taxa, 61 gene first- and second-position alignment matrix. <italic>Acorus </italic>was chosen for two reasons. First, it is well supported as the sister to all other monocots [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>]. Thus, <italic>Acorus </italic>plus grasses represent monocot diversity about as well as any two groups of monocots. Second, unlike grasses, its chloroplast genome does not appear to have evolved at unusually high rates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]. The <italic>Acorus </italic>dataset consisted of 40 protein gene sequences, 22 newly determined in this study and 18 from preexisting databases. This corresponds to 65.6% (40/61) of the genes and 71.4% (32,072/44,937) of the nucleotide characters analyzed by Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>].</p><p>A number of initial analyses were conducted in parallel on the "full" <italic>Acorus </italic>matrix, containing data for all 61 genes and including gaps where data for <italic>Acorus </italic>were not available, and a "truncated" matrix, containing only those 40 genes where <italic>Acorus </italic>sequences were available. Inspection of the resulting trees revealed no topological incongruences and no significant change in bootstrap support (BS) between the full and truncated analyses [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Additional files 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>]. The results presented hereafter for <italic>Acorus </italic>are based on the full matrix dataset. This allows us to include all available relevant data, allowing the fullest and most direct comparisons to the Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] analyses.</p><p>Representative results of either adding <italic>Acorus </italic>to the Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] matrix or substituting it for grasses are shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>. Using <italic>Acorus </italic>instead of grasses to represent monocots has a major effect on the results. This is especially dramatic for equal-weighted maximum parsimony (MP) analyses of both nucleotides and amino acids, where there is a shift from 100% BS for monocots-sister when only grasses are used to represent monocots (Figs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2D</xref>) to 100% and 93% support for <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister when <italic>Acorus </italic>is used instead (Figs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2E</xref>). The same topological shift is seen with maximum likelihood (ML) using equal rates across sites (cf. Figs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2G</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2H</xref>), although the swing in BS values is less pronounced (61% for grasses-sister vs. 100% for <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister). Transversion parsimony (RY-coding) of the original dataset (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2J</xref>) gives the <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister topology, but with poor support (56%). Substituting <italic>Acorus </italic>for grasses improves the support for <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister to 100% (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2K</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>The effect of changing sampling of monocots as a function ofphylogenetic method. </bold>Analysis of the 61-gene data matrix using: Rows <bold>A-C</bold>, DNA parsimony; <bold>D-F</bold>, protein parsimony; <bold>G-I </bold>DNA ML HKY85 with no rate categories; <bold>J-L</bold>, RY-coded DNA parsimony. The first column of trees is with the Goremykin et al. [19] taxon sampling (grasses, but not <italic>Acorus</italic>), the second is with <italic>Acorus </italic>but not grasses, and the third is with both grasses and <italic>Acorus</italic>. All analyses used the first- and second-position matrix, either with or without the addition of <italic>Acorus </italic>as explained in Methods. Trees <bold>J-L </bold>use the same matrices, but with the nucleotides RY-coded.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2148-4-35-2"></graphic></fig><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Neighbor joining analyses using different evolutionary models and/or taxon sampling. </bold>Distance matrices were calculated from the first- and second-position matrix of Goremykin et al. [19] using (<bold>A</bold>) the K2P model, (<bold>B</bold>) the ML HKY85 model with four gamma-distributed rate categories and parameters estimated from the corresponding ML analysis, and (<bold>C</bold>) the K2P model with <italic>Acorus </italic>added to the first- and second-position matrix as described in Methods.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2148-4-35-3"></graphic></fig><p>Inclusion of both grasses and <italic>Acorus </italic>produced two very different topologies, depending on the method used. On the one hand, standard MP, with both nucleotides (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C</xref>) and amino acids (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2F</xref>), gives a grasses-sister topology in which monocots are paraphyletic with 100% BS (i.e., there is 100% support for <italic>Acorus </italic>as the sister to "dicots" to the exclusion of grasses). On the other hand, equal-rates ML (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2I</xref>) and transversion parsimony (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2L</xref>) give an <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister topology, with moderate (79%) to strong (98%) support, in which monocots are monophyletic with equivalent support.</p><p>To make the results more directly comparable to the Goremykin et al. study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] and to investigate the performance of various distance-based models, we tested many different neighbor joining (NJ) models. We did this also because, of all MP, ML and NJ methods initially investigated, the only approaches that failed to give the <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister topology when <italic>Acorus </italic>was substituted for grasses were the NJ methods without a ML model. When the PAUP* [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>] distance is set to any of 12 settings (Mean, P, JC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>], F81 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>], TajNei [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>], K2P [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>], F84 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>], HKY85 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>], K3P [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>], TamNei [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>], GTR [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>] or LogDet [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>]), <italic>Amborella</italic>, <italic>Calycanthus</italic>, and <italic>Acorus </italic>form a monophyletic group with 100% BS. Importantly, however, this same grouping is obtained, with all 12 distance settings, even when grasses are included, such that, as in equal-weighted parsimony analyses (Figs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2F</xref>), grasses are sister to all other angiosperms and monocots are not monophyletic (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref> and analyses not shown).</p><p>Finally, it should be noted that ML and NJ methods using models (see next section) that give <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister when only grasses represent monocots, continue to do so, but with higher BS, when <italic>Acorus </italic>is added, either with or without grasses [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Additional files 1</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Site-to-site rate heterogeneity</title><p>If the lineage leading to <italic>Amborella </italic>is sister to the rest of angiosperms, as the analyses with <italic>Acorus </italic>strongly indicate, why do so many of the Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] analyses support the grasses-sister topology? We explored this question by conducting analyses using a broad range of models and methods as applied to their data matrix (i.e., with only grasses representing monocots).</p><p>We first compared the relative likelihood of the grasses-sister and <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister topologies using ML with all 56 combinations of the 14 substitution models and four rate-heterogeneity conditions specified by the MODELBLOCK script provided by MODELTEST [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>]. The four rate-heterogeneity conditions are 1) equal rates across sites, 2) estimated percentage of invariant sites, 3) four gamma-distributed rate categories and 4) a combination of invariant sites and gamma-rate categories. With equal rates across sites, the grasses-sister topology received the higher likelihood for all 14 substitution models (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). For the least complex, Jukes-Cantor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>] model (a single substitution rate with equal base frequencies), all four rate-heterogeneity conditions preferred the grasses-sister topology. In a more complex model (F81), which uses estimated base frequencies, the <italic>Amborella-</italic>sister topology was preferred when either invariant sites or gamma rate categories were used but not when they were used in combination. For the other 12 models, the <italic>Amborella-</italic>sister topology was preferred for all three conditions that allowed for rate heterogeneity across sites (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The 56 MODELTEST models and the grasses- or <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister topology that received the higher likelihood.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="left"><bold>Model</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>equal</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>+I</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>+G</bold></td><td align="left"><bold>+I +G</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><bold>JC</bold></td><td align="left">grasses</td><td align="left">grasses</td><td align="left">grasses</td><td align="left">grasses</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>F81</bold></td><td align="left">grasses</td><td align="left">Amborella</td><td align="left">Amborella</td><td align="left">grasses</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>K80</bold></td><td align="left">grasses</td><td align="left">Amborella</td><td align="left">Amborella</td><td align="left">Amborella</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>HKY</bold></td><td align="left">grasses</td><td align="left">Amborella</td><td align="left">Amborella</td><td align="left">Amborella</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>TrNef</bold></td><td align="left">grasses</td><td align="left">Amborella</td><td align="left">Amborella</td><td align="left">Amborella</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>TrN</bold></td><td align="left">grasses</td><td align="left">Amborella</td><td align="left">Amborella</td><td align="left">Amborella</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>K81</bold></td><td align="left">grasses</td><td align="left">Amborella</td><td align="left">Amborella</td><td align="left">Amborella</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>K81uf</bold></td><td align="left">grasses</td><td align="left">Amborella</td><td align="left">Amborella</td><td align="left">Amborella</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>TIMef</bold></td><td align="left">grasses</td><td align="left">Amborella</td><td align="left">Amborella</td><td align="left">Amborella</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>TIM</bold></td><td align="left">grasses</td><td align="left">Amborella</td><td align="left">Amborella</td><td align="left">Amborella</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>TVMef</bold></td><td align="left">grasses</td><td align="left">Amborella</td><td align="left">Amborella</td><td align="left">Amborella</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>TVM</bold></td><td align="left">grasses</td><td align="left">Amborella</td><td align="left">Amborella</td><td align="left">Amborella</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>SYM</bold></td><td align="left">grasses</td><td align="left">Amborella</td><td align="left">Amborella</td><td align="left">Amborella</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><bold>GTR</bold></td><td align="left">grasses</td><td align="left">Amborella</td><td align="left">Amborella</td><td align="left">Amborella</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The four rate-heterogeneity conditions used in these MODELTEST analyses are: 1) "equal" = equal rates across sites; 2) "+I" = estimated percentage of invariant sites; 3) "+G" = four gamma-distributed rate categories; and 4) "+I+G" = combination of invariant sites and 4 gamma-rate categories.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>These results held when the parameters estimated on one topology (either <italic>Amborella</italic>- or grasses- sister) were used to calculate the likelihood of the other topology (the topology used had only a minor effect on the values of the parameter estimates). For both topologies, the model chosen by MODELTEST using either the hierarchical likelihood ratio tests or the Akaike information criterion was the 5-substitution-type-transversion (TVM) + I + G model, where the probability of going between A and G is equal to that of C and T. With this model, using parameter estimates from either topology, a heuristic search found the <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister topology with 98% BS, and the SH-test [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>] showed the grasses-sister topology to be significantly worse at the 5% level (p = 0.04).</p><p>These MODELTEST analyses identified site-to-site rate heterogeneity, accounted for using either gamma-distributed rates or invariant sites, as a critical analytical parameter. We therefore explored this in greater detail using one particular substitution model, the HKY85 model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>]. We chose the moderately complex and commonly used HKY85 substitution model with empirical base frequencies over the TVM model to help speed up the calculation of bootstrap replicates. A ML-HKY85 analysis with equal rates and an estimated transition:transversion (Ti/Tv) ratio of 1.485 gives the same, grasses-sister topology (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>) as found by Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] (see Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2G</xref>, which is equivalent topologically to their Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>), albeit with low BS (61%) for grasses-sister. In contrast, a tree built using four rate categories, with the gamma shape parameter (&#x003b1; = 0.31) estimated from the Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] matrix and topology, gives 96% BS for <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>). Although we present here only the commonly used, four-rate-category model, a two-rate-category model gives the same qualitative results in all cases analyzed [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">Additional file 3</xref>].</p><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>Maximum likelihood analyses using different evolutionary models. </bold>Trees <bold>A-C </bold>were calculated using the first- and second-position Goremykin et al. [19] matrix. Tree <bold>D </bold>was calculated using all three codon positions. All trees were built using ML with the HKY85 model and the following treatments of rate heterogeneity: <bold>A</bold>. No rate categories. <bold>B</bold>. Four gamma-distributed rate categories. <bold>C</bold>. Estimated proportion of invariant sites (no gamma rate categories). <bold>D</bold>. No rate categories (all three positions). Parameters were estimated separately for each analysis as described in Methods.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2148-4-35-4"></graphic></fig><p>To assess the stability of the topology to changes in the &#x003b1; parameter, we scanned the range &#x003b1; = [0.01&#x02013;20.0], with the number of rate categories fixed at four. The same, <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister topology obtained using the estimated &#x003b1; (0.31) was also recovered over a wide range of &#x003b1; values (&#x003b1; = 0.01&#x02013;9.0; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>). The BS for <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister and the SH-test p-value [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>] of the <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister over the grasses-sister topology both improve as &#x003b1; decreases to the estimated value and continue to improve as &#x003b1; approaches zero (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref>). As &#x003b1; approaches infinity, the rate categories approach the same value (i.e., equal rates) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">60</xref>]. Accordingly, the BS and p-value curves in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> approach the values of the equal-rates trees.</p><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>Bootstrap support and the SH-test p-value for the <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister or grasses-sister topologies as a function of (A) the gamma distribution &#x003b1; parameter value or (B) the proportion of invariable sites. </bold>The left vertical line in A and right line in B indicate the rate-heterogeneity parameter estimated from the data. The right vertical line in A and left line in B indicate the boundary where the topology of the best tree transitions between <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister and grasses-sister. All analyses were performed using the 61-gene first- and second-position matrix of Goremykin et al. [19] and the ML HKY85 model with the &#x003b1; parameter or proportion of invariant sites indicated on the X-axis. The transition-transversion parameter was estimated for each specified rate-heterogeneity parameter. p(&#x00394;|L<sub>Amb</sub>-L<sub>grasses</sub>|) signifies the SH-test p-value for the difference between the likelihood scores of the two topologies. Bootstrap searches and SH-tests were performed as described in Methods.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2148-4-35-5"></graphic></fig><p>We performed a similar analysis with the proportion of invariant sites (Plnvar option in PAUP). Using the estimated PInvar = 0.58 without gamma-distributed rate categories, we obtained the <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister topology (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4C</xref>) with 97% BS. As with &#x003b1;, the <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister topology was stable over a wide range of PInvar [0.09 &#x0003c;= PInvar &#x0003c;= 0.995 (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>)]. The BS and the SH-test p-value for <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister improve as PInvar increases (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>). The SH-test for <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister is significant at the 5% level using the estimated value of PInvar and remains significant as PInvar increases.</p><p>The BS for a sister-group relationship of <italic>Amborella </italic>and <italic>Calycanthus </italic>is identical (within the variance expected for BS values) with that for grasses-sister across the entire range of both &#x003b1; and PInvar values, while both of these BS values always equal 100 minus the BS value for <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister (Figs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>). This is exactly as expected (see Discussion) if the only difference between the grasses-sister/<italic>Amborella</italic>+<italic>Calycanthus </italic>topology and the <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister topology is where the outgroup branch roots within angiosperms. Put another way, almost all of the BS replicates were one of these two topologies.</p><p>There are 20,071 (out of 30,017; 66.9%) constant sites in theGoremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] matrix. When these constant sites are removed, the highest HKY85 ML tree (using equal rates) places <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister with 98% BS and with p = 0.03 for the SH-test relative to grasses-sister [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">Additional file 4</xref>, Fig. A]. Furthermore, NJ analysis with the equal-rate ML model also obtains <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister (with 100% BS) when constant sites are removed [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">Additional file 4</xref>, Fig. B]. This is another way of allowing the rates to increase since the rates of the sites that are changing are not constrained by the constant sites. This allows the ML model to work with a more homogenous set of rates and reduces the need for using rate categories. Removing these constant sites allows the ML model to simulate the actual evolutionary process of sites that are changing more accurately than when imposing a proportion of invariant sites because there is no invariant site weighting of the sites that are changing. As a consequence of the faster rate with constant sites excluded, the branch lengths of the resulting trees are ~2.6 times longer than when constant sites are included.</p><p>We further explored the NJ method using ML models of evolution to compute distances and with constant sites included. We were able to precisely reproduce the grasses-sister result (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> from Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]) with NJ and the K2P model(Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3A</xref>). NJ using a distance matrix calculated based on ML and using parameters estimated with the HKY85 model with equal rates alsogives grasses-sister with 100% BS. However, distances calculated using the ML HKY85 model and estimated proportion of invariant sites puts <italic>Amborella-</italic>sister with low BS of 58% [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S5">Additional file 5</xref>], while distances derived from the ML HKY85 model with four gamma-distributed rate categories estimated gives <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister with stronger support (89%; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Third codon positions</title><p>In order to most directly assess the Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] analyses, which used only first and second codon position, the above analyses were restricted to first and second codon positions. In addition, however, most of the above analyses were also carried out with a dataset that includes all three codon positions. The resulting trees provide similar if not higher support for <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister than those obtained with just first and second positions. For example, using all three positions, the gamma rates ML tree analogous to Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref> gives 100% BS for <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister, and the ML distance based NJ tree analogous to Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref> gives 99% BS for <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister (trees available upon request). The most noteworthy shift towards stronger support involves ML analysis with equal rates, where inclusion of third positions changes the topology, from grasses-sister (with 61% BS; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>) to <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister (and with 100% support; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4D</xref>). We also conducted a few analyses of third positions only (again using the set of taxa analyzed by Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]). These too recovered <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister, with 100% BS using ML with either equal rates or gamma-distributed rates [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S6">Additional file 6</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Individual gene analyses</title><p>By taking rate heterogeneity into account or improving taxon sampling, we have shown that the concatenated genes dataset supports the <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister hypothesis, strongly so in most analyses. To explore the effects of phylogenetic methods and taxon sampling on individual gene analyses, we analyzed each of the 61 genes in the Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] dataset individually (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>). These much smaller subsets of data are, as expected, more sensitive than the concatenated dataset to the model of DNA evolution, taxon sampling, and inclusion/exclusion of third positions. Without appropriately taking these factors into account some genes give topologies that conflict with the current consensus view of plant phylogeny. With all three positions and using ML with four gamma-distributed rate categories, the highest likelihood tree in 29 of 61 genes is the <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister topology and only five genes give grasses-sister (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref>). The highest scoring trees for the remaining genes (most of which are short) place a wide variety of groups as sister, in nearly all cases with low BS (data not shown). Bootstrap support values and the number of trees having <italic>Amborella </italic>sister increase with gene length (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6A</xref>). When MP is used on the same datasets the opposite pattern is observed. Here, the grasses are sister in 27 of 61 trees, whereas <italic>Amborella </italic>is sister with only 12 genes (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref>). Excluding third positions results in the same trend in terms of MP versus ML, but the support values are much lower and the number of highly unlikely topologies is much higher (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S7">Additional file 7</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p><bold>Support for <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister or grasses-sister from the 61 chloroplast genes analyzed individually. </bold><bold>A</bold>. ML HKY85 analyses with four gamma-distributed rate categories. Parameter estimates were calculated individually for each gene in a manner analogous to that performed on the concatenated dataset. <bold>B</bold>. MP analyses. All three codon positions are included in all analyses shown in both figures. Solid red lines correspond to <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister and dashed blue lines to grasses-sister topologies.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2148-4-35-6"></graphic></fig><p>The single gene trees also illustrate the effect of taxon sampling. When <italic>Acorus </italic>is added and all three positions are used in ML analyses with four rate categories, none of the gene trees find monocots sister, whereas exactly half of the 40 genes put <italic>Amborella </italic>sister [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S8">Additional file 8</xref>, top figure]. When the third position is excluded, 12 genes put <italic>Amborella </italic>sister and BS levels drop significantly, while still no genes put monocots sister [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S8">Additional file 8</xref>, bottom figure]. Very similar results are obtained when the grasses are removed [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S9">Additional file 9</xref>]. In contrast to the parsimony results without <italic>Acorus </italic>(where grasses-sister is the favored topology; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6B</xref>), when <italic>Acorus </italic>is added and parsimony is used (with all three positions), only two genes put monocots sister (and both with low, 13 and 34%, BS), whereas 11 of 40 genes put <italic>Amborella </italic>sister [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S10">Additional file 10</xref>, top figure]. With <italic>Acorus </italic>added and grasses removed, 21 genes place <italic>Amborella </italic>sister and 1 places <italic>Acorus </italic>sister [see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S10">Additional file 10</xref>, bottom figure].</p></sec><sec><title>Addition of Nymphaea</title><p>While this manuscript was in the final stages of preparation, the chloroplast genome sequence of <italic>Nymphaea alba </italic>became available (released to EMBL database on July 13, 2004). This sequence was generated as part of a very recent study, also by Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>], in which it was added, as the only new sequence, to the same data matrix as analyzed in their earlier study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] and subjected to a similar set of phylogenetic analyses. Under these conditions, the grasses-sister topology was again recovered (and with 100% support) in nearly all analyses, with <italic>Nymphaea </italic>and <italic>Amborella </italic>recovered as sister taxa (also with 100% support). In their abstract, Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>] present these findings as supporting their prior conclusion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] that monocots are sister to the rest of angiosperms. However, their Discussion presents a more nuanced treatment than before, concluding that "we may be some ways from being confident of identifying the most basal angiosperms. Clearly the sequencing of genomes for more closely related outgroups and putatively basal angiosperms will be important for overcoming potential problems of model misspecification and long-branch attraction."</p><p>We carried out a limited set of analyses of the 14-taxa Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>] data matrix. We did so because of time constraints and because it became immediately clear from our relatively few analyses with <italic>Nymphaea </italic>that our main results and conclusions were entirely unchanged by its inclusion/exclusion. Using the Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>] methods, we also recovered the same, grasses-sister trees they reported (data not shown). However, when using analytical conditions described in the preceding sections, we never found grasses-sister (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref>). Instead, grasses were grouped with the other core angiosperms with strong BS (86&#x02013;100%). Interestingly, contrary to most published studies (see Background and Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>), <italic>Amborella </italic>alone did not emerge as sister to all other angiosperms in any of these analyses. Most commonly (Figs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7B,7C,7D</xref>), <italic>Amborella </italic>and <italic>Nymphaea </italic>together comprised the sister lineage to other angiosperms (with 66&#x02013;100% BS), whereas an equal-rates ML analysis found <italic>Nymphaea </italic>deepest (albeit with low, 47% BS) and <italic>Amborella </italic>next deepest (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7A</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p><bold>Inclusion of <italic>Nymphaea </italic>in analyses that account for rate heterogeneity. </bold><bold>A</bold>. ML HKY85 with no rate categories (cf. Fig. 4A). <bold>B</bold>. ML HYK85 with four gamma-distributed rate categories (cf. Fig. 4B). <bold>C</bold>. ML with estimated proportion of invariant sites (no gamma rate categories; cf. Fig. 4C). <bold>D</bold>. NJ using a ML HKY85 model with four gamma-distributed rate categories to calculate distances (cf. Fig. 3B). All analyses used first- and second-positions only.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2148-4-35-7"></graphic></fig></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>The grasses-sister topology is an LBA artifact</title><p>That long branch attraction can be a serious problem in phylogenetic inference has long been known to the systematics community, ever since this phenomenon was first explored by Felsenstein [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>]. Felsenstein described conditions of unequal evolutionary rates under which phylogenetic inference will result not only in an incorrect topology, but will converge asymptotically to the wrong phylogeny with increasing confidence as more data are added, ultimately producing 100% support for the wrong tree (hence, be <italic>positively </italic>misleading). Hendy and Penny [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>] showed that this phenomenon can occur for parsimony even under equal evolutionary rates if taxa are insufficiently sampled along a branch, while Lockhart et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>] showed that an ML equal-rates model can incorrectly join long branches when there is rate heterogeneity across sites. In the case of DNA sequence data, due to the limited number of character states, taxa with the greatest sequence divergence are expected to be "attracted" to each other by chance alone if long and short branches are sufficiently different in length. With large amounts of data, this can result in spurious, yet strongly supported, relationships.</p><p>We used two complementary approaches to test the hypothesis that the grasses-sister topology favored in the study of Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] is caused by spurious attraction of the long branches leading to angiosperms and to grasses. Both approaches were designed to make the most direct comparisons possible to their dataset and phylogenetic methodology. First, and most importantly, we found that &#x02013; even in the absence of corrections for rate heterogeneity &#x02013; addition of just one more monocot to their dataset produced trees strongly supportive of 1) the <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister topology and 2) the idea that the grasses-sister topology is a consequence of LBA causing a misrooting of angiosperms. When the monocot <italic>Acorus </italic>was directly substituted for grasses, strong support for <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister was obtained (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). This even occurred under analytical conditions that give strong support for grasses-sister when <italic>Acorus </italic>is not included. When <italic>Acorus </italic>and grasses were both included, two alternative, seemingly radically different topologies were obtained. Reconciliation of these topologies gets to the heart of the phylogenetic issues at hand. For as Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref> shows, these two topologies are actually entirely congruent with respect to relationships among the various angiosperms, differing only in where the outgroup branch attaches within angiosperms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">62</xref>], i.e., on the branches leading either to <italic>Amborella </italic>or to grasses (also see Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> and its treatment in Results).</p><fig position="float" id="F8"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p><bold>Competing hypotheses for the rooting of angiosperms showing the same underlying angiosperm topology when outgroups are excluded. </bold><bold>A</bold>. Rooting within monocots (Mono), on the branch between grasses and all other angiosperms (see Fig. 2C, whose BS values are shown here, and also Fig. 2F; also see Goremykin et al. [19]). <bold>B</bold>. Unrooted network, with arrow showing alternative rootings as in A and C. <bold>C</bold>. Canonical rooting on the branch between <italic>Amborella </italic>and the rest of angiosperms (see Fig. 2I, whose BS values are shown here, and also Fig. 2L). We emphasize that 100% BS was obtained for <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister and for monocot monophyly (compared to 79% and 78% in C) using ML methods that allow for site-to-site rate heterogeneity (e.g., Additional files 1&#x02013;3).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1471-2148-4-35-8"></graphic></fig><p>The <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister topology is in agreement with the many diverse phylogenetic studies summarized in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref> and in Background, except for that of Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. With <italic>Acorus </italic>included (Figs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2I</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2L</xref>), it also shows monocots as monophyletic, consistent with a large body of evidence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>], and depicts faster chloroplast DNA evolution on the monocot lineage leading to grasses than in the <italic>Acorus </italic>lineage, also consistent with a substantial body of evidence (e.g. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]). Conversely, the grasses-sister topology (Figs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2F</xref>) is consistent only with the Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] results, fails to recover monophyly of monocots [has them either paraphyletic (Figs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2F</xref>) or even polyphyletic (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3C</xref>), and always with 100% support], and fails to portray the known rapid evolution of chloroplast DNA in the lineages leading to grasses. All this leads us to conclude that the grasses-sister topology is almost certainly an artifact, most likely due to LBA between the long branches leading to grasses and to angiosperms.</p><p>Second, we reanalyzed the same dataset used by Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] and found that methods that account for rate heterogeneity across sites [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">64</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B67">67</xref>] put <italic>Amborella </italic>sister, usually with high BS (Figs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2J</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4C</xref>, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>; also see most Additional files). This was true for all 14 MODELTEST substitution models (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>) except for the simplest, JC model. When rates vary between sites, as with the chloroplast dataset under consideration, it is usually appropriate to model the evolutionary process to reflect this. The evolutionary models explored here point to LBA as the cause of the controversial grasses-sister topology and demonstrate that even with conservative corrections for rate heterogeneity, <italic>Amborella </italic>moves to the sister position within angiosperms (e.g., Figs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5B</xref>).</p><p>In summary, our two principal approaches for reassessing the results and analyses of Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] lead to what we regard as compelling evidence for two major conclusions. First, <italic>Amborella</italic>, not grasses, is the sister angiosperm among this set of taxa. Second, any tendency for angiosperms to root on grasses is an LBA artifact stemming from the confluence of limited taxon sampling, rapid evolution in grasses, a long branch between the outgroups and angiosperms, and rate heterogeneity across sites. Furthermore, we point out that while our manuscript was nearly finished, two independent papers appeared [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">68</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">69</xref>] that also challenged Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] and reached similar conclusions to our study. Both studies are complementary to ours, because instead of taking the Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] 61-gene chloroplast dataset as the starting point, as we did, they used a 3-gene dataset (the same two chloroplast genes and one nuclear gene) plus the Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] set of taxa as the starting point for a variety of taxon-sampling experiments. In addition, an important forthcoming study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">70</xref>] which added five new chloroplast genome sequences to the dataset of Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>], found "strong support" for the Amborella-sister topology. That four entirely independent studies, using a variety of taxon sets, character sets, and analytical approaches, all lead to such similar results and conclusions makes it all the more likely that the grasses-sister topology is indeed a phylogenetic artifact.</p></sec><sec><title>Is <italic>Amborella </italic>or <italic>Amborella</italic>+Nymphaeaceae sister to the rest of angiosperms?</title><p>Although our results reject grasses/monocots as the sister to all other angiosperms, support for <italic>Amborella </italic>as the first branch of angiosperm evolution must necessarily be qualified given the very limited sampling of whole chloroplast genomes (besides <italic>Amborella</italic>, only monocots, <italic>Calycanthus</italic>, and eudicots; see Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). There is still uncertainty as to the exact placement of <italic>Amborella </italic>relative to the other two deepest lineages of angiosperms, especially Nymphaeaceae [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>], although the overall weight of published evidence currently favors <italic>Amborella </italic>as <italic>the </italic>deepest angiosperm (see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>] and references in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). This uncertainty is heightened by our limited analyses that included <italic>Nymphaea </italic>and used methods that account for rate heterogeneity. These analyses never recovered an <italic>Amborella</italic>-sister topology. Instead, they most commonly found a sister clade comprising both <italic>Amborella </italic>and <italic>Nymphaea </italic>(Figs. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7B,7C,7D</xref>), or even found <italic>Nymphaea </italic>alone to be the sister-most angiosperm (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7A</xref>). Likewise, in the one analysis reported by Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>] in which <italic>Amborella </italic>and <italic>Nymphaea </italic>were found sister to the other angiosperms these two taxa clustered as sisters rather than forming a basal grade.</p><p>Clearly, then, the question of which group is sister to the rest of extant angiosperms should be regarded as unsettled and in need of further exploration, using much more data (such as whole chloroplast genomes from a large number of diverse angiosperms, as well as more mitochondrial and/or nuclear data) and better analytical methodologies as they become available. At the same time, we must face up to two serious limitations arising from extinction. First, <italic>Amborella trichopoda </italic>is the only known species in the entire Amborellaceae/Amborellales, i.e., it is the only taxon available whose DNA can be used to represent a lineage of ca. 150 million years in age arising at or near the base of angiosperms. Second, the stem branch leading to angiosperms is long in length and years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">62</xref>] (also approaching 150 million years) and thus represents a long-branch attractor, with the potential to spuriously attract other branches besides that leading to grasses. LBA between outgroup and ingroups is particularly insidious, because, as illustrated in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> (C and F vs. I and L), it tends to mask the long nature of the ingroup branches. <italic>Amborella </italic>does not show any evidence of having a long branch in published analyses with more extensive taxon sampling. It is nonetheless difficult to rule out (but see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]) the possibility that <italic>Amborella </italic>may be only near-sister among angiosperms (e.g., part of a Nymphaeaceae/<italic>Amborella </italic>clade that itself is the earliest branch of angiosperms; as suggested by Barkman et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>] and some of our analyses), with its generally sister position representing only a slight topological distortion (nearest neighbor interchange) caused by attraction to the long outgroup branch. For that matter, we point out (also see [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">71</xref>]) that the long branch leading to angiosperms also makes it difficult to rule out the possibility that the monophyletic-gymnosperm topologies recovered by multigene analyses (e.g., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">72</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B74">74</xref>]) might result from LBA between angiosperms and the outgroup branch leading to seed plants.</p></sec><sec><title>General implications</title><p>Many of our analyses, including all but one of the 61-gene concatenate analyses shown, included only first and second codon positions. This is because Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] chose to exclude third codon positions from their analyses, and because we wanted to make the most direct comparisons possible to their analyses. Third positions were excluded because most of the 61 chloroplast genes were claimed to be "very divergent" at synonymous sites (K<sub>s </sub>for most genes between <italic>Pinus </italic>and angiosperms was between 0.50 and 1.50 substitutions/site), which they felt could lead to "misleading" phylogenetic results. However, because our analyses with all three positions or only third positions gave such similar results to those using only first and second positions, we believe that for this particular dataset third positions are not contributing "excessive" homoplasy and leading to spurious affiliations. This conclusion is consistent with a considerable body of literature dealing with the phylogenetic utility of third positions in organellar genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75">75</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B80">80</xref>], while simulations have shown that "saturated" data can be very reliable, provided that taxon sampling is sufficiently high [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. Caution is nonetheless well advised in situations involving relatively sparse taxon sampling (some of which may be unavoidable, i.e., where extinction has been significant) and/or greater divergences than in this study. For example, chloroplast third positions are problematic in analyses across all of algal/plant evolution (e.g., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B81">81</xref>]), and even appear to be problematic at the relatively shallow level of seed plant phylogeny [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">73</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">82</xref>].</p><p>Our findings, and those of others [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">68</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">70</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B83">83</xref>], highlight the potential danger of phylogenetic analyses that employ lots of genes, but too few and/or the wrong taxa. Adequate taxon sampling is in a sense even more important here than with single or few-gene trees, because of the potential for even subtle systematic bias in a particular lineage's evolution to generate strongly supported misleading trees. Equally, if not more importantly, our results emphasize the crucial importance of using phylogenetic methods that best model the underlying molecular evolutionary processes, especially by accounting for site-to-site rate variation.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title>Sequencing chloroplast genes from <italic>Acorus</italic></title><p>We used long PCR to generate full-length or partial sequences from <italic>Acorus gramineus </italic>Soland. (a voucher specimen is deposited at the IND herbarium) for 22 of the 61 chloroplast genes analyzed by Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. Long PCRs were conducted using the AccuTaq&#x02122; LA DNA Polymerase (Sigma, Atlanta, GA, USA), following instructions provided by the manufacturer. Initially, sets of primers designed by Graham and Olmstead [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>], which cover a large portion of the chloroplast genome (<italic>psbC-D </italic>and <italic>psbE-J </italic>operons; from <italic>rpl2 </italic>to 3'-<italic>rps12 </italic>gene), as well as the primers described in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B84">84</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B87">87</xref>] for the <italic>rbcL</italic>, <italic>atpB</italic>, <italic>trnL-F</italic>, and <italic>trnE-D </italic>region, respectively, were used for amplifications and/or sequencing. For the most part, however, based on the initial sequences, a number of sequencing primers were designed and used for chromosome walking with long PCR products. Primer sequences are available upon request from SS. PCR products were separated by electrophoresis using 0.8% agarose gels, visualized with ethidium-bromide, and cleaned using Qiagen columns (Valencia, CA, USA). Cleaned products were then directly sequenced using the BigDye&#x02122; Terminator cycle sequencing kit (PE Applied Biosystem, Foster City, CA, USA) on an ABI 3100 DNA automated sequencer (PE Applied Biosystem, Foster City, CA, USA). Sequence data were edited and assembled using Sequencher&#x02122; 4.1 (Gene Codes Corporation, Ann Arbor, MI, USA). The <italic>Acorus </italic>sequences for these 22 chloroplast genes (<italic>atpA</italic>, <italic>atpE</italic>, <italic>clpP</italic>, <italic>cemA</italic>, <italic>lhbA</italic>, 3'-<italic>petB</italic>, <italic>petD</italic>, <italic>petG</italic>, <italic>petL</italic>, <italic>psaB</italic>, <italic>psaI</italic>, <italic>rpl20</italic>, <italic>rpoA</italic>, <italic>rpoB</italic>, <italic>rpoC1</italic>, <italic>rpoC2</italic>, <italic>rps2</italic>, <italic>rps14</italic>, <italic>rps18</italic>, <italic>rps19</italic>, <italic>ycf3</italic>, <italic>ycf4</italic>) are deposited in GenBank (accession numbers AY757810-AY757831). These were combined for phylogenetic analyses with full-length or partial <italic>Acorus </italic>sequences already available in GenBank for 18 other chloroplast genes [AF123843 (<italic>psbB</italic>, <italic>psbT</italic>, <italic>psbN</italic>, <italic>psbH</italic>), AF123771 (<italic>rps7</italic>, 3'-<italic>rps12</italic>), AF123828 (<italic>psbE</italic>, <italic>psbF</italic>, <italic>psbL</italic>), AF123813 (<italic>psbD</italic>, <italic>psbC</italic>), AF123785 (<italic>rpl2</italic>), D28866 (<italic>rbcL</italic>), X84107 (<italic>rps4</italic>), U96631 (<italic>psbA</italic>), AB040155 (<italic>matK</italic>), AF197616 (<italic>atpB</italic>), and AJ344261 (<italic>psaA</italic>)]. The 40 <italic>Acorus </italic>genes used here come from two closely related species &#x02013; <italic>A. calamus </italic>(14 genes) and <italic>A. gramineus </italic>(26 genes) &#x02013; and correspond to 65.6% (40/61) of the genes and 71.4% (32,072/44,937) of the nucleotide characters analyzed by Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Alignment</title><p>For all first and second codon position analyses, the data matrix provided by V. Goremykin was used without modification. For analyses that included <italic>Acorus</italic>, the <italic>Acorus </italic>genes were individually aligned with the individually extracted gene alignments from the Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] dataset using CLUSTALW [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B88">88</xref>], and the resulting gene alignments were concatenated to regenerate a matrix identical to the original except for the extra row containing <italic>Acorus</italic>. Using the same procedure, <italic>Acorus </italic>was also added to the amino acid matrix provided by V. Goremykin. The relevant 61 chloroplast genes of <italic>Nymphaea </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>] were likewise added to both alignments.</p><p>We also constructed a new matrix consisting of all three codon positions by extracting genes from 13 sequenced chloroplast genomes of land plants (GenBank numbers: AP002983, AP000423, AJ271079, Z00044, AJ400848, AJ506156, AJ428413, X86563, AB042240, X15901, D17510, AP004638, X04465), aligning them, and hand editing apparent mistakes. The first and second position version of this matrix was nearly identical to the Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] matrix, except for a few minor differences (the overall length was slightly shorter due to removal of terminal extensions that either were created by single taxon indels or where multiple extending genes were nonhomologous). All phylogenetic trees resulting from this first and second position matrix and the Goremykin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>] matrix were identical in topology and nearly identical in BS values. All alignments used in this study are available in Nexus format upon request of DWR.</p></sec><sec><title>Phylogenetic analyses</title><p>Phylogenetic analyses were performed in PAUP* 4.0b10 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]. Unless specified, all nucleotide-based trees were built using only first- and second-codon positions. For ML analyses, parameters were initially estimated using an equal-weighted parsimony tree. A ML tree was then built, and parameters were re-estimated using this tree if it differed from the parsimony tree. This iteration was continued until the last two topologies converged (the final ML topology was almost always equal to the one in which the ML parameters were estimated from the parsimony topology). For all ML analyses we also calculated a NJ tree using distances calculated from the ML model being tested. For DNA and protein parsimony the default PAUP* 4.0b10 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>] step matrices were used.</p><p>Bootstrap support [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B89">89</xref>] was estimated with 100 replicates using parameters estimated from the final topology. Thus the methodology cited for a particular tree refers to the model used for the bootstrap replicates. For parsimony and ML searches the heuristic algorithm was used with simple and as-is stepwise addition, respectively; tree bisection-reconnection swapping; and no limit on the number of trees saved in memory. Unless specified, the default PAUP* settings were used in all analyses. An automated script (available upon request from DWR) was used to run the analyses. Detailed log files and trees of each analysis were saved and are available upon request from DWR. Most analyses were performed on two 3 GHz Linux machines. Treetool [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B90">90</xref>] was used for viewing and printing trees.</p><p>The Shimodaira-Hasegawa (SH) test [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>] was performed using the "lscores" command of PAUP* with the options SHTest = RELL and BootReps = 10000. ML parameters being tested were estimated on each topology to calculate its own log likelihood except where otherwise specified.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Abbreviations</title><p>BS &#x02013; bootstrap support; LBA &#x02013; long branch attraction; ML &#x02013; maximum likelihood; MP &#x02013; maximum parsimony; NJ &#x02013; neighbor joining; Ti/Tv &#x02013; transition:transversion; NT &#x02013; nucleotides; Plnvar &#x02013; proportion of invariant sites</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>SS generated the new sequences (from <italic>Acorus</italic>) used in this study and conceived and drafted the first and last figures. DWR carried out the phylogenetic analyses and made all other figures. All three authors contributed to the overall design of the study, drafted parts of the manuscript, and read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1"><caption><title>Additional File 1</title><p><bold>Trees from truncated matrix with <italic>Acorus</italic></bold>. These first- and second-position trees show that the results are essentially the same when positions that have <italic>Acorus </italic>data missing are removed. The first row using the ML HKY85 model is with four rate categories and parameters estimated as described in Methods. The third row uses the ML model parameters calculated as in the first row to calculate a distance matrix that was used for NJ analyses. For comparison the corresponding bootstrap values for <italic>Amborella </italic>sister to the angiosperms in the full matrix, going across each row, are 1. (99 vs. 100, 100 vs. 100), 2. (NA but same topology and similar BS, 100 vs. 100), 3. (86 vs. 88, 84 vs. 90).</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-4-35-S1.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S2"><caption><title>Additional File 2</title><p><bold>Trees from truncated RY-coded matrix with <italic>Acorus </italic>included</bold>. This are the same analyses as in Additional file 1 except the DNA is RY-coded. For comparison, the corresponding BS values for the <italic>Amborella </italic>sister relationship in the full matrix, along each row, are: 1. (100 vs. 100, 100 vs. 100), 2 (98 vs. 100, 100 vs. 100), 3. (100 vs. 100, 100 vs. 100). </p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-4-35-S2.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S3"><caption><title>Additional File 3</title><p><bold>Comparison of gamma-distributed rates with two versus four rate categories</bold>. This figure shows that using two rate categories gives essentially the same results as using four rate categories with this dataset. The dataset is the first- and second-position, 61-gene matrix with grasses, <italic>Acorus</italic>, or both used to represent monocots. The ML HKY85 model was used and parameters were estimated as described in Methods.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-4-35-S3.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S4"><caption><title>Additional File 4</title><p><bold>Trees when constant sites are removed from the first- and second-position matrix of Goremykin et al. [19]</bold>. <bold>A</bold>. ML HKY85 and equal rates. <bold>B</bold>. NJ with distances calculated using an ML HKY85 model and equal rates.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-4-35-S4.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S5"><caption><title>Additional File 5</title><p><bold>NJ analysis using ML proportion of invariant distances</bold>. Distances were calculated using the ML HKY85 model, the estimated proportion of invariant sites, and the first- and second-position matrix of Goremykin et al. [19].</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-4-35-S5.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S6"><caption><title>Additional File 6</title><p><bold>ML trees using third positions only</bold>. <bold>A</bold>. HKY85 model with equal rates. <bold>B</bold>. HKY85 model with four gamma-distributed rates.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-4-35-S6.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S7"><caption><title>Additional File 7</title><p><bold>Sister group to the rest of angiosperms found in individual gene analyses using first- and second-position data without <italic>Acorus </italic></bold><bold>Top</bold>, ML HKY85 with four gamma-distributed rates. <bold>Bottom</bold>, Parsimony analysis.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-4-35-S7.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S8"><caption><title>Additional File 8</title><p><bold>Sister group to the rest of angiosperms found in individual gene analyses using the ML HKY85 model with four gamma-distributed rates and <italic>Acorus </italic>added</bold>. <bold>Top</bold>, all three positions. <bold>Bottom</bold>, first and second positions.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-4-35-S8.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S9"><caption><title>Additional File 9</title><p><bold>Sister group to the rest of angiosperms found in individual gene analyses using the ML HKY85 model with four gamma-distributed rates with <italic>Acorus </italic>added and grasses removed</bold>. <bold>Top</bold>, all three positions. <bold>Bottom</bold>, first and second positions.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-4-35-S9.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S10"><caption><title>Additional File 10</title><p><bold>Sister group to the rest of angiosperms found in individual gene analyses using parsimony on all three positions</bold>. <bold>Top</bold>, <italic>Acorus </italic>added. <bold>Bottom</bold>, <italic>Acorus </italic>added and grasses excluded.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1471-2148-4-35-S10.pdf" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We thank Ulfar Bergthorsson, Eric Knox, and Richard Olmstead for useful comments on earlier versions of the manuscript, and Vadim Goremykin for providing the 61-gene data matrices that were the starting point for this study. Funding for this work came from National Institutes of Health grant GM-35087 to J.D.P.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mathews</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Donoghue</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The root of angiosperm phylogeny inferred from duplicate phytochrome genes</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1999</year><volume>286</volume><fpage>947</fpage><lpage>950</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10542147</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.286.5441.947</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mathews</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Donoghue</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Basal angiosperm phylogeny inferred from duplicate phytochromes A and C</article-title><source>Int J Plant Sci</source><year>2000</year><volume>161</volume><fpage>S41</fpage><lpage>S55</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/317582</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parkinson</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Adams</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multigene analyses identify the three earliest lineages of extant flowering plants</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>1999</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1485</fpage><lpage>1488</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10607592</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0960-9822(00)80119-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qiu Y-L</surname><given-names>JLee</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernasconi-Quadroni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Zanis</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmer</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Savolainen</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The earliest angiosperms: evidence from mitochondrial, plastid and nuclear genomes</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1999</year><volume>402</volume><fpage>404</fpage><lpage>407</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10586879</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/46536</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qiu Y-L</surname><given-names>JLee</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernasconi-Quadroni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Zanis</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmer</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Savolainen</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogeny of basal angiosperms: analyses of five genes from three genomes</article-title><source>Int J Plant Sci</source><year>2000</year><volume>161</volume><fpage>S3</fpage><lpage>S27</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/317584</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Angiosperm phylogeny inferred from multiple genes as a research tool for comparative biology</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1999</year><volume>402</volume><fpage>402</fpage><lpage>404</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10586878</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/46528</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Zanis</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Basal lineages of angiosperms: relationships and implications for floral evolution</article-title><source>Am J Bot</source><year>2000</year><volume>161</volume><fpage>S97</fpage><lpage>S107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/317581</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barkman</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Chenery</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>McNeal</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyons-Weiler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellisens</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolfe</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>dePamphilis</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Independent and combined analyses of sequences from all three genomic compartments converge on the root of flowering plant phylogeny</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>13166</fpage><lpage>13171</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11069280</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.220427497</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Olmstead</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Utility of 17 chloroplast genes for inferring the phylogeny of the basal angiosperms</article-title><source>Am J Bot</source><year>2000</year><volume>87</volume><fpage>1712</fpage><lpage>1730</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11080123</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitlock</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernasconi-Quadroni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Dombrovska</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Was the ANITA rooting of the angiosperm phylogeny affected by long-branch attraction?</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2001</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>1745</fpage><lpage>1753</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11504854</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borsch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilu</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Quandt</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilde</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Neinhuis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Barthlott</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Noncoding plastid trnT-trnF sequences reveal a well resolved phylogeny of basal angiosperms</article-title><source>J Evol Biol</source><year>2003</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>558</fpage><lpage>576</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14632220</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1420-9101.2003.00577.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zanis</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathews</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Donoghue</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The root of the angiosperms revisited</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2002</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>6848</fpage><lpage>6853</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12011443</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.092136399</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zanis</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogenetic analyses and perianth evolution in basal angiosperms</article-title><source>Ann Mo Bot Gard</source><year>2003</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>129</fpage><lpage>150</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hilu</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name><name><surname>Borsch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Savolainen</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Alice</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauquet</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Neinhuis</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Slotta</surname><given-names>TAB</given-names></name><name><surname>Rohwer</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chatrou</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Angiosperm phylogeny based on matK sequence information</article-title><source>Am J Bot</source><year>2003</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>1758</fpage><lpage>1776</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nickerson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Drouin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The sequence of the largest subunit of RNA polymerase II is a useful marker for inferring seed plant phylogeny</article-title><source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source><year>2004</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>415</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15062783</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ympev.2003.08.013</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stellari</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaramillo</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kramer</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of the APETALA3 and PISTILLATA lineages of MADS-box-containing genes in the basal angiosperms</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2004</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>506</fpage><lpage>519</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14694075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msh044</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Uehara</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Imafuku</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasebe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogeny and divergence of basal angiosperms inferred from APETALA3- and PISTILLATA-like MADS-box genes</article-title><source>J Plant Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>229</fpage><lpage>244</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15138844</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10265-004-0153-7</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Judd</surname><given-names>Walter S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kellogg</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name><name><surname>Donoghue</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><source>Plant systematics : a phylogenetic approach</source><year>2002</year><edition>2nd</edition><publisher-name>Sunderland, Mass., Sinauer Associates</publisher-name><fpage>xvi, 576</fpage></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goremykin</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirsch-Ernst</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name><name><surname>W&#x000f6;lfl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellwig</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of the Amborella trichopoda chloroplast genome sequence suggests that Amborella is not a basal angiosperm</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2003</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1499</fpage><lpage>1505</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12832641</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msg159</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hillis</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inferring complex phylogenies</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1996</year><volume>383</volume><fpage>130</fpage><lpage>131</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8774876</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/383130a0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hillis</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Taxonomic sampling, phylogenetic accuracy, and investigator bias</article-title><source>Syst Biol</source><year>1998</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12064238</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/106351598260987</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graybeal</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Is it better to add taxa or characters to a difficult phylogenetic problem?</article-title><source>Syst Biol</source><year>1998</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12064243</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/106351598260996</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pollock</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Zwickl</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>McGuire</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillis</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increased taxon sampling is advantageous for phylogenetic inference</article-title><source>Syst Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>664</fpage><lpage>671</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12228008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10635150290102357</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zwickl</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillis</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increased taxon sampling greatly reduces phylogenetic error</article-title><source>Syst Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>588</fpage><lpage>598</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12228001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10635150290102339</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dahlgren</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bremer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Major clades of angiosperms</article-title><source>Cladistics</source><year>1985</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>349</fpage><lpage>368</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Donoghue</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seed plant phylogeny and the origin of angiosperms: an experimental cladistic approach</article-title><source>Bot Rev</source><year>1986</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>431</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loconte</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cladistics of the Spermatophyta</article-title><source>Brittonia</source><year>1990</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>211</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nixon</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><name><surname>Crepet</surname><given-names>WL</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Friis</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A reevaluation of seed plant phylogeny</article-title><source>Ann Missouri Bot Garden</source><year>1994</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>484</fpage><lpage>533</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Olmstead</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Morgan</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Les</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mishler</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Duvall</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hills</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Kron</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rettig</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Conti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Manhart</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sytsma</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Michaels</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kress</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Karol</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Hedren</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaut</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wimpee</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Furnier</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>QY</given-names></name><name><surname>Plunkett</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Swensen</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Gadek</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Quinn</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Eguiarte</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Golenberg</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Learn</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>SCH</given-names></name><name><surname>Dayanandan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogenetics of seed plants - an analysis of nucleotide-sequences from the plastid gene rbcL</article-title><source>Ann Mo Bot Gard</source><year>1993</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>528</fpage><lpage>580</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Nickrent</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoot</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Sweere</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuzoff</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kron</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Swensen</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmer</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaw</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gillespie</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kress</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sytsma</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Angiosperm phylogeny inferred from 18S ribosomal DNA sequences</article-title><source>Ann Mo Bot Gard</source><year>1997</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>49</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Savolainen</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoot</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bayer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fay</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>deBruijn</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogenetics of flowering plants based upon a combined analysis of plastid atpB and rbcL gene sequences</article-title><source>Syst Biol</source><year>2000</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>306</fpage><lpage>362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12118410</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10635159950173861</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaut</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Muse</surname><given-names>SV</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Clegg</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relative rates of nucleotide substitution at the rbcL locus of monocotyledonous plants</article-title><source>J Mol Evol</source><year>1992</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>292</fpage><lpage>303</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1404415</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00161167</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>LQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pond</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaut</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A survey of the molecular evolutionary dynamics of twenty-five multigene families from four grass taxa</article-title><source>J Mol Evol</source><year>2001</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>144</fpage><lpage>156</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11231894</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eyre-Walker</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaut</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Felsenstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Correlated rates of synonymous site evolution across plant genomes</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>1997</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>455</fpage><lpage>460</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9100375</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaw</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Parkinson</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seed plant phylogeny inferred from all three plant genomes: monophyly of extant gymnosperms and origin of Gnetales from conifers</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>4086</fpage><lpage>4091</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10760277</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.97.8.4086</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Olmstead</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>SCH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Rooting phylogenetic trees with distant outgroups: A case study from the commelinoid monocots</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2002</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1769</fpage><lpage>1781</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12270903</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Felsenstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cases in which parsimony or compatibility methods will be positively misleading</article-title><source>Syst Zool</source><year>1978</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>401</fpage><lpage>410</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Felsenstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Parsimony in systematics: biological and statistical issues</article-title><source>Annu Rev Ecol Syst</source><year>1983</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>313</fpage><lpage>333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.es.14.110183.001525</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hendy</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Penny</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A framework for the quantitative study of evolutionary trees</article-title><source>Syst Zool</source><year>1989</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>296</fpage><lpage>309</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goremykin</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirsch-Ernst</surname><given-names>KI</given-names></name><name><surname>W&#x000f6;lfl</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellwig</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The chloroplast genome of Nymphaea alba: Whole-genome analyses and the problem of identifying the most basal angiosperm</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2004</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1445</fpage><lpage>1454</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15084683</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msh147</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duvall</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Clegg</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name><name><surname>Kress</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hills</surname><given-names>HG</given-names></name><name><surname>Eguiarte</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaut</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmer</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Learn</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogenetic hypotheses for the monocotyledons constructed from rbcL sequence data</article-title><source>Ann Mo Bot Gard</source><year>1993</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>607</fpage><lpage>619</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Angiosperm Phylogeny Group (APG)</collab></person-group><article-title>An update of the Phylogeny Group classification for the orders and families of flowering plants: APGII</article-title><source>Bot J Linn Soc</source><year>2003</year><volume>141</volume><fpage>399</fpage><lpage>436</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1095-8339.2003.t01-1-00158.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Monocot relationships: an overview</article-title><source>Am J Bot</source><year>2004</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>1645</fpage><lpage>1655</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B44"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudall</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fay</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Givinish</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Systma</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pires</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Wilson K L and Morrison D A</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Higher-level systematics of the monocotyledons: an assessment of current knowledge and new classification</article-title><source>Monocots: systematics and evolution</source><year>2000</year><publisher-name>Collingwood, Australia, CSIRO Publishing</publisher-name><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>16</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B45"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Swofford</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><source>PAUP*: Phylogenetic analysis using parsimony (* and other methods). Version 4.0b10.</source><year>2003</year><publisher-name>Sunderland, Massachusetts, Sinauer Associates</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B46"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jukes</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cantor</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Munro H N</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of protein molecules</article-title><source>Mammalian Protein Metabolism</source><year>1969</year><publisher-name>New York, Academic Press</publisher-name><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>132</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Felsenstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolutionary trees from DNA sequences: a maximum likelihood approach</article-title><source>J Mol Evol</source><year>1981</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>368</fpage><lpage>376</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7288891</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tajima</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimation of evolutionary distance between nucleotide sequences</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>1984</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>285</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6599968</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A simple method for estimating evolutionary rates of base substitutions through comparative studies of nucleotide sequences</article-title><source>J Mol Evol</source><year>1980</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7463489</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Felsenstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distance methods for inferring phylogenies - a justification</article-title><source>Evolution</source><year>1984</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>24</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kishino</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yano</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dating of the human-ape splitting by a molecular clock of mitochondrial DNA</article-title><source>J Mol Evol</source><year>1985</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>160</fpage><lpage>174</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3934395</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B52"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimation of evolutionary distances between homologous nucleotide sequences</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>1981</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>454</fpage><lpage>458</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6165991</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nei</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimation of the number of nucleotide substitutions in the control region of mitochondrial DNA in humans and chimpanzees</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>1993</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>512</fpage><lpage>526</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8336541</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B54"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lanave</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Preparata</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Saccone</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Serio</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new method for calculating evolutionary substitution rates</article-title><source>J Mol Evol</source><year>1984</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6429346</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B55"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Marin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Medina</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The general stochastic model of nucleotide substitution</article-title><source>J Theor Biol</source><year>1990</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>485</fpage><lpage>501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2338834</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B56"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steel</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recovering a tree from the leaf colourations it generates under a Markov model</article-title><source>App Math Lett</source><year>1994</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>19</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0893-9659(94)90024-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B57"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lockhart</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Steel</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Penny</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Hendy</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recovering evolutionary trees under a more realistic model of sequence evolution</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>1994</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>605</fpage><lpage>612</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B58"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Posada</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Crandall</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MODELTEST: testing the model of DNA substitution</article-title><source>Bioinformatics</source><year>1998</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>817</fpage><lpage>818</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9918953</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/14.9.817</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B59"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shimodaira</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple comparisons of log-likelihoods with applications to phylogenetic inference</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>1999</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>1114</fpage><lpage>1116</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B60"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Maximum likelihood phylogenetic estimation from DNA sequences with variable rates over sites - approximate methods</article-title><source>J MOL EVOL J MOL EVOL</source><year>1994</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>306</fpage><lpage>314</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00160154</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B61"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lockhart</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Larkum</surname><given-names>AWD</given-names></name><name><surname>Steel</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Waddell</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Penny</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolution of chlorophyll and bacteriochlorophyll: The problem of invariant sites in sequence analysis</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1996</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>1930</fpage><lpage>1934</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8700861</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.93.5.1930</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B62"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Qiu</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name><name><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Les</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Parks</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular Phylogenetics of the Magnoliidae: Cladistic Analyses of Nucleotide Sequences of the Plastid Gene rbcL</article-title><source>Ann Mo Bot Gard</source><year>1993</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>587</fpage><lpage>606</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B63"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stevenson</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Loconte</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Rudall P J, Cribb P J, Cutler D F and Humphries C J</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Cladistic analysis of monocot families</article-title><source>Monocotyledons: systematics and evolution</source><year>1995</year><publisher-name>Kew, UK, Royal Botanical Gardens</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B64"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Among-site rate variation and its impact on phylogenetic analyses</article-title><source>Trends Ecol Evol</source><year>1996</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>372</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0169-5347(96)10041-0</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B65"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Felsenstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Taking variation of evolutionary rates between sites into account in inferring phylogenies</article-title><source>J Mol Evol</source><year>2001</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>447</fpage><lpage>455</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11675604</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s002390010234</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B66"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buckley</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chambers</surname><given-names>GK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exploring among-site rate variation models in a maximum likelihood framework using empirical data: Effects of model assumptions on estimates of topology, branch lengths, and bootstrap support</article-title><source>Syst Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>86</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12116595</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/106351501750107495</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B67"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Maximum likelihood estimation of phylogenetic trees is consistent when substitution rates vary according to the invariable sites plus gamma distribution</article-title><source>Syst Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>713</fpage><lpage>722</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12116941</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/106351501753328839</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B68"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Amborella not a "basal angiosperm"? Not so fast</article-title><source>Am J Bot</source><year>2004</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>997</fpage><lpage>1001</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B69"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Degtjareva</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Samigullin</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Sokoloff</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Valiejo-Roman</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene sampling versus taxon sampling: Is Amborella (Amborellaceae) a sister group to all other extant angiosperms.</article-title><source>Botanichesky Zhurnal</source><year>2004</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>896</fpage><lpage>907</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B70"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>dePamphilis</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Raubeson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Leebens-Mack</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>McNeal</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Boore</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuehl</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The utility of whole chloroplast genome sequencing for reconstructing deep nodes in plants with an example from basal angiosperms [abstract]</article-title><source>Botony 2004</source><year>2004</year><publisher-name>Salt Lake City, Utah, Botanical Society of America</publisher-name><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.2004.botanyconference.org/engine/search/index.php?func=detail&#x00026;aid=308"/></citation></ref><ref id="B71"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donoghue</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Doyle</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seed plant phylogeny: demise of the anthophyte hypothesis?</article-title><source>Curr Biol</source><year>2000</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>R106</fpage><lpage>R109</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10679315</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0960-9822(00)00304-3</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B72"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bowe</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Coat</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>dePamphilis</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogeny of seed plants based on all three genomic compartments: Extant gymnosperms are monophyletic and Gnetales' closest relatives are conifers</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><year>2000</year><volume>97</volume><fpage>4092</fpage><lpage>4097</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10760278</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.97.8.4092</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B73"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Zanis</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogeny of seed plants based on evidence from eight genes</article-title><source>Am J Bot</source><year>2002</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>1670</fpage><lpage>1681</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B74"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burleigh</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathews</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogenetic signal in nucleotide data from seed plants: implications for resolving the seed plant tree of life</article-title><source>Am J Bot</source><year>2004</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>1599</fpage><lpage>1613</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B75"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoder</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Vilgalys</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruvolo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular evolutionary dynamics of cytochrome b in strepsirrhine primates: the phylogenetic significance of third-position transversions</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>1996</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1339</fpage><lpage>1350</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8952078</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B76"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olmstead</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Reeves</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yen</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Soltis Douglas E, Soltis Pamela S and Doyle Jeff J</surname></name></person-group><article-title>Patterns of sequence evolution and implications for parsimony analysis of chloroplast DNA</article-title><source>Molecular systematics of plants II : DNA sequencing</source><year>1998</year><publisher-name>Boston, Kluwer Academic Publishers</publisher-name><fpage>164</fpage><lpage>187</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B77"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>K&#x000e4;llersj&#x000f6;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Farris</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Bremer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Fay</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Humphries</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Seberg</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Bremer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Simultaneous parsimony jackknife analysis of 2538 rbcL DNA sequences reveals support for major clades of green plants, land plants, seed plants and flowering plants</article-title><source>Plant Syst Evol</source><year>1998</year><volume>213</volume><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>287</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B78"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>K&#x000e4;llersj&#x000f6;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Farris</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Homoplasy increases phylogenetic structure</article-title><source>Cladistics</source><year>1999</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/clad.1999.0085</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B79"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Savolainen</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Chase</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Salamin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>F&#x000e9;drigo</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Naylor</surname><given-names>GJP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogeny reconstruction and functional constraints in organellar genomes: plastid atpB and rbcL sequences versus animal mitochondrion</article-title><source>Syst Biol</source><year>2002</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>638</fpage><lpage>647</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12228005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/10635150290102348</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B80"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanderson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wojciechowski</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Error, bias, and long-branch attraction in data for two chloroplast photosystem genes in seed plants</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2000</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>782</fpage><lpage>797</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10779539</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B81"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delwiche</surname><given-names>CF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuhsel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogenetic analysis of tufA sequences indicates a cyanobacterial origin of all plastids</article-title><source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source><year>1995</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>110</fpage><lpage>128</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7663757</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/mpev.1995.1012</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B82"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Magall&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanderson</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationships among seed plants inferred from highly conserved genes: sorting conflicting phylogenetic signals among ancient lineages</article-title><source>Am J Bot</source><year>2002</year><volume>89</volume><fpage>1991</fpage><lpage>2006</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B83"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Delsuc</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Penny</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-scale phylogeny and the detection of systematic biases</article-title><source>Mol Biol Evol</source><year>2004</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>1455</fpage><lpage>1458</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15084674</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/molbev/msh137</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B84"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taberlet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gielly</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pautou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouvet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Universal primers for amplification of the non-coding regions of chloroplast DNA</article-title><source>Pl Mol Biol</source><year>1991</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1105</fpage><lpage>1109</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00037152</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B85"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olmstead</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Michaels</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Monophyly of the Asteridae and identification of their major lineages inferred from DNA sequences of rbcL</article-title><source>Ann Missouri Bot Garden</source><year>1992</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>249</fpage><lpage>265</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B86"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoot</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Culham</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Crane</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The utility of atpB gene sequences in phylogenetic relationships: comparison with rbcL and 18S ribosomal DNA sequences in Lardizabalaceae</article-title><source>Ann Mo Bot Gard</source><year>1995</year><volume>82</volume><fpage>194</fpage><lpage>207</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B87"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yen</surname><given-names>AC-T</given-names></name></person-group><source>Molecular systematics of Cyperaceae tribe Cariceae and genus Carex</source><year>1999</year><publisher-name>Seattle, Washington, University of Washington</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B88"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CLUSTAL W: improving the sensitivity of progressive multiple sequence alignment through sequence weighting, position-specific gap penalties and weight matrix choice</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1994</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>4673</fpage><lpage>4680</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7984417</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B89"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Felsenstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Confidence limits on phylogenies: an approach using the bootstrap</article-title><source>Evolution</source><year>1985</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>783</fpage><lpage>791</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B90"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maciukenas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>TREETOOL: a phylogenetic data visualizer, editor, and tree formatter</article-title><year>1994</year><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://iubio.bio.indiana.edu/soft/molbiol/unix/treetool"/></citation></ref><ref id="B91"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Soltis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The origin and diversification of angiosperms</article-title><source>Am J Bot</source><year>2004</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>1614</fpage><lpage>1626</lpage></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



