<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Neurol</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Neurology</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2377</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15347428</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC517935</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1471-2377-4-11</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2377-4-11</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Effects of age and leg length upon central loop of the Gastrocnemius-soleus H-reflex latency</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sadeghi</surname><given-names>Shahram</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>SHSADEGHI@SUMS.AC.IR</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ghavanini</surname><given-names>Mohammadrezaalavian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>alavianm@sums.ac.ir</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ashraf</surname><given-names>Alireza</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>ALIREZAASHRAF@YAHOO.COM</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jafari</surname><given-names>Peyman</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>PJBIOSTAT@YAHOO.CO.UK</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Pain research group, multidisciplinary pain clinic of iran jahad danesh gahi, no 31, karimkhan zand ave. shahid hosseini alley, Tehran, Iran</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of physical medicine and rehabilitaton, shiraz medical school, zand avenue, Shiraz, Iran</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Department of biostatistics, shiraz medical school, zand avenue, Shiraz, Iran</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>3</day><month>9</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>11</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2377/4/11"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>5</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>3</day><month>9</month><year>2004</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2004 Sadeghi et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2004</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Sadeghi et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Sadeghi
               Shahram
               
               SHSADEGHI@SUMS.AC.IR
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Effects of age and leg length upon central loop of the Gastrocnemius-soleus H-reflex latency
         </dc:title><dc:date>2004</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>BMC Neurology 4(1): 11-. (2004)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1471-2377(2004)4:1&#x0003c;11&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1471-2377</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>central loop of the gastrocnemius-soleus H-reflex latency (T<sub>c</sub>) that looks promising in the diagnosis of S1 radiculopathy; has been investigated in a few studies and only two of them have focused on the constitutional factors affecting it. Although leg length has been shown to contribute to the T<sub>c</sub>, the role of age is controversial. More confusing, none of the previously performed studies have used strict criteria to rule out subclinical neuropathy, so the results could be misleading. This study has been performed to determine the influence of leg length and age on T<sub>c </sub>among a carefully selected group of healthy volunteers.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>after screening forty six volunteers by taking history, physical examination and a brief electrophysiologic study; forty of them were selected to enroll into the study. T<sub>c </sub>was obtained in all the study subjects and leg length and age were recorded for correlational analyses.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>this group was consisted of 26 males (65%) and 14 females (35%) with the age range of 19&#x02013;65 years (Mean &#x000b1; SD: 37 &#x000b1; 10.7) and leg length range of 29.5&#x02013;43 centimeters (36.4 &#x000b1; 3.4).</p><p>Mean &#x000b1; SD for T<sub>c </sub>was 6.78 &#x000b1; 0.3. We found a significant correlation between T<sub>c </sub>and leg length (p value= 0.003, r = 0.49 and confidence interval 95% = 0.59&#x02013;0.88), no significant correlation was found between age and T<sub>c </sub>(p value= 0.48, r = 0.11), also we obtained the regression equation as: T<sub>c </sub>= 0.04L + 5.28</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>in contrast to leg length, age was not correlated with T<sub>c</sub>. Future studies are required to delineate other contributing factors to T<sub>c</sub>.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>central loop of gastrocnemius-soleus H-reflex latency</kwd><kwd>Central S1 loop latency</kwd><kwd>sacral radiculopathy</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>The H-Reflex evaluates S<sub>1 </sub>radiculopathy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>]. The measured latency, however, is neither specific nor sensitive for S<sub>1 </sub>spinal nerve disease, as it traverses a long pathway. Pease et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>] were the first who described the central loop of the gastrocnemius-soleus H-Reflex latency (Central S<sub>1 </sub>loop latency or T<sub>c</sub>) and suggested it might be promising in the diagnosis of S1 radiculopathy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>].</p><p>Unfortunately, T<sub>c </sub>has been the subject of few studies, and as far as we know, only 5 articles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>] have been published on this issue so far. Among them, two have specifically evaluated the constitutional factors contributing to T<sub>c</sub>. Leg length has been shown to have a significant effect on T<sub>c</sub>. It is controversial whether age entails a similar effect. Wang et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>] found a direct correlation between age and Tc. This observation was not confirmed by Ghavanini et al in an independent study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>].</p><p>The current study has been performed to determine the influence of leg length and age on T<sub>c</sub>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>We enrolled 46 volunteers to this study after obtaining informed consent. Following a standard history taking, all of them underwent physical examination and a brief electrophysiologic evaluation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>] to rule out asymptomatic polyneuropathy, including determination of: right peroneal nerve conduction velocity (PNCV), distal motor latency of right deep peroneal nerve (PDML) and standard gastrocnemius-soleus H reflex latency (T<sub>p</sub>). We defined our exclusion criteria as: history of sacral radiculopathy or diabetes mellitus or any other disease with potential to cause neuropathy, any abnormality in neurological or musculoskeletal physical examination, or any of the following findings: PNCV less than 40 m/s, PDML more than 5 ms or prolonged T<sub>p </sub>(according to Braddom and Johnson's study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>].</p><p>Since we were supposed to rule out subclinical peripheral neuropathy and one component of the related electrodiagnostic study was measuring the distal motor latency for the deep peroneal nerve, the temperature at the dorsum of the foot was kept almost at 32&#x000b0;Celsius.</p><p>The leg length of each person was measured as the distance from middle of the midpopliteal crease to the point at the most proximal part of the medial malleolus, in centimeters.</p><p>Subject's age to the nearest year was also recorded.</p><p>For obtaining T<sub>c</sub>, we used DANTEC 2000 c equipment, the sensitivity, sweep, and filter were set at: 0.2&#x02013;1<sup>mv/div</sup>, 5<sup>ms/div</sup>, and 2&#x02013;10,000<sup>Hz </sup>respectively. The technique was the same as described in the Literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. Briefly: the volunteers lied prone on the examining table with the feet off the edge of the plinth. The E<sub>1 </sub>was placed at the middle of the line connecting midpoint of popliteal crease to the point at the most proximal part of the medial malleolus, and the E<sub>2 </sub>over the Achilles tendon (both were surface electrodes). The ground electrode was posed proximal to E<sub>1 </sub>and a disc electrode (anode) was placed on the anterior superior iliac spine. Then we inserted a monopolar 70<sup>mm </sup>needle (cathode) at a point 1<sup>cm </sup>medial to the posterior superior iliac spine, perpendicular to the frontal plane, and retracted it just a little after reaching the sacrum. Stimulus duration of 1 ms at 0.5 HZ was then applied while increasing current intensity to obtain both H and M waves simultaneously. M wave is the earlier wave and H is the later one. The interpeak latency was measured in milliseconds (ms) and recorded as T<sub>c</sub>. This measurement was only performed on the right lower extremity.</p><p>Descriptive statistics were applied to depict Mean &#x000b1; SD of age, leg length and Tc. The independent effect of leg length and age on T<sub>c </sub>was assessed by multiple regression model. The analyses were performed using SPSS 10.0 software. Kolmogrov-Smirnov test was used for evaluating the normal distribution of the variables.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>From 46 subjects who volunteered to participate in this study; five cases were excluded after history taking and physical examination (two because of history of sacral radiculopathy, two because of diabetes mellitus and one because of asymmetry in ankle reflexes) and one case after electrophysiologic evaluation; thus we completed the study with 40 subjects. Subjects' characteristics are shown in table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>subjects' characteristics</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td align="left">Number of subjects</td><td align="left">40 (26 males, 14 females)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Age range (years)</td><td align="left">19&#x02013;65</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Leg length (centimeters)</td><td align="left">29.5&#x02013;43</td></tr><tr><td align="left">T<sub>c </sub>&#x000b1; SD</td><td align="left">6.78 &#x000b1; 0.3</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>The group consisted of 26 males (65%) and 14 females (35%). Kolmogrov-Smirnov test showed normal distribution of the variables.</p><p>You are provided with the information below: (Mean &#x000b1; SD) Age: 37.0 &#x000b1; 10.7 years (range: 19&#x02013;65); leg length: 36.4 &#x000b1; 3.4 cm (range: 29.5&#x02013;43); Tc= 6.78 &#x000b1; 0.3 There was a significant correlation between T<sub>c </sub>and leg length (P value = 0.003, r= 0.49, CI 95% = 0.59&#x02013;0.88).</p><p>There was no correlation between T<sub>c </sub>and age (p value = 0.48, r = 0.11) We also found this regression equation: T<sub>c </sub>= 0.04L + 5.28 (L is leg length in centimeters, T<sub>c </sub>is represented in milliseconds.)</p></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>In this study we found a significant correlation between leg length and Tc, but we were unable to show such a relation between age and T<sub>c</sub>.</p><p>Pease et al were the first, studied T<sub>c </sub>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>], and reported Mean &#x000b1; SD of 7 &#x000b1; 0.3<sup>ms </sup>which is very close to our results (Tc= 6.78 &#x000b1; 0.3). They didn't specifically consider the leg length, age or any other potential confounding variables to T<sub>c</sub>.</p><p>Zhu et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>] evaluated 60 persons and reported Mean T<sub>c</sub>: 6.8 ms and its SD: 0.33 ms, again close to our results. They also reported that T<sub>c </sub>and person's height were correlated but didn't study any correlation between age and T<sub>c</sub>.</p><p>Wang et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>] evaluated 40 persons and found this regression equation:</p><p>T<sub>c </sub>= 0.02A + 0.003H + 0.92 (H: Height and A: Age), and stated that age is a contributing factor on T<sub>c</sub>.</p><p>Another research was performed by Ghavanini et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>], in which 39 subjects were evaluated. The reported T<sub>c </sub>&#x000b1; SD was 6.9 &#x000b1; 0.4; two regression equations were also suggested: T<sub>c </sub>= 0.097Tp + 4.045 and Tc = 0.051L + 4.92 (L=leg length in centimeters); results are close to ours, and age was not found to affect T<sub>c</sub>.</p><p>A summary of the above data plus detailed demographic data are provided in the table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>comparing related studies</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td></td><td align="center" colspan="4">Subjects' characteristics</td><td align="center" colspan="3">Tc</td></tr><tr><td></td><td colspan="7"><hr></hr></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Group size (persons)</td><td align="center">Mean age (yr)</td><td align="center">Mean L (cm)</td><td align="center">Mean H(cm)</td><td align="center"><italic>Mean</italic></td><td align="center"><italic>SD</italic></td><td align="center">Correlation (r) with A-H-L</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">Present study</td><td align="center">40</td><td align="center">37.0</td><td align="center">36.4 M:38.1 F:33.2</td><td align="center">?</td><td align="center">6.78</td><td align="center">0.3</td><td align="center">No-?-0.49</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Pease et al [2]</td><td align="center">20</td><td align="center">?</td><td align="center">?</td><td align="center">?</td><td align="center">7.0</td><td align="center">0.3</td><td align="center">?-?-?</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Zhu et al [3]</td><td align="center">60</td><td align="center">43</td><td align="center">?</td><td align="center">169</td><td align="center">6.8</td><td align="center">0.33</td><td align="center">No-0.54-?</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Wang et al [5]*</td><td align="center">40</td><td align="center">?</td><td align="center">?</td><td align="center">?</td><td align="center">?</td><td align="center">?</td><td align="center">?-?-?</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Ghavanini et al [6]**</td><td align="center">39</td><td align="center">41</td><td align="center">M:39.8 F:37.0</td><td align="center">M:172.2 F:159.5</td><td align="center">6.9</td><td align="center">0.4</td><td align="center">No-0.56&#x02013;0.62</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>A: age (yr); L: leg length (cm); H: height (cm); Tc: central loop of the H-reflex latency (ms); M: male; F: female; No: no correlation was found; ?: not reported</p><p>*: suggested a regression equation: Tc = 0.02A+0.03H+0.92</p><p>**: Suggested two regression equations: Tc = 0.051L+4.928; Tc = 0.097Tp+4.04</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Limitations</title><p>In this study we focused on age and leg length as potential contributing factors on the T<sub>c</sub>. we didn't control, randomize or observe other possible confounding (contributing) factors with potential to affect this parameter.</p><p>We observed a significant correlation between leg length and T<sub>c </sub>(P value = 0.003, r= 0.49, CI 95% = 0.59&#x02013;0.88), that is compatible to a previous published work [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>] (r = 0.54, p value less than 0.01).</p><p>Had we found any association between T<sub>c </sub>and age, the question might have been raised that subclinical neuropathy of old age could have been contributive; obviously, this is not the case in our study.</p><p>Although F-wave has been used to evaluate the possibility of proximal neuropathy; it was not measured in this study. Alternatively, we measured H-reflex latency to exclude proximal neuropathy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>].</p><p>It should be emphasized that noninvasive methodologies for the diagnosis of subclinical S1 radiculopathy are now available [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. It is also acceptable to stimulate the S1 spinal nerve at the S1 foramen by magnet, instead of deep tissue needling; nevertheless, we used more popular techniques for this study.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>We found that between age and leg length, only the latter can affect T<sub>c</sub>. It may be reasonable to consider leg length for calculating T<sub>c </sub>and to "narrow" the normal limits.</p><p>Further studies with larger sample sizes are required for detecting other contributing factors and standardizing T<sub>c </sub>according to leg length.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>None declared.</p></sec><sec><title>Abbreviations</title><p>T<sub>c</sub>: central loop of the gastrocnemius-soleus H-Reflex latency</p><p>T<sub>p</sub>: gastrocnemius-soleus H-Reflex latency</p><p>PNCV: right peroneal nerve conduction velocity</p><p>PDML: right peroneal nerve distal motor latency</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contribution</title><p>SS: examining the cases, calculation of TC, writing the paper.</p><p>MRAG: suggesting the research, supervision and helping with calculation of TC.</p><p>AA: examining the cases, calculation of TC</p><p>PJ: statistical consultant (data analysis)</p></sec><sec><title>Pre-publication history</title><p>The pre-publication history for this paper can be accessed here:</p><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2377/4/11/prepub"/></p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors would like to thank:</p><p>Ali Bidari, MD, assistant professor of rheumatology, Iran university of medical sciences, for his great help in the revision of the manuscript</p><p>Mojtaba Mahjoob, MD, resident of surgery, and Masoome Rostamzade, English instructor, for translating the manuscript.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dumitru</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><collab>ed</collab></person-group><source>Electrodiagnostic medicine</source><year>2002</year><edition>2</edition><publisher-name>Philadelphia: Hanley and Belfus,inc.</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pease</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozakiewicz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Central loop of the H reflex : Normal values and use in S1 radiculopathy</article-title><source>Am J phys Med Rehabil</source><year>1997</year><volume>76</volume><fpage>182</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9207699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00002060-199705000-00002</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Starr</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Haldeman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chu</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugerman</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Soleus H reflex to S1 nerve root stimulation</article-title><source>Electroencephalogr Clin Neurophysiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>10</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11003059</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0924-980X(97)00058-1</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pease</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lagattuta</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spinal nerve stimulation in S<sub>1 </sub>radiculopathy</article-title><source>Am J Phys Med Rehabil</source><year>1990</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>80</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2331343</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hoffmann reflex elicited by magnetic stimulation of S<sub>1 </sub>nerve roots in the diagnosis of diabetic radiculopathy</article-title><source>Zhonghua Yi xue Za Zhi</source><year>1998</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>501</fpage><lpage>503</lpage><comment>chinese</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10923457</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghavanini</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghadi</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ghavanini</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The central loop of the H reflex in the S<sub>1 </sub>spinal nerve: Normal values and constitutional influencing factors</article-title><source>Electromyogr clin neurophysiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>262</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11572185</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frigns</surname><given-names>CJM</given-names></name><name><surname>Laman</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Dujin</surname><given-names>MAJ</given-names></name><name><surname>van-Duijn</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Normal values of patellar and ankle tendon reflex latencies</article-title><source>Clin Neurol Neurosurg</source><year>1997</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9107465</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0303-8467(96)00593-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Braddom</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Standardization of H reflex and diagnostic use in S<sub>1 </sub>radiculopathy</article-title><source>Arch phys Med Rehabil</source><year>1974</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4823067</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strakowski</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Redd</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name><surname>Pease</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>H-reflex and F wave latencies to soleus normal values and side to side differences</article-title><source>Am J Phys Med Rehabil</source><year>2001</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>491</fpage><lpage>493</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11421516</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00002060-200107000-00004</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buschbacher</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Normal range for H-reflex recording from the calf muscles</article-title><source>Am J Phys Med Rehabil</source><year>1999</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>S75</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10573102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00002060-199911001-00014</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Braddom</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Standardization of the H reflex and diagnostic use in s1 radiculopathy</article-title><source>Arch phys med rehabil</source><year>1974</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>161</fpage><lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4823067</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mazzocchio</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Scarfo</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Mariottini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Muzii</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name><name><surname>Palma</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>recruitment curve of the soleus H reflex in chronic back pain and lumbosacral radiculopathy</article-title><source>BMC musculoskeletal disorders</source><year>2001</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>4</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11722799</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2474-2-4</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



