<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Endocr Disord</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Endocrine Disorders</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1472-6823</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15745442</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC555571</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1472-6823-5-2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1472-6823-5-2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Influence of antioxidant (L- ascorbic acid) on tolbutamide induced hypoglycaemia/antihyperglycaemia in normal and diabetic rats</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sreemantula</surname><given-names>Satyanarayana</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>nandinisai@hotmail.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kilari</surname><given-names>Eswar K</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>ekilari@rediffmail.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vardhan</surname><given-names>Vishnu A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>profssn@rediffmail.com</email></contrib><contrib id="A4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jaladi</surname><given-names>Rajasekhar</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>rajasekhar_27@hotmail.com</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Pharmacology Division, University College of Pharmaceutical sciences, Andhra University, Visakhapatnam, &#x02013; 530 003, India</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>3</day><month>3</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1472-6823/5/2"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>5</month><year>2004</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>3</day><month>3</month><year>2005</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2005 Sreemantula et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Sreemantula et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Sreemantula
               Satyanarayana
               
               nandinisai@hotmail.com
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            Influence of antioxidant (L- ascorbic acid) on tolbutamide induced hypoglycaemia/antihyperglycaemia in normal and diabetic rats
         </dc:title><dc:date>2005</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>BMC Endocrine Disorders 5(1): 2-. (2005)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1472-6823(2005)5:1&#x0003c;2&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1472-6823</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>Diabetes mellitus is a chronic metabolic disorder characterized by hyperglycaemia. Increased oxidative stress and decreased antioxidant levels are the leading cause of diabetes and diabetic complications. So it is felt that supplementation of antioxidants may be useful in controlling the glucose levels and to postpone the occurrence of diabetic complications. The objective of our study is to find the influence of antioxidant supplementation (L-ascorbic acid) on tolbutamide activity in normal and diabetic rats.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>L- ascorbic acid/tolbutamide/L-ascorbic acid + tolbutamide were administered orally to 3 different groups of albino rats of either sex in normal and diabetic condition. Blood samples were collected from retro-orbital puncture at different time intervals and were analyzed for blood glucose by GOD-POD method. Diabetes was induced by alloxan 100 mg/kg body weight administered by I.P route.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>L-ascorbic acid/ tolbutamide produced hypoglycaemic activity in a dose dependant manner in normal and diabetic condition. In the presence of L-ascorbic acid, tolbuatmide produced early onset of action and maintained for longer period compared to tolbutamide matching control.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Supplementation of antioxidants like L-ascorbic acid was found to improve tolbutamide response in normal and diabetic rats.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>Diabetes mellitus is a chronic metabolic disorder characterized by hyperglycaemia. It requires life long treatment with drugs coupled with diet control and exercise. It may be due to decrease in the synthesis of insulin (Type-I diabetes) or due to decrease in the secretion of insulin from &#x003b2;-cells of islets of Langerhans of pancreas (Type-II diabetes). Insulin is the drug of choice in type &#x02013; I diabetes and sulfonylureas are the drugs of choice in type II. Among sulfonylureas, tolbutamide is the drug of choice for geriatrics because of its short duration of action and lower incidence of hypoglycaemia in early hours of night.</p><p>Diabetes is one of the stress related disorder. Diabetic subjects are shown to have increased oxidative stress and decreased antioxidant levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. It was also shown that tight control of blood glucose is possible with decrease in oxidative stress [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Antioxidants are claimed to work as antistress agents by decreasing oxidative stress. L-ascorbic acid used in therapy for disorders like scurvy produces antioxidant activity. Earlier reports show that the relationship between scurvy and diabetes mellitus indicates the low levels of plasma ascorbic acid in diabetic rats compared to control rats [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. Hence the present study was conducted to find the influence of L-ascorbic acid, a water soluble antioxidant and a free radical scavenger on the hypoglycaemic and antihyperglycaemic activities of tolbutamide in normal and diabetic rats.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>All animal experiments were performed in accordance with our institutional animal ethics committee. Albino rats of either sex (Mahaveer Enterprises, Hyderabad) weighing between 125 &#x02013; 175 g were used in the study. They were housed five per cage at temperature 22 &#x000b1; 2&#x000b0;C and 12/12 h light/dark under controlled environment. Rats were fed with standard pellet diet. (Mahaveer Enterprises, Hyderabad) and water <italic>ad libitum</italic>. They were divided into 3 groups of five each. They were fasted for 18 h prior to the experiment allowing access to water only, and the water was withdrawn during the experiment. Blood samples were collected from the retro-orbital plexus of each rat at 0, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2, 4, 6 hr after drug administration. Blood glucose levels were determined by using GOD &#x02013; POD method [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>].</p><p>Group I received L-ascorbic acid 60 mg / kg body weight, Group II received tolbutamide 20 mg/kg body weight and Group III was given L-ascorbic acid (60 mg / kg body weight) prior to the administration of tolbutamide 20 mg/kg body weight in normal rats. In clinical practice tolbutamide and vitamin C are administered orally hence in our study also this was administered orally.</p><sec><title>Induction of diabetes</title><p>Albino rats of either sex weighing between 125 to 175 g were fasted overnight before injection with alloxan. Alloxan monohydrate was dissolved in saline solution and was administered at a dose of 100 mg/kg body weight intraperitonially. Animals were treated with 10% dextrose orally to combat the early phase of hypoglycaemia. Rats showing fasting blood glucose levels above 150 mg/dl were selected for the study. They were divided into 3 groups of five each. Group I received L-ascorbic acid 40 mg/kg body weight and Group II received tolbutamide 20 mg/kg body weight while Group III was given L-ascorbic acid 40 mg/kg prior to tolbutamide administration (20 mg/kg). L-ascorbic acid dose was fixed based on its response, which produced above 40%.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>The significance of blood glucose reduction produced by L-ascorbic acid with tolbutamide compared to tolbutamide control was determined by applying students unpaired t-test and the significance is indicated by * mark.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The presence of L-ascorbic acid upto 20 &#x003bc;g did not interfere with the blood glucose estimation when tested with different quantities in <italic>in vitro</italic> studies. In normal rats L-ascorbic acid at the dose of 60 mg/kg body weight administered orally produced 50.91% blood glucose reduction at 0.5 h and 20 mg/kg body weight of tolbutamide produced 33% at 4 h as peak effects. In the presence of L-ascorbic acid (60 mg/kg), the action of tolbutamide was early in onset and maintained for 6 h. In diabetic rats, oral administration of L-ascorbic acid alone at the dose of 40 mg/kg body weight produced 42.53% blood glucose reduction at 1.5 h and tolbutamide 20 mg/kg body weight produced 45.09 at 4 h. Administration of L-ascorbic acid 40 mg/kg body weight prior to tolbutamide produced antidiabetic activity at 0.5 h and was maintained for 6 h. The percent blood glucose reduction with L-ascorbic acid / tolbutamide/ L-ascorbic acid + tolbutamide in normal rats and diabetic rats were given in table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref> &#x00026;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Percent blood glucose reduction (Mean &#x000b1; SEM) with L-ascorbic acid/ tolbutamide / L-ascorbic acid + tolbutamide in normal rats (n= 5)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center"><bold>Time in hours</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>L-ascorbic acid 60 mg/kg bd.wt.</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Tolbutamide 20 mg/kg bd.wt.</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>L-ascorbic acid 60 mg/kg bd.wt. + Tolbutamide 20 mg/kg bd.wt.</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">0.5</td><td align="center">50.91 &#x000b1; 0.49</td><td align="center">10.08 &#x000b1; 1.08</td><td align="center">53.57 &#x000b1; 2.01***</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">20.26 &#x000b1; 3.14</td><td align="center">15.56 &#x000b1; 1.48</td><td align="center">28.70 &#x000b1; 1.75***</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1.5</td><td align="center">6.06 &#x000b1; 1.3</td><td align="center">18.75 &#x000b1; 2.1</td><td align="center">23.25 &#x000b1; 1.72</td></tr><tr><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">1.65 &#x000b1; 0.93</td><td align="center">22.22 &#x000b1; 2.13</td><td align="center">29.78 &#x000b1; 2.57</td></tr><tr><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">-2.83 &#x000b1; 0.4</td><td align="center">33.0 &#x000b1; 0.69</td><td align="center">45.21 &#x000b1; 2.79**</td></tr><tr><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">10.28 &#x000b1; 1.02</td><td align="center">12.54 &#x000b1; 2.5</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Significance *** P &#x0003c; 0.001, **P &#x0003c; 0.01</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Percent blood glucose reduction (Mean &#x000b1; SEM) with L-ascorbic acid/ tolbutamide / L-ascorbic acid + tolbutamide in diabetic rats (n = 5)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center"><bold>Time in hours</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>L-ascorbic acid 40 mg/kg bd.wt.</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Tolbutamide 20 mg/kg bd.wt.</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>L-ascorbic acid 40 mg/kg bd.wt. + Tolbutamide 20 mg/kg bd.wt.</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">0</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">0.5</td><td align="center">18.23 &#x000b1; 1.88</td><td align="center">3.03 &#x000b1; 0.8</td><td align="center">23.55 &#x000b1; 2.37***</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1</td><td align="center">35.45 &#x000b1; 3.26</td><td align="center">7.83 &#x000b1; 1.84</td><td align="center">35.59 &#x000b1; 4.48***</td></tr><tr><td align="center">1.5</td><td align="center">42.53 &#x000b1; 1.78</td><td align="center">18.58 &#x000b1; 2.49</td><td align="center">57.49 &#x000b1; 1.63**</td></tr><tr><td align="center">2</td><td align="center">34.04 &#x000b1; 2.22</td><td align="center">37.97 &#x000b1; 6.40</td><td align="center">59.74 &#x000b1; 1.22*</td></tr><tr><td align="center">4</td><td align="center">20.02 &#x000b1; 3.32</td><td align="center">45.09 &#x000b1; 4.95</td><td align="center">62.55 &#x000b1; 0.64**</td></tr><tr><td align="center">6</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center">21.6 &#x000b1; 1.94</td><td align="center">39.43 &#x000b1; 2.15***</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Significance *** P &#x0003c; 0.001, **P &#x0003c; 0.01, *P &#x0003c; 0.05</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>The drug interaction studies are usually conducted in animal models to find out the mechanism before they are conducted in humans. We have selected rat as animal model since it is one of the animal, which synthesize ascorbic acid and can be maintained easily in the laboratory conditions.</p><p>Reactive oxygen species (ROS) are thought to be implicated in the pathogenesis of diabetes as well as other diseases[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. Reactive oxygen species usually comprise radicals that have the ability to oxidize and damage DNA, proteins and carbohydrates. Hyperglycaemia appears to induce oxidative stress on cells and this can cause an increase in the production of free radicals[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Human antioxidant enzymes are mobilized during hyperglycaemia, but they cannot meet the continued demand due to increased oxidative stress[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. This problem is either due to decreased intake of needed precursors or an inability to synthesise the antioxidant enzymes[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. Antioxidant supplementation may provide the only means to reverse this process[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Use of typical antioxidants alone or in combination may retard or even prevent the normal progression of diabetic complications.</p><p>It was reported that L-ascorbic acid levels were decreased in diabetic patients and rats[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. So it is felt that L-ascorbic acid supplementation may help in the treatment of diabetes mellitus. In the present study L-ascorbic acid and tolbutamide reduced blood glucose levels in normal &#x00026; diabetic rats in a dose dependent manner. L-ascorbic acid when administered alone produced an early onset of action 0.5 &#x00026; 1.5 h in normal and diabetic rats respectively. This early onset may be due to increase in the insulin secretion which support earlier reports that L-ascorbic acid supplementation increase the plasma insulin concentration[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]. Tolbutamide when administered in therapeutic dose produced the maximum effect at 4 h and was maintained up to 6 h in both normal and diabetic rats. In the presence of L-ascorbic acid the onset of action of tolbutamide was early and maintained for longer duration compared to tolbutamide control. Tolbutamide acts by stimulating insulin secretion (pancreatic)[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>] and also by increasing tissue uptake of glucose (extra pancreatic)[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>]. The early onset of action was noticed to be due to L-ascorbic acid, which was maintained later due to tolbutamide activity since both are reported to have influence on insulin secretion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>The study indicates that additive action of L-ascorbic acid on pharmacodynamic response of tolbutamide may be useful to improve the tolbutamide activity in insulin resistant cases and to postpone the occurrence of diabetic complications. However further work on human patients is required to confirm the observation in diabetic condition and usefulness of L-ascorbic acid as supplemental agent for improved control of blood glucose levels when administered along with sulfonylureas.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The author(s) declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>SS Conceived of the study, participated in the design of the study, performed the statistical analysis and drafted the manuscript.</p><p>EK Participated in the design and coordination and in the standardization of methods.</p><p>RJ Carried out the study in normal rats.</p><p>VA Carried out the study in diabetic rats.</p><p>All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Percent Blood Glucose Reduction with L-ascorbic acid / tolbutamide / L-ascorbic acid + tolbutamide in normal rats (n = 5)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1472-6823-5-2-1"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Percent Blood Glucose Reduction with L-ascorbic acid / tolbutamide / L-ascorbic acid + tolbutamide in diabetic rats (n = 5)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1472-6823-5-2-2"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Pre-publication history</title><p>The pre-publication history for this paper can be accessed here:</p><p><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1472-6823/5/2/prepub"/></p></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The authors thank the UGC for sanctioning research fellowship (JRF) to J. Rajasekhar for pursuing Ph.D programme. The authors also thank M/s Hoechst Marion Roussel Ltd., Mumbai for supplying tolbutamide as gift sample.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Mcvie</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaramillo</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of modest vitamin E supplementation on blood glycated hemoglobin and triglyceride levels and red cell indices in type I diabetic patients</article-title><source>J Am Coll Nutr</source><year>1996</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>458</fpage><lpage>461</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8892171</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nourooz-Zadeh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahimi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tajaddini-Sarmadi</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Tritschler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Halliwell</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Betteridge</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relationship between plasma measures of oxidative stress and metabolic control in NIDDM</article-title><source>Diabetologia</source><year>1997</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>647</fpage><lpage>653</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9222643</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s001250050729</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feillet-coudray</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rocke</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>coudray</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Grzelkowska</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Azais-Braesco</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Dardevet</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazur</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lipid peroxidation and antioxidant status in experimental diabetes</article-title><source>Clin chim Acta</source><year>1999</year><volume>284</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10437641</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0009-8981(99)00046-7</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sardas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yilmaz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Oztak</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Cakir</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Karakaya</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assessment of DNA strand breakage by comet assay in diabetic patients and the role of antioxidant supplementation</article-title><source>Mutation Res</source><year>2001</year><volume>490</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>129</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11342238</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Owens</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vitamin C survey in diabetes</article-title><source>New Eng J Med</source><year>1941</year><volume>224</volume><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>323</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Losert</surname><given-names>VW</given-names></name><name><surname>Vetter</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Wendt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The influence of Vitamin C (ascorbic acid) on glucose tolerance, insulin activity and insulin elimination from the blood</article-title><source>Arzneim Forsch/Drug Res</source><year>1980</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6989374</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Trinder</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determination of blood glucose using an oxidase &#x02013; peroxidase system with a non-carcinogenic chemogen</article-title><source>J Clin Pathol</source><year>1969</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>158</fpage><lpage>161</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5776547</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toyokuni</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reactive oxygen species &#x02013; induced molecular damage and its application in pathology</article-title><source>Pathol Int eb</source><year>1999</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1440-1827.1999.00829.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ceriello</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>DelloRusso</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Amstad</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerutti</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High glucose induces antioxidant enzymes in human endothelial cells in culture</article-title><source>Diabetes</source><year>1996</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>471</fpage><lpage>476</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8603769</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mates</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez-jimenez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant enzymes and their implications in pathophysiological process</article-title><source>Front Biosci</source><year>1999</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>339</fpage><lpage>345</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of antioxidants in the prevention and treatment of disease</article-title><source>J Int Fed Clin Chem</source><year>1998</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10181011</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halliwell</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gutteridge</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lipid peroxidation, oxygen radicals, cell damage, and antioxidant therapy</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>1984</year><fpage>1396</fpage><lpage>1397</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6145845</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(84)91886-5</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Salem</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hassaneen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Gadban</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Elwan</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Awad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Basu</surname><given-names>TK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Antioxidant Status and Insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus (IDDM)</article-title><source>J Clin Biochem Nutr</source><year>1999</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>107</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Hsieh-Chen</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Tasi</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>L-ascorbic acid produces hypoglycaemia and hyperinsulinaemia in anaesthetized rats</article-title><source>J Pharm Pharmacol</source><year>1989</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>346</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2569525</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vigneri</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Pezzino</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of the <italic>in vitro </italic>effect of biguanides and sulfonylureas on the insulin binding of its receptors in target cells</article-title><source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>1982</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7033271</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peifer</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Halter</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Beacd</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Portel</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential effects of tolbutamide on first and second phase insulin secretion in non insulin dependent diabetes mellitus</article-title><source>J Clin Endocrinol Metab</source><year>1981</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>1256</fpage><lpage>1262</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7028776</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>



