<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="editorial"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Microbiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Microbiol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Microbiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-302X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38116524</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC10728808</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2023.1338999</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Editorial: Recent highlights in the development of therapeutic antiviral strategies</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Malnou</surname><given-names>C&#x000e9;cile E.</given-names></name><uri xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/611092/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Ligat</surname><given-names>Ga&#x000eb;tan</given-names></name><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/536560/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff><institution>Institut Toulousain des Maladies Infectieuses et Inflammatoires (Infinity), Universit&#x000e9; de Toulouse, Institut national de la sant&#x000e9; et de la recherche m&#x000e9;dicale (INSERM), Centre national de la recherche scientifique (CNRS), Universit&#x000e9; Toulouse III - Paul Sabatier (UPS)</institution>, <addr-line>Toulouse</addr-line>, <country>France</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited and reviewed by: Anna Kramvis, University of the Witwatersrand, South Africa</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Ga&#x000eb;tan Ligat <email>gaetan.ligat@inserm.fr</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>05</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>1338999</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2023 Malnou and Ligat.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Malnou and Ligat</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article related-article-type="commentary-article" id="RA1" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/research-topics/49203/recent-highlights-in-the-development-of-therapeutic-antiviral-strategies" ext-link-type="uri">Editorial on the Research Topic <article-title>Recent highlights in the development of therapeutic antiviral strategies</article-title></related-article><kwd-group><kwd>antiviral strategies</kwd><kwd>viral inhibitor</kwd><kwd>vesicles</kwd><kwd>miRNA</kwd><kwd>genes editing and silencing</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>The author(s) declare financial support was received for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article. CM received financial support from the ANR Corofet grant (ANR-21-CE14-0030), the D&#x000e9;fi Cl&#x000e9; Cell Based Biotherapies Occitanie (EXOBARRIER), and the D&#x000e9;fi Cl&#x000e9; Risques Infectieux et Vecteurs Occitanie (ZIKEV-sf). GL received financial support from the D&#x000e9;fi Cl&#x000e9; Cell Based Biotherapies Occitanie (INTERCYTE). Our team received institutional grants from INSERM, CNRS, and Toulouse III University.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="0"/><page-count count="2"/><word-count count="1265"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Virology</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Recent developments in antiviral therapies are at the forefront of medical research, shaping the landscape of viral disease management and offering new hope in the fight against viral infections. Biotherapies, in the realm of antiviral treatments represent a cutting-edge approach to combat viral infections. These therapies leverage biological agents such as antibodies, interferons, or engineered immune cells to directly target viruses, or host factors, to improve the immune response. One notable example is the development of monoclonal antibodies, which have shown remarkable effectiveness in neutralizing viruses like SARS-CoV-2. The development of interferon-based therapies is another notable recent innovation. These treatments stimulate the host immune response, which improves its capacity to fight viral infections such as Hepatitis B Virus (HBV) infection. Recently, nucleic acid technologies have revolutionized antiviral strategies. mRNA vaccines, exemplified by those designed to combat COVID-19, have demonstrated effectiveness and adaptability against emerging viral variants. However, challenges persist in the pursuit of effective antiviral treatments. New therapeutic strategies need to be developed to overcome viral resistance. Beyond therapeutic strategies, a comprehensive approach to antiviral efforts includes a focus on prevention, early detection, and public education. Vaccination campaigns, innovative strategies for rapid viral detection, and public awareness programs all contribute to the fight against viral infections and improve global health outcomes.</p><p>In this Research Topic, we have collected original research and review articles covering many different aspects of therapeutic antiviral strategies.</p><p>Among them, several manuscripts mainly focused on antiviral therapies against coronaviruses. In an elegant study, <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2023.1185504" ext-link-type="uri">Andreu et al.</ext-link> report for the first time the broad-spectrum antiviral activity of a Dextran sulfate-based extrapolymeric substance produced by the lactic acid bacterium <italic>Leuconostoc mesenteroides</italic> B512F. They evaluated the toxicity and antiviral efficacy upon inhalation of this exopolysaccharide substance in mouse models susceptible to SARS-CoV-2 infection, and demonstrated a strong inhibition of SARS-CoV-2 infection <italic>in vivo</italic>. Moreover, they also demonstrated a broad-spectrum antiviral activity of this substance against several enveloped viruses such as SARS-CoV-2, HCoV229E, HSV-1, in <italic>in vitro</italic> models and in human lung tissue. In another study, <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2023.1206951" ext-link-type="uri">Piacentini et al.</ext-link> showed that the anti-infective drug nitazoxanide has a potent antiviral activity against three human seasonal coronaviruses HCoV-229E, -NL63, and OC43 in cell culture. Nitazoxanide does not affect HCoV adsorption, entry or uncoating, but acts at post-entry level, interfering with the spike glycoprotein maturation. Together, these two studies propose promising tools for the treatment of seasonal coronavirus infections. Finally, <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2023.1138864" ext-link-type="uri">Guan et al.</ext-link> summarized the antiviral mechanisms of stress granules (SGs) and provided new insights into the development of SG-targeted antiviral drugs according to different pathways, particularly in the context of SARS-CoV-2.</p><p>Apart from the example of the study of <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2023.1185504" ext-link-type="uri">Andreu et al.</ext-link> using a bacterium deriving molecule as antiviral treatment, other works presented in this Research Topic have used such antiviral approaches. In an interesting study, <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2023.1269869" ext-link-type="uri">Wiggins et al.</ext-link> engineered two bacterial strains (<italic>Lactobacillus casei</italic> and <italic>Lactococcus lactis</italic>) for expressing scytovirin, a lectin deriving from cyanobacteria, on the bacterial surface. They demonstrated that both bacterial strains neutralize pseudotyped Ebolavirus in a cell-based assay. In a similar way, <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2023.1251275" ext-link-type="uri">Kan et al.</ext-link> proposed a potential new drug to treat porcine epidemic diarrhea virus (PEDV) infection, by using <italic>Lactiplantibacillus plantarum</italic> supernatant. This acts by promoting the balance of intra- and extracellular Ca 2+ concentrations, thereby inhibiting PEDV proliferation with depends on intracellular Ca 2+ level.</p><p>In another work, <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2023.1173061" ext-link-type="uri">Qi et al.</ext-link> evaluated the potential for synergistic effects of combination therapies to treat chronic hepatitis B infection. They presented two combination approaches aiming to target HBsAg and HBV-DNA. The first involved the use of antibodies followed by the administration of a therapeutic vaccine. The second combined antibodies with Entecavir. In both cases, they have shown that they constitute promising strategies to treat hepatitis B.</p><p>Finally, three reviews present current knowledge in antiviral approaches for chosen viruses. In the first one, <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2023.1255935" ext-link-type="uri">Peng et al.</ext-link> presented functional epitopes and neutralizing antibodies of vaccinia virus, and discussed their potential value in the context of smallpox prevention and treatment. In a second manuscript, <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2023.1233433" ext-link-type="uri">Afzal et al.</ext-link> reviewed current advances in therapeutic strategies, immune-based therapies and vaccine candidates for Hantavirus infections. Lastly, <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2023.1321116" ext-link-type="uri">Gourin et al.</ext-link> presented the state of the current knowledge about anti-human cytomegalovirus (HCMV) therapies. They described the various molecules developed against HCMV with their mode of action, preclinical tests, clinical studies and possible resistance.</p><p>Significant progress has been made over the past decades in the development of new antiviral therapeutic approaches. In addition to the discovery and development of treatments for viral infections for which we do not yet have a strategy, the main challenge is to develop therapeutic approaches to overcome resistance mutations and toxicity of approved therapies. Overall, this Research Topic covered a large panel of antiviral strategies including new drugs, immune-based therapies, therapeutic antibody, and vaccine, and offer new perspectives for therapeutic intervention.</p><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s1"><title>Author contributions</title><p>CEM: Writing &#x02014; original draft, Writing &#x02014; review &#x00026; editing. GL: Writing &#x02014; original draft, Writing &#x02014; review &#x00026; editing.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>The authors would like to thank the authors and reviewers of this Research Topic for their contribution and quick respond in all stages of the revision process.</p></ack><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s3"><title>Publisher's note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec></back></article>
