<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="letter" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Blood Cancer J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Blood Cancer J</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Blood Cancer Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2044-5385</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC10730864</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">967</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41408-023-00967-8</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Correspondence</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Unraveling the genomic underpinnings of unbalanced <italic>MYC</italic> break-apart FISH results using whole genome sequencing analysis</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gagnon</surname><given-names>Marie-France</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Penheiter</surname><given-names>Alan R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>Faye</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sadeghian</surname><given-names>Dorsay</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>Sarah H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Karagouga</surname><given-names>Giannoula</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McCune</surname><given-names>Alexa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zepeda-Mendoza</surname><given-names>Cinthya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-5536-9011</contrib-id><name><surname>Greipp</surname><given-names>Patricia T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Xinjie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ketterling</surname><given-names>Rhett P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6918-3376</contrib-id><name><surname>McPhail</surname><given-names>Ellen D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7132-0226</contrib-id><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>Rebecca L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-2496-8000</contrib-id><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>Jess F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Vasmatzis</surname><given-names>George</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-5229-4897</contrib-id><name><surname>Baughn</surname><given-names>Linda B.</given-names></name><address><email>baughn.linda@mayo.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03zzw1w08</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.417467.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0443 9942</institution-id><institution>Division of Laboratory Genetics and Genomics, Department of Laboratory Medicine and Pathology, </institution><institution>Mayo Clinic, </institution></institution-wrap>Rochester, MN USA </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/03zzw1w08</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.417467.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0443 9942</institution-id><institution>Center for Individualized Medicine, </institution><institution>Mayo Clinic, </institution></institution-wrap>Rochester, MN USA </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02qp3tb03</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.66875.3a</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0459 167X</institution-id><institution>Division of Hematopathology, Department of Laboratory Medicine and Pathology, </institution><institution>Mayo Clinic, </institution></institution-wrap>Rochester, MN USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>19</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>19</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>12</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>190</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>7</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>30</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>7</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2023</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>B-cell lymphoma</kwd><kwd>Cancer genomics</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/100011542</institution-id><institution>Mayo Clinic | Center for Clinical and Translational Science, Mayo Clinic (CCaTS)</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>UL1TR002377</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Baughn</surname><given-names>Linda B.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer Nature Limited 2023</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par1"><italic>MYC</italic> rearrangements (<italic>MYC</italic>-R) constitute an integral defining feature in the diagnostic classification of mature aggressive B-cell lymphoma (BCL) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Specifically, diffuse large B-cell lymphoma (DLBCL)/high-grade B-cell lymphoma (HGBCL) with <italic>MYC</italic> and <italic>BCL2</italic> rearrangements (and/or <italic>BCL6</italic> rearrangements) circumscribe a subset of higher-risk tumors. Current guidelines recommend investigating <italic>MYC</italic>-R with fluorescence in situ hybridization (FISH) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. In accordance with the diversity of rearrangement partners including immunoglobin (IG) and non-IG partners and the variability of breakpoints in the <italic>MYC</italic> locus, a break-apart (BAP) FISH probe is commonly utilized. Dual-color dual-fusion FISH probes (D-FISH) spanning <italic>MYC</italic> and IGH, IG-lambda (IGL) or IG-kappa (IGK) may also be used. We have previously demonstrated that in suspected HGBCL unbalanced rearrangements are identified in 11.9% of cases with abnormal results with the <italic>MYC</italic> BAP probe. In approximately 8.5% of cases, these cannot be reconciled with IGH/<italic>MYC</italic> D-FISH results and remain of ambiguous significance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Forty-three percent of unbalanced cases also harbor a concurrent <italic>BCL2</italic> rearrangement (unpublished data), thereby emphasizing the importance of informed interpretation of results for accurate diagnostic classification and therapeutic management. In this study, we sought to elucidate the significance of these unbalanced rearrangements with whole genome sequencing (WGS) analysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Survey</title><p id="Par2">An online survey comprising 6 questions was distributed to the International Cytogenetic community via email (<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">Supplementary Methods</xref>) to delineate the scope of FISH strategies used to investigate <italic>MYC</italic>-R and the interpretation practices of unbalanced <italic>MYC</italic> BAP results across clinical laboratories.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>FISH analysis</title><p id="Par3">FISH analysis consisted of commercial <italic>MYC</italic> BAP and <italic>MYC</italic>/IGH D-FISH probe sets (Abbott Laboratories, Des Plaines, IL). The <italic>MYC</italic> BAP probe set included a red (R) and a green (G) probe which respectively hybridized 5&#x02032; and 3&#x02032; to the <italic>MYC</italic> gene, yielding a fusion (F) signal in the setting of an intact <italic>MYC</italic> locus. While typical <italic>MYC</italic>-R are indicated by balanced, separate red (R) and green (G) signals (RGF-type pattern), unbalanced patterns represent unbalanced or isolated R or isolated G signals. Cases with isolated R signals in the absence of isolated G signals (such as 1R1F) were referred to as RF-type patterns, and cases with isolated G signals in the absence of isolated R signals (such as 1G1F), were referred to as GF-type patterns (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1A</xref>).<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Representation of findings obtained with whole-genome sequencing and correlation with fluorescence in situ hybridization results.</title><p><bold>A</bold> Representation of a typical red (R)-green(G)-fusion(F)-type pattern, <bold>B</bold> Representation of an unbalanced RF-type pattern, <bold>C</bold> Representation of an unbalanced GF-type pattern, <bold>D</bold> Illustration of breakpoints identified at the <italic>MYC</italic> locus in our cohort with whole-genome sequencing (GRCh38 reference genome, created with Gviz and trackViewer R packages), <bold>E</bold> Circos plot illustrating <italic>MYC</italic> rearrangement partners identified in our cohort (created with circlize R package).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41408_2023_967_Fig1_HTML" id="d32e367"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Whole genome sequencing</title><p id="Par4">WGS was performed with DNA extracted from formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded (FFPE) sections using Qiagen AllPrep or DNA FFPE kits (Cats #80234, #56404). A modified Covaris fragmentation protocol designed to capture larger insert sizes was used [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Libraries were multiplexed on an Illumina NovaSeq S4. Mapping to the GRCh38 reference genome and structural variant calling were performed with BIMA 3.1.5/SVAtools pipeline [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. FFPEseq mean and range of uniquely mapped fragments for the 14 libraries was 492&#x02009;M (386M-685M). Tumor bridge coverage (average number of fragments (read-pairs) spanning a position in the genome), adjusted for library insert length and pipeline estimated tumor percentage, was 30.5&#x000d7; (14.2&#x000d7;&#x02013;61.4&#x000d7;).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Clinical evolution</title><p id="Par5">Baseline demographic characteristics, management approaches and response to treatment were extracted from medical chart review.</p><p id="Par6">This study was approved by the Mayo Clinic Institutional Review Board (15-007359).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec8"><title>Survey of interpretation practices of unbalanced <italic>MYC</italic> break-apart results</title><p id="Par7">Fifty-four responses were obtained to the survey querying laboratory practices regarding FISH strategies and interpretation of unbalanced <italic>MYC</italic> BAP results. The survey participants were derived from &#x02265; 31 different institutions located in &#x02265;4 different countries (23 responders did not provide information related to their work institution). Twenty-three of 54 laboratories (43%) only performed the <italic>MYC</italic> BAP probe and 30/54 (56%) laboratories performed the <italic>MYC</italic> BAP and IGH/<italic>MYC</italic> D-FISH probes upon initial investigation. One of 54 laboratories (2%) performed the <italic>MYC</italic> BAP, IGH/<italic>MYC</italic>, IGK/<italic>MYC</italic> and IGL/<italic>MYC</italic> D-FISH probe sets upon initial investigation. <italic>BCL2</italic> and <italic>BCL6</italic> rearrangements were sought upfront by 36/54 (67%) responders and 14/54 (26%) only queried these rearrangements in the event of a <italic>MYC</italic>-R. Thirty-six percent and 42%, respectively, reported interpreting RF- and GF-type patterns as a <italic>MYC-R</italic>, 58 and 56% reported RF- and GF-type patterns as equivocal, respectively, and 6 and 2% reported RF and GF-patterns as negative for a <italic>MYC-R</italic>, respectively (Supplementary Fig. <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>). These data demonstrate significant variability in the interpretation of unbalanced <italic>MYC</italic> BAP results with most laboratories reporting an equivocal result.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Cohort description and associated FISH analysis results</title><p id="Par8">Our cohort included 14 cases of DLBCL/HGBCL evaluated in our clinical FISH laboratory between 2019 and 2021 and selected sequentially in inverse chronological order of sampling (with preference given to internal cases for clinical correlation). Seven cases had an unbalanced <italic>MYC</italic> BAP result, including 5 cases with a RF-type pattern and 2 cases with a GF-type pattern on <italic>MYC</italic> BAP analysis in the absence of an IGH partner by D-FISH. Seven specimens with a typical RGF-type pattern with a known <italic>MYC</italic>-IGH (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1) or unknown (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;6) partner were also included. These served as controls to verify the ability of the WGS methodology from FFPE sections used in this study to identify rearrangements and dissect the genomic architecture at the <italic>MYC</italic> locus.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Whole genome sequencing results</title><p id="Par9">A <italic>MYC-R w</italic>as confirmed in all control cases with a balanced pattern on BAP FISH (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). These involved previously reported rearrangement partners/loci (IGH (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1), IGL (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;2), <italic>ZCCHC7</italic> (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1), <italic>RFTN1</italic> (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1), <italic>DMD</italic> (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1) and <italic>BCL11A</italic> (<italic>n</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;1)). A structural variant (SV) involving the <italic>MYC</italic> region was also detected in all 5 cases with a RF-type pattern. In line with the higher number of R signal(s) observed on BAP FISH, a relative gain of genomic material 5&#x02032; of the <italic>MYC</italic> gene or relative loss of material 3&#x02032; of the <italic>MYC</italic> gene was detected with WGS in all these cases. Putative fusion events juxtaposing <italic>MYC</italic> to (1) an intergenic region upstream of <italic>TG</italic>, (2) <italic>TG</italic>, (3) <italic>IRF8</italic>, and (4) <italic>SPAG1</italic> was detected in 4/5 cases, while case 5 involved a copy number (CN) gain of <italic>MYC</italic>. WGS also allowed to resolve the unbalanced FISH results for cases with a GF-type pattern and revealed SVs leading to a higher copy number (CN) of the 3&#x02032;<italic>MYC</italic> BAP FISH probe-binding sequence in comparison with the 5&#x02032; region in both cases with a GF-type pattern, thereby also reconciling BAP FISH results. The first case with a GF-type pattern juxtaposed <italic>MYC</italic> with <italic>ACTB</italic> and the second involved a CN loss including <italic>MYC</italic> and the 5&#x02019; FISH probe-binding sequence. Of all cases with unbalanced FISH results, this case represented the only one in which WGS revealed a deletion involving <italic>MYC</italic> in our study cohort. <italic>MYC</italic> overexpression by immunohistochemistry (&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;40%) was detected in 4/5 and 2/2 cases with RF- and GF-type patterns, respectively, suggesting that in 6/7 cases, the unbalanced <italic>MYC</italic> rearrangement was associated with increased MYC expression. In 7 cases with a typical pattern, overexpression of MYC was documented by IHC.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Correlation of fluorescence in situ hybridization and whole-genome sequencing results at the <italic>MYC</italic> locus in 14 patients with DLBCL/HGBL.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Case</th><th>Group</th><th>FISH nomenclature</th><th>WGS result summary</th><th>Breakpoint relative to <italic>MYC</italic></th><th>Breakpoint relative to partner gene</th><th><italic>MYC</italic> overexpression by IHC</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1</td><td>RF</td><td>nuc ish(5&#x02019;MYCx3,3&#x02032;MYCx2)(5&#x02019;MYC con 3&#x02032;MYCx2)[42/100]/(MYCx3)[30/100]</td><td><italic>MYC</italic>:<italic>:TG</italic> (deletion within copy gain of chr8 leading to this juxtaposition event)</td><td>Intergenic, telomeric to <italic>MYC</italic></td><td>Intergenic, centromeric to <italic>TG</italic> (break within <italic>KCNQ3</italic>)</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td>2</td><td>RF</td><td>nuc ish(5&#x02032;MYCx2,3&#x02032;MYCx1)(5&#x02032;MYC con 3&#x02032;MYCx1)[100]</td><td><italic>MYC</italic>::<italic>TG</italic></td><td>Intergenic, telomeric to <italic>MYC</italic>, centromeric to <italic>PVT1</italic></td><td><italic>TG</italic>, intron 26 (NM_003235.5)</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td>3</td><td>RF</td><td>nuc ish,(5&#x02032;MYCx2&#x02009;~&#x02009;3,3&#x02032;MYCx1-2)(5&#x02032;MYC con 3&#x02032;MYCx1-2)[97/100]</td><td><italic>MYC</italic>:<italic>:IRF8</italic></td><td>Intergenic, telomeric to <italic>MYC</italic> and <italic>PVT1</italic></td><td><italic>IRF8</italic>, intron 2 (NM_002163.4)</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td>4</td><td>RF</td><td>nuc ish(5&#x02032;MYCx2&#x02009;~&#x02009;3,3&#x02032;MYCx1-2)(5&#x02032;MYC con 3&#x02032;MYCx1-2)[61/100]</td><td><p><italic>MYC</italic>::<italic>SPAG1</italic></p><p>Templated insertion of <italic>MYC</italic> telomeric to <italic>ADAM7</italic></p><p><italic>2. MYC::ADAM28</italic></p></td><td><p>1. Intergenic, telomeric to <italic>MYC</italic> and <italic>PVT1</italic></p><p>2. Intergenic, centromeric to <italic>MYC</italic></p></td><td><p>1. <italic>SPAG1</italic>, intron 10, (NM_003114.5)</p><p>2. <italic>ADAM28/ADAM7</italic></p></td><td>No</td></tr><tr><td>5</td><td>RF</td><td>nuc ish(5&#x02019;MYCx2&#x02009;~&#x02009;5,3&#x02019;MYCx1&#x02009;~&#x02009;2)(5&#x02019;MYC con 3&#x02019;MYCx1&#x0223c;2)[100]</td><td>Relative gain of <italic>MYC</italic>, break in <italic>PVT1</italic></td><td>Telomeric to <italic>MYC</italic>, <italic>PVT1</italic>, intron 1 (NR_003367.3)</td><td>NA</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td>6</td><td>GF</td><td>nuc ish(5&#x02019;MYCx1&#x02009;~&#x02009;3,3&#x02019;MYCx2&#x02009;~&#x02009;4)(5&#x02019;MYC con 3&#x02019;MYCx1&#x0223c;3)[80/100]</td><td><italic>MYC</italic>::<italic>ACTB</italic> (fusion predicted)</td><td>Genic, <italic>MYC</italic> intron 1</td><td><italic>ACTB</italic>, Intron 2 (NM_001101.5)</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td>7</td><td>GF</td><td>nuc ish(5&#x02019;MYCx1,3&#x02019;MYCx2)(5&#x02019;MYC con 3&#x02019;MYCx1)[68/100]</td><td>Relative copy number loss including <italic>MYC</italic> in the setting of copy number gain of chr8q</td><td>NA</td><td>NA</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td>8</td><td>RGF</td><td>nuc ish(5&#x02032;MYCx2&#x02009;~&#x02009;4,3&#x02032;MYCx2&#x02009;~&#x02009;4)(5&#x02032;MYC sep 3&#x02032;MYCx1)[90/100]</td><td><italic>MYC</italic>::IGH (with trisomy 8)</td><td>Genic, <italic>MYC</italic> intron 1</td><td>Intergenic, centromeric to IGHE</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td>9</td><td>RGF</td><td>nuc ish(5&#x02032;MYC,3&#x02032;MYC)x2&#x0223c;4(5&#x02032;MYC con 3&#x02032;MYCx1&#x02009;~&#x02009;2)[93/100]</td><td><italic>MYC</italic>::<italic>RFTN1</italic> fusion predicted (with trisomy 8)</td><td>Genic, <italic>MYC</italic> exon 3 (NM_002467))</td><td>Intron 2 of <italic>RFTN1</italic> (NM_015150)</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td>10</td><td>RGF</td><td>nuc ish(5&#x02032;MYCx2&#x02009;~&#x02009;5,3&#x02032;MYCx2&#x02009;~&#x02009;5)(5&#x02032;MYC con 3&#x02032;MYCx1&#x02009;~&#x02009;2)[100]</td><td><p>1. <italic>MYC</italic>::<italic>DMD</italic></p><p>2. <italic>CASC8</italic>::<italic>PTCHD1</italic></p><p>3. <italic>CASC8</italic>::<italic>DMD</italic></p><p>4. <italic>MYC</italic>::<italic>DMD</italic></p></td><td><p>1. Genic, <italic>MYC</italic> 3&#x02032;UTR</p><p>2. Upstream of <italic>MYC</italic>, <italic>CASC8</italic> intron 4 (NR_117100)</p><p>3. Upstream of <italic>MYC</italic>, <italic>CASC8</italic> intron 4</p><p>4. Intergenic, telomeric to <italic>MYC</italic></p></td><td><p>1. <italic>DMD</italic>, intron 1, (NM_000109)</p><p>2. Intergenic, centromeric/upstream of <italic>PTCHD1</italic> (NM_173495)</p><p>3. <italic>DMD</italic>, intron 1 (NM_00109)</p><p>4. <italic>DMD</italic>, intron 1 (NM_00109)</p></td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td>11</td><td>RGF</td><td>nuc ish(MYCx2)(5&#x02032;MYC sep 3&#x02032;MYCx1)[96/100]</td><td><italic>MYC</italic>::<italic>ZCCHC7</italic> fusion predicted</td><td>Intergenic, Breakpoint centromeric to <italic>MYC</italic></td><td>Intron 2 of <italic>ZCCHC7</italic> (NM_032226)</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td>12</td><td>RGF</td><td>nuc ish(MYCx2)(5&#x02032;MYC sep 3&#x02032;MYCx1)[92/100]</td><td><italic>MYC</italic>::IGLL5 fusion (2 rearrangements)</td><td><p>1. Intergenic, telomeric to <italic>MYC</italic>, upstream of <italic>PVT1</italic></p><p>2. Intergenic, telomeric to <italic>MYC</italic> and <italic>PVT1</italic></p></td><td><p>1. IGLL5, intron 1 (NM_001178126)</p><p>2. IGLL5, intron 1</p></td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td>13</td><td>RGF</td><td>nuc ish(MYCx2)(5&#x02032;MYC sep 3&#x02032;MYCx1)[94/100]</td><td><italic>MYC</italic>::IGL</td><td>Telomeric to <italic>MYC</italic>, <italic>PVT1</italic> intron 1 (NR_003367.3) and deletion of <italic>PVT1</italic> (complex event)</td><td>Intergenic, downstream of (telomeric) IGLL5</td><td>Yes</td></tr><tr><td>14</td><td>RGF</td><td>nuc ish(MYCx2)(5&#x02032;MYC sep 3&#x02032;MYCx1)[100]</td><td><italic>MYC</italic>::<italic>BCL11A</italic></td><td>1. Intergenic, telomeric/downstream of <italic>MYC</italic> and <italic>PVT1</italic></td><td><italic>BCL11A</italic> intron 1 (NM_022893.4)</td><td>Yes</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>NA</italic> not applicable, <italic>RGF</italic> red-green-fusion-type pattern, <italic>RF</italic> red-fusion-type pattern, <italic>GF</italic> green-fusion type pattern, <italic>FISH</italic> fluorescence in situ hybridization, <italic>WGS</italic> whole-genome sequencing</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Clinical correlation</title><p id="Par10">Clinical information was available for 3 cases with a RF-type pattern (Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>). While one case exhibited a favorable response to MR-CHOP chemotherapy, the other two cases remained refractory to therapy (R-CHOP and R-CHOP followed by R-ICE, polatuzumab+bendamustine respectively) and expired from disease. In the first case with a GF-type pattern, a favorable response to R-CHOP chemotherapy was exhibited; nonetheless, the patient expired from sepsis and multi-organ failure. In the second case, no systemic therapy was provided to the patient.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par11">The relevance of elucidating the implications of unbalanced <italic>MYC</italic> BAP results is underscored by the variability of interpretative practices across clinical laboratories highlighted by the survey we distributed to the cytogenetics community. Our study reveals the presence of true SV juxtaposing the <italic>MYC</italic> locus with a partner gene in most of these cases (4/5 with a RF-type pattern and &#x000bd; with a GF-type pattern). The remaining two cases (1/5 with a RF-type pattern and 1/2 with a GF-type pattern) also displayed a SV involving the <italic>MYC</italic> locus, yet these consisted of CN alterations and would not be considered as <italic>MYC</italic>-R per current DLBCL/HGBCL classification schemes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. In all cases, material 5&#x02032; of <italic>MYC</italic> for RF-type patterns and 3&#x02032; of <italic>MYC</italic> for GF-type patterns was present at a higher copy number state relative to 3&#x02032; and 5&#x02032; regions, thereby explaining the unbalanced FISH results.</p><p id="Par12"><italic>MYC</italic>-R in DLBCL/HGBCL are thought to be acquired through aberrant activation-induced cytidine deaminase (<italic>AICDA</italic>)-mediated somatic hypermutation (SHM) and class-switch recombination (CSR) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. While <italic>AICDA</italic> mediates SHM and CSR at the IG loci, off-target mutagenic activity of this enzyme may occur in lymphoma-associated oncogenes such as <italic>MYC</italic> and result in oncogenic rearrangements. Breakpoints associated with <italic>MYC</italic> rearrangements exhibit significant variability within the <italic>MYC</italic> region. They may occur in a region designated as the &#x0201c;genic cluster&#x0201d; which encompasses a segment ~1.5&#x02009;kb upstream of the transcription start site and the first exon and intron of <italic>MYC</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. In our cohort, one case with a GF-type pattern exhibited a breakpoint within intron 1, a mechanism which has been suggested to result in aberrant <italic>MYC</italic> expression through dissociation of the natural promoter regions P1 and P2 and regulatory sites, resulting in transcription initiation from a cryptic promoter P3 in intron 3 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Breakpoints located downstream of <italic>MYC</italic> may result in aberrant activation through the acquisition of <italic>MYC</italic> super-enhancers within a topologically-associated domain (TAD) comprising <italic>MYC</italic>, thus allowing for <italic>MYC</italic> activation through long-range loop interactions favored by a common CTCF binding site located 2&#x02009;kb upstream of <italic>MYC</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Heterologous enhancers conferred by the rearrangement event may promote aberrant <italic>MYC</italic> expression in this setting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. In line with these considerations and in support of their potential for <italic>MYC</italic> activation, 4/5 RF-type cases involved breakpoints located downstream of <italic>MYC</italic>.</p><p id="Par13">By study design, all cases with unbalanced FISH results and a confirmed <italic>MYC</italic>-R by WGS involved a non-IG partner gene. Consequently, the potential significance of these rearrangements must be taken into the context of the unclear prognostic relevance of non-IG <italic>MYC</italic>-R [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. An additional interpretative consideration of cases with unbalanced FISH results relates to the observation that these involved novel non-recurrent non-IG partner genes. Accordingly, in the absence of RNA expression data, whether these result in <italic>MYC</italic> overexpression remains difficult to ascertain, yet these were associated with <italic>MYC</italic> overexpression by IHC. Also, recently Collinge et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] demonstrated that unbalanced patterns with loss of R or G signals were associated with mRNA expression levels comparable to HGBCL with <italic>MYC</italic> and <italic>BCL2</italic> rearrangements exhibiting balanced <italic>MYC</italic> FISH results. Similarly, several of the <italic>BCL2</italic> rearrangement in RF-type cases involved non-IG partners. In light of a paucity of data on atypical <italic>BCL2</italic> rearrangement partners, their clinical significance remains ambiguous. Our study is further limited by a limited sample size which precluded a refined analysis of potential differential implications of different unbalanced patterns by FISH. A recent study suggested that while patterns with 5&#x02032;<italic>MYC</italic> gains may adversely impact prognosis, a loss of 3&#x02032;<italic>MYC</italic> may not portend similar deleterious implications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>].</p><p id="Par14">In all, our study reveals that true genomic SV involving the <italic>MYC</italic> locus often underlie unbalanced <italic>MYC</italic> BAP FISH results. While these SV may result in a juxtaposition of <italic>MYC</italic> with a rearrangement partner, less frequently, they may also be associated with a CN alteration at the <italic>MYC</italic> locus. Accordingly, our results counsel caution in the interpretation of the significance of these unbalanced BAP <italic>MYC</italic> signal patterns. While larger studies are needed to validate our findings, an interpretation rendered as &#x02018;likely positive&#x02019; for a rearrangement at the <italic>MYC</italic> gene locus may be most judicious. While the significance of an unbalanced pattern by <italic>MYC</italic> BAP analysis cannot be ascertained with BAP FISH testing alone and data remains currently limited, most cases have been shown to represent true rearrangements at the <italic>MYC</italic> gene region (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). This may allow communication of the atypical nature of results while also providing added context reflecting the current body of evidence for the provider. Additional testing may assist in further clarifying whether a true rearrangement juxtaposing <italic>MYC</italic> with a gene partner and resulting in <italic>MYC</italic> overexpression is present.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Proposed algorithm to guide the interpretation of unbalanced results obtained with the <italic>MYC</italic> break-apart (BAP) probe based on study results.</title><p>Unbalanced patterns include RF (red-fusion)-type and GF (green-fusion)-type patterns. See text for further information. *It has previously been shown that evaluation for <italic>MYC</italic> rearrangements using only the <italic>MYC</italic> BAP is associated with a false negative (FN) rate of at least 4%. This FN rate can be reduced using IG/<italic>MYC</italic> D-FISH probes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. DF: probe dual color, dual-fusion probe set, IHC immunohistochemistry, RNAseq RNA sequencing, SV structural variant, WGS whole genome sequencing.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41408_2023_967_Fig2_HTML" id="d32e1299"/></fig></p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><sec id="Sec13"><title>Supplementary information</title><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41408_2023_967_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplemental material</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41408-023-00967-8.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The Mayo Clinic Department of Laboratory Medicine and Pathology provided funding for this study. The authors wish to acknowledge Mayo CCaTS for supporting this work (grant number UL1TR002377).</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>MFG and ARP: data curation, formal analysis, writing-original draft. FH and DS: data curation, writing-review and editing. SHJ: data curation, formal analysis, writing-review and editing. GK and AM: sample preparation, writing-review and editing. CZM, PTG, XX, RPK, EDM, RLK, and JFP: formal analysis, writing-review and editing. GV: data curation, formal analysis, writing-review and editing, supervision. LBB: Conceptualization, data curation, formal analysis, supervision, methodology, writing&#x02013;review and editing, project administration.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>For original data, please contact Baughn.linda@mayo.edu.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par15">XX served as a consultant for Kura oncology. GV is the owner of WholeGenome LLC. LBB served as a consultant for Roche-Genentech. The remaining authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaffe</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Quintanilla-Martinez</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Swerdlow</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The International consensus classification of mature lymphoid neoplasms: a report from the Clinical Advisory Committee</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2022</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>1229</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood.2022015851</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35653592</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Swerdlow SH, Campo E, Harris NL, Jaffe ES, Pileri SA, Stein H, et al. WHO Classification of Tumours of Haematopoietic and Lymphoid Tissues. Lyon: International Agency for Research on Cancer (IARC); 2017. 585 p.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alaggio</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Amador</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Anagnostopoulos</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Attygalle</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Araujo</surname><given-names>IBO</given-names></name><name><surname>Berti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The 5th edition of the World Health Organization classification of haematolymphoid tumours: lymphoid neoplasms</article-title><source>Leukemia</source><year>2022</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>1720</fpage><lpage>48</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41375-022-01620-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35732829</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Leval</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Alizadeh</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergsagel</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name><name><surname>Campo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dogan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genomic profiling for clinical decision making in lymphoid neoplasms</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2022</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>2193</fpage><lpage>227</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood.2022015854</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36001803</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gagnon</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Greipp</surname><given-names>PT</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoppman</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ketterling</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MYC break-apart FISH probe set reveals frequent unbalanced patterns of uncertain significance when evaluating aggressive B-cell lymphoma</article-title><source>Blood Cancer J</source><year>2021</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>184</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41408-021-00578-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34819491</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Smadbeck</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckloff</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Karagouga</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chromosomal junction detection from whole-genome sequencing on formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded tumors</article-title><source>J Mol Diagn</source><year>2021</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>375</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmoldx.2020.12.006</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33387698</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lieber</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mechanisms of human lymphoid chromosomal translocations</article-title><source>Nat Rev Cancer</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>387</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrc.2016.40</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27220482</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben-Neriah</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Slack</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ennishi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Mottok</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>High-resolution architecture and partner genes of MYC rearrangements in lymphoma with DLBCL morphology</article-title><source>Blood Adv</source><year>2018</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>2755</fpage><lpage>65</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/bloodadvances.2018023572</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30348671</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Busch</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Klose</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Woessmann</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreuder</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Level of MYC overexpression in pediatric Burkitt&#x02019;s lymphoma is strongly dependent on genomic breakpoint location within the MYC locus</article-title><source>Genes Chromosomes Cancer</source><year>2004</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>178</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/gcc.20063</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15287031</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schuijers</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Manteiga</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Weintraub</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamudio</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Hnisz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional dysregulation of MYC reveals common enhancer-docking mechanism</article-title><source>Cell Rep.</source><year>2018</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>349</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2018.03.056</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29641996</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Drier</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitton</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cotton</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaur</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Issner</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Detection of enhancer-associated rearrangements reveals mechanisms of oncogene dysregulation in B-cell lymphoma</article-title><source>Cancer Discov</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>1058</fpage><lpage>71</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/2159-8290.CD-15-0370</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26229090</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Copie-Bergman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuilliere-Dartigues</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Baia</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Briere</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Delarue</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Canioni</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MYC-IG rearrangements are negative predictors of survival in DLBCL patients treated with immunochemotherapy: a GELA/LYSA study</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2015</year><volume>126</volume><fpage>2466</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2015-05-647602</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26373676</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosenwald</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bens</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Advani</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrans</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Copie-Bergman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Elsensohn</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prognostic significance of MYC rearrangement and translocation partner in diffuse large B-cell lymphoma: a study by the lunenburg lymphoma biomarker consortium</article-title><source>J Clin Oncol</source><year>2019</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>3359</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.19.00743</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31498031</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Collinge</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben-Neriah</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilton</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Alduaij</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Tucker</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Slack</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Do Unbalanced MYC Break-Apart FISH Patterns Indicate the Presence of a MYC Rearrangement?</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2022</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>9244</fpage><lpage>6</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2022-170065</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Toruner</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Clinical impact of 5(&#x02018;)MYC or 3(&#x02018;)MYC gain/loss detected by FISH in patients with aggressive B-cell lymphomas</article-title><source>Cancer Genet</source><year>2023</year><volume>272-273</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cancergen.2022.12.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36566629</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>King</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>McPhail</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasmatzis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Pearce</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Smadbeck</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>False-negative rates for MYC fluorescence in situ hybridization probes in B-cell neoplasms</article-title><source>Haematologica</source><year>2019</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>e248</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3324/haematol.2018.207290</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30523057</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
