<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="letter" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur J Trauma Emerg Surg</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Eur J Trauma Emerg Surg</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>European Journal of Trauma and Emergency Surgery</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1863-9933</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1863-9941</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">37367971</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC10728227</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2314</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00068-023-02314-9</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Letter to the Editor</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title><italic>ER24/1 !</italic>: The greatest emergency of our time</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>van Ee</surname><given-names>Elaine Pei-Jing Xiao-Wei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>Nicolas D. John</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0816-3413</contrib-id><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>John Howard</given-names></name><address><email>JHB121654@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05xvt9f17</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.10419.3d</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 8945 2978</institution-id><institution>Leiden University Medical Center, </institution></institution-wrap>Leiden, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/02e2c7k09</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5292.c</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2097 4740</institution-id><institution>TU Delft, </institution></institution-wrap>Delft, The Netherlands </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7839.5</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 1936 9721</institution-id><institution>JW Goethe University, </institution></institution-wrap>Frankfurt am Main, Germany </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>27</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>27</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>49</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>2323</fpage><lpage>2325</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>5</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2023</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article's Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article's Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Johann Wolfgang Goethe-Universit&#x000e4;t, Frankfurt am Main (1022)</institution></funding-source></award-group><open-access><p>Open Access funding enabled and organized by Projekt DEAL.</p></open-access></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer-Verlag GmbH Germany, part of Springer Nature 2023</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="Par1">The artistic video presentation accompanying this editorial, titled &#x0201c;<italic>ER24/1 !&#x0201d;</italic> was created by the Dutch artist, Maria Koijck, and is the fourth in a series of five different and unique artistic creations, each assembled using medical waste collected from procedures in five different subspecialties [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. The medical waste represented here in <italic>ER24/1 !</italic> consists of 146&#x000a0;kg (139 bags) of single-use, disposable waste generated while treating 92 patients, during 24&#x000a0;h on a weekday at a single Emergency Department in the Netherlands. Once collected, the discarded waste was assembled and captured on film by the artist, and edited by Eva Glasbeek. The accompanying music was composed and performed by Lucas Raimbault.</p><p id="Par2"><italic>Background of &#x0201c;ER24/1 !&#x0201d;:</italic> Maria Koijck [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>] was diagnosed with breast cancer in 2009 and treated with a mastectomy and breast reconstruction at the University Medical Center Groningen (UMCG), in the Netherlands. Following this life-altering experience, she chose&#x02014;through her art&#x02014;to turn this traumatic experience into something positive. Shocked by the amount of discarded single-use medical supplies used in her breast reconstruction, she asked the surgical staff to collect the pre-, intra-, and post-operative waste, and with it, she created her first work of art using medical waste [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. She hoped that her creation would make others aware of the enormous amount of waste generated from a single surgery&#x02014;her own surgery. In the artist&#x02019;s own words, these creations are &#x0201c;to raise awareness in the medical community of the shocking amount of waste used in these medical procedures. Hopefully, by highlighting this astonishing amount of waste, my art will open people&#x02019;s eyes and motivate them to act to help reduce medical waste&#x0201d; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>].</p><p id="Par3">The World Health Organization (WHO) defines healthcare systems as &#x0201c;<italic>organizations, people and actions whose primary intent is to promote, restore or maintain health</italic>&#x0201d; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Contrary to this definition, healthcare systems, through their disproportionally large environmental footprint, have an unintended negative impact on human health, and instead of promoting it, they cause significant disease, suffering, and death. Healthcare&#x02019;s oversized environmental footprint is caused primarily by air pollution, through excessive energy use&#x02014;electricity, gas, steam, air conditioning, and incineration of waste [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Air pollutants, in the form of particulate matter, carbon monoxide, ozone, nitrogen dioxide, and sulfur dioxide increase the incidence and severity of illnesses like stroke, heart disease, lung cancer, and acute and chronic respiratory disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. To put this into perspective, &#x0201c;Air pollution exceeds malaria in the number of premature deaths globally by a factor of 19; it exceeds violence by a factor of 16, HIV/AIDS by a factor of 9, alcohol by a factor of 45, and drug abuse by a factor of 60." [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. The&#x000a0;Lancet&#x000a0;Commission on Pollution and Health reports that &#x0201c;&#x02026;pollution is responsible for approximately 9 million deaths per year, or 1 in 6 deaths worldwide&#x0201d; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Healthcare systems cause up to 5% of global greenhouse gas emissions, equivalent to the annual emissions from 514 coal-fired power plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. If the healthcare sector were a country, it would be the fifth largest greenhouse gas emitter on the planet. There is a strong correlation between the size of a country&#x02019;s climate footprint and its health sector spending. Generally, the greater the spending, as measured by a country&#x02019;s GDP, the higher the per capita healthcare emissions. Accordingly, the United States&#x02019; healthcare sector is the world&#x02019;s number one greenhouse gas emitter, in both absolute and per capita terms, producing 7 times more emissions per person than China, and 57 times more per person than India. Of the air pollution attributable to the health sector, 71% is derived from the healthcare supply chain, through the production, transport, and disposal of goods such as pharmaceuticals and other chemicals, food and agricultural products, hospital equipment, single-use instruments, and excess packaging [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].</p><p id="Par4">Eighty-five percent of this waste is general, non-hazardous, and comparable to domestic waste, while the remaining 15% is hazardous material that may be infectious, chemical, or radioactive. Whether hospital waste is labeled as &#x02018;hazardous&#x02019; or &#x02018;non-hazardous&#x02019; influences how it is processed and disposed of. If non-hazardous waste is incorrectly labeled as &#x02018;hazardous&#x02019;, it is processed and disposed of using methods that cause significantly more emissions of pollutants and a greater environmental footprint. Every year, an estimated 16 billion injections are administered worldwide; however, not all the needles and syringes are correctly disposed of. Hospitals in the US generate over 29 pounds of waste per bed per day, or more than 5 million tons of waste each year [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. A large portion of this waste is in the form of disposable, single-use plastic, a great deal of which could be reduced or eliminated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>].</p><p id="Par5">Emergency departments (ED) make up a big part of the activity in a hospital and consequently are also major contributors to hospital waste production. Emergency departments in the United States attend approximately 140 million patients yearly [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Due to this large patient turnover and the high level of stress in busy emergency departments, those who work in these environments often do not prioritize sustainability and proper waste separation and/or disposal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The 139 bags of medical waste represented here in <italic>ER24/1 !</italic> were generated treating 92 patients on 1&#x000a0;day, in 1 ED in the Netherlands. Imagine how much waste is generated treating the 6100 patients seen each day in the Netherlands [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], or the amount of waste generated in the 734,000 daily ED visits in Europe plus the US [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]!</p><p id="Par6">In 2019, a study describing a program to reduce ED waste in a regional hospital in Australia found that efforts to improve waste segregation and recycling failed due to poor compliance. The authors reported that &#x0201c;Staff felt that the process was time consuming and complicated and environmental services staff were seen mixing different waste bins together to simplify the process&#x0201d; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. In an urban tertiary-care academic medical center in the United States, researchers measured the amount of waste generated in their ED, over a period of 24&#x000a0;h (weekday). They reported 671.8&#x000a0;kg of total waste of which the majority (65%) was plastic, there were 200 unused items, and only 14.9% of the waste disposed of in red bags met the criteria for &#x0201c;hazardous&#x0201d; medical waste [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Several authors have proposed measures to improve routine waste management practices in EDs, including stricter recycling and sorting practices, restocking and donating unnecessary items, composting, diverting, and reducing food waste, electronic waste sorting, reusing items, and reducing low-yield laboratory testing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Emergency departments interact with many other specialties and are, thus, uniquely positioned to lead hospital efforts and set an example of best practices for promoting sustainability measures. From a global perspective, the main barriers standing in the way of implementing sustainable practices in the healthcare sector include lack of awareness about the health hazards related to healthcare waste, inadequate training in proper waste management, absence of waste management and disposal systems, insufficient financial and human resources, and the low priority given to the topic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p><p id="Par7">While artists usually do not offer solutions to problems, their creations, in the form of literary, performing or visual art, can heighten our awareness leaving us with impressions that cause us to reflect, debate, and act. It is our hope that disseminating this artistic presentation and accompanying editorial throughout the medical community will help to chip away at these barriers by <italic>heightening awareness</italic> of the shocking amount of waste being generated and the resulting associated health hazards. We hope that the images featured and described in this presentation will cause our fellow healthcare colleagues to act, and while performing their busy daily routines, decide not to use that overpackaged item, or to clean and reuse or recycle that perfectly functional instrument, or not needlessly open that sterile instruments set, or dispose of non-hazardous and/or hazardous waste in the correct bin. These small changes in our busy daily routines, if performed by many, can make a big difference. Given that the healthcare community&#x02019;s primary objective is to promote, restore, and maintain human health, to do so we must extend that care to our planet. After all, our patient&#x02019;s health is inextricably tied to the health of our planet. We hope that this artistic presentation inspires our fellow healthcare colleagues to take action in caring for our planet&#x02019;s health, with the same compassion and dedication they apply in their daily jobs caring for their patients.</p><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><sec id="Sec2"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="68_2023_2314_MOESM1_ESM.mp4"><caption><p>Supplementary file1 (MP4 132069 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="68_2023_2314_MOESM2_ESM.png"><caption><p>Supplementary file2 (PNG 21256 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></p></sec></sec></body><back><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Open Access funding enabled and organized by Projekt DEAL.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p id="Par8">The authors have no financial, non-financial and/or competing interests to declare that are relevant to the content of this Letter to the Editor.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Maria Koijck - surgery waste. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.mariakoijck.com/surgery-waste">https://www.mariakoijck.com/surgery-waste</ext-link>. Accessed 26 May 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nelissen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Baby Fe&#x02019;s first environmental footprint &#x02013; there must be a better way!</article-title><source>Editorial. Int J Surg</source><year>2022</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>106874</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijsu.2022.106874</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36067961</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Maria Koijck - spatial art. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.mariakoijck.com/">https://www.mariakoijck.com/</ext-link>. Accessed 26 May 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Dit, is het afval van &#x000e9;&#x000e9;n operatie, mijn operatie ! <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ajneXFJ1k2I">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ajneXFJ1k2I</ext-link>. Accessed 26 May 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Everybody business: strengthening health systems to improve health outcomes: WHO&#x02019;s framework for action. World Health Organization. Geneva. 2007. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/handle/10665/43918/9789241596077_eng.pdf">https://apps.who.int/iris/bitstream/handle/10665/43918/9789241596077_eng.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 26 May 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization. Health-care waste. WHO. 2018. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/health-care-waste">https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/health-care-waste</ext-link>. Accessed 26 May 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eckelman</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherman</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimated global disease burden from US health care sector greenhouse gas emissions</article-title><source>Am J Public Health</source><year>2018</year><volume>108</volume><issue>suppl 2</issue><fpage>S120</fpage><lpage>S122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2105/AJPH.2017.303846</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29072942</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">World Health Organization &#x02013; air pollution. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.who.int/health-topics/air-pollution#tab=tab_1">https://www.who.int/health-topics/air-pollution#tab=tab_1</ext-link>. Accessed 26 May 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Casey</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Su</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Henneman</surname><given-names>LRF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Improved asthma outcomes observed in the vicinity of coal power plant retirement, retrofit and conversion to natural gas</article-title><source>Nat Energy</source><year>2020</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>398</fpage><lpage>408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41560-020-0600-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32483491</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lelieveld</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pozzer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000f6;schl</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Loss of life expectancy from air pollution compared to other risk factors: a worldwide perspective</article-title><source>Cardiovasc Res</source><year>2020</year><volume>116</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1910</fpage><lpage>1917</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cvr/cvaa025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32123898</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fuller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Landrigan</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Balakrishnan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pollution and health: a progress update</article-title><source>Review</source><year>2022</year><volume>6</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>E535</fpage><lpage>E547</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Healthcare&#x02019;s climate footprint; how the health sector contributes to the global climate crisis and opportunities for action. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://noharm-global.org/sites/default/files/documents-files/5961/HealthCaresClimateFootprint_092319.pdf">https://noharm-global.org/sites/default/files/documents-files/5961/HealthCaresClimateFootprint_092319.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 26 May 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kalarikkal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Recycling of medical plastics</article-title><source>Adv Ind Eng Polym Res</source><year>2021</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>208</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Chemicals and pollution action: how to reduce the impacts of single-use plastic products. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.unep.org/news-and-stories/story/how-reduce-impacts-single-use-plastic-products">https://www.unep.org/news-and-stories/story/how-reduce-impacts-single-use-plastic-products</ext-link>. Accessed 26 May 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Centers for disease control and prevention - emergency department visits. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/fastats/emergency-department.htm">https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/fastats/emergency-department.htm</ext-link>. Accessed 26 May 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elmer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mikati</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Callaway</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Death and end-of-life care in emergency departments in the US - original investigation | emergency medicine</article-title><source>JAMA Netw Open</source><year>2022</year><volume>5</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>e2240399</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamanetworkopen.2022.40399</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36331501</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erkamp</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>van Dalen</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>de Vries</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predicting emergency department visits in a large teaching hospital</article-title><source>Int J Emerg Med</source><year>2021</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>34</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12245-021-00357-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34118866</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">European emergency medicine in numbers. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://eusem.org/images/European_EM_in_numbers.pdf">https://eusem.org/images/European_EM_in_numbers.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed 26 May 2023.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Church</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Briggs</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate emergency: towards a greener emergency department</article-title><source>Emerg Med Australas</source><year>2019</year><volume>31</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>274</fpage><lpage>275</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1742-6723.13269</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30808069</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hsu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Theil</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mello</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dumpster diving in the emergency department: quantity and characteristics of waste at a level I trauma center</article-title><source>West J Emerg Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>21</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>1211</fpage><lpage>1217</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5811/westjem.2020.6.47900</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32970577</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spruell</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Webb</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Steley</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Environmentally sustainable emergency medicine</article-title><source>Emerg Med J</source><year>2021</year><volume>38</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>315</fpage><lpage>318</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/emermed-2020-210421</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33483340</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Linstadt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Slutzman</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The climate-smart emergency department: a primer</article-title><source>Ann Emerg Med</source><year>2020</year><volume>76</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>155</fpage><lpage>167</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.annemergmed.2019.11.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31983497</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McAlister</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Barratt</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The carbon footprint of pathology testing</article-title><source>Med J Aust</source><year>2020</year><volume>212</volume><issue>8</issue><fpage>377</fpage><lpage>382</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5694/mja2.50583</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32304240</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">van Ee E. Reflecting on environmental sustainability in management and organisation of healthcare - Growing environmental sustainability as part of daily practice in an emergency department. MSc thesis - Erasmus University Rotterdam, the Netherlands, 2022 June. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/366486029">https://www.researchgate.net/publication/366486029</ext-link>. Accessed 26 May 2023.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
