<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="letter" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BMC Genomics</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BMC Genomics</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1471-2164</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38105226</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC10726491</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">9881</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-023-09881-6</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Matters Arising</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Response to correspondence on &#x0201c;B chromosomes of multiple species have intense evolutionary dynamics and accumulated genes related to important biological processes&#x0201d;</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>Syed F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Valente</surname><given-names>Guilherme T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Martins</surname><given-names>Cesar</given-names></name><address><email>cesar.martins@unesp.br</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/00987cb86</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.410543.7</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2188 478X</institution-id><institution>Department of Structural and Functional Biology, </institution><institution>Institute of Bioscience at Botucatu, Sao Paulo State University (UNESP), </institution></institution-wrap>Botucatu, 18618-689 SP Brazil </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05gzceg21</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.9723.f</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0944 049X</institution-id><institution>Animal Genomics and Bioresource Research Unit (AGB Research Unit), Faculty of Science, </institution><institution>Kasetsart University, </institution></institution-wrap>50 Ngamwongwan, Chatuchak, Bangkok, 10900 Thailand </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>18</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>18</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>24</volume><elocation-id>779</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>6</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>7</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2023</copyright-statement><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated in a credit line to the data.</license-p></license></permissions><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; BioMed Central Ltd., part of Springer Nature 2023</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="Par1">The correspondence article by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] (Ruiz-Ruano and Camacho, 2023) raises a number of important and valid concerns in our previous article [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>](Ahmad et al. 2020). We are grateful to commentators for their exquisitely detailed and rigorous comments on our paper. Here, we respond to make corrections recognizing our unintentional mistakes in the paper and address the major comments in the following points.</p><sec id="Sec1"><title>1. Information of sequenced data in our study</title><p id="Par2">We acknowledge the comment by Ruiz-Ruano and Camacho [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] that &#x0201c;The reads deposited in the Sequence Read Archive (SRA) had already been trimmed but it was not specified in the paper&#x0201d;. Here, we would like to inform the readers of our paper [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] that the sequenced data was submitted to SRA as trimmed reads and did not have raw data available. We apologize for the inconvenience caused by the unavailability of the raw data due to HPC technical maintenance. However, the mentioned fact is not so dramatic since an initial data analysis concerning the quality of reads by FastQC toolkit and data filtering would show that the mentioned library was already filtered. We believe that the preprocessing filtering step of raw data has no significant effect on utilizing this data resource for further research. Therefore, this sample should be treated as trimmed data and appropriate filtering/trimming options should be considered by retrievers as per the requirements of downstream analysis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>2. Inaccuracies in our supplementary figures and tables of [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]</title><p id="Par3">In response to the errors mentioned in &#x0201c;misleading datasets&#x0201d; by Ruiz-Ruano and Camacho [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], we acknowledge these errors, and therefore we provide the following details:</p><p id="Par4">We rechecked the missing accession numbers in the coverage plots of Figures S7 and S8 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] and enlist these IDs with relevant information (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><p id="Par5">
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Missing data from Figures S7 and S8 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Transcript ID of reference transcriptome</th><th align="left">0B reads</th><th align="left">1 (2) B reads</th><th align="left">1(2)B/0B</th><th align="left">Annotation</th><th align="left">Gene/Repeat Type</th><th align="left">Log<sub>2</sub> ratio</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">
<bold><italic>Astyanax mexicanus</italic></bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ARA0AAA39YG16EM1.b.am.1</td><td align="left">727</td><td align="left">14,308</td><td align="left">19.68</td><td align="left">novel_gene</td><td align="left">Gene</td><td align="left">4.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ARA0AAA100YB14EM1.b.am.1</td><td align="left">10</td><td align="left">160</td><td align="left">16</td><td align="left">Wu</td><td align="left">Gene</td><td align="left">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ARA0AAA109YO19EM1.b.am.1</td><td align="left">9</td><td align="left">73</td><td align="left">8.11</td><td align="left">(CAA)n</td><td align="left">DNA_repeats</td><td align="left">3.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ARA0AAA114YD18EM2.b.am.1</td><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">128</td><td align="left">18.29</td><td align="left">Dldh</td><td align="left">Gene</td><td align="left">4.19</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ARA0ABA18YP03EM1.b.am.1</td><td align="left">9</td><td align="left">63</td><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">unknown</td><td align="left">unknown</td><td align="left">2.81</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ARA0ABA86YJ16EM1.b.am.1</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">39</td><td align="left">13</td><td align="left">(TTGT)n</td><td align="left">DNA_repeats</td><td align="left">3.7</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ARA0ABA110YF05EM1.b.am.1</td><td align="left">11</td><td align="left">111</td><td align="left">10.09</td><td align="left">unknown</td><td align="left">unknown</td><td align="left">3.34</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ARA0AGA13YG24EM1.b.am.1</td><td align="left">89</td><td align="left">472</td><td align="left">5.3</td><td align="left">unknown</td><td align="left">unknown</td><td align="left">2.41</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">
<bold><italic>A. correntinus</italic></bold>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ARA0AAA7YM13EM1.b.am.1</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">152</td><td align="left">152</td><td align="left">(AATA)n</td><td align="left">DNA_repeats</td><td align="left">7.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ARA0AAA8YO20EM1.b.am.1</td><td align="left">102</td><td align="left">143</td><td align="left">1.4</td><td align="left">ERV1A-CPo_I-int</td><td align="left">DNA_repeats</td><td align="left">0.49</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ARA0AAA105YI15EM1.b.am.1</td><td align="left">277</td><td align="left">1496</td><td align="left">5.4</td><td align="left">Tars</td><td align="left">Gene</td><td align="left">2.43</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ARA0ABA109YD04EM1.b.am.1</td><td align="left">311</td><td align="left">400</td><td align="left">1.29</td><td align="left">(AAT)n</td><td align="left">DNA_repeats</td><td align="left">0.36</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ARA0AAA27YN14EM1.b.am.1</td><td align="left">572</td><td align="left">3585</td><td align="left">6.27</td><td align="left">unknown</td><td align="left">unknown</td><td align="left">2.65</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ARA0ABA89YC04EM1.b.am.1</td><td align="left">118</td><td align="left">933</td><td align="left">7.91</td><td align="left">unknown</td><td align="left">unknown</td><td align="left">2.98</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ARA0AAA69YE12EM1.b.am.1</td><td align="left">1005</td><td align="left">1612</td><td align="left">1.6</td><td align="left">I-3_DR</td><td align="left">DNA_repeats</td><td align="left">0.68</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ARA0ABA32YK17EM1.b.am.1</td><td align="left">70</td><td align="left">376</td><td align="left">5.37</td><td align="left">unknown</td><td align="left">unknown</td><td align="left">2.43</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par6">We further clarify that the transcriptome assembly of <italic>A. mexicanus</italic> (used as reference for both <italic>A. mexicanus</italic> and <italic>A. correntinus</italic>) was retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genotoul-contigbrowser.toulouse.inra.fr:9099/ngspipelines/data/1651096bdb/analysis96cf6c918ccontigs.fa.gz">http://genotoul-contigbrowser.toulouse.inra.fr:9099/ngspipelines/data/1651096bdb/analysis96cf6c918ccontigs.fa.gz</ext-link>, although this link is currently inaccessible. This transcriptome assembly was submitted by Hinaux et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>] in the web browser <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genotoul-contigbrowser.toulouse.inra.fr:9099">http://genotoul-contigbrowser.toulouse.inra.fr:9099</ext-link>. The transcriptome assembly of <italic>L. migratoria</italic> (used as reference for <italic>A. flavolineata</italic>) was retrieved from NCBI database (accession ID: GDIO00000000.1).</p><p id="Par7">In addition, we clarify that &#x0201c;The information regarding <italic>A. mexicanus</italic> and <italic>A. correntinus</italic> has been mistakenly interchanged&#x0201d;. The <italic>A. mexicanus</italic> mappings in Table&#x000a0;3 of Ahmad et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] correspond to <italic>A. correntinus</italic> and vice versa. In addition, the column of &#x0201c;2B&#x0201d; actually correspond to &#x0201c;1B&#x0201d; reads in the Supplementary Dataset 3 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. We are sorry that such mistakes could have caused confusion for readers, but at the same time we reinforce that the BMC Genomics makes available contacts of the authors that should be reached in any doubt while accessing data.</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>3. Low reproducibility and data normalization</title><p id="Par8">In their comment, the commentators pointed out a core issue of low reproducibility in the results of <italic>A. correntinus</italic>, mainly in the transcriptome-based coverage ratio analysis. We appreciate the commentators&#x02019; efforts in their attempts to reproducing the results and detecting many false positive genes. They emphasize data normalization due to higher sequencing coverage in B+(1B) dataset, which we neglected in our article [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>], and they offer a rigorous explanation of the approaches employed for avoiding false-positive genes on B chromosomes.</p><p id="Par9">Meanwhile, we would like to point out that due to the scarcity of a gold-standard protocol to study B chromosomes, uncertain mapping parameters, and lack of rigorous statistical significance criteria for normalization, it is difficult to rule out the possibility of false-positive genes/sequences on B chromosomes and data validation. Therefore, specialized bioinformatic tools with detailed step-by-step protocols with given instructions on adapting the appropriate technique are essential for valid detection of genes on B chromosomes. This can further benefit the B chromosome research community and also allow beginner bioinformaticians or biologists with basic computational skills to avoid the technical errors. Nevertheless, due to the variety of experimental systems, providing a universal strategy for each approach is not feasible. Therefore, it is recommended to identify the most optimal parameters for one&#x02019;s specific study in order to get the best results.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>4. Additional issues and corrections</title><p id="Par10">Here, first we would like to sincerely apologize for the unintended errors in our published work:</p><p id="Par11">
<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par12">We acknowledge that some of the references were mistakenly not cited in the given context.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par13">We apologize for mistakenly not citing the &#x0201c;2019 bioRxiv preprint&#x0201d; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] reference in the statement &#x0201c;evolutionary success of the B chromosome lies on its gene contents&#x0201d;.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par14">We acknowledge that schematic model shown as Fig.&#x000a0;9 in our manuscript was partially adopted from idea presented in Martis et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Although we have cited Martis et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>] in our work [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>], we apologize for the unintentional omission of this mention in figure caption.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par15">We agree with the concern of utilizing data from microdissected B chromosome sequences may have generated bias as discussed in the comment. We want to clarify that although we applied stringent filtering criteria for this analysis, we recognize the limitations of low coverage data and the pseudo-scaffolding strategy must be considered before drawing any strong conclusion from this data. However, this was not a mistake since that was the data which was generated and retrieved from NCBI at that time.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par16">Apart from admitting the errors mentioned, we respectfully disagree with some of the conceptual critiques on our paper&#x02019;s speculations, as stated in the discussion section of commentary.</p></list-item></list>
</p><p id="Par17">Concerning the definition of B chromosome, we do not attempt to define &#x0201c;B chromosome&#x0201d;, but only to contrast the characteristics of A (regular chromosomes) and B by noting that in most of the cases reported, Bs are unpaired unlike A. Although an initial definition for universal properties of B chromosomes was proposed in 1993 (1st B Chromosome Conference, Spain (Beukeboom 1994 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>])) we see that Bs exhibit diverse behavior across different organisms and have generated extensive debates among scientists, as registered during the 5th B Chromosome Conference (Serbia, 14&#x02013;17 October, 2023 - <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://5thbcc.com/">https://5thbcc.com/</ext-link>).</p><p id="Par18">In regards to the comment of null hypothesis, we acknowledge that the phenomenon of selfish transmission has not been observed in any of the three species we studied, but our aim was to study whether B chromosomes tend to accumulate certain sequences that could confer them a transmission advantage. It is important to clarify that our paper does not include a &#x0201c;null hypothesis&#x0201d;; instead, we establish a research question in the introduction to delineate the objectives of our study, which had an exploratory goal.</p><p id="Par19">We do not agree with comment that our claim of &#x0201c;migration of substantial genomic regions from A to B chromosomes via transpositions, duplications and rearrangements&#x0201d; lacks data support. Our paper presents genome-based detection, FISH mapping, qPCR validation and literature review as supporting evidence for our statement.</p><p id="Par20">We disagree with the commentary point of tagging one of our paper&#x02019;s sentences as &#x0201c;an anti-Darwinian post-adaptive statement&#x0201d;. In our paper, we suggest that B chromosomes may have acquired a tendency to gain sequences for their own maintenance in the cell. We want to clarify that, this mention in our study does not contradict Darwinism in any way; and we further encourage future studies to test whether these sequences on B are accumulated by chance randomly or by selection. To avoid the discrepancy regarding our original paper&#x02019;s sentence we revised the sentence as follow:</p><p id="Par21">It seems that the movement of sequences onto the B chromosome after its formation per se is likely not selected for, but instead these events may be undirected, and certain sequences, once moved, could be advantageous to the B chromosome.</p></sec><sec id="Sec231"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par23">The advancement of B chromosome science depends on the continuous development of research methods that contribute to improve existing knowledge and overcome the limitations of previous studies to generate new insights. One example is our study published in 2020, which contributes to the field of B chromosome biology by generating high coverage sequencing datasets and providing insights into detection of sequences located on B chromosome of different species. Nevertheless, our study (Ahmad et al. 2020) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] was not without errors and certain technical limitations in its methodological approach, as pointed out by commentators [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] (Ruiz-Ruano and Camacho, 2023). We acknowledge the potential bias, and appreciate this feedback of several corrections. We do believe that there are still many challenges and gaps in analytical approaches to fully understand the B chromosome genomic content that need to be addressed by future studies. It is recommended to establish well-defined and gold-standard protocols, especially bioinformatic tools, that can ensure better reproducibility of results and reliability of the methodology employed for studying the complexity of B chromosomes.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We acknowledge the two anonymous reviewers for their valuable suggestions and comments that helped us to improve our revised manuscript.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>SFA, GTV and CM drafted and revised the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Not applicable.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>Not applicable.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar3"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par28">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par29">Not applicable.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par26">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ruiz-Ruano FJ, Camacho JPM. Irreproducible results and unsupported conclusions in Ahmad [BMC Genomics(2020) 21:656]. BMC Genomics.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ahmad</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Jehangir</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardoso</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><name><surname>Margarido</surname><given-names>VP</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabral-de-Mello</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>B chromosomes of multiple species have intense evolutionary dynamics and accumulated genes related to important biological processes</article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2020</year><volume>21</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>656</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-020-07072-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32967626</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Hinaux H, Poulain J, Da Silva C, Noirot C, Jeffery WR, Casane D, et al. De Novo sequencing of <italic>Astyanax mexicanus</italic> Surface Fish and Pach&#x000f3;n Cavefish transcriptomes reveals Enrichment of mutations in Cavefish Putative Eye genes. PLoS ONE. 2013;8. 10.1371/journal.pone.0053553.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ruiz-Ruano</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Navarro-Dom&#x000ed;nguez</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000f3;pez-Le&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabrero</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Camacho</surname><given-names>JPM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolutionary success of a parasitic B chromosome rests on gene content</article-title><source>bioRxiv</source><year>2019</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/683417</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martis</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Klemme</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Banaei-Moghaddam</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Blattner</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Macas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmutzer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Selfish supernumerary chromosome reveals its origin as a mosaic of host genome and organellar sequences</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2012</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>13343</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1204237109</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22847450</pub-id>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beukeboom</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bewildering bs: an impression of the 1st B-Chromosome conference</article-title><source>Heredity</source><year>1994</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>328</fpage><lpage>36</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/hdy.1994.140</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
