<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="article-commentary"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Natl Sci Rev</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Natl Sci Rev</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">nsr</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>National Science Review</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2095-5138</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2053-714X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC10727839</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nsr/nwad240</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">nwad240</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>PERSPECTIVE</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading"><subject>EARTH SCIENCES</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="category-toc-heading"><subject>Special Topic: Mass Extinction</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>Nsr/9</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="category-taxonomy-collection"><subject>AcademicSubjects/MED00010</subject><subject>AcademicSubjects/SCI00010</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Analysis of ancient mass extinction recoveries in marine environments: generating strategies for managing outcomes of the current mass extinction</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Bottjer</surname><given-names>David J</given-names></name><!--dbottjer@usc.edu--><aff>
<institution>Department of Earth Sciences, University of Southern California</institution>, <country country="US">USA</country></aff><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp"/></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">E-mail: <email>dbottjer@usc.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>1</month><year>2024</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2023-09-12"><day>12</day><month>9</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>12</day><month>9</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>nwad240</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>4</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>05</day><month>9</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>08</day><month>9</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="corrected-typeset"><day>31</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2023. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of China Science Publishing &#x00026; Media Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted reuse, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="nwad240.pdf"/><counts><page-count count="3"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p>The defining feature of a mass extinction and its associated recovery is the global amount of extinction that occurred [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. However, there is finer-scale detail to the story, as seen in the ongoing modern mass extinction (the sixth mass extinction), which exhibits variable effects among marine ecosystems and environments, and hence geographic areas [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. One of the best examples of extreme effects on a broad geographic scale is the plight of modern coral reef ecosystems, which as the &#x02018;canary in the coal mine&#x02019; are showing extensive signs of continued devastation [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Another example of an extreme effect on the broad geographic but individual species scale is the plight of the polar bear, a marine mammal that largely depends upon extensive arctic sea ice to pursue its hunting lifestyle [<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. With increased global warming, arctic sea ice has been disappearing rapidly over recent years, thus imperiling the survival of polar bears. Intriguingly, it has been recently suggested that polar bears may have an enhanced chance of surviving the current mass extinction in nearshore glacial environments of Southeast Greenland, where they hunt from glacial ice (Fig. <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1A</xref>), which could act as a refugium for the bears [<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Although much of the possible variability in biotic devastation due to the ongoing modern mass extinction in marine environments and ecosystems remains to be determined, this sort of information will be very relevant in predicting and managing how the oceans will recover once this mass extinction episode subsides.</p><fig position="float" id="fig1"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Examples of the role of refugia in surviving mass extinctions. (A) Modern polar bear in southeast Greenland using glacial ice (from [<xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]&#x02014;reprinted with permission from AAAS). (B) Earliest Early Triassic fossil sea urchin (echinoid) showing disarticulated spines surrounding the crushed test, which lived in a deeper-water slope setting in what is now China. Scale is in cm/mm. Photograph by Amanda Godbold. Reproduced with permission.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="nwad240fig1" position="float"/></fig><p>One way to better understand this biological and spatial variability is to examine ancient mass extinctions, particularly those with the largest amount of extinction (the Big Five mass extinctions [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]), where nature has already run the experiment and we can determine variability due to the mass extinction, and how the recovery proceeded. These mass extinctions are complex intervals in Earth's history, and some of the best cases for geographic and ecosystem variability are from the end-Permian mass extinction and the following Early Triassic, the &#x0223c;5-million-year-long recovery period after this mass extinction [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. The end-Permian mass extinction, the largest of the Big Five ancient mass extinctions affecting marine species (80%&#x02013;94%), occurred &#x0223c;252 million years ago, and was caused by a variety of factors set off by a geologically rapid increase in atmospheric and ocean temperature [<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. This temperature increase was ultimately caused by emplacement and eruption of what is called the Siberian Traps large igneous province [<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. This igneous event involved 2&#x02013;7 million cubic kilometers of basalt that erupted on the landmass now known as Siberia [<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Much of the erupting magma passed through carbon-rich sedimentary rocks, the baking of which produced a significant amount of carbon dioxide and hence atmospheric global warming [<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. The geologically sudden global warming caused by this volcanic event is called a hyperthermal, and it can serve as an analogue to our modern global warming, particularly since the modern warming is caused by burning of carbon rich products from sedimentary rock, in this case by our own species [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. However, a crucial difference is that the modern rate of warming is occurring much faster than that which caused the end-Permian mass extinction (e.g. [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]).</p><p>Much like the trend of increasing biotic degradation seen in modern reefs, biotic complexity of Early Triassic reefs was significantly reduced compared with the preceding Late Permian [<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Lower Triassic reefs are typically relatively small constructions made primarily of microbial features and sponges (e.g. [<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]). Reef recovery after the end-Permian mass extinction is characterized by the appearance of scleractinian corals, more than 5 million years later in the Middle Triassic [<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Similarly, fossils of sea urchins, or echinoids (a group of echinoderms), were strongly affected by the end-Permian mass extinction and are a relatively rare occurrence in the Early Triassic [<xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. In marine environments, the global warming associated with this mass extinction shifted the oceanic oxygen-minimum zone onshore, strongly contributing to extinction [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Since echinoids are so rare during this recovery interval, it has been of great interest to find an earliest Early Triassic occurrence of echinoids in a deeper-water slope setting (Fig. <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1B</xref>), which was presumably cooler and with sufficient oxygen, where they survived in what is thought to have been a refugium [<xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>].</p><p>As a baseline for the temporal and geographic variability of recovery from this mass extinction, much of the Early Triassic level-bottom shallow seafloor seems to have undergone severe extinction, with only a depauperate fauna, compared to similar seafloor environments before the mass extinction (e.g. [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]). However, several level-bottom environments and locations during this time have been shown to have had a much more diverse and ecologically complex marine fauna (e.g. [<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9&#x02013;12</xref>]). This confirms that the recovery from the end-Permian mass extinction was temporally, geographically and ecologically patchy, with marine communities in some ecosystems and/or parts of the world recovering more quickly than in others.</p><p>These variable biotic, environmental and geographic patterns of recovery from the end-Permian mass extinction can be used as a foundation for a more general model of such variability in mass extinction recovery. Thus, rather than uniform devastation, the Earth is a mosaic of ecosystems and environments, each of which is responding in a different way and at a different rate to the changing environment, caused largely by variability and duration of that mass extinction's trigger and kill mechanisms. Each ecosystem and environment will show different levels of extinction, from mild to extreme. Coming out of a mass extinction the recovery will develop, with these different ecosystems and environments having suffered differing amounts of extinction. Upon this template recovery will ensue, again with this mosaic pattern. Depending upon when the extinction has happened in geological time, varying effects due to differences in paleogeography and ocean chemistry as well as the dominance of different evolutionary faunas, will occur [<xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].</p><p>As this variability has increasingly been documented from the marine Early Triassic, a number of ways of measuring recovery have been utilized. Early Triassic ecological recovery studies have used paleoecological data to establish recovery stages from 1 (least) to 4 (most recovered) (e.g. [<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]). Using this approach, different ecosystems at different times in the Early Triassic can be categorized as having recovered on the 1&#x02013;4 scale (e.g. [<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]), and pieces of this mosaic will differentially take a longer or shorter amount of time to recover. Other ways to assess recovery have included using various measures of biodiversity combined with information on degree of ecological complexity [<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. From such studies it has been shown that Early Triassic pelagic ecosystems appear to have recovered faster than benthic systems (e.g. [<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]), and different benthic systems, including those defined by bioturbation, appear to have recovered faster than others [<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">11&#x02013;13</xref>]. In contrast, reef ecosystems show the longest time to recovery (e.g. [<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]). It is this mosaic of extinction devastation and subsequent recovery that has led to the variety of recovery schemes utilized for the end-Permian mass extinction, which largely depend upon data type and availability for the ecosystem that is being studied.</p><p>Understanding this mosaic and its recovery categorization for the end-Permian mass extinction will be very important for planning and managing the recovery from the sixth mass extinction in modern environments. Establishing which Early Triassic ecosystems in level-bottom environments suffered the most will point the way to modern studies on similar ecosystems and environments. Knowing which modern ecosystems are likely to suffer the most, particularly for marine environments, which have received less attention than terrestrial environments, will allow for establishment of strategies to enable these settings to recover in more rapid fashion [<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. There has already been significant progress in accumulating knowledge on the varying effects of the current mass extinction on different environments and ecosystems (e.g. [<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]). Thus, the well-known plight of modern reef ecosystems has stimulated a wide variety of reef conservation biology research (e.g. [<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]). Much of this research has focused on the effects of ocean acidification, not only for reefs, but all settings, particularly for open ocean ecosystems (e.g. [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]). Less well-studied are the extensive nearshore and shelf level-bottom environments. In these settings the changing role of bioturbators during such mass extinction stresses is in need of additional attention, as these processes affect not only ecological structure but also biogeochemical processes (e.g. [<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]). Comparison of ancient and modern outcomes from mass extinction stresses also needs to filter out additional effects caused by human activity, unique to the modern extinction, such as overfishing, overhunting and global use of pesticides and fertilizers [<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Proceeding in a systematic way, this most important project of conservation paleobiology and paleoecology will allow better management of Earth's ecosystems as mass extinction stresses are diminished. If these modern stresses continue beyond expectations, a very important product of these investigations will be to predict where refuges, such as for the polar bear, might exist for organisms to survive the sixth mass extinction.</p></body><back><ack id="ack1"><title>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</title><p>Thanks to all my colleagues and former students who over the years have taught me much about mass extinctions and their recoveries. Comments and suggestions for improvement by Corinne Myers and three anonymous reviewers on an earlier draft of this paper are greatly appreciated.</p></ack><sec id="sec2"><p>
<bold>
<italic toggle="yes">Conflict of interest statement</italic>.</bold> None declared.</p></sec><ref-list id="ref1"><title>REFERENCES</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Kolbert</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</string-name>
</person-group>. <source>The Sixth Extinction</source>. <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Henry Hold and Company</publisher-name>, <year>2014</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Chaudhary</surname>
<given-names>C</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Alfaro-Lucas</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Simoes</surname><given-names>MVP</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<source>Prog Oceanogr</source>
<year>2023</year>; <volume>213</volume>: <fpage>e103001</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pocean.2023.103001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Laidre</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Supple</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Born</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<source>Science</source>
<year>2022</year>; <volume>376</volume>: <fpage>1333</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.abk2793</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35709290</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Bottjer</surname>
<given-names>DJ</given-names>
</string-name>
</person-group>. <source>Science</source><year>2012</year>; <volume>338</volume>: <fpage>336</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1228998</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23087236</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Dal Corso</surname>
<given-names>J</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Callegaro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<source>Nat Rev Earth Environ</source>
<year>2022</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>197</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>214</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s43017-021-00259-4</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Martindale</surname>
<given-names>RC</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Velledits</surname><given-names>F</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>Palaeogeogr Palaeoclimatol Palaeoecol</source><year>2019</year>; <volume>513</volume>: <fpage>100</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.palaeo.2017.08.014</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Thompson</surname>
<given-names>JR</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>S-x</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q-Y</given-names></string-name></person-group>
<italic toggle="yes">et al.</italic>
<source>R Soc Open Sci</source>
<year>2018</year>; <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e171548</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsos.171548</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Godbold</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Schoepfer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<source>Geology</source>
<year>2017</year>; <volume>45</volume>: <fpage>607</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1130/G38793.1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Brayard</surname>
<given-names>A</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Krumenacker</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Botting</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<source>Sci Adv</source>
<year>2017</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>e1602159</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciadv.1602159</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28246643</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Dai</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>JHFL</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<source>Science</source>
<year>2023</year>; <volume>379</volume>: <fpage>567</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>72</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.adf1622</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36758082</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Foster</surname>
<given-names>WJ</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Godbold</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Brayard</surname><given-names>A</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<source>PeerJ</source>
<year>2022</year>; <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>e14357</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.14357</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36569998</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Friesenbichler</surname>
<given-names>E</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Hautmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Bucher</surname><given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group>. <source>PeerJ</source><year>2021</year>; <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>e11654</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.11654</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34322318</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Feng</surname>
<given-names>X</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Z-Q</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Benton</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<source>Sci Adv</source>
<year>2022</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>eabo0597</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciadv.abo0597</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35767613</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author">
<string-name>
<surname>Calosi</surname>
<given-names>P</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name><surname>Putnam</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>Twitchett</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></string-name><etal>et al.</etal></person-group>
<source>Annu Rev Mar Sci</source>
<year>2019</year>; <volume>11</volume>: <fpage>369</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-marine-010318-095106</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
