<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="discussion"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Public Health</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Public Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2296-2565</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38125850</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC10731282</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fpubh.2023.1305655</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Public Health</subject><subj-group><subject>Opinion</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Double trouble: compounding effects of COVID-19 pandemic and antimicrobial resistance on drug resistant TB epidemiology in India</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Husain</surname><given-names>Aliabbas A.</given-names></name><uri xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1712751/overview"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Kashyap</surname><given-names>Rajpal Singh</given-names></name><xref rid="c001" ref-type="corresp">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff><institution>Advanced Research Center, Central India Institute of Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Nagpur</addr-line>, <country>India</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Adwoa Asante-Poku, University of Ghana, Ghana</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Felix Khuluza, Kamuzu University of Health Sciences (formerly College of Medicine-University of Malawi), Malawi</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Rajpal Singh Kashyap <email>raj_ciims@rediffmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>1305655</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>02</day><month>10</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>13</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2023 Husain and Kashyap.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Husain and Kashyap</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><kwd-group><kwd>TB</kwd><kwd>MDR-TB</kwd><kwd>India</kwd><kwd>antimicrobial resistance</kwd><kwd>COVID-19</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>The author(s) declare that no financial support was received for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="1"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="29"/><page-count count="4"/><word-count count="2702"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>section-at-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Infectious Diseases: Epidemiology and Prevention</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Antimicrobial resistance (AMR) has been regarded as a global health threat by the WHO (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). The rise of general AMR to multiple drugs in the Indian population poses a formidable challenge to the TB control strategies, especially for drug-resistant tuberculosis (DR-TB). India has been regarded as having one of the highest burdens of drug resistant (DR) pathogens, including multi-drug-resistant TB (MDR-TB), which accounts for a quarter of the global burden (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). A 6-year observational study in south India on the prevalence of DR-TB indicated a high proportion (11%) of rifampicin and isoniazid mono-resistance in new cases (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Increasing trends of DR-TB in new cases highlight potential public health concerns, as globally, 78% of rifampicin-resistant TB (RR-TB) cases were identified to be MDR-TB (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). In India, major mediating factors for the high incidence of DR-TB in new cases include transmission of AMR strains in endemic communities and acquired DR due to misuse and overuse of antimicrobials.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>The COVID-19 pandemic and its consequences on TB care in India</title><p>A compounding effect of COVID-19 on TB care has been extensively reported earlier in various countries (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). According to a recent WHO global TB report, India was the largest contributor to the global shortfall in TB case notification in 2020 compared to other high-burden countries (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). A significant impact of reduced TB case notification was directly observed on the incidence of TB and DR-TB in India, which showed a significant decline in 2020 (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>) compared to previous years, which should be mainly attributable to restricted access to healthcare facilities amid lockdown measures in the country (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). Available reports suggest MDR-TB patients co-infected with COVID-19 pose formidable challenges in treatment, as COVID-19 can favor bacterial replication in the lungs through interference in intestinal homeostasis (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). The empirical use of antibiotics is considered to be an important risk factor for the development of resistance (<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). As per a recent modeling analysis report, COVID-19 in India contributed to about 216 million excess doses of antibiotics in between epidemic peaks (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Reports from a meta-analysis by Langford et al. (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>) showed high antibiotic usage (~71.9%) in hospitalized COVID-19 patients, even though only 6&#x02013;9% of them were confirmed to have bacterial infection. Studies also indicate high antibiotic prescribing patterns of almost 82% in Southeast-Asian countries (excluding China) during the pandemic period (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). As a result, the incidence of MDR infections in COVID-19 patients is estimated to be around 32&#x02013;50% (<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>). Additionally, oral glucocorticoids such as methylprednisolone and intravenous monoclonal antibody tocilizumab therapy to control IL-6-induced cytokine release syndrome (CRS) were used rampantly in India during the second wave, despite a stringent WHO advisory on their administration (<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). A case report by Khayat et al. indicated that prolonged corticosteroid therapy in COVID-19 leads to significant CD4 and CD8 T-cell depletion and may promote the development of active infection in latent close contacts of TB cases (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). This represents a significant public health concern, particularly for COVID-infected close contacts of MDR-TB cases, who might be at high risk for conversion to active infection due to depletion and dysfunction of T-cells similar to HIV.</p></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Increasing AMR in India and its impact on MDR-TB epidemiology</title><p>India has been regarded as the global capital of AMR (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). According to the national anti-TB DR survey conducted by the Indian government in collaboration with the WHO and the United States Agency for International Development (USAID), it was found that around 23% of new cases showed resistance to any drug, with MDR-TB detected in 3% (<xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). In addition, ~36% of MDR-TB cases tested for resistance to second-line anti-tuberculosis medications showed resistance to fluoroquinolones (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). One of the major drivers of AMR in India is the irrational consumption of non-prescribed drugs taken as self-medication (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). India is regarded as the top consumer of antibiotics for humans among all other countries (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). Between 2005 and 2009, India witnessed a 40% rise in the sale of antibiotics, with sales of new-generation cephalosporin increasing by almost 60% (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). According to one survey, ~52% of the Indian population is estimated to be self-medicating (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Despite regulations on the sale of schedule H1 and X drugs in India, second-line drugs like fluoroquinolones are readily available over the counter (OTC) in pharmacies due to their rampant empirical use against a wide variety of infections. Such OTC practices are even more prevalent in peripheral and rural zones of India, wherein mostly experienced and untrained pharmaceutical staff can prescribe the wrong combination and duration of drugs to the locals. As a result, it is estimated that the majority of people consuming OTC drugs generally under-dose themselves, exposing bacteria to non-lethal drug concentrations and thereby developing DR. <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figures 1A</xref>, <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">B</xref> shows general drug resistant pattern of carbapenem, fluoroquinolones and aminoglycosides on common invasive isolates of <italic>E. coli, P. aeruginosa</italic> in India and China. In addition to self-medication, high prescription and consumption patterns of second- and third-line antibiotics (<xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Figure 1C</xref>) and mismanagement of TB presumptive cases by private physicians and pharmacists at the primary care level have been attributed to bolstering AMR cases in Indian communities (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). A study published by Arinaminpathy et al. (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>) shows mismanagement and a lack of standard of care followed by private practitioners among presumptive TB cases as one of the major drivers for MDR-TB development. Similar studies by Kwan et al., based on referral rates of patients to healthcare centers, have shown a significant impact of urban pharmacies on TB control (<xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Their study shows low referral rates of presumptive cases by urban pharmacies as a major compounding factor for low detection rates and disease control.</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Trend of Antibiotic resistance (2019&#x02013;20) among second line drugs against invasive isolates of <bold>(A)</bold>
<italic>Pseudomonas aeruginosa</italic> and <bold>(B)</bold>
<italic>E. coli</italic> in India and China. <bold>(C)</bold> Represents trend of antibiotic consumption pattern of common drugs in Indian population represented as defined daily dose (DDDs) per million populations. Source: One Health Trust. Resistance Map: Antibiotic resistance 2023. <ext-link xlink:href="https://resistancemap.onehealthtrust.org/AntibioticResistance.php" ext-link-type="uri">https://resistancemap.onehealthtrust.org/AntibioticResistance.php</ext-link> (accessed May 31, 2023).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fpubh-11-1305655-g0001" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Actions taken so far to combat AMR and DR-TB in India</title><p>To combat AMR, India introduced several measures, including the &#x0201c;Red Line&#x0201d; campaign in 2016 and the National Action Plan (NAP) on AMR in 2017 (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). Additionally, the Cosmetics and Drug Act launched in 2013 prohibited the sale of Schedule H1 drugs without prescription in India, which includes second- and third-generation antibiotics and anti-TB drugs. With due cognizance of AMR, the National Center for Disease Control under the Ministry of Health and Family Welfare, Government of India, developed a national plan on AMR containment with the objectives of improving awareness and surveillance of AMR in Indian health settings. In 2017, India launched its revised national strategic plan (NSP) with the ambitious goal of ending TB by 2025. Under its revised NSP (2017&#x02013;25), the Government of India introduced several aggressive steps, such as decentralization of DR-TB services for better accessibility under the private sector, universal drug susceptibility testing (U-DST) for presumptive patients from MDR-TB hotspots, and scaling up diagnostic services of CBNAAT, True NAT, and line probe assays in low-resource settings for better surveillance and diagnosis (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s5"><title>Discussion</title><p>Despite the aggressive efforts made under the revised NSP, DR-TB cases continue to bolster in Indian health settings. Improved commitments are needed to integrate antimicrobial stewardship programs under pandemic response to frontline providers for the management of TB patients co-infected with COVID-19. Integration of TB health services with AMR programs can be done to leverage the expertise of TB control planners for strengthening diagnostic capacity for AMR testing, surveillance, better quality assurance, record keeping, and logistics. Expanding the diagnostic scope of TB testing laboratories for AMR surveillance in high-endemic spots for TB can be useful for developing important public health measures for combating AMR. Joint efforts and funding commitments from major TB stakeholders are needed globally to develop improved diagnostics and surveillance tools to detect AMR in second- and third-line drugs in high-TB settings. Similarly, efforts are needed to develop diagnostic stewardship programs that include mandatory U-DST for second-line drugs in COVID health care settings, COVID-19 hotspots and TB-endemic settings for early diagnosis and treatment outcomes. Accelerated surveillance and vigilance at local pharmacies is needed to minimize the sale of OTC schedule H1 and X drugs. The development of an online, multilingual, free consultation system for primary care physicians with TB health care providers with expertise in clinical and management experience can improve AMR stewardship for DR-TB. The European respiratory society has a similar web-based free consultation system for South Africa (<xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>), which can be extended to highly endemic South Asian countries for better DR-TB management.</p><p>The alarming rise of AMR in Indian communities in the aftermath of waves combined is a major risk driver for future MDR-TB epidemics in India. The country needs immediate attention on surveillance of DR in COVID hotspots to minimize future transmission of MDR in communities. Additionally, increased political commitments and advocacy are needed to bolster antimicrobial stewardship in COVID care hospitals and quarantine zones to minimize the irrational use of empirical regimens. Such advocacy is needed to prevent the risk of the development of AMR in Indian communities and improve treatment outcomes for cases of MDR-TB in India in the near future.</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s6"><title>Author contributions</title><p>RK: Writing &#x02013; original draft, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing. AH: Conceptualization, Writing &#x02013; original draft, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s8"><title>Publisher's note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World health Organisation</collab></person-group>. <source>Antimicrobial Resistance</source>. (<year>2021</year>). Available online at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/antimicrobial-resistance" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/antimicrobial-resistance</ext-link> (accessed May 23, 2023).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taneja</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antimicrobial resistance in the environment: the Indian scenario</article-title>. <source>Indian J Med Res.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>149</volume>:<fpage>119</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/ijmr.IJMR_331_18</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31219076</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shivekar</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaliaperumal</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Brammacharry</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakkaravarthy</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Raj</surname><given-names>CKV</given-names></name><name><surname>Alagappan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Prevalence and factors associated with multi-drug-resistant tuberculosis in South India</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>175</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>52</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-020-74432-y</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31932743</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aznar</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Espinosa-Pereiro</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Saborit</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jov&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez Martinez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez-Recio</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on tuberculosis management in Spain</article-title>. <source>Int J Infect Dis</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>108</volume>:<fpage>300</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2021.04.075</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33930543</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Husain</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Monaghan</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kashyap</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Impact of COVID-19 pandemic on tuberculosis care in India</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Infect.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>27</volume>:<fpage>293</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmi.2020.08.014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32822881</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glaziou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Predicted impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on global tuberculosis deaths in 2020</article-title>. (<year>2020</year>) <italic>MedRxiv</italic>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/2020.04.28.20079582</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><source>World Health Organisation Global Tuberculosis Report</source>. (<year>2021</year>). Available online at: <ext-link xlink:href="http://file:///D:/Data%20from%20C%20drive/Downloads/9789240037021-eng.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">file:///D:/Data%20from%20C%20drive/Downloads/9789240037021-eng.pdf</ext-link> (accessed June 1, 2023).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Central Tuberculosis Division, Government Government of India</collab></person-group>. <source>India Tuberculosis Report 2021. India: Revised National Tuberculosis Control Program</source>. (<year>2021</year>). Available online at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://tbcindia.gov.in/showfile.php?lid=3587" ext-link-type="uri">https://tbcindia.gov.in/showfile.php?lid=3587</ext-link> (accessed December 10, 2021).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Stop TB Partnership</collab></person-group>. <source>The Potential Impact of the Covid-19 Response on Tuberculosis in High-Burden Countries: A Modelling Analysis</source>. (<year>2020</year>). Available online at: <ext-link xlink:href="http://www.stoptb.org/assets/documents/news/Modeling%20Report_1%20May%202020_FINAL.pdf" ext-link-type="uri">http://www.stoptb.org/assets/documents/news/Modeling%20Report_1%20May%202020_FINAL.pdf</ext-link> (accessed November 10, 2021).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marwah</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Peter</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><name><surname>Ajai Kumar</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhati</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Multidrug-resistant tuberculosis in COVID-19: double trouble</article-title>. <source>Med J Armed Forces India</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>77</volume>(<issue>Suppl. 2</issue>):<fpage>S479</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>82</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mjafi.2021.05.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34334915</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pelfrene</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Botgros</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Cavaleri</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antimicrobial multidrug resistance in the era of COVID-19: a forgotten plight</article-title>. <source>Antimicrob Resist Infect Control</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>10</volume>:<fpage>21</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13756-021-00893-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33514424</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Menon</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahu</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wig</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>National clinical registry for COVID-19 team. Clinical profile of hospitalised COVID-19 patients in first &#x00026; second wave of the pandemic: insights from an Indian registry based observational study</article-title>. <source>Indian J Med Res</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>0153</volume>:<fpage>619</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>28</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/ijmr.ijmr_1628_21</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Adebisi</surname><given-names>YA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jimoh</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogunkola</surname><given-names>IO</given-names></name><name><surname>Uwizeyimana</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Olayemi</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Ukor</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The use of antibiotics in COVID-19 management: a rapid review of national treatment guidelines in 10 African countries</article-title>. <source>Trop Med Health.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>23</volume>:<fpage>49</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>51</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s41182-021-00344-w</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34162445</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sulis</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Batomen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotwani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gandra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Sales of antibiotics and hydroxychloroquine in India during the COVID-19 epidemic: an interrupted time series analysis</article-title>. <source>PLoS Med</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>18</volume>:<fpage>e1003682</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.1003682</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34197449</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Langford</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>So</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Raybardhan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Leung</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Westwood</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>MacFadden</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Bacterial co-infection and secondary infection in patients with COVID-19: a living rapid review and meta- analysis</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>26</volume>:<fpage>1622</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmi.2020.07.016</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32711058</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pierce</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>COVID-19 and antimicrobial stewardship: lessons learned best practices, and future implications</article-title>. <source>Int J Infect Dis.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>113</volume>:<fpage>103</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijid.2021.10.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34624517</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pasero</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Cossu</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Terragni</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Multi-drug resistance bacterial infections in critically ill patients admitted with COVID-19</article-title>. <source>Microorganisms</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>9</volume>:<fpage>1773</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/microorganisms9081773</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34442852</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaudhry</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Tocilizumab and COVID-19</article-title>. <source>Indian J Crit Care Med</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>24</volume>:<fpage>741</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5005/jp-journals-10071-23608</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33132549</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khayat</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Vali</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>COVID-19 promoting the development of active tuberculosis in a patient with latent tuberculosis infection: a case report</article-title>. <source>Respir Med Case Rep.</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>101344</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rmcr.2021.101344</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33495728</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Ministry of Health and Family Welfare GoI</collab></person-group>. <source>Report of the First National Anti-tuberculosis Drug Resistance Survey: India 2014&#x02013;16</source>. (<year>2018</year>). Available online at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://tbcindia.gov.in/showfile.php?lid=3315" ext-link-type="uri">https://tbcindia.gov.in/showfile.php?lid=3315</ext-link> (accessed December 10, 2022).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kashyap</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Husain</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Over-the-counter drug distribution and tuberculosis control in India</article-title>. <source>Lancet Infect Dis.</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>1208</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>9</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(16)30262-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27568358</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Boeckel</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gandra</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ashok</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Caudron</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Grenfell</surname><given-names>BT</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Global antibiotic consumption 2000 to 2010: An analysis of national pharmaceutical sales data</article-title>. <source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>. (<year>2014</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<fpage>742</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>50</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(14)70780-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25022435</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marathe</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamat</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Tripathi</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Raut</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Khatri</surname><given-names>NP</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Over-the-counter medicines: global perspective and Indian scenario</article-title>. <source>J Postgrad Med</source>. (<year>2020</year>) <volume>66</volume>:<fpage>28</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/jpgm.JPGM_381_19</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31898596</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dixit</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Trigun</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Antimicrobial resistance: progress in the decade since emergence of New Delhi Metallo-&#x003b2;-lactamase in India</article-title>. <source>Indian J Community Med.</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>44</volume>:<fpage>4</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/ijcm.IJCM_217_18</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30983704</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arinaminpathy</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Batra</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Khaparde</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vualnam</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Maheshwari</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The number of privately treated tuberculosis cases in India: estimation from drug sales data</article-title>. <source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>. (<year>2016</year>) <volume>16</volume>:<fpage>1255</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(16)30259-6</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27568356</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kwan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Daniels</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergkvist</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Pai</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Das</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Use of standardized patients for healthcare quality research in low- and middle-income countries</article-title>. <source>BMJ Global Health</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>4</volume>:<fpage>e001669</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmjgh-2019-001669</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31565413</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ranjalkar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandy</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>India's National Action Plan for antimicrobial resistance - An overview of the context, status, and way ahead</article-title>. <source>J Family Med Prim Care</source>. (<year>2019</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>1828</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4103/jfmpc.jfmpc_275_19</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31334140</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Husain</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kupz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kashyap</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Controlling the drug-resistant tuberculosis epidemic in India: challenges and implications</article-title>. <source>Epidemic Health</source>. (<year>2021</year>) <volume>43</volume>:<fpage>e2021022</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4178/epih.e2021022</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33831293</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Foster</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Makanda</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Schoeman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Tisile</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Westhuizen</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The role of counselling in tuberculosis diagnostic evaluation and contact tracing: scoping review and stakeholder consultation of knowledge and research gaps</article-title>. <source>BMC Public Health.</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>190</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12889-022-12556-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35090414</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
