<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="editorial"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Immunol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Immunol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Immunol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Immunology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-3224</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38116003</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC10728813</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2023.1340844</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Editorial: The role of radiotherapy in reshaping tumor immune microenvironment</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Xiaoyu</given-names></name><xref rid="fn003" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#x02020;</sup>
</xref><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Mengyu</given-names></name><xref rid="fn003" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>&#x02020;</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2224284"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Yue</surname><given-names>Jinbo</given-names></name><xref rid="fn001" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1133958"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<institution>Department of Radiation Oncology, Shandong Cancer Hospital and Institute, Shandong First Medical University and Shandong Academy of Medical Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Jinan, Shandong</addr-line>, <country>China</country>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited and Reviewed by: Vito Longo, National Cancer Institute Foundation (IRCCS), Italy</p></fn><corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: Jinbo Yue, <email xlink:href="mailto:jbyue@sdfmu.edu.cn">jbyue@sdfmu.edu.cn</email>
</corresp><fn fn-type="equal" id="fn003"><p>&#x02020;These authors have contributed equally to this work and share first authorship</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>05</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>14</volume><elocation-id>1340844</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2023 Hu, Zhao and Yue</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Hu, Zhao and Yue</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article related-article-type="commentary-article" id="RA1" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/research-topics/38489" ext-link-type="uri">Editorial on the Research Topic <article-title>The role of radiotherapy in reshaping tumor immune microenvironment</article-title>
</related-article><kwd-group><kwd>radiotherapy</kwd><kwd>immunotherapy</kwd><kwd>immune microenvironment</kwd><kwd>autophagy</kwd><kwd>colorectal cancer immunotherapy</kwd><kwd>represented by immune checkpoint inhibitors (ICIs)</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="6"/><page-count count="2"/><word-count count="788"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>section-in-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Cancer Immunity and Immunotherapy</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Immunotherapy, represented by immune checkpoint inhibitors (ICIs), has improved outcomes in several types of cancers. However, many patients still do not respond (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). The anti-tumor response mediated by ICIs depends on the infiltration of cytotoxic T lymphocytes (CTLs) that can recognize and kill tumor cells (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>). Tumors can be classified into three primary immune phenotypes based on the spatial distribution of CTLs within the tumor microenvironment (TME): these are the immunoinflammatory phenotype, the immunoexclusionary phenotype, and the immune-desert phenotype (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>). Immunoinflammatory tumors, a.k.a &#x0201c;hot tumors&#x0201d;, are characterized by substantial T cell infiltration, amplified IFN&#x003b3; signaling, and a high tumor mutation burden (TMB). These tumors typically show increased sensitivity to ICIs (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Conversely, immunoexclusionary and immune-desert tumors, which have less immune activity, are often termed &#x0201c;cold tumors&#x0201d;.</p><p>Radiotherapy (RT) can not only directly destroy tumors but also induce a systemic immune response. Radiation induces immunogenic death in tumor cells, activates anti-tumor immune responses, and produces an effect similar to an &#x0201c;<italic>in situ</italic> vaccine&#x0201d; (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Moreover, RT has a multifaceted regulatory effect on immune cells and tumor stroma cells. It can also influence the TME by inducing production of various cytokines, ultimately transforming cold tumors into hot and enhancing the efficacy of immunotherapy (<xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). RT can reshape the immune TME from multiple perspectives, although its specific mechanisms have not been fully elucidated.</p><p>In this Research Topic, multiple studies investigate the role of RT in remodeling the immune TME. <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2022.992626" ext-link-type="uri">Gao et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link> have identified three autophagy-related genes&#x02014;SHC1, NAPSA, and AURKA&#x02014;associated with RT and the prognosis of lung adenocarcinoma. NAPSA and AURKA were also closely associated with T<sub>H</sub>2 cell infiltration. T<sub>H</sub>2 cells promote tumor activity by facilitating angiogenesis and inhibiting the cell-mediated immune response that destroys tumor cells. Accumulating evidence suggests that autophagic activity can regulate immune cell infiltration by modulating both the innate and adaptive immune systems. Therefore, it is possible that autophagy-related genes may inhibit antitumor immunity by promoting T<sub>H</sub>2 cell infiltration following RT. Hence, targeting autophagy-related genes could represent a novel immunomodulatory strategy to enhance the effectiveness of RT in patients with lung adenocarcinoma.</p><p>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2023.1105180" ext-link-type="uri">Shi et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link> provide a summary of radioimmunotherapy in the treatment of colorectal cancer, discussing its current status and future prospects. Patients with microsatellite instability (MSI) comprise less than 5% of rectal cancer cases, while the majority of colorectal cancers are of the microsatellite stable (MSS) type. These MSS patients derive little-to-no benefit from immunotherapy alone. Due to the synergistic effect between RT and immunotherapy, RT can release tumor antigens, reshape the immune microenvironment, and increase the anti-tumor immune response, thereby producing a synergistic therapeutic effect. Numerous prospective phase II studies suggest that the combination of RT with immunotherapy, used for pMMR/MSS locally advanced rectal cancer, has achieved a higher rate of complete pathological response (pCR) (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>).</p><p>
<ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fimmu.2023.1125905" ext-link-type="uri">Chi et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link> show that hRT&#x02019;s regulation of the immune microenvironment depends on the dosage and fractionation pattern of the RT. RT can potentiate antigen presentation, leading to the upregulation of pro-inflammatory cytokine levels and cytotoxic T cell-mediated immunogenic cell death. However, RT can also induce immunosuppressive responses, characterized by the augmented recruitment and infiltration of regulatory T cells, myeloid-derived suppressor cells (MDSCs), and molecules associated with immune checkpoints. Combining RT with immunotherapy may shift this balance, tipping it towards immune activation. This combination could potentially overcome resistance to ICIs and other forms of immunotherapy. Strategies to enhance the efficacy of such combinations warrant further exploration.</p><p>In recent years, numerous <italic>in vivo</italic> studies have revealed the synergistic tumoricidal effects of combining RT with PD-1/-L1 inhibitors. The dynamic nature of the PD-1/-L1 axis, however, has confounded efforts towards a consensus on the optimal timing or dose-fractionation strategy for doing so (<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Understanding the synergistic effects of combining RT with PD-1/PD-L1 blockade requires investigation into the dynamic changes in tumor immune status and circulating biomarkers induced by RT in relation to PD-1/PD-L1 expression. <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fonc.2022.989190" ext-link-type="uri">Yoon et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link> demonstrate that, following RT, PD-L1 expression levels in tumor cells and intratumoral MDSCs, TAMs, and DCs are upregulated, mainly during the period of tumor regression. With tumor regrowth, PD-L1 levels in tumor cells were found to decrease to levels comparable to those at baseline.</p><p>Our understanding of how RT can reshape the immune TME across various levels has continued to grow, informed by a legion of molecular and animal studies as well as clinical trials. As research in this area progresses, it is anticipated that the confluence of RT and immunotherapy will yield increasingly potent therapeutic interactions.</p><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s1"><title>Author contributions</title><p>XH: Writing &#x02013; original draft. MZ: Writing &#x02013; original draft. JY: Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s2"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s3"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mellman</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Elements of cancer immunity and the cancer-immune set point</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>541</volume>(<issue>7637</issue>):<page-range>321&#x02013;30</page-range>. doi:&#x000a0;<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature21349</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bruni</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Angell</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Galon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The immune contexture and Immunoscore in cancer prognosis and therapeutic efficacy</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Cancer</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>20</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<page-range>662&#x02013;80</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41568-020-0285-7</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hegde</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Karanikas</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Evers</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The where, the when, and the how of immune monitoring for cancer immunotherapies in the era of checkpoint inhibition</article-title>. <source>Clin Cancer Res</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>22</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<page-range>1865&#x02013;74</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-15-1507</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Radiation as an <italic>in situ</italic> auto-vaccination: current perspectives and challenges</article-title>. <source>Vaccines (Basel)</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>7</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>100</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/vaccines7030100</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31455032</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sharabi</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>DeWeese</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Drake</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Radiation and checkpoint blockade immunotherapy: radiosensitisation and potential mechanisms of synergy</article-title>. <source>Lancet Oncol</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>16</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<page-range>e498&#x02013;509</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1470-2045(15)00007-8</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xiao</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Total neoadjuvant treatment and PD-1/PD-L1 checkpoint inhibitor in locally advanced rectal cancer</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source> (<year>2023</year>) <volume>14</volume>:<elocation-id>1149122</elocation-id>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2023.1149122</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37033988</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
