<!DOCTYPE article
PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="editorial"><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Oncol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Oncol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Oncol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Oncology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2234-943X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">38125943</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC10731952</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fonc.2023.1335049</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Oncology</subject><subj-group><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Editorial: Minimally invasive therapies and molecular mechanisms related to recurrence in hepatobiliary and gastric cancers</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>Manqiu</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/2596450"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/investigation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Wei</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1992028"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/validation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Yuming</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/624492"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Jia</surname><given-names>Changchang</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn001" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/1291705"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/conceptualization/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/supervision/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/validation/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-original-draft/"/><role content-type="https://credit.niso.org/contributor-roles/writing-review-editing/"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
<institution>Department of Cell-Gene Therapy Translational Medicine Research Center, The Third Affiliated Hospital of Sun Yat-Sen University</institution>, <addr-line>Guangzhou</addr-line>, <country>China</country>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
<institution>Department of Hepatobiliary and Pancreatic Surgery, The First Affiliated Hospital, Zhejiang University School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Hangzhou</addr-line>, <country>China</country>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
<institution>Department of Radiation Oncology, Wake Forest University School of Medicine</institution>, <addr-line>Winston-Salem, NC</addr-line>, <country>United States</country>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited and Reviewed by: Liang Qiao, Westmead Institute for Medical Research, Australia</p></fn><corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: Changchang Jia, <email xlink:href="mailto:jiachch3@mail.sysu.edu.cn">jiachch3@mail.sysu.edu.cn</email>
</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>12</month><year>2023</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2023</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>1335049</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>08</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>11</month><year>2023</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2023 Kang, Chen, Jiang and Jia</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2023</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Kang, Chen, Jiang and Jia</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article related-article-type="commentary-article" id="RA1" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/research-topics/49241" ext-link-type="uri">Editorial on the Research Topic <article-title>Minimally invasive therapies and molecular mechanisms related to recurrence in hepatobiliary and gastric cancers</article-title>
</related-article><kwd-group><kwd>gastric cancer</kwd><kwd>anastomotic leakage</kwd><kwd>hepatocellular carcinoma</kwd><kwd>primary hepatic neuroendocrine tumors</kwd><kwd>radiomics</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="4"/><page-count count="2"/><word-count count="612"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>section-in-acceptance</meta-name><meta-value>Gastrointestinal Cancers: Hepato Pancreatic Biliary Cancers</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>This research aims to establish a platform for evaluating the clinical effectiveness and safety of minimally invasive therapies for liver, gallbladder, and gastrointestinal tumors. Additionally, it seeks to explore advanced non-invasive diagnostic methods for predicting tumor prognosis and unravel the molecular mechanisms associated with tumor recurrence in these areas. The study, enriched with cutting-edge research contributions, has successfully achieved its primary goals and formulated recommendations for advancing the treatment and prognosis of these tumors in the future.</p><p>For instance, <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fonc.2023.1163463" ext-link-type="uri">He et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link> conducted a retrospective analysis of clinical and pathological data in gastric cancer patients to investigate risk factors and outcomes of conservative treatment for anastomotic leakage (AL) following gastric resection. Their findings identified low serum albumin, diabetes, laparoscopic surgery, total gastrectomy, and proximal gastrectomy as predictive risk factors for anastomotic leakage. The study emphasizes a shift from surgical to combined conservative and endoscopic interventions in the treatment of anastomotic leakage, with technological advancements supporting the efficacy of endoscopic treatment. This study focuses on analyzing risk factors and treatment options for anastomotic leakage after gastric resection, offering crucial recommendations for managing postoperative complications that significantly impact postoperative survival and quality of life, particularly in the context of tumor diseases (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>).</p><p>Furthermore, <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fonc.2023.1251873" ext-link-type="uri">Liang et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link> explored the relationship between lipid metabolism, the use of lipid-lowering medications, and liver cancer. Given the liver&#x02019;s pivotal role in lipid metabolism and the rising prevalence of obesity (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>), understanding the connection between lipid metabolism, the utilization of lipid-lowering drugs, and the development of liver tumors becomes imperative. Employing Mendelian randomization analysis, the research establishes a causal relationship between individual serum lipid markers and the incidence of liver cancer. The study also employs drug target Mendelian randomization (DMR) analysis to assess the causal impact of LDL-c-lowering medications on the risk of liver cancer, suggesting that such drugs can mitigate the risk by reducing LDL-c levels. This study provides unique insights into predicting the occurrence of liver cancer and offers valuable recommendations for prevention.</p><p>Additionally, <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fonc.2023.1278467" ext-link-type="uri">Chen et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link> conducted a significant study using dual-region CT radiomics to predict FOXM1 expression and prognosis in hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC). Integrating FOXM1 expression with radiomics offers a fresh perspective on non-invasive tumor characterization, implying its potential in providing molecular insights. Within this Research Topic, a case report by <ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fonc.2023.1225583" ext-link-type="uri">Tang et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link> details two cases of primary hepatic neuroendocrine tumors (PHNET). The report aims to document the characteristics of this rare liver tumor, advance comprehension of the disease, enhance diagnostic precision, and explore standardized diagnostic and treatment approaches.</p><p>Collectively, the articles within this Research Topic effectively align with its objectives and exhibit significant innovation. They emphasize the adoption of minimally invasive or non-invasive methods for the treatment and prognostication of liver, gallbladder, and gastrointestinal tumors, offering increased convenience in clinical diagnosis and treatment while mitigating patient discomfort. Pioneering reports, such as the use of Mendelian randomization analysis to establish the causal link between lipid-lowering drugs, LDL-c levels, and the development of liver cancer (<ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fonc.2023.1251873" ext-link-type="uri">Liang et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link>), serve as exemplary models for future research endeavors. The study on radiomics, a fusion of imaging and molecular detection, represents a burgeoning research domain with promising applications in the management of advanced tumors (<ext-link xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fonc.2023.1278467" ext-link-type="uri">Chen et&#x000a0;al.</ext-link>). This research has the potential to provide optimal solutions for addressing the clinical challenges encountered by patients with advanced tumors who cannot undergo invasive testing due to their physical condition, thereby offering a viable remedy for this clinical predicament (<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>).</p><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s1"><title>Author contributions</title><p>MK: Investigation, Writing &#x02013; original draft. WC: Supervision, Validation, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing. YJ: Supervision, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing. CJ: Conceptualization, Supervision, Validation, Writing &#x02013; original draft, Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s3"><title>Conflict of interest</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p><p>The author(s) declared that they were an editorial board member of Frontiers, at the time of submission. This had no impact on the peer review process and the final decision</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s4"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamarajah</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Navidi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Griffin</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Impact of anastomotic leak on long-term survival in patients undergoing gastrectomy for gastric cancer</article-title>. <source>Br J Surg</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>107</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<page-range>1648&#x02013;58</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bjs.11749</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fleming</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Graetz</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Margono</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Global, regional, and national prevalence of overweight and obesity in children and adults during 1980-2013: a systematic analysis for the Global Burden of Disease Study 2013</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>384</volume>(<issue>9945</issue>):<page-range>766&#x02013;81</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(14)60460-8</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ten</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pater</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Storm</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiskirchen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiskirchen</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lammers</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The hepatic lipidome: From basic science to clinical translation</article-title>. <source>Adv Drug Deliv Rev</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>159</volume>:<page-range>180&#x02013;97</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.addr.2020.06.027</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Han</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Occult extracranial Malignancy after complete remission of pineal mixed germ cell tumors: a rare case report and literature review</article-title>. <source>BMC Pediatr</source> (<year>2023</year>) <volume>23</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>447</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12887-023-04213-9</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37679697</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
