<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">pbio</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosbiol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1544-9173</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1545-7885</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC539341</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.0030040</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Synopsis</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Genetics/Genomics/Gene Therapy</subject><subject>Infectious Diseases</subject><subject>Microbiology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="System Taxonomy"><subject>Eubacteria</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Multiple <named-content content-type="genus-species">Campylobacter</named-content> Genomes Sequenced</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Synopsis</alt-title></title-group><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>4</day><month>1</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>4</day><month>1</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>3</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e40</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; 2005 Public Library of Science.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article id="d35e72" related-article-type="companion" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pbio.0030015" xlink:title="research article" vol="3" page="e15">
<article-title>Major Structural Differences and Novel Potential Virulence Mechanisms from the Genomes of Multiple <italic>Campylobacter</italic> Species</article-title>
</related-article></article-meta></front><body><p>In 1995, the first complete bacterial genome sequence was published. Now, nearly 200 bacterial genomes have been completed, and a new one hits the scientific press most weeks. This burgeoning industry is not just scientific &#x0201c;stamp collecting,&#x0201d; however. Having all these genome sequences may provide useful clues about why some bacteria cause human disease, how to control their spread, and how to treat the infections caused by them. By comparing genome sequences, scientists can learn much more about what makes a bacteria tick than they can learn from a single sequence.</p><p>Derrick Fouts and his colleagues have taken this comparative approach with <named-content content-type="genus-species">Campylobacter</named-content>. Infection with a <named-content content-type="genus-species">Campylobacter</named-content> species is one of the most common causes of human bacterial gastroenteritis. In the US, 15 out of every 100,000 people are diagnosed with campylobacteriosis every year, and with many cases going unreported, up to 0.5% of the general population may unknowingly harbor <named-content content-type="genus-species">Campylobacter</named-content> in their gut annually. Diarrhea, cramps, abdominal pain, and fever develop within 2&#x02013;5 days of picking up a pathogenic <named-content content-type="genus-species">Campylobacter</named-content> species, and in most people, the illness lasts for 7&#x02013;10 days. But the infection can sometimes be fatal, and some individuals develop Guillain-Barr&#x000e9; syndrome, in which the nerves that join the spinal cord and brain to the rest of the body are damaged, sometimes permanently.</p><p>Campylobacteriosis is usually caused by <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content>, a spiral-shaped bacterium normally found in cattle, swine, and birds, where it causes no problems. But the illness can also be caused by <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. coli</named-content> (also found in cattle, swine, and birds), <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. upsaliensis</named-content> (found in cats and dogs), and <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. lari</named-content> (present in seabirds in particular). Disease-causing bacteria generally get into people via contaminated food, often undercooked or poorly handled poultry, although contact with contaminated water, livestock, or household pets can also cause disease.<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0030040-g001"/>
</p><fig id="pbio-0030040-g001" position="float"><caption><title>Genome sequencing and comparison of four species of <named-content content-type="genus-species">Campylobacter</named-content>
</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0030040.g001"/></fig><p>In 2000, <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content> was the first food-borne pathogen to be completely sequenced, but we still know little about how <named-content content-type="genus-species">Campylobacter</named-content> species cause disease. In their search for clues, Derrick Fouts and coworkers have completely sequenced the genome of <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content> strain RM1221 (isolated from a chicken carcass) and compared it with the previously sequenced <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. jejuni</named-content> strain NCTC 11168 and with the unfinished sequences of <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. coli</named-content> strain RM2228 (a multi-drug-resistant chicken isolate), <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. lari</named-content> strain RM2100 (a clinical isolate), and <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. upsaliensis</named-content> strain RM3195 (taken from a patient with Guillain-Barr&#x000e9; syndrome).</p><p>The researchers describe numerous differences and similarities between these different <named-content content-type="genus-species">Campylobacter</named-content> strains and species. For example, there are major structural differences between the genomes caused by the insertion of new stretches of DNA. Some of these pieces of DNA may carry genes that improve bacterial virulence or fitness, so their presence could help to explain the different biological behaviors of these strains. There are also major variations in the genes responsible for synthesis of molecules that are important for the interaction of <named-content content-type="genus-species">Campylobacter</named-content> with the environment. Such differences could underlie the host specificity of the different species.</p><p>Differences between the <named-content content-type="genus-species">Campylobacter</named-content> species in genes that are likely to be involved in aspects of bacterial virulence, such as adherence, motility, and toxin formation, are all detailed by Fouts et al., who also describe a new putative <named-content content-type="genus-species">Campylobacter</named-content> virulence locus. Further work is needed to relate these genomic differences to functional differences, but this detailed comparative genomic analysis provides the core blueprint for this important family of human pathogens. And in doing so, it lays the foundation for the development of new ways to monitor and control <named-content content-type="genus-species">Campylobacter</named-content> in the food chain and in human infection.</p></body></article>
