<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">pbio</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosbiol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1544-9173</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1545-7885</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC546042</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.0030058</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Synopsis</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Ecology</subject><subject>Evolution</subject><subject>Microbiology</subject><subject>Zoology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="System Taxonomy"><subject>Eubacteria</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Aging and Death in <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content>
</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Synopsis</alt-title></title-group><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>1</day><month>2</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>1</day><month>2</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>3</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id>e58</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; 2005 Public Library of Science.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article id="d35e74" related-article-type="companion" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pbio.0030045" xlink:title="research article" vol="3" page="e45">
<article-title>Aging and Death in an Organism That Reproduces by Morphologically Symmetric Division</article-title>
</related-article></article-meta></front><body><p>As human beings, aging and death are an inevitable part of our lives. As we pass through each decade, the concrete signs of aging&#x02014;greying hair, aches and pains, the gradual failure of one organ system after another&#x02014;and the realization that we are mortal increasingly occupies our thoughts.</p><p>All other multicellular animals and plants also show clear signs of aging, as do some single-celled organisms. In the yeast <named-content content-type="genus-species">Saccharomyces cerevisiae</named-content> (baker's yeast), for example, the function of individual cells gradually declines with time, and each yeast cell has a finite life span. In organisms like this, it has been proposed that reproduction by asymmetric division is a prerequisite for aging. In other words, for a unicellular organism to age, when it divides, it must give rise to a &#x0201c;parent&#x0201d; cell and a smaller offspring cell (as in yeast), which then has to go through a juvenile phase of growth or differentiation before it divides. At each cell division, the parent cell becomes older until it reaches its natural life span and dies.<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0030058-g001"/>
</p><fig id="pbio-0030058-g001" position="float"><caption><title>A growing microcolony of <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content>
</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0030058.g001"/></fig><p>But what about organisms that produce two apparently identical cells when they divide? Do such organisms age? The assumption has been for some years that cells that divide symmetrically do not age and are functionally immortal. Eric Stewart and colleagues have now tested this idea by analyzing repeated cycles of reproduction in <named-content content-type="genus-species">Escherichia coli</named-content>, a bacteria that reproduces without a juvenile phase and with an apparently symmetric division.</p><p>
<named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> is a rod-shaped organism that reproduces by dividing in the middle. Each resultant cell inherits an old end or pole and a new pole, which is made during the division. The new and the old pole contain slightly different components, so although they look the same, they are physiologically asymmetrical. At the next division, one cell inherits the old pole again (plus a brand new pole), while the other cell inherits, a not-quite-so-old pole and a new pole. Thus, Stewart and co-workers reasoned, an age in divisions can be assigned to each pole and hence to each cell.</p><p>The researchers used automated time-lapse microscopy to follow all the cell divisions in 94 colonies, each grown from a single fluorescently labeled <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> cell. In all, the researchers built up a lineage for 35,049 cells in terms of which pole&#x02014;old or new&#x02014;each cell had inherited at each division during its history. They found that the cells inheriting old poles had a reduced growth rate, decreased rate of offspring formation, and increased risk of dying compared with the cells inheriting new poles. Thus, although the cells produced when <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> divide look identical, they are functionally asymmetric, and the &#x0201c;old pole&#x0201d; cell is effectively an aging parent repeatedly producing rejuvenated offspring.</p><p>Stewart and his colleagues conclude that no life strategy is immune to the effects of aging and suggest that this may be because immortality is too costly or is mechanistically impossible. This may be bad news for people who had hoped that advances in science might eventually lead to human immortality. Nevertheless, <named-content content-type="genus-species">E. coli</named-content> should now provide an excellent genetic platform for the study of the fundamental mechanisms of cellular aging and so could provide information that might ameliorate some of the unpleasantness of the human aging process.</p></body></article>
