<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS Biol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">pbio</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosbiol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Biology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1544-9173</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1545-7885</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC539064</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.0030030</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Synopsis</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Development</subject><subject>Evolution</subject><subject>Genetics/Genomics/Gene Therapy</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="System Taxonomy"><subject>Caenorhabditis</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The Evolution of Self-Fertile Hermaphroditism: The Fog Is Clearing</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Synopsis</alt-title></title-group><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>1</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>12</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>28</day><month>12</month><year>2004</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>3</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e30</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; 2005 Public Library of Science.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article id="d35e69" related-article-type="companion" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pbio.0030006" xlink:title="research article" vol="3" page="e6">
<article-title>
<italic>fog-2</italic> and the Evolution of Self-Fertile Hermaphroditism in <italic>Caenorhabditis</italic>
</article-title>
</related-article></article-meta></front><body><p>The nematode <named-content content-type="genus-species">Caenorhabditis elegans</named-content> is a little less lonely than the rest of us&#x02014;it is a self-fertile hermaphrodite, which as a larva makes and stores sperm before switching to egg production for the remainder of its lifespan. (<named-content content-type="genus-species">C. elegans</named-content> also maintains some males at a low frequency, about 1 in 500, and the hermaphrodite's eggs can be fertilized by sperm either from males or themselves.) A sister species, <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. briggsae</named-content>, is also hermaphroditic, but phylogenetic evidence suggests the last common ancestor of the two species had a female/male mode of reproduction. This raises the question of how the sex determination mechanisms, which must have evolved independently, differ between the two species. In this issue, Sudhir Nayak, Johnathan Goree, and Tim Schedl show that a crucial difference lies in the activities of two genes.</p><p>In <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. elegans</named-content>, the early period of sperm production is controlled by multiple proteins, two of which are the focus of this study, the RNA-binding protein GLD-1 (encoded by the gene <italic>gld-1</italic>) and the F-box-containing protein FOG-2 (encoded by the gene <italic>fog-2</italic>). Together, they repress translation of a gene, <italic>tra-2</italic>, by binding to its messenger RNA. This allows another gene, <italic>fem-3</italic>, to transiently masculinize the larval germline to produce sperm.<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-0030030-g001"/>
</p><fig id="pbio-0030030-g001" position="float"><caption><title>Wild-type <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. elegans</named-content> hermaphrodite stained to highlight the nuclei of all cells</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pbio.0030030.g001"/></fig><p>Comparing the genomes of <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. elegans</named-content> and <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. briggsae</named-content>, Schedl and colleagues found they share 30 out of 31 sex determination genes, but not <italic>fog-2</italic>. More surprisingly, they found that the role of <italic>gld-1</italic> in sex determination is opposite in the two species. When <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. elegans</named-content> is deprived of <italic>gld-1</italic>, would-be hermaphrodites produce only oocytes. But when <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. briggsae</named-content> is deprived of <italic>gld-1</italic>, would-be hermaphrodites produce only sperm. Thus, the authors conclude, the control of hermaphrodite spermatogenesis is fundamentally different in the two species.</p><p>By further examining the <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. elegans</named-content> genome, the authors showed that <italic>fog-2</italic> arose from a gene duplication event after the <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. elegans</named-content>&#x02013;<named-content content-type="genus-species">C. briggsae</named-content> split, which occurred approximately 100 million years ago. Since then, its final exon, which codes for the C-terminal end of the protein, has undergone rapid evolution. The authors also show that this is the &#x0201c;business end&#x0201d; of the protein for its interaction with GLD-1, suggesting that the divergence of <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. elegans</named-content> and <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. briggsae</named-content> sex determination pathways resulted, in part, from FOG-2's new interaction with GLD-1.</p><p>Exactly what the role of <italic>fog-2</italic> is in <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. elegans</named-content> is still unclear. The authors speculate that it may recruit additional factors onto the <italic>gld-1/tra-2</italic> mRNA complex, increasing efficiency of translation repression. Much remains to be discovered about <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. briggsae</named-content> sex determination as well. The authors suggest that additional genetic differences promoting self-fertility are likely to have accumulated since the two species diverged, which may act to strengthen the male&#x02013;female germline switching signal. Investigation of this possibility may shed more light on how hermaphroditism operates in these two species, and how a developmental pathway controlling sex determination can evolve.</p></body></article>
