<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="other"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">pmed</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosmed</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1549-1277</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1549-1676</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">15737002</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">PMC549594</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pmed.0020047</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Correspondence and Other Communications</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline"><subject>Neurology/Neurosurgery</subject><subject>Pathology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="System Taxonomy"><subject>Pathology</subject><subject>Neurology</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Free Community Science and the Free Development of Science</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Correspondence</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stallman</surname><given-names>Richard</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="n1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><institution>Free Software Foundation</institution><addr-line>Boston, Massachusetts</addr-line><country>United States of America</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="n1">E-mail: <email>rms@gnu.org</email></corresp><fn id="n2" fn-type="COI-statement"><p>
<bold>Competing Interests:</bold> I own stocks through mutual funds that are rather general, and I don't know what companies they invest in. My only professional relationships are with the Free Software Foundation (FSF) and the Union for the Public Domain. A list of the FSF's corporate donors can be found at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fsf.org">http://www.fsf.org</ext-link>. I have received probably 60 different travel grants and honoraria this year. Most were from universities, conferences, and government bodies, but included also Google and OSDL.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>2</month><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id>e47</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright: &#x000a9; 2005 Richard Stallman.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2005</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><related-article id="d35e103" related-article-type="companion" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1371/journal.pmed.0010016" xlink:title="health" vol="2" page="e16">
<article-title>A Free Community Approach to Classifying Disease</article-title>
</related-article></article-meta></front><body><p>In free community science, where large numbers of scientists participate as volunteers in a single project, the ideal of scientific cooperation finds a new expression. Free community science was inspired by the free software movement, which itself was inspired by the application of the ideal of scientific cooperation, as it was applied to software development by the operating system developers of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology Artificial Intelligence Lab in the 1970s. This ideal has suffered for two decades from corporate pressure to privatize science, so it is very gratifying to see that the free software movement can today help reinvigorate the principle that inspired it.</p><p>The ideal of scientific cooperation goes beyond the conduct of individual projects. Scientific cooperation is also being reinvigorated today through the open-access movement, which promotes the public's freedom to redistribute scientific and scholarly articles. In the age of the computer networks, the best way to disseminate scientific writing is by making it freely accessible to all and letting everyone redistribute it. I give a vote of thanks to the Public Library of Science for leading the campaign that is now gaining momentum. When research funding agencies pressure journals to allow free redistribution of new articles they fund, they should apply this demand to the old articles &#x0201c;owned&#x0201d; by the same publishers&#x02014;not just to papers published starting today.</p><p>Journal editors can promote scientific cooperation by adopting standards requiring internet publication of the supporting data and software for the articles they publish. The software and the data will be useful for other research. Moreover, research carried out using software cannot be checked or evaluated properly by other scientists unless they can read the source code that was used.</p><p>A significant impediment to publication and cooperation comes from university patent policies. Many universities hope to strike it rich with patents, but this is as foolish as playing the lottery, since most &#x0201c;technology licensing offices&#x0201d; don't even cover their operating costs. Like the Red Queen, these universities are running hard to stay in the same place. Society should recognize that funding university research through patents is folly, and should fund it directly, as in the past. Meanwhile, laws that encourage universities to seek patents at the expense of cooperation in research should be changed.</p><p>Another impediment comes from strings attached to corporate research funding. Universities or their public funding agencies should ensure private sponsors cannot block research they do not like. These sponsors must never have the power to veto or delay publication of results&#x02014;or to intimidate the researchers. Thus, sponsors whose interests could be hurt by publication of certain possible results must never be in a position to cut the funding for a specific research group.</p><p>The free software movement, the free redistribution policy of this journal, and the practice of free community science for developing diagnostic disease classifications [<xref rid="pmed-0020047-b1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>] are all based on the same fundamental principle: knowledge contributes to society when it can be shared and developed by communities. All three face opposition from those who would like to privatize knowledge and charge tolls for its use. In the free software movement we have 20 years' experience in resisting this opposition, and we have built up considerable strength and momentum. We can give the other two movements a boost, so they can advance more quickly.</p></body><back><fn-group><fn id="n3" fn-type="other"><p>
<bold>Citation:</bold> Stallman R (2005) Free community science and the free development of science. PLoS Med 2(2): e47.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pmed-0020047-b1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Graeber</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Radotra</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A free community approach to classifying disease</article-title><source>PLoS Med</source><year>2004</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>e16</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15578101</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>
